With that, I should be able to switch back to the
doc cam---just on the stroke of four!  Well, welcome
to Statistical Physics.  I guess the bells are
our cue to get started. I am David Schaich and will
be your host for this module. And the name is
pronounced like in handshake. It's
easier to say that it is the spell. I think when I
was testing this doc cam itself over the weekend,
it was also not responding to zoom in or out, but just
get set up with some of the things I'll be going
through today, and in particular, I should
probably put a microphone in case I want anything
I'm saying to be picked up by any of these
recordings. I'm trying to make several.
The various logistical things to go through today,
some of which you might have seen earlier in other
modules, one of those is the attendance and
well-being monitoring system that the department
is. So I've got a six digit number for you all to
plug into that system. You want to record it. And
we're engaged with this stuff. That's very, very I
hate to leave that up on the top there as we go
forward.
And at least part of today will be spent on.
Logistics and other important things, but I want
to say, first of all, I should. Introduced myself
in a bit more detail in a lecture here in
theoretical physics, mathematical sciences. I've
been here for three years now and this is the
third time I've taught this module in a different
way after the excitement of the past few years.
And it is at this point a sufficiently small
module that I think I can introduce myself and ask
you to introduce yourselves and try to attach
names to faces Musubi masks. So if you're all
right with that, would you start by the left side
here and possibly introduce yourself to each other?
How many logical you could get together at the
past? If you want to see your name, that's all it
has to be.
George, George.
Right, right, John. Well, try to remember those
that, like you said at.
I'm just debating what to talk about first, maybe
the best thing to do would be to talk about why
we're doing what we're doing before going into
battle and then what? So I want to introduce and
motivate statistical physics as really one of the
pillars of physics over the past couple of
centuries that I'm sure for the next couple of
centuries coming up after that, which goes along
with relativity and quantum mechanics as.
Really, the the essence of what physics amounts to
in practice in these days and also
playing an important role in all sorts of
applications from the realm of nuclear physics,
particle physics, cosmology, to figuring squishier
stuff like climate physics and biological physics,
and compared to quantum mechanics and relativity,
which we usually consider in the context of
individual objects or simple systems, just
physical physics really has the unique feature.
That is what happens when phenomena emerge from
collections of large numbers of degrees of freedom
like atoms. So in a gram of water, the sort of
large number have in mind here is roughly 10 to
the power of 22 atoms in a couple of dozen drops
of water. And what that enables, in contrast to
some of the simpler and more fundamental things I
imagine you've already seen, is really the
emergence of waiting for the arrow of time, which
is not quite in theory. No, there. But we know
that in this series of pictures, we're putting a
drop of purple dye into a cup of water and seeing
how it expands outward as time goes on until it is
uniformly distributed throughout that water. And
if we think about this for a sec, we. Realised
from the classical or quantum mechanics of atoms
bouncing off each other in the dye, in the water.
We believe in atoms, all those processes look the
same no matter whether time is going forward or in
reverse. If you have two atoms or billiard balls
that come in and out of each other, we reverse
time. They come in off each other in the opposite
direction. But in this physical process coming
from the last number of degrees of freedom,
there's a clear direction to how things are
evolving. We are used to seeing things like milk
and coffee spreading out, and even though the
individual processes at play in that spreading out
are all reversible. It would be very surprising if
we were to see this process going in the opposite
direction, starting from a uniform mixture of
water dye and seeing all the dye.
Collect himself in a small region in that water.
So there is something.
The serious and fundamental to how the universe is
evolving, that is coming from the axis of physics
properties. The properties of statistical physics
that we can keep an eye on as we go through the.
This monument and setting that aside, can just
briefly look through the rough outline of this
march divided up into 10 units and 12 weeks. So
we'll be doing. A little less than one minute a
week or a little more than one week a unit, and
there won't be a very hard and rigid schedule. Go
over things in these lectures and tutorials, see
how quickly we go, and we need to speed up or add
more material as the term goes up. Again, this is
the first time I've will actually be able to do
this module in person.
And the basic idea that we are the plane that
we're following, what is essential physics from a
mathematical perspective is based on the idea of
what are called sophistical ensembles, which you
can see popping up a few times throughout this
course. And what we'll be doing later today or
later this week is putting in place the
probability fundamentals that define what a.
Statistical ensemble is and then looking for two
or three different examples of those ensembles and
applying them to various systems and in questions
so.
If I were to say things just the sentence, an
ensemble is a statistical system subject to a
certain set of constraints and different
constraints, four to five different ensembles. So
after we look at what we call the microeconomic
ensemble, canonical ensemble, which are subject to
slightly different sets of constraints, we'll get
to all the details in due time to apply that to
the idea of gases and thermodynamic cycles,
followed by what is called a grand canonical
ensemble. Another change in the constraints that
are imposed, which will more then apply to look at
quantum statistics and quantum gases. And all of
those ensembles will be simplified by assuming
that the many particles in these systems are not
interacting with each other. They are just free to
dance around without any care as to what any of
the other particles are doing. Maybe. An example
of that sort of behavior is in the physics of
light photons, which basically pass right through
each other as waves wrap up the term by at least
beginning to look at interacting systems where
individual particles are interacting with each
other, bouncing off of each other, which is where
things start to get really interesting and we'll
have a lot of broader applications to fill
whatever time remains once we get to that point.
And I'll try to not get too bogged down in in
these logistics, which I at least find fairly dull,
but we have three class meetings a week and then
one tutorial. And for whatever reason, those three
class meetings have to end here. And then on
Tuesday mornings will be next door. And the
tutorial also will be here on Friday afternoons.
There is a canvass site that I think most of you
have visited at this point. I said that link in an
announcement through canvas. And I have office
hours, twice a week following the lecture at this
time on Mondays, as well as the Friday morning
lecture, which will give me a chance if you come
to me with any questions at those office hours. I
have another lecture tutorial meeting immediately
afterwards kicks in. You don't need to be brought
up in half over.
Among the the whole group now what might be more
interesting, but how are you seen on canvas is
some of the assessments that are coming up in the
schedule for that. Where will have just the final
exam of the exam period when it comes to tests and
then all the interim assessment will be
essentially homework, a couple of traditional
homework assignments, some projects, no problems
to work through with the paper, and then a two
part computer project where you will have to write
some computer programs that will look at the
emergence of statistical behavior from a.
Underlying stochastic probabilistic process that
is happening with some level of randomness, but
repeatedly and giving rise to immersions. Have
from that, I don't think there's anything I can do
with those lights to.
Resolution of that can. Sorry about that.
There are various policies about deadlines and
exemptions and deductions that I will set aside
unless there are questions with them, I just say
that for each of these Intermap. Assignments,
we've been given a fixed deadline that's
coordinated within the department, and it's not in
my power to change the assignment itself or be
available to you in at least a week in advance and
hopefully much more than that. The first deadline
is coming up for that first part of the computer
project in a little under three weeks at this
point in mid-February.
So I'm going through.
But I call lecture notes, which is a bit of a
misnomer here, since these are
being updated from some of the asynchronous
materials that. Or developed for promoting of the
jury in the last term. So these are more like a
transcript of what I would say in the full lecture,
and there's not any guarantee that or let me put
it another way. I'm definitely not going to be
just reading off of these lecture notes when we're
meeting in person, which we get a bit tedious.
I will be going through with the material in the
order in style it's presented here and essentially
saying a bit more about things that seem to merit
a bit more discussion, maybe glossing over things
like these logistics that are reasonably well
covered in the lecture notes themselves. And I
know in past. Editions of this molecule, so the
students have been concerned about the appearance
of quantum physics or computer programming in the
outline of the assessment, so it's worth
emphasizing up front that there's no missing
background about any computer programming or
familiar with quantum physics. Everything you need
for that will be covered and in particular for
computer programming, starting at the editorial
this Friday, getting a bit of an introduction to
the programming languages that I personally
recommend for the project work, which is Python
and programming languages go User-Friendly and
very widely used around the world as well as being.
All pre and. It's also something that there are.
Various resources available online where you can
run Python code in case you have any trouble
getting it set up on the basis of your own.
Of which are links there often require creating a
a free account.
I should say that even though I recommend Pythonic
find it easy to work with your choice, if you
prefer to do that, project a different programming
language that you're already familiar with, feel
free to do so. Though I would warn against people,
which is not really up to the task that will be
assigned.
And.
You're all in your third year studies at this
point. You are experts in mathematical sciences
studying, but you know how to get the most out of
coming to how to get the most out of the module,
which includes coming to class. Even if everything
feels very easy for you and you're on top of
things, coming to class gives you an opportunity
to dig more deeply into some of the things that
will be oversimplified. Or perhaps glossed over
too quickly. So you're welcome to ask about
extensions or applications. Or anything else that.
Is it any interest to you as we really go through
the material and you'll see in these lecture notes,
there are gaps, there are going to be some
tutorial style exercises? Distributed both on
canvas and in person, and there will also, of
course, be a computer project and homework
assignment that you can work through to really get
a good grasp on the physics and confidence that
you fully understand it well enough to to actually
do things with it. So feel free to ask questions
to me, to each other or to any of the additional
books and and resources that are collected
on this last page of the logistics, which will.
Give you more perspectives and. Information about
any particular topic, especially if you are.
Having difficulty understanding any particular
aspect or even understanding why we're talking
about any particular aspect, all of those
questions are welcome and none of them is going to
be
stupid or otherwise. Problematic. So are there any
questions about the logistics, the health of the
course, the module before you really go into
actual physics and mathematics?
When will the computing project be released? So
the first part that's due in mid-February should
come out in the next few days before a tutorial
this Friday. I want to have it in your hand so you
can connect it up to what we'll be talking about
in terms of computer programming there. In fact, I
wanted to have it in your hand today, but it's
coming up as soon as possible this week.
And you'll see it on canvas and depending on. How
you set your notifications, you might get a
notification there. Just keep an eye out for it.
Other questions
could be it's an individual project, so you're
welcome to talk with each other about it, but
whatever you code up and turn in these to be your
own work, representing your understanding in the
usual way.
The questions and. Feel free to follow up with any
later on, but let's get back to introducing more
of this topic to physical fitness over here from
time to time. See if any questions. Come up in
the chair, so.
The basic starting point for medical science is
using mathematics to make predictions for
observable phenomena.
In physics in particular, it's this has been a
tremendously successful enterprise and there's.
Even discussions about whether it is a reasonably
successful, which I will not get into. In this
module, though, those of you who are interested in
philosophy are probably already familiar with that
argument, that mathematics is unreasonably
effective in the physical sciences and the various
debates around that topic. But in the domain of
statistical physics, what we're really going to
see is. That seems sort of amazingly broad
applications of simple mathematical principles to
all sorts of physical systems and ranging from
subatomic scales to cosmological scales beyond the
galaxy. And.
The temperature is colder than the vacuum of outer
space to really the temperatures of the sort of
heat seeing how statistical physics governs the
spectrum of radiation emitted by the sun. Later as
one application. They are the turban and.
I've already just said at the big picture level
brought up the fact that some physical physics
differs from sort of relativistic quantum
mechanics in terms of producing a clear arrow of
time in the evolution of systems. One other
difference that is at the practical level. Is the
use of probabilities to. Describe phenomena and
describe things, describe physical processes in
probabilistic terms, the Catholic terms that
involve stochastic randomness rather than the in
principle, perfectly predictive behavior of those
other pillars of physics. And even in quantum
physics that are there is.
You might might know or might not it's not
required for this knowledge of others because they
have to have intrinsic uncertainties in quantum
physics. The Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle
places sharp restrictions upon how well you say
the position or momentum of an object can be
something easily known. And there is a
probabilistic aspect to quantum wave functions.
But even in quantum physics, you can in principle,
perfectly predict. Distributions and probabilities,
whereas in sophistical physics.
The approach is characterized by practical
limitations on the. The way the extent to which
physical systems can be predicted that are arising
from just the sheer number of degrees of freedom.
Number of independent objects that are involved, I
think, of this number tend to be power. Twenty two
twenty three came up in the big picture. This is
known as Avogadro's number, describing the number
of atoms that are in everyday amounts of substance.
So it's about 18 grams of water. Twenty two liters
of air at sea level. Atmospheric pressure and
temperature. Evolve just this enormous amount of
information, amount of constituents and. You're
not impressed by the about 10, 20, 30 objects.
Maybe I could ask.
How easy would it be to write down? That's amount
of information in your laptop or even a
supercomputer. So.
If we use some of the math about imagining that
each of these atoms could be described just with a
single bytes of information, which is certainly
optimistic once we get up to the level of interior
light that you might have on your hard drive.
That's 10 to 12 buttons, so you accounted for one
part in 10 to the 10th and the 11th of a 18 grams
worth of water. So that is sort of large numbers
we're talking about in order to write down or
specify positions or velocities of this number of
objects. We need something like one hundred
billion terabytes worth of information and we want
to analyze that level of information on a
continuous basis going forward as the systems
evolve in time. So that is what's leading us to
where that's showing the impossibility of
predicting all of those positions and velocities.
The final thing is the ad in full detail, even
though in principle it's possible with. One
hundred billion terabytes of data that is updated
continuously in practice, that's not something
that we as humans will ever be able to do. So the
alternative that statistical physics is based on
is.
Figuring out what we want to analyze from these
large sets of data sets. And coming up with.
Simple mathematical descriptions of those based on.
A. Stochastics, treatment of the underlying
processes is one of those underlying processes are
essentially invisible. And just. As a brief,
historical aside,
approaches, statistical physics approaches were
developed in the eighteen hundreds and into the
nineteen hundred as by folks like little Boltzmann,
Willard Gibbs, Albert Einstein, Max Hawk where.
There was a great deal of debate at that time
about whether or not the atoms and molecules that
I've claimed are not familiar substances actually
exist, if it was well beyond the capabilities of
19th century technology to see an individual atom
or even an individual molecule. So the proposition,
that stuff we interacted with in measuring
temperature and pressure and intensity of the
large scale macroscopic or thermodynamic
properties of systems, the claim that all that
stuff was really made up of atoms was.
Generally, a fair amount of debate and both men in
particular had to spend sort of his entire life in
arguments about whether it was valid or useful to
even hypothesize that atoms existed in this. No.
We should ask, who in this room believes that
atoms are better for the air and the other
substances that were made out of.
One, I'll confess to that. And most hands do seem
to be up here. Willing to accept the atomic
hypothesis. But if I were to ask about whether,
you know, who in the room believes that same
fundamental strength is in the live space time
dimensions of what are responsible for those atoms
at the most fundamental level. With a show of
hands. There are fewer hands, including my own,
you sort of get a sense for the style of debates
that were going on around the development of
statistical physics and really.
Crucial advance that allowed Adams to be
conclusively established is something that really
existed in in physics and in everyday substances
was the application of sophistical physics to a
process known as Brownian motion, which is where
microscopic but still. Visible particles, so you
can the of pollen suspended in water, we observe
it to randomly move around in the early eighteen
hundreds and after scientists had done sufficient
experimentation to prove that these objects, these
particles and. In this water, we're not, in fact,
alive, and they were just randomly. The debate
became what was causing this range of motion, and
it was Albert Einstein, actually his Ph.D. thesis,
who showed that if you hypothesize the existence
of atoms and molecules and say that these
suspended particles are being moved around by
being knocked against by all the atoms and water
molecules in the water that they're floating in,
you can reproduce that observed random behavior of
those microscopic pollen grains. And the. I sense
irritation, part of his miracle here in 1985 was.
A famous application of statistical physics that
sort of finally cracked the debate about the
existence of atoms leaving all of us to find them
fairly uncontroversial. How these compare to
fundamental strains this in these times and some
of the questions that. Folks like Baltimore did
Einstein would encountered back at that time to
deal with high school physics or. Sort of
handwaving or physically motivated questions that
if we're supposing that all of the observable
behaviors of these systems are caused by atoms and
molecules bouncing into each other, why is it that
we don't see any of that sort of bouncing if we
have a gas in the container? You say that this
pressure is due to. Atoms bouncing off the walls
of the container, exerting force on the wall and
the wall in terms of the force of the atoms by
third law of motion. Why don't we see all sorts of
fluctuations every time a particle is hitting that
wall? Why does it seem very smooth, regular and
undisturbed in its behavior? So. There is an
answer to that question at the mathematical level,
rather than the handwaving physics level and the.
Fundamentals to that answer are coming from two
mathematical principles known as the law of large
numbers and the central limit theorem that are
sort of core topics of this first unit.
So. But the questions about that sort of big
picture motivation before I dive into the more.
Detailed mathematics.
So what we're going to do for the remainder of
today is really set up a. Abstracts, well,
foundation for the probabilistic discussions that
will be applied in physics, so it's going to have
a slightly different flavor compared to some of
the later calculations that will be doing in
particular in terms of. How abstract will trying
to keep things, at least at first, just by going
through a sequence of definitions of what we're
going to be talking about and why the first of
those being that we're going to consider random
experiments by which I mean some some experiments,
some observation or manipulation of the physical
world that has an element of randomness to it. So
flipping a coin is a simple example of that, where
at least in principle, if we do precisely how much
force I exerted on the coin as I flipped it and
how much resistance encountered to the air as it
rose and fell, we could predict exactly how it
would land, where it went. But again, there's too
much data to process in all of that to. Predicted
precisely in practice. So believe leave it as a
random process in which the coin can land randomly,
either heads with 50 percent probability or tails
with the other 50 percent. I'm actually getting
ahead of myself a bit.
There's more information in the world after I flip
a coin and just heads or tails and we'll see that
after we do that experiment. So you're flipping a
coin? There is.
If Islamic State's Omega for the whole, which
includes not only the orientation of that coin, it
says, by the way, but also the fact that it's
bounced off the desk and landed on the floor where
it's sitting, what time everything happened, what
the temperature is in the world around it. And
sort of any other aspect of the physical world
that could potentially be impinging on this
process, this random experiment that we are
considering.
And from all of those possible states, all we can
do the usual mathematical things and just collect
all the possibilities into a capital or make a set
of all those possible states, all the possible
ways that that coin could have landed in all the
possible locations, including possibilities that.
And I flipped it outside, a seagull could have
swooped in and out of the area, seagulls do. And
obviously, we are not interested in all aspects of
that fourth state of the universe. There's just
too much information there that is not going to be
relevant to. The physics of the observables that.
We actually want to bring the physical physics
methods to bear upon him. So what we. What to do?
So if that signal is required, we can just throw
that out as an experiment. The.
What we want to do is really pull out. The
information we actually care about, which in the
context of flipping a coin is I started off with
is whether it lands, heads or tails in each case
with 50 percent probability.
So this is getting rid of things like the
temperature in the location where it landed and
it's also getting rid of perhaps possibilities
that don't match cleanly onto the heads or tails.
Question.
We would typically focus on one flipping a coin.
So if the coin lands on its side, we can just
throw that away through this measurement, throw
away that iteration of the random experiment.
If we consider acting with this measurement, that
is.
Producing all of that full information to just the
small subset, we care about applying that
measurement to the full set of all states, America
leaves us with the set of all outcomes instead of
the outcome space that we actually care about.
Even though I tried to keep these definitions,
yeah. Maximally abstract at this point. I think
there are some simple examples, including flipping
a coin that we can go through just to make sure
everything is is clear. So.
This outcome is a can just be a finite set, like
flipping a coin and it ends heads or tails. Or it
can be accountably infinite or even continuous to
see examples of all of those later on. But a
simple example is. If we take the six sided die
and we roll it and then we measure the number that
comes out on top, so we throw away all the
information about where the dye ends up, how long
it took to get there.
We do that measurements we end up with. And
outcomes based that I imagine or I hope you should
be able to to tell me to write down. So go ahead
and shout it out.
That's the one. So it's a set of possible values
we can get from that measurement of what number is
on top.
Which could be one, two, three, four or five or
six. So that is a danger in any of the given
states we could have information about the
position of that. Whether it's orientation,
whether it's.
Oriented NASA at some angle to the temperature.
The color of the dye, the face of the moon.
All aspects of the universe that comes out after
we do that random experiment of rolling to die.
This next example is maybe a little less trivial
because we can see that it's possible to.
Defiant experiments that. Or a little more
complicated than simply flipping a coin or willing
to die. So in this case, you flip a coin four
times. We count that as a single experiment.
That's sort of for.
Four coin flips after each of which we measure
then whether that coin lands, heads up or tails up.
Then doing that measurement. From this single
experiment involving four coin flips is going to
give us another outcome space and maybe we can
just go through quickly the possible outcomes in
this outcome space. So any example, tell it to me
and I'll write it down on the dock in or four
heads.
It one on Portillo's is another, and there are.
Other possibilities.
Between.
Which. I would.
To have all of them, but let's put some ellipses
there to keep moving on. I guess you can tell the
size of the number of elements in a just by
inspection. Would that be at.
Yeah, to the fourth. There are two possibilities
for each of the four experiments. Which is 16. And
then. To connect these very trivial experiments
illustrating these abstract definitions, we can
start to think about how they apply to some of the.
Systems where statistical physics was developed
that tend to be powered, twenty three atoms in
some container.
The state of those atom's. Which can include a
whole lot of information, some of which is obvious,
like the ten to twenty three positions. Of all
those ads.
Would there normally draw three of them rather
than the ten to twenty three of them, and we could
also imagine that each of those ordinary items has
some velocity.
Characterizing the state.
Each of them could be a different isotope of argon.
Would be that has a slightly different maps, it
could be a different electronic stage.
Which would affect the. The orientation's that
spins.
And that's all information that would be in that
full state lawmaker describing this gas in this
container. And if any of my handwriting is
impossible to read up there and hopefully be
clearer when I scan these notes and and upload
them to canvas after the fact. But given all of
these pieces of data, what. What would you be
interested in measuring about some gas in some
container that would arise from.
From the behavior of these individual constituents.
Yeah, that's a good one.
Putting the thermal in the thermodynamic. Well,
it's that one, yeah, that what may well be. Fixed
by the container, if we assume it's a rigid
container, but it's also a large scale process.
And given the volume and the number of atoms.
That is related as well to the overall density of
atoms in that volume and that density, in fact,
could well have some.
Gradients, there might be regions in the volume
where atoms were more densely located than
elsewhere. And I think I heard someone say.
Pressure, which is also another of the classic
thermodynamic quantities that arises in some way
from the behavior, from the dynamics of these 10
of the 20, 30 atoms, and the way it arises is what
we will be. We tackle them with statistical
physics, so.
With those first set of definitions
taken care of, we can actually generalize the.
The concept of measurements to simply considering
those measurements to be a label that we can put
on each of the states, that big set of mega
characterizes the.
The full information of the world and of the
system that we have. So if we take. Each of the
possible states is impossible.
Descriptions of the system of the world, I imagine
giving it a unique label, that that uniqueness
means that we can refer to the state as a whole
interchangeably with that label and refer to it
just as that label function el. And set aside the
details of what exactly is contained in the state
as a whole now with measurements, we're formally
doing something different. We're actually throwing
out a lot of the information in the states that we
are not interested in, but precisely because we're
not interested in what we're throwing out, we can
use this measurement as a label to refer to each
stage just in terms of what we want to measure. So
going back to the simple example, if you flip a
coin, we can say it just it lands heads or tails.
And that's all the information that we need to
know, even though there's a lot more in the four
states of America that. We could in principle talk
about. And ignored that relevant information.
Basically leaves the outcome space any equivalent
to the full set of possible states of the world
that America and in fact, in some of the
references in those, for the reasons that they
never distinguish between the experimental
outcomes and the measurement outcomes in the first
place. But it is a good thing to keep in mind to
know that. Information is. Is being removed by the
process of measurement and that there is always
more about the world that could be incorporated
into the outcome of that round of experiments, and
we're making the choice of what exactly we're
going to look at when we bring that measurement to
bear and talk about outcomes rather than of system
states of the universe.
With an eye on the time, just a couple of minutes
are left, so I will wrap up by.
Emphasizing that we've sort of reached the end of
the formal abstract definitions here
that connect us now from random experiments to
probabilities. So. So the last step. From our
outcomes, space to probability spaces is to define
an event where that event is any subset of. The
outcome space A. So.
If we the coin flipping examples a bit too simple
for this, but if we think about that ruling as
excited Diagne, an event could be rolling a six or
that event could be rolling anything other than a
six. So it doesn't correspond directly to what we
would measure, but it does correspond to a subset
of those measurements. A third example, I guess,
could be rolling any even number from that guy
that brings in the measurements to four and six.
And from all of those events. We can define the
event space that we are interested in, we'll call
F, and it is the events in that event space that
we will assign probabilities of happening. So for
this, the three examples that are here and we know
there's a one in six chance of rolling or six if
we have a fair die, there's a five six chance of
rolling in other than a six and a 50 percent
chance of of rolling an even number. So all of
those. All probabilities. Our mapping from that
set of all possible events to not negative real
numbers between zero percent to one hundred
percent, and tomorrow morning we will go through
the properties of probability and start to get
into the wall. First numbers, that central limit
theorem applying it. So are there questions about
what we've seen so far today?
Do we need to measure it or not, look at it that
way? No.
Essentially, the statement of a major function
here just means that the event is being projected
to be presented percentage between zero percent to
one hundred percent. That's all that needs to come
out from that.
And if there are questions about the role that
we've seen so far today, it's the first day of
office hours is starting. As soon as I get back to
my office in the theoretical physics will come by
with questions about logistics, background or the
explosion itself, in addition to any of the
mathematical content. And with that, I'll
wrap it up for today and look forward to seeing
you tomorrow morning at.