All right, those bells mean it's going to get going, so welcome back
to the Friday afternoon, approaching the end of this
week.  I may not have the recording going the whole
tutorial session today, but I figured it should
pick up the number for the
attendance system for this session:
one zero eight
three eight six.
The plan for today, you might have guessed by
what I have on the screen already, is just to wrap up going
through that Python programming demo notebook,
just to make sure everything in there is brought
up more together and a chance to see what is going
on. This is the last detail for this. The first
parts of that computer project is due next
Thursday, and I have already some questions about
it if there are immediate ones that are want to
bring up here in the group. This is a time for
that.
Meantime.
This. System connected, running online and get
back to the point where we set aside this last
week to look at the. That example of the
programming for that that showed up in the one of
the lecture notes.
Know that was covering that inversed transform
sampling in the creation of a histogram and the
comparison of that histogram to the expected
probability distribution and actually the next and
final part in this double.
Is to some extent equivalent to that was that
given that the lecture where we're grabbing some
random numbers out of a probability distribution
and adding them to some running total, the the
roulette game, that was the total of winnings
minus that's that were put in. And the more
general context that can be applied to bottom, not
only the Electoral College, those are things we
have this random walk where we take some steps of
a certain length here with the
length of each step being chosen randomly
according to this probability distribution that we
set up based on inverse transfer of sampling. So
particular the distribution here. Is P of X is X
over two, so it's weighted towards larger steps of
length to are maximally probable. And the cut off
on the size of the step from zero to two is just
required to ensure that this probability
distribution integrates to a hundred percent over
its entire range.
So
from.
I think we may have done last time the from this
distribution, it's an easy integration to compute
both the the true mean and the variance of this
probability distribution. So I'll set that. Aside
for now and try to remember and see witness, it's
never one, certainly.
Yeah, that's the first thing we did
with Peter was checking that distribution. I have
some recollection of going through the computation
of that. We had standard deviation on the board
last time. So I won't repeat that here. What we
want to implement in. The.
Want until now is.
Organizing in some sensible way that we can
understand multiple groups over these random
numbers where we have some number of repetitions
of this whole random thought process, each of
which has some number of steps with step lengths
randomly drawn from this probability distribution
that we've defined.
And in fact, going further here, it added a third
level of forelimbs. This outer level is
considering. Different options for the total
number of steps in the walk, so as we go over each
and step in this outermost for loop within which
everything from that I've highlighted has been
inducted. Indicating that it is being repeated for
every. Integer in this array that's being called a
step.
So first we go through this loop with 10 steps in
each walk.
And with that fixed number of steps, we have to.
Some over the given number of repetitions or
number of samples is written here that we are
doing, and this was set up above to be one hundred
thousand samples. It took zero seconds to compute
a histogram of those hundred thousand random
numbers from the distribution. But now we are.
Getting one hundred thousand samples for every
step in this walk of ten steps and the final
innermost loop at three levels of invitation to
Python is carrying out that step. So we say that
our water starts out at some distance zero from a
starting point. And with every step. It takes it
adds to that distance some number given by.
The transform that we related to the probability
distribution, if I developed in this case to route
times in uniform, random number drawn between zero
and one with a flat probability distribution.
And then at the end of those steps, we have some
results for the final position of the walker
that's held this running somebody and we. Add that
results to the very last elements in this rain
called El, which I'm calling out to, so a race to
find up there. Zero is appended before we start
going through the samples. And then with each
sample we add or accumulate in this running solid,
the position, the final position of the water
attribute that mark. So l I called, I chose that
name probably because I had in mind this was the
length of the walk after a certain number of steps.
So once we've gone through a hundred thousand
repetitions of those random walks with some number
of steps, we just normalize the length by the
number of samples that I've got added of added in
and print that out, which will finally take more
than zero seconds. As you can see, even with 50,
60, 80 steps being repeated, one hundred thousand
times is taking a total, only about 10 seconds for
all eight of those independently. Now, if we were
pressed for time or we're trying to do a larger
number of samples, we could. Take a shortcut and
and say that in the process of taking 80 step
random walks, if we look at just the first 10
steps of those, then those are ten steps, random
walks. And similarly, the first 20 steps are 20
step random walks. And we could have got numbers
for we could have gotten all eight of these
numbers with some statistical fluctuations just by
looking at
seven some blocks of the final 80 step random box.
Now, if we were to do that, the results would be
correlated. The ADF walks would have built within
the seven mixed up blocks and therefore depend on
how the 70 that walks turned out. But it may be an
interesting question you can do on your own to see
how significant those correlations are for a given
number of samples and whether it would cause
problems to do that on computational shortcuts.
But for now, we can see a nice linear trend in the
final positions of the walker with the number of
steps. Which is pretty much what we would expect
based on the central limit theorem, especially
because we have this probability distribution
where the walks are always non-negative. So the
water is always going in the same direction. The
question is just how much it stops. Think at this
point in time, and in particular from the central
limit theorem would expect that the, um, the final
position, if we average things out with a
sufficient number of repetitions, would just be
those insteps times, the median length of a step
that you have for third's. That was computed
exactly for the simple distribution, which is
something we can test by fitting these data to a
straight line. Holding on to that of any questions
about this process of how groups were nested
within groups, within news in order to get lots of
repetitions of random walks with various white
flags.
Everyone seems.
Happy with that process and the fitting, maybe a
more interesting application of this code, because
we're doing something more than just adding the
result of well organized way, we want to take some
data that we've. Accumulated sarcastically based
on pseudo random numbers and.
Do some analysis of it just in Python itself, in
order to extract the key features, describing it
in this case, the the slope and intercept of what
looks here like a straight line. So we'll assume
that this walk line is a straight line. The walk
is some constant eight times the number of steps,
plus some concept B that we expect to be zero
since when the number of steps is zero and where
it started and there is built in to Python A.
Polynomial fitting subroutine that can do this
just. The single line of code we take, this
polynomial fitting subroutine, we tell it the. X
values, we want to fit as an array. That's the
walk lengths defined. In the previous block of
code, the next argument is the the why variables
also in an array of the same size so that each X
is associated to a corresponding Y value. So those
two arrays together define the points to be fit.
And then this final argument is just the order of
the polynomial fitting function that is being
applied, which can be anything up to in this case,
about seven, six or seven, so that there's enough
degrees of freedom to actually constrain. The
coefficients that appear in that polynomial.
If I.
But this hit pretty quickly, I've gone ahead and
extracted these parameters and be doing what that
output looked like, but if I didn't have that
knowledge.
Should have done things I could just have. Printed
the output. We'll see what all is returned, and
indeed, it is just these two numbers, one of which
is very close to zero with some sort of percent
level or even permitted level non-zero value that
we could attribute to statistical fluctuations,
the other of which is very close to that mean of
the single step length for thirds. And if I were
to put these points to a cubic function rather
than a linear one, get out.
Three things close to zero, and then the one
remaining non-zero coefficients is recognizable as
four thirds with a little less precision. And this
can show us the relationship between this, the
output and the. The terms that appear in the
polynomials highest power term in this case and
and Cuba term in this, Kubelik fit as the first
coefficient and the index zero the and squared
term has the second coefficient. The end term for
the linear dependence has that third coefficient
of the closet intercept is the very last one. So
if I undo those changes, I could just as well have
generalized this by saying that the intercept is
always going to be the last element of this output
array and then the linear still interceded is the
second to last index minus two, which gets us back
to where we started. And that also provides
through this that part of the library that we
looked at for the histogram.
A set of tools to plot these results, in addition
to the data points that walk length and l values
that we showed up here and put into the fit with
some options for how they are to appear. It's
reasonably straightforward to. Continuous
functions. On top of those points where the trick
is to. Come up with some densely spaced set of
points along that x axis, ranging from zero to 80
in this case and steps of zero point one. There
are going to be a hundred points in this in the
array that this. A range routine provides. And
then by some of Python's Magic, the. We can define
happy for that function to be just the cause of a
times X plus the cost of B, which automatically
inherits the same array dimensions as an X, and
sorry for all the documentation that keeps popping
up when I don't move the mouse quickly enough. So
plotting then those points X and the P that are
produced from them juice, that orange line that we
can check by is in perfect agreement with the data
points computed above. So that's. How fitting or
at least polynomial fitting works in Python? It's
also possible to. Fits, there are Pythonic
utilities out there that without much more work
than this, can fit a set of data to essentially
any function. You can like that. As long as you
can write down period for that function, you will
use that to minimize the deviations between the
data points and the filter constructs.
Which this demo doesn't get into since then,
there's a trick that can be used to simplify it
into some types of fits. For instance, if we were
looking at this data and we were thinking, well.
It looks pretty linear as.
As the clock length dependence on the number of
steps that maybe we don't want to assume it's
linear. We could. Either fit it to some polynomial,
as we did in Kubic case just a few minutes ago, or
try to fit this as a general Powerwall, which is
to say fitting L is proportional to the number of
steps to some unknown power alpha. And try to
extract from that the power elfa describing the
leading dependence of this fit on an. So this
automatically implements what we already knew,
that when N equals zero equals zero net
intercepted, the linear fit vanishes that's
imposed here. And this is actually well, as I said,
it's certainly possible to use Python to fit to it
in the Powerwall. But it's already possible to do
this using that same. Polynomial fit that we are
looked at just by taking the log of both sides and
using the properties of the log to pull down that
power on in as the coefficient on a log in term.
Plus, this multiplicative factor C, which becomes
a coefficient Moxey. So in terms of what rythm
about the logarithm and this is just a linear
function, Y equals Alpha times X, so it's a
constant.
And in Python, we implement this is. Setting a
blog of that array of what lengths from 10 to 80
of the law of the walk like this, the number of
steps this here is the actual distance that is
traveled by the walk and then just fit that to
another linear fit where I can generalize this to
pull out those last two.
Elements of the output array that correspond to
the coefficients of the polynomial being fit, and
we find that. So Alpha, then, is the coefficient
of the linear term, it comes out to be one, two,
maybe better precision than we had any right to
expect, about five significant figures from that
quick 10 second calculation. And see, then, is the
exponential of the constant term, which we expect
to be from the work above that mean of the single
step probability distribution. And indeed. That is
recovered again to into terbil level precision and
the thought that we put out looks essentially the
same as the linear fit because it essentially is a
linear fit. I'm just putting that power law types
of our alpha rather than what is exactly a
straight line.
So that is what is in the Python program in
general, any questions about anything that's come
up so far or.
Anything else to do with that computer project
next Thursday?
Goodness. So.
With that. I guess crash course through Python
programming dealt with in some time related. There
are some funny things we can do this afternoon
that build up upon some of the stuff that. Came up
this morning, so there are two options.
Which I made, one of which may be best to postpone
until next week, when we'll have talked a bit
about Serling's the. But only a passing.
What we can go to now is.
Turnon.
This dog of.
One of the things we looked at this morning, which
was
a step. In the derivation of that second ball of
the animals.
I'm waiting for. He's got to make up.
Would this be better focused?
A.
Maybe that's the best it'll be able to do. We had
this equation twenty one.
Here we were just interested in establishing an.
That's reestablishing a lower bound of the
possible number of microstates, equivalently, the
entropy of the combined system that would be able
to say it was.
At least as large as the entropy of the two
subsystems treated independently, and it can
actually be interesting to dig into this overall,
also a bit more detail.
And try to.
Need some intuition or some appreciation for the
role of large numbers in statistical physics and
especially in. Its application to
the entry of two identical systems that are
combined and brought into triple contact, allowed
to exchange energy from one to the other.
So we have.
The rewrite. That's some. You talk about assistant
energy as the. Now, use of energy, the system when
you take. Timeously. Number of microstates in
system one with that energy. Multiplied by.
Microstates from System two, with that same
Hitachi's,
we cannot impose not only a lower bound. On this,
but also Benham's on both sides of. By supposing
that we know what the maximum term this is, so.
Let's.
I'm just trying to think of a good notation to
write this down.
But, Max. We find this to be the maximum value for
any value of each one of these products that we're
microstates and systems one and two with the
overall conservation of energy on the combined
system.
Adding up to some 60. Ben. You know, first of all,
that. This, Max, is only a single term in itself,
so just as with the case of. The independent
system is showing up in the election, we know that.
The song as a whole is at least as large as the
musical term limits, but because we have.
Identified this particular term as the largest
term, we also know that. This end has to be
smaller than the overall number of terms.
I would just call in terms of the risk of using
using an interest in many things, so the number of
terms. Times the word has turned into something so
that all is fairly obvious on.
And it is possible for this inequality to be
inequality can be saturated when every turn in the
sun, every one of those entrance terms has that
same maximum about.
And. In practice, some examples that. Illustrate.
What these gowns can be.
And as a.
In terms of absolute numbers, they are rather
large because we're always with large numbers of
degrees of freedom and responding with large
numbers of microstates, but the relative range
here can be surprisingly sharp.
Maybe a.
It's great that the.
This can be a relatively tight.
Now, the total number of microstates for combined
system and just as a.
Wolf.
A qualitative example.
We supposed. That subsystem has in degrees of
freedom, which is different. Well. You're going to
identify that with the number of terms in this.
Then we can expect that this is not a proof, but a
very handwaving quality, the argument can expect
that the.
On.
Maximum.
Number of microstates in this combined system
should have. Left room for Few's, exponentially
large in that number of degrees of freedom.
And also that the number of terms you can expect,
the number of hospital. Ways of distributing
energy between these two systems is going to
depend more. Like a linear dependence on a number
of degrees of freedom rather than the
exponentially large. No, microstates, so the
inequality. That we have with state of the usual
order, ten of twenty three. More coming from our
is no motivated for statistical physics, this
bound comes down to become.
Ten to the power.
Exponential even handed out twenty three squiggly
lines there.
So.
In absolute terms, there is a wide range of ten to
twenty three or twenty three orders of magnitude
from one side and. Of this inequality to the other,
if we look at the.
Entropies so. And requires taking the law of the
with microstates, you know that.
The logarithm of the exponential is just the
arguments. Twenty three is roughly smaller than
the entropy of this combined system, which we know
is roughly smaller than that same. By the end of
the twenty three.
Plus, the longer ten to the twenty three, which is.
What are those numbers that you get used to if you
do enough statistical physics, it's ten to twenty
three plus about 50. So the entropy here in here
coming from that range microstates is somewhere
between ten to the twenty three instead of twenty
three point fifty, which is to a very good
approximation, still ten to twenty three. So in
relative terms. There's a very narrow band of
entropies, and indeed we can say, is that the. The
single next midterm in the summer, all
possibilities. Provides a good approximation, it
almost separates the whole entropy of this whole
system. And this is going ahead with the arguments
sort of claiming that the.
Numbers of microstates scale exponentially the
numbers, its renewable energy scale linearly. And
this is something that you can actually compute
for yourself in a in some simple examples, which.
We will get a start on that for the remainder of
today and check in on that. How things are doing
next week, I'll show I was able to come up with
four. An example of this or more specific. Example
of these sorts of battles. Or. Suppose we have a
system, one is.
Ten of those two states spends. In that magnetic
field, we are for convenience with a set age to be
born that. So that's he drops out of expressions,
we know that the energy one you see it is minus
two times the number of spins that align with that
magnetic field, minus the total number of spins.
To those in parentheses, the minus age, which is
one stays out, sorry about that. And that will
also be.
The identical system for. That's to to the energy
of system two is that same?
Mine is twice.
Plus, it's just a one minus the. And it ten in
each system.
So
we bring these two systems together.
And allow them to exchange energy in verbal
contact.
And. Fixing the total energy one plus two to be a
C minus 10.
The question is.
What do those inequality's?
What our inequalities.
For the balance on.
The Entropa.
Compared to the true entropy, so that spin comes
from approximating the total number of microstates
in the combined system just by being the single
largest. Term in the overall somewhere in this mix
comes from. Approximating every single term in
that cell to be maximally large.
And that is the question I will. Back to you to go
to work out for the next 10 minutes and possibly
the next week, depending on how quickly we're able
to get through it, and then we can generalize.
To. The situation, if. And he pulls 20 or 40 or
higher numbers. In. Each of those systems.
Still with the total
combined energy fixed.
So you have to keep that on the screens.
Sorry that this kid was not projecting as well as
it ought to, hopefully. As I talked through that
cell, it made enough sense for you to follow up on
any questions about that task.
What was that? Yeah, that's why I the.
Turn the lights away. What I can do is repeat at
least the test itself on the word.
Stood on this side of the border, should be
checked out in that was made here so
we could have a system number one
to
10 spins
and then
falling behind. That projector which I made.
It's true that it not eligible for.
So what to do, they're going to contact.
Utah energy that
you want
to
to.
There was some positive news that wasn't equal to
one.
And from the building arguments that we just went
through.
Showed how in the colonies,
the
entropy of this combined system can be executed by
considering both the.
Single distribution of these interviews with the
largest number of microstates, as well as keeping
track of the number of homes missing,
and that gives us more than the average.
It's also not too hard in this situation with just
about 10 minutes to determine the crew
as well, and
that we would find if we assume that every term in
the sub had its maximum value and we had prepared,
how good about this one comes first for any of
those 10 which can be dealt with just a bit of.
Computation by hand, binomial coefficients will
become useful, and if that is done,
you.
Or larger numbers of students in each of the two
systems still with the same strategy.
So.
Or at least pause the recording and stop talking
to.
I get the sense that done at this point, there was
not much time left over after that happened and
the.
Introduction to the problem, so I'll leave it to
you to think about it. We can pick up with it this
time next Friday
or over the weekend, on Monday.