Well, there are the bells marking the hour, so we'll
start getting underway, first with that usual six-digit number for you to plug in:
three nine one, six two eight.  I'll leave that up there.
Welcome back to week four and
hopefully a bit better weather over the coming few
days than over the last few.
In terms of logistics, we have
on the twenty-
first
of February
I can mention that as it is weuk four, that week-three
mini-questionnaire has run its course. So
thanks for all of you who sent in feedback and
information about how things are going on there.
The consensus seems to be that there are no major
issues with this module, at least so far. The
average feeling was the pace was just a little
faster than slow. Difficulty was a little more
difficult than easy, which is about the level I
think is appropriate for a math three hundred
level module. To be more interesting was the
homework assignment that I was using to try to get
the focus on this projector there. So that is now.
Available on canvas, due a week from Thursday, the
end of March 3rd May. Spend some time looking at
that in the editorial this Friday. What else we
have to. Entertain ourselves with may also look at
the. First part of the computer project, if the
issues showed up there as I go through that
marking, which may or may not be completed at that
point. And I should say there was some interesting
discussion over the weekend revisiting some of the
topics we were talking about over the past couple
of weeks in terms of how there is moves, large
scale macroscopic behavior emerges from the equal
probability of all the various micro states in the
canonical ensemble. Are there any questions from
anyone here about that or any other topics we've
seen so far?
Just as a reminder, a quick recap of where we are
right now, and we will be going to the focus on
the canonical ensemble last week.
This is. The approach, this statistical ensemble
that we get, if we are able to fix the temperature
and the number of degrees of freedom in our system,
and we went through somewhat detailed mathematical
justification for how the temperature can be fixed
even while being the first law of thermodynamics
concerning the total energy of the universe. By
coupling the system to enlarge, the reservoir
imposes that fixed temperature. And one of the key
outcomes of that mathematical derivation was the
definition of the precision function for the
canonical ensemble condition called Z, which sums
over all of the microstates of the system. And
this so-called Boltzmann's factor, the exponential
of negative data times the energy of that micro
state where beta is. Something we identify with
the inverse temperature, all of this in
thermodynamic equilibrium obtained by maximizing
the entropy, we zoom out and hope that things
remain. Visible, this thinking.
From this Patricia function, there is so called
free energy specifically attributed to Helmholtz,
which pulls out of the.
Logo of Z times, the negative temperature, which
provides them some compact expressions for drive
quality, is an economical approach, including the
average internal energy, which is no longer fixed
thanks to thermal contact with the large thermal
reservoir. This is a derivative with respect to
beat a bit at times F and eventually. Which is the
negative derivative derivative with respect to
temperature of that free energy and by itself and
what we are doing today is looking at these
particular observable derived quantities in two
similar situations that will differ only by the
amount of information that is. Present is is
knowable in principle in the systems we are
looking at.
This is where we left off last time we started
looking at the behavior of spins and I saw our
usual two state degrees of freedom spin's pointing
out we're down the mathematics of the coins and
energy given by coupling to an external magnetic
field of strength. Pinche.
Wonder if
was
once a
little
more.
Maybe just a little speak up if anything is clear,
to see if you need to clarify whatever is up there
are looking first. And so it's been six and
astounded that we can distinguish from one another
by looking at their position in the summer. They
basically have an address that experimenter can
focus on in order to tell which STEM is pointing
up, which is pointing down the precision function.
Our starting point with the approach is that the
sum over all possible orientations of all and of
the system. Which ends up boiling down to a fairly
compact expression, two times the hyperbolic
cosine of the dimensionless, a bit at times the
magnetic field strength divided by the temperature,
all of that with the overall factor of. Negative
temperature or negative on the health reality,
then? Brings in the logarithm of that molecules of
the power and with that overall factor of
temperature that I was jumping ahead to. So we
pick up from here, we are basically left in the
position of. Carrying out. A. Few quick
computations to extract the observers that we want,
starting with. The energy.
Let's see. How this derivative. She was up on the
projector. This is hopeless, I may have switched
you up on the board at the expense of the
recording, possibly having a harder time capturing
things on.
You're taking, as I mentioned, to recap the
derivative with respect to the temperature of the
times. So the overall factor would be the
consistent whatever data and we are left with that
constant negative end up front and then data. But
the more the rhythm of the hyperbolic cosine of
the H, they're just churning through the chain
rule. The arguments in the water rhythm comes down
to the denominator. Synecdoche. Get agent and
chamber will takes the derivative. Of the argument,
the water in which is twice the hyperbolic sign of
an age. And finally, the derivative of the
argument of that sign with respect to data is just
an additional factor of age.
Was canceled and we are left with minus in times
age with the, of course, being that hyperbolic.
Tangent. Of Bayridge.
So it looks like the.
Exonerating art is more valuable than the text,
since you can check that text in the PDF a printed
copies. You have what really should be good to
proceed. So we have the energy for these
distinguishable stains or the average internal
energy being negative and types of fuel, strange
types of hyperbolic tangents of middle age. And
from this we can pretty much immediately write
down the entropy that is always related to the
average internal energy. Minus the Helmholtz free
energy, but multiply it by an overall factor of
inverse temperature. So there are just two terms
here, baiba times.
Minus 10, the range that we have from the energy
and then the better times this negative and want
to caution each of the three energy. So you have
these two challenges.
Hyperbolic charges, plus the water with the
otherwise hyperbolic. Cosine. Which is a bit
awkward. You look like an idiot. This is how those
functions look if we normalize by those three
factors. So both internal energy and entropy are
extensive quantities so we can divide through by
the number of degrees of freedom in the system and
and also normalize the energy by that external
magnetic field strength. So that is the limit of.
Zero temperature, it reduces two to one, I should
say, divided by just plain numbers to appear on
these vertical axis and similarly this horizontal
axis is that. Ratio of temperature and magnetic
field strength to your average is one over the age.
So as the temperature goes to zero, we have data
heading to infinity and as the temperature itself
and the inverse goes to zero, the. Way to proceed
and start making sense of these complicated
equations for energy and entropy in terms of
tensions and clashes and so on, is to extract the
asymptotic behavior and the approach to
the temperature. And as I started to say, as we
take that temperature to zero and lot debate that
goes off to infinity, that both the Cinching Kosh
approach to the X, the ratio of them is detached,
which approaches one. There's a nice and that
leaves us with negative one with the energy in
that low temperature limit where bid age becomes
very large. And this, of course, corresponds to
exactly that same energy that. We computed with
Biggie about systems previously, all of the skins
here are aligned with the magnetic field or
contributing a negative unit of light of speech to
the energy. So this Grasset Energy is the stage
that we divide out to the.
And we also saw that real estate energy at the
ground state is a single microstates. So it is
reasonable to see that the entropy at the top of
this page here is heading to zero, which
corresponds to the the logarithm of what we can
see this from that complicated expression in terms
of consciousness, Wongs of Koshetz, that's what we
saw the potential as to one, the water rhythm of
twice hyperbolic cosine approaches, just the water
rhythm of that E to the H, which is Bureij and the
relative negative side, three, two times cancel.
Confirming our intuition that if a single
microstates in the ground state, we had an
Entropia on zero.
So that at least narrows down the asymptotic low
temperature limit, what is called. Absolutely zero,
where generally the statistical systems freeze in
a single micro states with management effort. And
again, this is a key feature of the economic cycle
where we can adjust this temperature and get the
energy as a driver observable rather than focusing
on the energy and extracting the temperature the
way we did the microeconomics case. We can build
on. It's just this somewhat trivial limit of
absolute zero with a single microstates and
entropy, by considering how the system approaches
that that limits for a little bit non-zero
temperatures there. And the canonical approach are
bowsman factor.
Either the mindless energy over you is now no
longer just zero for any. System by the state,
except for the lowest energy ground state, we have
this non-zero probability of finding the system.
In some of those higher energy microstates, the
first of which we looked at again back in Unit two.
So about this time last we saw that just putting a
single spin in this extraordinary field led to the
next available energy. Of minus eight times and
minus two. Where this is going to be called in
terminology, I may use to think of the first
excited state where the states are being talked
about here are different from the microstates. So
any particular. Energy state, energy level. Try to
call it in correspondence, you will be realized by
many different micro states in these statistical
systems. And in the case of certain systems, at
least all of these energy levels are going to be
I'm going to differ from each other by the same
procedure, we just put one more spin to align
against the magnetic field, increasing the overall
energy by two units out of the total. And so the
energy gap between every pair of subsequence
energy levels is this constant factor of two times
that it feels right. We also did see back in. In
Unit two. So.
With that said, that reminder of how all of our
microstates.
Or falling into energy levels with a constant
spacing between them. We can.
Consider this limit of low, but nonzero
temperature is a bit age is not infinite, but it
is much larger than one, which means that this
exponential, either the minus beta age that's
appearing in these Courchesne attaches is a very
small number that we can use. A consistent
expansion, so. Just to see how that works. We'll
break down again the result that we have, that
energy we divide up and we're just left with the
negative hyperbolic tangent. A better age. Which
is the negative ratio of simulcasts, the one minus.
This exponential factor E to the minus, to the age
of the one plus exponential growth needed to be at
age.
Which if we expand in the geometric series, one
over one plus X is approximately equal to one plus
X plus X squares of the numerator comes along for
the ride.
And that denominator expands to approximately one
minus E minus tumed H plus quarter of this small
number squared, which would be of the minus four
of H, which will neglect for now. So is that
approach, that calculation fairly familiar, the
expansion of one of the one four six as this power
series of X?
There are. No objections that I see, and at this
point, all that remains is.
Expanding this productive terms, so we have an
overall minus one out front and then two factors
of minus E to the minus to the age coming from the
cross turns the negative up front. That's a plus
to. Even to. In an age, I'll just leave it there,
neglect the higher order, temperature dependent
terms I can identify. This twice the age as the
energy gap, so we recover that asymptotic absolute
zero limit of the energy in these units
approaching negative one, and then we see that for
small but not zero temperatures. It.
Increases, there's a positive contribution that is
exponentially suppressed by the energy gap
compared to this low temperature. And this results
here matches up and should. Still a contract of.
The level at which we start collecting turns.
So we reproduce a result, we were targeting that.
He's excited to see the effects, so the influence
on the energy of our system from microstates other
than the grounds to include higher energy use are
exponentially suppressed in the face of the energy
gap between these energy levels and that. Turns
out to be a generic feature of economical systems
with a non-zero energy gap.
And at least the qualitative quantitative
calculation that you have extracted, all of it,
admitting that having gone through that we can
recognize this exponential dependence as.
Consistent with or being motivated by the
exponential Boltzmann factor that is appearing in
the probabilities. So it's probably going to be
proportional to the minus stuff I look at ratios
and probabilities. It is that's a difference
between the energies that comes out from the
properties of the exponential.
We can show you the. Same sort of calculation
expansion for. The entropy.
And this here, if we divide by then, is that a
factor of better over at times the internal energy
we just computed, minus the number three energy?
So putting in the expansion that we have been over
and for the energy was minus one, plus two each,
the minus beta energy gap, plus border either
minus two. Beta energy, gamma.
And the parenthesis did not go there have to.
Subtract the three hours, which was minus one,
plus one over Beita for sorry, it over Beda times,
that logarithm of my standing on the screen twice.
Hyperbolic, cosine h there is the other end of
that parenthesis, so you've already done the
expansion for one of these factors, the expansion
for the free energy. This is the one.
Twice the hyperbolic cosine of age, if we. Cloud
the E to the plus the age factor from the
definition of hyperbolic cosine. You're left with
one plus E to the minus to be the H. And then
distributing the law, the of a product is the sum
of the logs in the blink of an exponential is just
its arguments. So this equals B, the H plus the
logarithm of one, plus our small number, which we
can expand already as that small number is a minus
Tubin H plus order, that small number squared
minus four to eight, which is also where our
expansion to the energy.
When we start churning out terms, so putting all
of these. Together and the expression of love we
have. At the end over in. Is. I would have.
You have the missing factor.
Each because without have the expression up here
is the energy divided by at a time stage here, we
just want. Energy over and cancel those games in
overall factor of age there and there. So now I'm
happier with the units on this expression.
Kim. S..
That was minus one here is kids better divided by
its bitter. And then I have.
Two terms here.
A minus or sorry, a.
Close to each, Peter.
Times E to the minus, to Delta E from the
expansion of the energy and then just to the
radiation that you can convince them to be only.
The single E to the minus two bit H e from the
free energy and then all of the other terms and
order to the minus to.
Beta of the energy here, is that what you want to
define is to each. Is the energy out there to be
useful of the
things we said to their terms that we have to get
them all exponentially suppressed the energy gap
compared to an absolute zero limit on the
vanishing entropy, the one of these exponentially
suppressed terms has a slight counteracting effect
from the non zero. They will delta itself, which
is not going to change the quality of the behavior
of the functions. You can see going back to. These
plots showing them that low energy, there's both
this exponentially fast approach to the symbolic
limits, despite the different prefectures in both
cases. So that is. What we can learn about the low
temperature of bit of this system of distinguished
hospitals, the. Are there questions out there
about the calculations that should get a bit messy
going through the mind or about the.
The quality of. Information to take away that an
exponentially fast conversions to the limit of
absolute zero in terms of the energy gap between
subsequent energy levels, the system.
Moving on to forget the other one that we have in
here, where the temperature goes to infinity,
which corresponds to the ground zero. This one
will turn out to be a bit more straightforward and
less messy. This is high temperatures, but not
infinitely high temperatures where now these low
parameter that we can work with is exactly the
speed of age itself. As the temperature becomes,
margins of risk become small. And for the internal
energy we have to do is the usual Taylor series
expansion provided its. I've been a bit of the
leading term state agent and plus one third the
human factor, and we can expect things to come the
full power of the age. And as the temperature goes
to infinity, this term goes like minus H over T
varnishing. Like one over tea, which is in fact
what we saw in the Michael Campbell case when we
fixed the temperature predicted and we fixed the
energy predicted, the temperature coming from the
independence of the entropy of the energy. We saw
that. The temperature very like minus teenage
poverty, and as the energy went to zero, the
temperature diverged and the same thing is going
on here. The energy is vanishing as the
temperature, but it's the same relationships with
the role of dependent and independent variables
clipped
into the entropy. You can start off with that same.
Calculation, I'll go ahead and distribute the as
it is to the energy and the free energy in this
expression so that it's easier to keep track of
them. Just as before you plug in. The. Expansion
for the High-temperature energy here, there is
another factor of. Each to account for the overall
factor of data. So the first term we have minus
data squared and then the next term disappeared a
few times at age times, data over. And and is
accounted for. I'll just call it something of
order given to the 4th began just days before the
the over the free energy. Is just the horn of
twice the hyperbolic cosine. We're doing a
different expansion of the arguments of this law
and the limits where Bureij becomes very small,
all of the very large hyperbolic cosine has its
usual.
Power, serious expansion. You can pull off this
particular factor of the one, two plus. One of the
court itself, which we know is one plus 1/2 times
its arguments squared, plus order of the argument
to the fourth power.
Which we can then expand the log log of one plus a
small number is at the beginning of that small
number itself getting up to be age to the fourth.
So putting these terms together, the interview
ends up with a. One or two, and then plus one half
billion squared, minus eight squared, leaves us
with a negative one half. It declared in the
corrections. An ordinary village to the fourth
power.
Which is what is written below and. You see, that
has happened here goes to infinity and zero. This
approach is this constant value of two, which is
where it is heading to. Up on the screen, you're.
Check the numerical value matches up. With the
election there. Which is, in fact, exactly what we
can recognize for. The microeconomic ensemble of
all to the end of the microstates in the system
had the same energy and the entropy would just be
the of the debt and more to what we have here in
the a temperature regime. So we actually see the
canonical and canonical ensembles coming together
in this way, which we can interpret positively as.
The energy's coming from these experience,
interacting with that external metallic feel,
albeit negligible compared to the temperature. So
effectively, the system behaves as though every
microstates had the same energy independent of how
it spins for aligned compared to that external
fuel. The
technology neglected compared to the water
temperature that.
So that is. How all of these drives qualities
behave already for reasons of
temperature for the case, the distinction is
better solved. Well, if we have enough time, we
want to do that same sort of thing for
indistinguishable spins in the middle, which will
be distinguishable by virtue of being in a gas of
spin. So the idea here comes a pause. As for any
final questions about the distinguishable case.
And move on to the contrast, so we are considering
nearly the same setup we have and spins into a
dynamic equilibrium, get an external magnetic
field of strength, each that determines the energy
of any configuration of these spins. Only now
rather than. Identifying these things with sea
molecules in a solid position is fixed and can be
identified and distinguished from each other. We
said that the spoons are free to move as though
they were particles in a one dimensional gas.
And we will assume that need movement that they're
doing is slow so that the energy continues to be
defined by their interactions with this magnetic
field and in the kinetic energy that they have is
negligible. So when we look at them, you will just
see the same sort of.
Google stands in that extra room in Edgefield.
The difference being compared to the
distinguishable case, we can't reliably say that.
If we look at the second and third steps here and
we look back whether the second and third spins
are still in the same positions that they were
before, we can keep track of where these things
are. They can move freely past each other. And.
There's no way to assign a label to them or know
that by looking at a particular position in this
line, we will pick out a particular step.
So what we have to do in this case, as always, is
start by computing the petition function, which is
a set of goals and factors over all the
microstates of the system. And the question now is,
what are the microstates of the system? What we
can no longer distinguish between. Cases where a
certain spin is pointing a certain way versus
another has been pointed the same way since May
well have been indistinguishable and the
microstates side cannot pretend that we have
information. About which is pointing which way.
In other words, because the spins on this motion,
all the federations. Also are indistinguishable,
at least in the case. That they have the same
energy or the same number of downward would spins.
So we saw this the beginning of this year, but you
get the replica. To configurations of spins, one
up and one down. And the order in which one is up,
one is down can no longer be distinguished. So
both of those configurations are a single
microstates.
The. Solution to how to cut electricity or
something. I actually said already in that little
spiel, just what we can distinguish is the total
number of operating expenses corresponding to the
total energy, which is now the only way we are
able to identify which micro state is which. Each
micro state has a one to one correspondence with
the energy that comes from how many schemes are
pointing out versus how many are down.
So.
We can organize all of these microstates in order
to take the sun in the petition function just by.
Enumerating the materials that are available, do a
quick example with just four foreskins should be
true enough to fit in this gap. And in the time
that remains
where. The microstates that we have to respond to
the five values that the energy of these this
Forssmann system can take to the ground, state
energy is minus four times age and there is a
constant energy gap between all of the higher
energy levels that electricity with that
corresponds to energy minus to two energy, zero
energy plus to age with a higher energy state that
has plus four age and.
Out of the possible spin configurations, in this
case, keeping the magnetic field, pointing out
that the ground state is all for spins aligned
with its highest energy state. Somebody has, of
course, been RNC aligned. And with each higher
energy level, one of those spins is flipped and we
cannot. Distinguish between. We cannot determine
which stand is flat because they are
indistinguishable, so all the permutations of that
collapse to a single microstates.
And similarly. As we have.
Two or three spins pointing down.
So some of these microstates you can simulate some
of these energy values, the state energy plus the
energy gap time, some integer, which, you know,
ranges from zero. We have the real state up to an
inclusive for that highest energy state. So this
gives us and plus one that total microstates for
any particles imaginable where you can have the
partition function for these indistinguishable
particles. Is the sun over those endless one
bowsman factors, even the better times and minus
Tulk? Which if we pull out that constables would
refactor it to the end of each. We can. Recognize
that this is the seed of the virus to their age is
the fixed quantity to the virus, to their age
raised to the cave power to destroy the sun, which
turns out to be. A ratio of this exponential one
minus. Even minus two times, that was one bit over
one minus due to the minus two. So this is another
manifestation of that symmetric series that popped
up in the case of distinguishable stands, one over
one minus X, at least one X is less than one is
for this exponential. That is equal to the sum of
powers to the K from K to infinity. And the fact
that this song has to be cut off to our total
number of particles just means that we saw or
subtract the similar song from Kate, ranging from
Air Force One up to infinity if we extract an axe
to the end of this one. From that second summer,
get another geometric series just with that
overall factor of the year plus one leading to an
equation for.
So.
I think I will try to speed through the rest of
this unit in the few remaining minutes, there's a
quick exercise to take the logarithm of this
equation. Forty four, which will bring in three
terms corresponding to the three factors being
multiplied, multiplied by each other. And on that
homework assignment that's now available. You can.
Take this towards free energy through the
calculation to determine that internal energy and
entropy and the high temperature limits so we can
look at to wrap things up today, here is how the
results that you're going after compare with the
case of distinguishable particles that we spent a
fair amount of time computing in some detail. So
for the energy normalized by the end times, it
gets the same. Temperature over H. The story lines.
Are the same distinguishable results that we
disputed in some detail already in the solid blue
line is now the indistinguishable result coming
from this new setup where the spinners are. I
guess I can move freely through each other, what
we can see is that although the. Zero temperature
limit of absolute zero is the same. As soon as the
temperature is not zero a. Clearly observable
difference in this observable quantity of.
And. Even though there is still exponential
approach to that after the zero minutes.
There is a measurable or an observable difference
in the energy of these systems, depending solely
on their information content, whether the spirits
are distinguishable. And maybe the most striking
difference is. What happens with the entropy
normalize by in high temperatures, where if we
recall that for the distinguishable case, this was
approaching? The logarithm of two. And what is
happening? In the. In this case, there's actually
an approach to.
The. Voyeurism of an endless one over in. By and
so even in the. Have some high your limit with the
energy's all come together.
For the same reason that the temperature dominates
and the system is essentially microeconomic, all
items are. There is a exponentially smaller number
of microstates leading to the suppress entropy for
the in this case.
In. The conclusion takeaway here is you have
rushed through a bit of the second calculation is
just that. For two physical systems, identical in
all aspects except their information, contact with
their hands are distinguishable or not in
principle. Was it measurable, physical difference
in the internal energy? Or in other words,
information is physical. Which is the takeaway
message provided by physicist Wolf Landauer just a
few decades ago, so this investigation is about
information in physics is recent. And even ongoing
research. That shows up even in the simple case of
the spin systems that we're using as our most
basic example. So.
I will stop there for today. Next time is of the
essence of generalizing from. This week's belongs
to continuously moving particles in some container
that will be maybe a bit more obviously physical,
a bit more familiar.
Are there any questions about the canonical
ensemble background or the physics of information
that you looked at today?
The site was shut down recording. See you tomorrow
morning, also heading to my office hours right now.
Questions come to mind.