OK, that should be the recording underway, so we can
get going. There's a few people connected by
Zoom in addition to the smaller crowd today.
Imagine I saw some of you were up a bit late last
night working on the computer project, which is
now through.  The next homework assignment due in a
couple more weeks, should be available on the
weekend, finishing touches on that. And, of course,
there's a forecast for unpleasant weather later
today. Well, it's sunny and calm at the moment.
That's how weather forecasts go, but set that
aside, get underway with CNN attendance monitoring.
Members of the. Three, two.
We.
And then they'll resume with the set up of the
canonical ensemble. So it's been a few days with a
computer project in between. Let's do a quick
recap of what we did earlier this week. So.
There is the visible.
After.
Ramped up the micro ensemble on Monday and moved
into.
Somewhat more natural and more tractable
economical ensemble.
So far, just developing some of the. Formalism and.
Defining characteristics for this self where you
bring in you have to see some of this sort of
demonic about the reminder of the differences
between microeconomic or ensemble's. We're in the
microbiological case, we directly impose the
conservation.
Of energy. What's called the first law of
thermodynamics, which requires that the systems we
consider be completely isolated from the rest of
the universe. You're showing some insulation
around a closed container filled with some
particles that have some some number of particles
and the total energy, both of which are conserved.
And in the canonical case, we. Remove the.
Condition that the system be completely isolated
from the rest of the universe and instead of
directly imposing conservation of energy.
We allow the system to exchange energy with its
surroundings and.
Demand that those surroundings.
Chokepoints visible despite being zoomed out of
the surroundings, fix a constant touch in addition
to the possible.
Now, this is much closer to the sorts of everyday
situations that you would want to work with and
also turns out to be more natural and convenient
for analysis just is the reason why we didn't do
so many examples or analysis with microeconomic.
All of us looking at spin systems and seeing that
the. Temperature can be can behave naturally, but
can also exhibit some strange behavior like
singularities and negative values. So in the
canonical case, once we finish building up this
groundwork, we will see how we can.
Fix the temperature on. Rather than the energy.
And fixing the temperature. But also demanding the
first lawsuit and the cancellation of the total
energy of the universe.
Requires this system being verbal contact with a
large. External thermal reservoir.
Which has this characteristic temperature that the
system picks up by virtue of this double contact.
Now, what we want is not to have to worry about
what that thermal reservoir is or maybe just see
that it's there is playing the role of fixing the
temperature and we don't care about it beyond that.
And the way we are, I guess, in the process of
managing that is what's known as the replica trick
introduced by Gears
in the skills and contacts for the form of that
thermal reservoir
that we want to show will be.
We'll drop out of all of the defendants and all
the characteristics of the system that we are
interested in.
The focus here a bit better.
So having imposed this on Zazi, we want to. Turn
the crank on, derive the properties of the system,
which if they're independent of the reservoir and
the way that we are proceeding with that is
imposing thermal equilibrium.
By maximizing. The Entropia.
Subject to constraints on that conservative total
energy, which.
It's time to come back to the actual building in
which that process was underway, and maybe I
should highlight here before just to emphasize the
importance of one of the things that popped out of
that interview maximization was the appearance of
the canonical petition function.
Which is the sum over all microstates of an
exponential factor of times, what is now at the
gross multiplier multiplied the energy of that
microstates exponentially, the negative side. What
we have here, which is going to turn out to be.
The fundamental starting point for analysis and
the canonical ensemble, so that gets us back to
more or less would be more and more questions
about the current state of things. What we did
earlier this week.
That's coming in terms either so.
We didn't quite have time to get through the.
Conclusion to this calculation on one day,
remember that on Tuesday when we last met, we were
aiming for an expression for the temperature of
the overall. Universe, the system of combined with
the thought of, is in contact with in order to get
that temperature in the microeconomic approach
that describes the overall universe with conserve
energy, we need to take the derivative of the
entropy with respect to the considerable energy.
And that energy comes from counting the total
number of microstates, maximizing it for thermal
equilibrium. Which is.
The condition that we have imposed miscalculation
and we got to the point of computing the
expression for the entropy in terms of the
logarithm of the partition function, plus this
other parameter, bita times that total energy of
ours, the number of replicas that we have in the
system plus several reservoir. So this is the
quantity that we want to take the derivative with
respect to that whole entity that we argued last
time that we have to include in this the
derivative of these. Parameters that have been
introduced into the modified entropy to capture
constraints on the probabilities so that data and
the prediction function. We are now viewing as
functions of this total energy, so when we take
the derivative of this expression, some of the
terms are easy. The. Total eight times better.
Just gives us a better front, but then we have to
use the product rule and worry about the energy
derivative of that parameter data, as well as the
energy derivative of the logarithm of the
parameters. And that, in turn, depends on better
sort of tracking through the chamber rule.
Derivative of the log is one of its arguments over
his head with the customer up front. And then we
take the derivative of the argument of the law
with respect to the parameter. It depends on the
user data and to get the overall energy out of our
pulling through. We have a debate on DFT energy,
which is the major problem that we've defined. So
one of the final steps in this calculation is
figuring out this one derivative of Z with respect
to detail, which is straightforward enough to
compute plugging in. The expression for the
British function we have from Tuesday just is no
microstates of the exponential minus speed of
times energy derivative with respect to better
than closedown, a negative energy for each micro
state we can recognize.
From also earlier in this page, the. Whatever is
that factor times the exponential speed of times
energy. So what is appearing in this interview?
The expression. Is. Despite the probability the
occupation. I believe I should say that this
particular crusade is realized by one of the
replicas in this overall system.
So plugging that in then gives us a sum over all
microstates of the occupation, probability of
times, the corresponding energy, which again from
earlier work, we can relate to the total energy
divided by the number of Republicans. So it's like
this result into where it appears in our
expressions for the average temperature for the
Hubble. It's actually become much simpler than
they might have looked up till now, whatever
temperature is just below. And now we have reached
the goal of this whole analysis. We have
expressions for all of the parameters that appear
in the probabilities for our system of interest
with no reference to any details of the thermal
reservoir. There are no more factors of our than
of Republicans. There are no more extensive
quantities that add up among all those Republicans,
like the overall energy or part of the number of
Republicans. What we have is. Just expressions for.
The temperature in terms of the parameters that
appear defining thermal equilibrium by maximizing
the entropy that up in the petition functions in,
so plugging in its relation that the beta
parameter is the inverse of the temperature, we
can rewrite that particular function as some of
the microstates of the exponential. Of minus the
energy divided by the fixed temperature.
That is. The only remaining input from the last
album Reservoir we're in contact with. And
similarly, the probabilities are also just that
same exponential factor mobilized by the
partnership function itself.
With this calculation done, all all the features
of the thermal reservoir having dropped out, we
can see that we're talking about our system of
interest, that omegle with microstates and with
corresponding probabilities, with no reference to
any details of the thermal sample. There's a
reservoir that is fixing the temperature and
beyond fixing the temperature. No, I have no
information about that thermal reservoir is even
knowable in the canonical approach. I just have
this particular probability distribution, which is
known depending on which side of the Atlantic I
happen to be on is either bowsman or Gibs
distribution. And the factor of the exponential of
the negative energy caused by temperature itself
is always known as the bottom factor. So it
becomes exponentially suppressed as the energies
become very large compared to the temperature. And
we can also see that. There is a connection that
can be made to microeconomic ensemble here that if
we were to fix the energies of all these
microstates, the way that we had to propose in the
microeconomic ensemble with an isolated system of
being conservation of energy, then all these
probabilities with the equal energy would result
in equal probability, just as we saw for
throughout the microeconomic context. So here we
are able to generalize this to let the energy vary
from state to state with a fixed temperature. So
that is the bubble development of the
microeconomic ensemble. With the petition function
and probabilities being the key. Characterising
factors that we can now apply to derive other
observables in terms of Sulpice here and see if
that whole somewhat extended argument we went
through introducing the replicator to the thermal
reservoir and then showing that it can be ignored.
Any questions about that or your objections to.
That overall approach.
So we have a bit a bit less where we're going
forward, especially next week when we start to
look at concrete realisations of systems covered
by the economic of what we've actually yet to
begin that later today. But the first step is to
build up things in full generality is driving some
of the. Interesting observables of measurable
quantities in terms of the fixed particle number
and fixed temperature of the canonical approach,
starting there with the internal energy of our
system, which is sort of turning around the micro
canonical rotation we went through about this time
last week where we fixed the energy and saw that
the temperature was derived as.
A prediction of the macroeconomic approach in the
classical ensemble, will we have the temperature
fixed, predicting the energy is going to be an
outcome rather than an input. And as we're saying,
with the thermal contact to the thermal reservoir,
the energy of the system is able to fluctuate, to
vary from microstates, microstates. So in order to
talk about anything stable and predictable in
thermodynamic equilibrium, we have to consider the
expectation value of the energy. For which we
apply the basic definition of what the expectation
is with the reminder that it depends on the fixed
temperature, expectation, value. The energy is
just the sum of the microstates of the energy of
each state, whether by the probability of the
system adopting that microstates that's coming
back from the first unit on the probability
definition's, it's like again. Now, the problem is
that we have computed gives this expression where?
We have. We saw over microstates of that
exponential Boltzmann factor, we divide the energy,
which is actually similar to something we saw just
on the previous page, albeit with a different
interpretation of the probabilities as
probabilities for a particular system of interest
to adopt a micro state rather than occupation.
Probabilities for what micro state we would be
likely to see for various replicas of those
replicas have now gone away and. We can interpret.
The same sort of calculation that we did now in
terms just of the system itself, so the derivative
of the one percent is one of resetting times, the
derivative with respect to data. The definition
for that as the sum of the microstates of each of
the minus. I am taking the derivative love you
just heard of that song,
you just end up with how of the negative energy
for each microstates is turning into some
exponential factor sticks around and we can then.
Replace the exponential factor by the
probabilities the negative side comes up front and
end up with. Now the average with the expectation
value for the internal energy of our economical
system related to the derivative of the log of the
partition function with respect to the inverse
temperature. And in this case, it was easier to
work with the inverse temperature and take a
derivative of better times rather than working
with the temperature, taking the derivative to
divide it by the temperature. It's easy enough to
use the chain rule to swap back and forth between
these two equivalent ways of expressing the
temperature, either directly or in terms of its
inverse. Theta just brings in a factor of negative
T squared relating to derivative. So it's.
Maybe a useful check to rerun that this derivative
computation in terms of the temperature rather
than its inverse. But given this relation now
between energy and official function, we can.
Note something interesting, which is already a
benefit to working in economic terms rather than
micro canonical and part of the reason why. The
canonical ensemble is called a canonical, ordinary
or typical approach, you want to ask what happens
to this internal energy related to the protection
function as the fixed temperature of the canonical
ensemble varies? This is similar to. The question
that we put in the opposite terms on the previous
year. No, not at all. Some of the.
How does the temperature of the number of
microstates depend on the energy available
biotechnical case here?
We can define it's called a heat capacity to be
directly this dependence of the energy on the
temperature. So just the derivative of the average
internal energy that we have an expression to
extract from the petition function improbabilities
and we can see, which I think will be included in
the homework for the next couple of weeks, that
this kid's capacity for an economical system is
always negative and turns out to be zero only in
special circumstances. And what this amounts to is
the. Statement that we will always be working with
so-called natural systems for the economical
approach imposes this natural behavior that we
expect at higher energies correspond to higher
temperatures and vice versa, which was only true
in certain situations in the canonical approach.
So just by changing the perspective to fix the
temperature rather than the energy, we have
avoided some of the strange behavior we
encountered with microeconomic ensemble. And we
don't have to worry about specifying whether or
not systems are natural that comes out of the
construction that we are putting in place. The
only problem will be an interesting one. The way
to show that the sea capacity is not negative is
to look at fluctuations of the energy about its
expectation of value and as a special case of a
fairly general of the size of the fluctuation,
dissipation or fluctuation response through. This
can be related to how the energy changes and
responds to a change in the temperature given by
the derivative of
the.
The terminology of calling that dissipation is
maybe a bit more dated because it's a relation
between the fluctuations of the energy in the sub
over microstates of the canonical ensemble.
Connected to the response of that energy to change
in some fixed control parameter, in this case the
temperature. He is going to be something useful to
explore.
So are there questions about. Internal energy or
heat capacity at this.
Sort of basic, almost definitional level and
economical on some level.
What other derived quantity that we will quickly
relate to the.
Expression's and. Partition function. And
probabilities that we have available is, of course,
the entropy. This is where we started driving.
Driving observables in the MicroCon approach is.
Just as important, if not more so, in the
canonical ensemble that we're directly maps on to
day
situations and the general definition of the
entropy that is independent of what ensemble we
consider, what quantity is fixed. Is this what we
started off with last week as some of the
microstates of this very transparent, opaque,
non-transparent product of the probability times
their lord?
So that's coming from that equation to see what we
need to do is just insert the probabilities that
we have for the canonical ensemble and as in a
previous calculations, turns out to be. Quicker
just to expand the logarithm and keep the other
factor of the probabilities floating around for
the time being. So the probability that the system
is in microstates, I. With energy, Eastby is.
That's both the distribution and then the
calculation follows through from the properties of
that law. So the.
More to the product is the sum of the logs and the
border, the inverse is the biggest. So we have a
negative Wanstead and then the of the exponential
function is going to bring down a negative data. I
can't let you go go negative, Simon.
And some of the I p e. The negative signs cancel
here as well. The mindset is constant, as with
some of the microstates. So we just have this
first term sum of all probabilities has to go to
one. And in the second term, we recognize the
expectation value.
For the internal energy, so we become a logarithm
of the petition function plus. By the times, the
expectation value for the internal energy, we can
also write equivalently in terms of the
temperature that is fixed and the canonical
approach, and we do see the promised dependence on
the logarithm of the production function here,
which is not something that can easily be
simplified, recalling that the production function
is the sum overall microstates it's. Encompassing
the information about all of those microstates and
their individual energy is. But the appearance of
this logarithm of the partition function, both in
the entropy as well as this, as a derivative of
expression for. The expectation value is, as you
suggest, or I guess confirm something that I
forecast earlier, that the prediction function
really is the fundamental equality in the economic
approach. The general starting point from which
all of these other derived observables like energy,
intrepidity, capacity and eventually more can be
derived. And given this of central role of the
petition function, in particular, the logarithm,
the petition function that we're seeing
specifically it is useful for practical
calculations. To.
Define the quantity related to the longer the
production function that has dimensions of energy
and can be. Used essentially to simplify or
streamline some of the dictation and the
calculations. And this is what is known as a free
energy. And in the specific case of the class,
it's called the help of three energy, named after
19th century German physicist Helmholtz, which we
defined to be equivalent with working in terms of
temperature or the inverse of the logarithm, the
petition function. Times the negative temperature.
We're divided by the negative of the inverse
temperature.
Which.
Just to restate the fundamental. Some objects we
are working with the probabilities.
Which we can recall are whatever is in time is the
ultimate factor into the minus energy over tea can
be recast into a overall exponential factor. The.
Tons of free energy that defines the overall
behavior of the entire system, some over all of
the microstates minus the energy for the
particular microstates which monitor this
probability, all normalize by the temperature in
the argument that exponential, which is already
bringing in the. Simply expression for the
petition itself, just as the exponential of the
negative free energy divided by temperature, which
is just inverting this equation. Thirty seven.
Given this definition of the free energy and all
of the projectable, see how close I can get.
The usefulness of defining this. Quantity based on
the production function is reveal.
In particular, when we had computers, derivatives
with or without actors of T so just.
Collecting this temperature derivative of the
water, the petition function, which is related to
the derivative with respect to data that we. Look
at to define the average internal energy, that's
what this equation. Thirty five is.
I have space up here, that was a thirty five,
which is the relation that the derivative with
respect to beta differs from the derivative with
respect to temperature by the overall factor of
minus two squared. So in that relation to, say, a
minus one over a few squared. Can he be beat up or
is it a up and this is. What we computed is the
negative expectation value of the internal energy.
The negatives then cancel out. So this derivative
of the. How much free energy normalized by
temperature gives us the. Average internal energy
normalized by a squared, which we can then look
into.
Slightly. More complicated derivative of the free
energy itself. So that expression is now
reproduced here.
First term is the.
Trivial, long said, derivative of T with respect
to this one, and then be the one that negative T.
The ones that were included above. So this is the
logarithm of that is the negative free energy
property that's negative for cancer services or
free energy itself, divided by two.
And then the second term brings in the specter of
average thermal energy over T-square times t that
negative sign comes along.
And we can check.
This is the expression, the computer earlier in
the week for the entropy is a function of T with
an overall negative side logarithm of Z, plus the
average internal energy only divided by T, and we
can confirm that all the units are matching up.
And all the terms of this expression is promised,
the couple's free energy has the same units as
neutral energy. And in the system of units we are
working with, energy and temperature have the same
dimensions than just the dimensionless entropy
coming out at the end.
So the.
The main observers will be interested in, at least
for the remainder of this year, the entropy and
average energy assumptions of T.. Now, I have
several expressions related to the Helmholtz free
energy, the centrifuges, the negative of the
temperature, derivative of the almost free energy
and the energy is that the temperature at times
entropy plus the free energy.
So those are. Ways of recasting some of the
previous general expressions in terms of the
border partisan function now showing up as this
free energy and relation between. Energy and
entropy, which will actually spend a few minutes
applying this to. Specific systems, having gone
through the general generic derivation of what
these quantities are, how they are related. And
before diving into battle paths again to see if
there are any questions or objections about.
General Foundation formulation of the economic
approach that we've done.
So there is time to at least start looking at a
first application of. The canonical example that
we have now defined mathematically justify that
and related between the fundamental microsleep,
probability is partition function and derive
quantities like energy and entropy. And maybe not
surprisingly, we are. Going to focus on that same
sort of storm systems that we've talked about a
few times in the past couple of units will be
looking in particular about the role of
information in these systems. By considering two
possible setups that differ only by the amount of
information that is knowable in principle. About
each of these spent systems, so this is connected
to what is a.
Important and hot topic in ongoing research,
especially once we bring in. Quantum field theory,
general relativity and all the other pillars of
modern physics, statistical physics has to
interact with the relevant regimes, the. The
dependence of systems on the information content,
what information is knowable about the principle
is.
Is subject still with a lot of uncertainty and
debates in particular related to what's called the
black hole information paradox, which is trying to
figure out how precisely or precisely how
information that falls into a black hole or regime
there, both general relativity and quantum physics
is important how that information is processed.
Preserved and eventually admitted in the hawking
radiation as that black hole evaporates over time,
which is part of the thermodynamics of black holes
and other contacts that you may have time to look
at just at the very end of the course where
there's strange behavior like negative
temperatures and systems that. Get get the colder,
the more energy they bring in, that's the general
motivation for picking up information in general,
the concrete calculations we'll be doing is
considering two to four to. Variations of the same
system and spins which. In one case, the spinach
will be distinguishable from each other in
principle, this.
In the other case, the spinners will be
indistinguishable in the way that we can set this
up physically. Is by fixing this belongs to a
particular position or allowing them to move in.
In whatever container is contained, they'll start
with the. Distinguishable case where the idea is
that the spin degrees of freedom will be
considering. Are all arranged in a line. And. In a
settlement that field. So repeat the ruling we had
earlier, some excellent field and spins that could
be aligned with or against it. And we will further
specify that these films are what form?
A solid material, so they may be identified with
the atoms and some crystal of the sound
like a building, for instance, the physical
context in which these systems were first
developed. And in this cell, the molecules that
correspond to these and other titles in this case
are fixed. They're not allowed to move around.
They can. Only align with or against the magnetic
field, and because they are associated with a
particular point in this solid, an observer can
look at that particular point and know that it is
that particular spin that has been observed by
focusing on a well-defined region in the solid.
In the canonical approach to generalizing the
microphone system we looked at earlier, too, now
allowing the energies of the microstates to to
vary all possible to the sort of equals to the end
configurations of these and spin's align our
values microstates with generally different energy
use and now different probabilities of being
adopted, exponentially suppressed by those
energies. And that's the time remaining.
We'll introduce a bit of a different, more
efficient notation for the systems, rather than
having to draw lots of arrows pointing either up
or down, and we'll represent appointing spins by
just an integer from a six one minus one. So
whenever. The value of this degree of freedom at
distinguishable speed and equals one that will be
point you spend aligned parallel to the magnetic
field, contributing a negative edge to the energy
and the downward pointing spins, or Angelyne
contributing a positive H to the energy so that
the total energy get that back realign. And the
projector is just now easily expressed in terms of
these n spin variables, plus or minus one with an
overall factor of negative. So this is the total
energy of the particular microstates eye, which is
specified in full by the configuration of the as a
set of integers that are plus or minus or
responding to upward and downward pointing spins.
So.
As we will see repeatedly and economic approach,
the starting point is the production function
called sense of the word, emphasize the
sensibility of these business and that petition
function is the sum over all of the possible
microstates. So on to the power and possible
configurations as Ceylan.
Which. Looks like. At the basic level, this factor
here, the Boltzmann factor, exponential minus
better times, energy, something over the two
values, plus or minus one of all of these spin
degrees of freedom as one through. So there are
enormous sums each over to of these. Where the.
Degrees of freedom being sucked over, the speed
variables a sudden appear in the.
Determination of the total energy of the
microstates that shows up in The Factor. Now,
since all of these spins are independent of each
other, they don't interact with each other, the
entities depend only on their orientation up or
down and not what any other spin is doing. We can
expand this exponential of the sun to be a product
of exponential growth and then redistributes all
of those factors in the product to the
corresponding sum over the two plus or minus spin
states.
In this overall sum over to the impossibility, so
we end up with any factors of two terms each.
And the factors, so this product just boils down
to a single. Some of the two possibilities raised
to the power in those two possibilities are Bess's
plus one, we have the exponential with the
positive arguments I've called X and magnetic
field divided by temperature. And similarly, when
this is negative one, we just pick up the negative
side in that argument, which you can recognize as
the hyperbolic cosine of this dimension, this kind
of magnetic field strength divided by temperature
with that factor. Up to the cosh to the sound of
the Excellency's, minus six, all raised to the
power at.
So. Maybe just wrapping up with the breaking down
the Helmholtz energy, it's simple enough, take the
rhythm of. This quantity that breaks down to we
have the logarithm of the argument two times of
hyperbolic, cosine and dividing by making the
better just gives. This expression for the
helpless, we understand that next week we will.
Turn through the expressions we've derived for the
democracy and interview to see how those behave
for the system wrap up there. We you seen set up
for this distinguishable, spent to resolve other
questions about anything we've seen so far this
week.
I guess I will have hopefully see you again this
afternoon, unless the storm shut everything down
on the. Look at some more aspects of Al Gore's
numbers, the. We'll exercise the post last week,
as well as some derivations related disturbance,
one can be a fun way to spend some time on a
Friday afternoon. See you that.
That.