I just heard the bells ringing over the wind, so
let's get started even though I'm still tracking down
all the bits and pieces I'm bringing in.  I guess the
place to pick up is where we wrapped up in
last week's tutorial, we had a discussion of well.
Maybe before diving into that, I can ask if there
are any questions about anything at all from, you
know, is this just a few hours ago, the this is
another chance in the tutorial context.
Without any more. Shouting to raise an issue, you
can't or I can ask how you got on with its
exercise of placing bounds of the entropy for two
spin systems that are in contact and are analyzed
as a whole, and they are canonical examples of the
total energy of those two systems is fixed and
allowed to share energy back and forth. And there
are some bounds on the entropy that we can derive
from that. Did that all go smoothly for you, for
that 10 speed system?
I am.
It's really nice enough that I forgot to put up
the security number for that.
That help.
Divans.
OK, so there is one. Three of.
So it's not out of the way.
With 10 spins, you can just go through and
enumerate all of these entropies and see what the
spread is, what sorts of numbers were. You coming
up with four new
systems?
What were you able to come up with numbers for
these men's?
All might be able to take a step back from just
jumping straight to the answers to these
inequalities and go through the pieces that are
showing up in them, this smacks and terms is if
you're going to have any.
Numbers for the the maximum.
Factor in the terms and one times have to for
particular division of the total energy between
the two or four, how many terms there are in total?
Fortunately, 10 spins is few enough that we can go
through the full calculation, if that's proved
sticky for you. So we have. Ten. Units of energy
and reset the magnetic field strength equal to one
and.
Could equivalently just work in units of strength,
so one possible way of distributing 10 units of
energy systems is to have all this in one of the
systems. None of it's in another.
And.
I kind of leave enough space, but here. There's a
Senate centuries between these two systems. So we
have all kinds of energy and neither one of the
two.
And what are the some of the other possibilities?
So this one corresponds to everything that's been
put in System 101, but even since then it's been
done system to
slot your.
What are some of the possibilities that can go
between these two limits?
So as we look, what's been reaction to this?
Still, you want some changes, we've see six terms
that answers that question and also a symmetry
between the six trials where the upper three or
just the. Interchange and reverse of the.
And then she needs energies, you want to relate
that to a number of ways, the number of microbes
that each of these systems that we have to get all
of. Forget the energy is distributed in this way,
so I will do the easy one that goes along with the
chocolate. There's only one way to have all the
things pointing out so that all publicity is one
is going to the.
A little bit more room between those two. Of. They
are the easiest way to go is to go down this
column, what is the what are the number of
microstates that we correspond to having those
minus eight units of energy in system one that.
As it happens, maybe I can step back and. To the
specter of war is just the binomial coefficient of
four of the ten storms
lined
up, the both of those cases.
The question then is. How does that generalize to
the intermediate or less trivial speed
configurations?
I can't quite hear the.
So for the. Evidence of energy, do we have?
The integration, of course, almost always been one
the opposite oriented, so she was turned down, she
was known for 10 ways of organizing. That would
seem to be any one of the ten. Each of those ten
is a different microstates.
So ships there as well.
And then the process continues as we keep slipping
additional standards, we have to choose on the
page, we tend to be quite a few.
What is the binomial factor?
Forty five. Yeah,
one in five said over to.
So that means there. No sweat lodge still
continues. And you
can use.
Seven, six, five, which. If my memory serves more
than twenty two to two to.
She had to double check that. And there were just.
One time and two to figure out the. Total number
of signs of term in the Senate. We started off
with so we are getting at one time and two, which
would be six to three inches of energy
is is one.
And then 10, 10 times to 10. Used to be used to
just extract know in and then forty five times one
hundred twenty one. Oh look, I had
54 of those two states with the most equal
distribution of states between the two. So next
year is be four hundred.
And the total. If you were to
sum up all of these terms. That might be dangerous,
but behind the screen here, you say. Paul is
five hundred.
So.
The. Battles that we begin this hour that we have
the logarithm of. This maximum value in the
natural place. Which I have.
Written down
five nine is going to be hopefully smaller, not
too much smaller than the true entropy of the
stone wall, distributions of energy logarithm
turns out to be nine, six, five.
And then this in turn is going to be smaller than
the logarithm of six times fifty four hundred,
which is just logarithmic six. Plus the water will
be fifty for the water. The six is that one point
eight. So. Eight plus three point five hundred and
twenty three, nine out of percent in the bounds
that we compute just in half a chalkboard for this
case of an equals 10.
And in particular, I asked once I finished typing
up this tutorial exercise, asked what fraction of
the true entropy would be accounted for by just
looking at either one of these two divisions of
energy with the largest factor in the moment to
five ratio that highlighted the 10 percent spread
on both sides of these bounds. I can say that
eight point six or nine point seven is about one
percent of the entropy of the system is accounted
for just by either one of these two ways of
distributing the energy reasonably equally. Which
is.
A significant fraction, and we can expect to that
as an increases to the truly larger values of this
saturation of the energy by the most likely set up,
most likely configuration is going to become even
more precise.
Of course, going on from end equals 10 to 20, 30,
40 or so on might be a bit tedious to do in a
table like this. But it is it's just a bunch of
computing or computations following a very
well-defined set of instructions, which is why
another tab in the window that I have here is a
Python notebook where I just wrote down the
automated calculation of all of this. And I was
thinking I could even. This is a short enough
program, much of it being. Displaying results in a
pretty way, I could have written this live in the
tutorial, but I figured that would be especially
soporific on a Friday afternoon with the exciting
outside. So let's just. Walk through the crowd
quickly, it won't take long. Setting that whole
number of spins up at the top, which on my
computer, I just read it as an input argument. We
can do a quick, warm up exercise of checking the.
Multiplicities, the number of multi states in a
single system of 10 spins that. Correspond to each
of the possible energies that the macro economic
system can have, plus 10 all pointed against the
magnetic field, I pointed down to minus 10. They
are all aligned. You see that these multiplicities
are the familiar ones here, ranging from one to
two hundred and fifty two. And the corresponding
entropy is just the logarithm of that. Might as
well turn that off. Just a quick sound check that
things like the binomial coefficients provided by
a scientific python are behaving as they should,
and similarly that that the log here is in the
natural base. What we have is two systems in terms
of contact with a fixed total energy. Which can
also be converted into an input argument, and we
want to accumulate all of the terms in this cell
over at one time, said to right here the log of
which defines the total energy, the total entropy
of the system. So if we cycle over all of the
possible numbers and upward pointing spins in the
first system, we can get the energy out of there
just two times and plus minus the total energy of
10. That means that in order to have the fixed
total energy of minus 10, the energy from the
second system has to be the remainder. And we can
figure out how many upward expense that
corresponds to just by converting this formula.
Taking the.
The negative side there
and minus the energy divided by two. It may turn
out to be that more than. The total number of
available spins would be present in order to
satisfy the total energy supply, since we never
have the plus 10 spin system here appearing in
these terms. And in that case, we can just
continue to the next option until we're done. We
have to do is compute the binomial coefficient of
picking. I spin up spins out of the total. Picking
up to speed up spins out of control, the
multiplicities for the separate systems, multiply
them together, add them to the list, and then
we're done sprinting things out. So putting out
that whole list, we see no more or less than I
have a more. We can extract the maximum elements
in the array as this max variable we defined last
week, the sum of all the elements in the array is
that total element for the combined system. And
the length of the array is the number of terms
that we have. And then adding up and taking borgs
gives us an entropy bound with. Eighty nine
percent
saturation of the entropy from any one of the most
likely states. So with that set up, have to change
and to.
See the results for larger systems going to the
larger limit, see larger numbers are appearing at
the entropy bound now is getting more like the.
Few percent level, the 10 percent level and 94
percent of the entropy is accounted for in the
most likely.
Distribution of energies, which corresponds to the
same minus four, minus six appearing in either
system.
And I think the largest I could repeat this for
before I went into the limits of double precision
floating point arithmetic and and computers is
five hundred twelve spins in each system. See if
that worked, if truncated some of the outputs,
conveniently, you see that the.
Little spin configurations we would have to
consider are about ten to the power, three hundred
six with five hundred eight terms. So as we
forecast last week, the number of terms is
increasing linearly with the number of degrees of
freedom and the entropy bound is better than one
percent in particular, that same setup with.
Evenly distributed energies were evenly
distributed, upper point expense accounts now for
more than ninety nine and a half percent of the
total energy, the total entropy.
If I switch to the dot cam and. To get it in focus.
You see the summary for these numbers.
Looking at how.
All
right, let's see how the.
The of that single likely distribution accounts
for a greater, greater fraction of the total
entropy as an increase is coming from the prisons
here up to the ninety nine point six percent that
we just read in the second four five hundred
twelve spins, saw that the number is five hundred
of these rounded out our 307, which is where we
run into double digit level. And maybe the
interesting thing about this is the.
The way that it's always the even distribution of
schemes and energy that dominates the entropy or
presumably dominate the number of microstates, so.
This is.
Essentially at. They are trying to use a. Somewhat
poetic term. We've seen that.
More may be disordered states, the ones with less
special configurations where there is a.
What is possible ways of organizing the degrees of
freedom subject to the constraints in the
sophistical ensemble or dominating the total
entropy of the system? So if we were to prepare
these two speed systems in maybe one of the
special states with all of the energy was in one
and none of it was in the other, after we put them
into the contact about the combined system to
reach equilibrium, we would expect to see the
system mostly in this more evenly distributed.
Divisions of energy between them and that is just
a consequence of the number of is the entropy that
corresponds to that situation. So this is the same
as if we were to consider what would happen if all
the air in this room happened to be hanging out in
one of the corners. At some point, we would expect
it to expand out into the vacuum and become more
or less evenly distributed. And you would not
expect the opposite process to occur over here
that's currently in the room to spontaneously
coalesce in one of the corners, which is
convenient because it helps us breathe
consistently. But that sort of distinction between
how the entropy is, the various configurations
differ. And how we can distinguish this and how in
the way that systems evolve from situations with
low entropy to situations with high entropy and
not the other way around is the way in which
the forward motion of time emerges from the
underlying macroscopic dynamics.
So are there questions about this example? I will
will be able to upload these comments on the
campus later today.
Because if not only about halfway through the
tutorial for today and can change gears to look at
something that came up earlier this week,
which is one of the things that's creating some
entropy among organizations that have your. Which
was the.
Sterling's approximation to. The factorial
function was logarithmic, asked a Tuesday, I think,
whether that was in.
Familiar approximations that indicate much
response so we can dig into it in a bit more
detail, in particular to write it in one of three
progressively more rigorous and more refined, more
accurate ways. So to the leading orders that we
kept in class, Sterling's formula. Expands the
what rhythm of conflict will emerge in as and more
than what is then up to terms that are more likely
and that we will. Almost always neglect when we
use sterling silver lining in this market. But
it's worth seeing how the full expression is
derived and getting some appreciation for. How it
works and it is for glory. So if we exponentially
both sides of this approximation, we extract in
fact will itself. Probably of exponentially lower
than functions, just identified that logarithm
into the power N minus the exponential, plus the
acceleration of minus N reorganizes its B ratio
and other natural basti to the power n. And this
is the crude approximation that's several people
found in roughly the same time a few hundred years
ago. It can be made more precise with that look
and factor of being identified. As a
multiplicative square root to play and the
expression for in with itself, with an infinite
series of power, suppressed corrections. So terms
that come in with.
Computable concerns, ABC and so on is suppressed
by whatever and whenever squared and so on and.
Keep the equation one up on the screen there. One
interesting aspect of this overall approximation
is the fact that this series does not converge for.
Olga. It is now zero and the radius of convergence
is essentially some. Over AK. One over. Next to
the case, which I imagine you've seen in the past
and know to be diversions, really the series
should not be considered diversions or rather
esoteric, even though the radius of convergence
vanishes. If the series is truncated. At an
appropriate power after the term and is expected
to provide a maximum precise approximation to this
vectorial.
The next time we'll look at some of the examples
we've watched over in the lecture, but.
There are a few ways to actually derive Stirling's
for.
So. What is the easiest that gives the weakest
constraint doesn't actually drive reform itself,
again, focuses on balance somewhat similar to the
ones being extracted for the last week. And.
And try to see how much of this.
A piece of notes I can fit onto the screen here.
There are three derivations in here of increasing
complexity. The first being just to. Drive to
balance on the water and vectorial for sure that
this is less than mile and which should be
reasonably straight forward and then. The other
tests show that in Victoria, those also greater
than and Morgan Minocin for much greater than
Warton, so. Once you were able to. Establishes the
equation to than just divided through by that and
again. Will. Give the result that. We will give
the medium term instruments for Chauvins. As Ed
goes to zero is and goes to infinity is one of the
more than correction points to zero this morning
in factorial asymptotically and Baillargeon Limits
is the same order of magnitude as an apple that
extracts that medium term.
So poised for. Maybe five minutes to let you drive
those inequalities, and if you. Is too much time
you? Wrap up with them quickly. You have already
the next step is going to be manipulations of the
gamma function that can be related to any
factorial. So leave that up on the screen for a
few minutes, pause the recording while you work,
and then come back to look at the second round of.
Derivations for Serling's formula.
I guess before I posed any questions about this
post here.
It's the shaking heads, so. Paul. Recording is
resumed and check in to see if
there are too many qualities here to start off
with.
He has. Wants to share how those can be derived.
Maybe I should ask, first of all, who believes
those McMullan's?
Scream and. Do they seem. Reasonable.
So it's.
I saw now and so does anyone able to.
Thrive is this battle between, say, the. The upper
limits on the logarithm in factorial, so if we
want to show that one is one more game, this is
equivalent to the size and. Saying that, in fact,
itself is less than exponential. But then when it
comes to power and rearranging, that's exponential
like Mr..
Is that is our folks happy with? That how do we
see whether or not that is the case?
You can't do induction, though, that maybe even to
fall for my inclinations, I just see that.
Specify in greater than one year of damage to one.
Whereas it's the
same number of troops all the way down to. We have
created more so and in any case, and is greater
than and minus one, it's products of a strictly
positive integers.
Implies that until the end is larger, that you
were reversing things and what is less than.
So that's
one down.
And that was the easy one, as you can see there,
any ideas for what to do about that? Second,
inequality, trying to show? That.
With less
than.
So what it's like here
is some water
and I've read.
That is true, false.
Of the.
Let's
go back to.
So.
And that's.
You want to travel to the border and write it down?
I can't pause the report again, that would.
The more comfortable. The recording back on just
before accountability, I think that argument does
does hold. I haven't gone through all the steps.
The trick that I like and which uses me is to give
the Palestinians more exponential tools, certainly
the Taliban, which is one plus one over and over,
two and square and so on, towards the settlement
from zero to infinity of.
Organic tools into this.
And I consider from that song The Sweet.
I know that not the F term. Within the cells,
there are additional type terms, some as a whole,
through isolation equal from Japan over inject a
little, rearrange the factorial to the left of the
inequality.
And in the end, to the rights
of the expression was opened up there as well. So
that is a good way of pointing out arguments that
I find amusing. So. Running out of time for today,
wrap up there and leave the second option, the
third derivations for you to think about just on
the second one, looks at the example function and.
Uses this to restore what's called weather
integral, relating confectionary to a simple
isidoro with the
complexity and an exponential minus X integrated
over the X and then if you. Look at this function.
Next to the N minus, and it's plotted here.
In the solid line, we can approximated by a
Galician tradition integral. And from that,
Russian people extract the. A square root and
factor that needs to be logarithmic chart
instruments formula. I'll leave that for you to
play with over the weekend. We'll pick up on
Monday with more about the physics of information
and develop into your ideal. Any questions to to
wrap up the week?
Take care of the wind. It doesn't get too
unpleasant out there. We'll see you next week.
Oh.