All right, good morning.
Let's get things set up and underway for Tuesday,
starting with this
number for the monitoring system, today
seven, six, three,
two three seven.
And we can pick up more or less where we left off
yesterday, just check in quickly to see if there
are any questions about either the computer
project---this is the last time we will
before it's due in a couple of days---or about the
micro canonical example that we wrapped up just to
be. And of yesterday
reiterate briefly that in the microeconomic
approach. The fundamental qualities that define
that ensemble is a probability face are the
conservation of energy and conserve particle, no.
And from that thing like. Entropy and also the
temperature are. Derived qualities that we saw at
the end of yesterday, Kim. In some situations,
behave as we expect in the everyday sorts of
experiences that we have or experiments that we
would do in a physics lab and in other ways, you
can look very different, for instance, in the
appearance of negative temperatures or divergences
in the case of spin systems. Or in general, in
general systems where the number of microstates
decreases as. The amount of energy available
increases and.
This is part of the motivation for turning now to
the next.
It's the physical exam over the next probably
states that will be considering before diving into
some more detailed applications of all these ideas.
So today is going to be more of a foundation
laying introduction to the canonical ensemble of
mathematical justification for what is physically
a more natural way of looking at physics, which is
to swap out the conservation of energy for a fixed
temperature that will define this ensemble. There
are many motivations for this, and this is the
reason why it's called the canonical ensemble
canonical meaning through ordinary or standard,
for one thing. Just this. Assumption,
microbiological case that. Energy can be exactly
conserved in the system of interest means, as we
said, that the system has to be perfectly isolated
from the rest of the universe, enclosed box full
of particles floating in a perfect void, which is
not what we have. In our lives or in any physics
experiment, fully isolating a statistical system
is simply impossible. People want to look at it or
do any work and do the experiments on it. And.
There's also the complication of driving a
temperature from a fixed energy. You also saw
practical difficulties in the canonical case with
unwieldy factorial, expressions that are popping
up, which will we will eventually avoid by.
Working with. A nice. Intensive temperature that
we can set and fixed the definition of this
ensemble rather than the internal energy, which is
an extensive bodily. So just to formally state the
definition, the canonical ensemble is taking our
usual musical ensemble as a probability space
subject now to the constraints of a fixed
temperature and the same conservative particle
number as in the case. And the question now
becomes, mathematically, how do we justify fixing
this temperature, which up till now we've seen as
a derived quantity following from the first law,
from a dynamic observation of energy. And the way
this is done is by placing. Our canonical ensemble
or system of interest in thermal contact with a
reservoir or a heat bath. Which is a much larger
external system called Omega's Reservoir, in
contrast to the Omega. Of the system we're going
to be interested in throughout this. Where the
overall system? The direct product of our system
with interest and this much larger reservoir
doesn't obey conservation of energy and is
therefore covered by the micropower example that
we are now familiar with.
Now, what this thermal contact does, if we look at
our system of interest just itself, its energy is
able to fluctuate by exchanging energy with this
large reservoir. And at the same time, because the
temperature is an intensive quantity, the same for
all of these systems that are in contact with each
other. The temperature of our economical ensemble
and media is going to be fixed by that much larger
reservoir. We will set things up so that the
system itself has a negligible effect from the of
contact, the overall setup.
So this is going to be. The analysis is going to
look a bit like that heated exchange that we
analyzed yesterday. I mean, that thermal contact
caused flow of energy between two different
systems, bringing their temperatures closer
together. The difference now is that the
temperature is something we can declare fixed from
the outset rather than something we have to derive,
at least for the ensemble of interest. Now. The
approach here is through the lengthy arguments as
to why we are able to do this and it's
mathematically justified and the approach is going
to be introducing a well motivated onsides for the
form of this federal reservoir and then showing
that. Once we go through the full analysis or
consideration based on that answer, that's all
reference to the reservoir drops out of. The
expressions we find governing the economical
system that we are targeting so that the answers
we adopted becomes irrelevant in the end. So
that's the specific form of the reservoir is
ultimately irrelevant, as long as it is present,
you will be able to conclude that the thermal
reservoir plays its role in fixing the temperature
of the economical system and allowing its energy
to fluctuate. So what that is, is what's known as
the replica trick that was introduced by Gibbs,
which is to say that the total system, the
combination of the reservoir and our system of
interest is just a large number of identical
replicas of that system of interest, which has a
few motivations. First of all, if we take it for
granted that we are interested in a well defined
or reasonable physical system of mega, then just
taking a bunch of copies of it guarantees that the
reservoir itself is also going to be equally.
Well, motivated and sensible, we can also sort of
take the more handwaving, physicist's perspective
of, for example, doing some experiment out here on
this room, bottle up some subset of that area,
then we can take this the air in this bottle as a
system of interest. It's nice to see also the
particle numbers conserved. It's in contact with
all the rest of the air in this room, which forms
that thermal ensemble and can be analyzed just as.
All just many times, larger amount of it.
So to continue developing this idea with a little
more formal but still very small example of it.
But consider again, it's been system as usual,
just to get started with a very small number of
spins so that we don't spend too much time drawing
arrows and can get the idea without
too much effort. So just two spins and we will say
the views are distinguishable so that we can tell
which spin is which and distinguish between the
cases where the spin on the left is pointing down
or the spin on the right is pointing down, both of
those being distinct microstates. So the total
number of microstates that we can have for these
two spins is just to the two or the four states
that are drawn here, both up, both down. And the
two possibilities for having one up and one down
and then.
The drawing here shows another extremely small
example of. How we can bring together a bunch of
replicas of this system. Choose one of these
replicas to be the Omega that we will. Declare to
be the one we are analyzing and say that all of
these replicas are in thermal contact with each
other, they have boxes drawn around them so that
they can to remind ourselves that the particle no
in each replica is conserved. And so long as each
of these systems is in contact, possibly through a
series of intermediates with the others, we can
wait long enough for the overall total system of
nine replicas of this to be set up to reach a
thermal equilibrium. I can mention that even
though I've laid out these replicas of this square
grid, that is not something that we need to assume
so long as there is some contact between. Each of
these replicas and the rest of the system, all of
them will evolve to thermodynamic equilibrium,
something that's sometimes called the zeroth law
of thermodynamics. It's more fundamental even than
the first or the second
and.
With this small example in mind, you can.
Start writing them mathematical expressions for
this overall system by defining the occupation. No.
Using that as a convenient. Quantity to manipulate
where this occupation number and supply
corresponds to each of those microstates in our
small system of. So in the example of health care
for Omega's, depending on the orientations of the
spin's and the four occupation numbers, one for
each of those microstates is the number of
replicas that adopt this particular small system,
microstates in any overall product state for the
total system of all our replicants. So I can't
quite. Fit everything onto the same page here, but
we can count the occupation numbers just from this.
Small example, so remind you that microstates one
has both arrows pointing down. So what is the.
Occupation number. For at microstates. In this
overall system.
I hear three, which are those three they're.
How about a to his first down, then up? And they
did three things up and down in the member for. It
was both up. What are the. Corresponding
occupation numbers and this small example for
those.
Yeah. Two for my great state to.
There's one, there's the other microstates, three.
And also here to again. And see one there and
there and then stay for there, is this the final
two? And we have there, which makes it.
Rewrite that result in this box, the occupation
numbers, for this example, three, two to two,
which do some to total number of nine replicas. In
fairly trivial way.
Now, from these occupation numbers, we can
equivalently work with the fraction of the total
number of replicas are in any particular
microsleep, we can look at the fraction of
replicas that are in the corresponding microphages
divide or normalized by the total number are. And
then that gives us occupation probabilities. Peace
of mind is the occupation number divided by half,
which is a well defined probability as it all sums
up to one. All replicas are accounted for. And
even though. I'm calling this the same with the
same label as the microsleep probabilities that we
were working with in the canonical ensemble. It is
not. Or at least not yet the same thing. Rather
than being able to interpret this, at least for
now, as the probability that our system is in
microstates, oh my God, this is the probability
that if we were to choose one of these replicas at
random, it would be in that microstates of the
small system. The notation suggests that. We will
eventually find this to be the same, that will
come in due course now.
For this. Overall system. The first law
laframboise dynamics between to hold energy
continues to be conserved, so we have a fixed
amount of energy in that overall system of all of
these replicas.
And we're going to assume that the contribution of
each of those are replicas to the total energy is
independent of all the others, so it could be
considered a an independent random variable. So
this is.
And assumption at this point, it holds. Pretty
straightforwardly, for now, the tracking systems
that we are focusing for the bulk of this term
will actually prove that in in Unit nine when we
define what it means to be interacting or not and
also holds more generally than that.
When interactions are allowed within each replica
of not between the different replica. So it's
going to be at this level A.
Conditions similar to the conservation of particle
no, within each of the replicas that we were able
to impose from the outset. We just have criminal
contact only. Which allows. Each of the energies
of each of these replicas to fluctuate so long as
their total adds up to this fixed and conserved
value.
Now. One other thing we can say about. The
energies of each of these replicas is that each
replica of each small system that we are actually
interested in can make it most and possible values
where M is the usual number of microstates in that
small system. Some of these values may well be the
same. That's no problem. We have survived the use
of K for two to six microstates equals a mega J.
We can just some over the same value of the energy
twice when we rearrange an expression for a total
energy of the replicas. This first quality is
trivial. Just saying it's we go over all of the
replicas. The energy is the sum. That's the
definition of extensibility, which the energy
obeys is an expensive quantity. And keeping the
number of replicas of the number of microstates
finite, it is just a straightforward rearrangement
of the sum of the energy of each replica, the sub,
instead of the number of replicas and so on in
each microstates Omega Sevi that comes along with
this possibly not unique energy use by the eye.
And this is on is now running from one up to. The
total microstates that our small system can take.
So what we've done here is a promising first step
towards our ultimate goal of removing the
reservoir from this analysis is find that the
overall total. Energy for this entire system with
its large heat that can be expressed just in terms
of the. Microstates of that small system.
Now, the. Next step, well, Paul is here to see if
the set up in the first steps are. Clear out 30.
Questions about the implications of this approach.
I'm not seeing any. We'll move on to the next step,
which is to essentially impose thermodynamic
equilibrium and say that the overall micro state
of the product of all of these are replicas can be
fully specified just by the fixed set of
occupation numbers. Nothing could be an
microstates of our system of interest.
Which is equivalent to assuming that the
occupation probabilities we have now defined our
concept of time, which is another way of defining
and equilibrium. So this guarantees that the total
energy of the overall system is conserved. And we
now want to. Use the tools from the previous unit
to use to extract the temperature. From that.
Overall micro economic system. And we've seen
yesterday that the first step to doing this
determination of the temperature in the
microeconomic approach is figuring out the number
of microstates at the overall total system can
have them taking. The logarithm of that gives us
the entropy. Taking the derivative of that will
give us the temperature.
So. The first step in this process is determining
the total number of microstates that we can have
across all our of these Reptilicus.
Now, the. The way to do this is to proceed.
Microsleep on microstates. Going over all of the
possibilities on. In the system of interest, so if
we first consider, say, microstates or maybe one,
you can think back to that step sample to
visualize this, you want to figure out the total
number of microstates among all our replicas. The
first step is figuring out how many times for a
given for a fixed occupation number that we are
now assuming characterizes the overall system. How
many distinct microstates can we build up by
requiring that in one copies of microstates make
one appear to be all replicas, which. I could
rephrase by saying, how many ways can we choose
and one out of those are replicas to have this
particular microstates and choosing. And so one
out of four is that binomial factor that should
now be familiar from the microeconomic also. And
now we just have to repeat this in times for all
of these microstates, keeping in mind that we've
already gone over all of the micro with all the
previous microstates up to be what we are
currently considering. So what would be the
corresponding factor looked like for the ends of
two copies of microstates or make it two in the
system?
Yes, you need to choose and two out of the
remaining power minus and one.
Replicas that have not yet been assigned a
distinct microstates, which. We express this. In
terms of the ratio we have.
Minus and one in the numerator or minus and one
minus into the denominator. And then similarly, we
move on. To that ominous and one, two, which we
choose and three and so on, and then need to
multiply all of these factors together in order to
find the total number of possibilities for all the
different distributions of the microstates among
the replicas and something. Very pleasant happens
when we do this multiplication example, if we look
up at the first microstates.
Factor and then multiply it by the second
microsleep factor, if you will, have those
pictorials in the numerator denominator, the R
minus one out. We can. C, the R minus and one
minus and two that will appear in the numerator of
the next factor, cancel out that denominator. So
the product of all of these binomial coefficients
for all of these different and microstates end up
telescoping into the overall R factorial from the
front, from the first step. And then a numerator
of this factor, we have the minus one factorial
and minus two factorial and minus three factorial
all the way up to.
And some factorial for the final microstates.
And in case you were wondering if it was
legitimate to think first about my personal legal
one and then move on to a mega to an omega three,
or there might be depending on which microstates
we chose to look at first or how we chose to label
them, we can see that this result. Is independent
of permutations or really thanks to computer
stupidity of multiplication, so we now have a
formal expression for the entropy of this overall
system of many replicas. Which is just the
logarithm of the total number of microstates, so
the logarithm of our factorial and then the
logarithm of the product converts to the logarithm
of some. And with an overall negative sine. To.
Account for the negative one power that puts all
of these log and Sevi factorial factors in the
denominator equation. Twenty eight. We have the
logarithm of our factorial number of replicas,
minus the sum of the logarithms of the factorial
of the occupation number for each of the
microstates of our system of interest, the mega
small system embedded in the large.
So as we saw yesterday for the microeconomic
ensemble, there are lots of factorial floating
around. Which in this case, if we we have started
off by assuming that's correct, because it's very
large, if we further assume that the occupation
numbers are very large for each micro state of the
small system and every single one of the
logarithms. In this expression can be approximated
using Sterling's formula, you might look more at
that on Friday. Maybe I can ask right now, is
Sterling's formula something familiar that you've
seen before or are you hearing about it for the
first time? Here I see you shaking hands. So we
may justify this result in tutorial on Friday,
what Sterling's formula says to the next two
leading orders of the first two terms is that the
logarithm of the factorial of a large number is
approximately that number. And log in is the
leading term. Minus the near term and. Up to
logarithmic corrections that are negligible for
and much larger than is to remember how negligible
those can be from last Friday. I mentioned that if
we had.
In order to power twenty three, Morgan is of order
50 now. Ten to the power. Twenty two times smaller
and easily negligible. In this approximation.
Of course, you may have. Seen already that
requiring. Every occupation number to be large.
For all in microstates of our school system.
Requires that the total number of replicas has to
be much larger than an end. And given that we're
recalling that and is frequently exponentially
large in the.
Number of degrees of freedom. As a rough guide to
its size and exponential of ten to twenty three,
the number of replicas that we are formally
assuming in this derivation by applying Solms
formula is. Probably quite large, which. Is the
how the dynamic limits, where we will see the
detailed form of the reservoir will become
irrelevant, to remind you is our ultimate goal.
So.
To see if I can fit both the approximation,
the first two terms of each formula and the gap on
the same page just to show off by. Filling in the
blanks here in the first half actuarial terms, I
think is approximated by. Our look, our minus ah.
And then we have some of the similar
approximations for every one of these. And I terms
and so I want to by. Minus and survivor and what
we can do with this. Is recall.
First of all, there are a few things we can do
that with this we saw before that the sun over all
of the occupation numbers.
Just count the total number of Republicans. So
when we have just met some over and over with two
negative signs, we get a positive, ah, that will
cancel out that factor. And we are left with an
expression.
In terms of the occupation numbers. Is our Lord,
our. Mine is similar, and so I like to survive.
And we can further try to remove dependence on the
form of the reservoir by plugging in the relation
between the occupation numbers and occupation
probabilities. But the number of replicas. In
microstates, biggest eye is just the total number
of replicas times the probability of finding each
replica. In that microstates.
Rewriting things in terms of. Or so each, and I
hear. Is going to be our times, your factor of our
is a concept that can come out of the sun, you
have a pie and then the log of the product or
times pie. Be called. A load of armor plus. The
blog of.
And since these pieces are well defined
probabilities, you can see in this first term, you
can take a constant Bulgar out of the sum. In this
first term, we're left with the sum of the pie
that equals one. And we have our Lowgar. Minus our
water that cancels out is just a. Single
expression miners are the some. Of Pinboard Pae.
For. These occupation probabilities. And.
It is. Tempting to interpret this as just the. The
entropy being an extensive comment is saying that
the sum over probabilities is the entropy for each
of these identical replicas that then sum up to
the total entropy when bringing in that factor. Ah,
that is what we are not quite at the stage to be
able to say that yet, though it is certainly in
line. With the goal we have in mind to be able to
interpret these probabilities in terms of
microstates of an individual system rather than
occupation, probability is describing the overall
are replicas.
The next step. Keeping things micro economical and
just as we saw them considering the temperature
yesterday. Is to.
Extract dependence on the energy from these
occupation probabilities. From which we will. Have
in mind, you believe that the average temperature
was the dependence of entropy on changes in energy
with a fixed number of degrees of freedom. In the.
Way to do this is to maximize the entropy, to
reflect the dynamic equilibrium that we started
off by assuming it now subject to. Two constraints
on the occupation probabilities. So when we last
maximized the entropy with the multiplier on the.
Probabilities requiring that they send up to one.
We had a similar expression for modified entropy
this essabar last time around. We call this alpha
parameter a lambda, the grass multiplier that.
Impose reflected this constraint at the in that
case, Microsoft families were vilified here for
the overall system of our replicas in addition to.
This constraint of probabilities themselves have
to add up to one hundred percent. We also have the
constraints that the total energy of the system of
car replicas, which depends on the occupation
probabilities and the energy use of the individual
microstates. This is also fixed as a mobile, that
first law of thermodynamics. And that comes in
with a second.
Multiplier in this modified energy. We have to
consider now with a different coefficient. Then I
have chosen to call my masturbator just for future
convenience.
So this is. As a similar calculation to. What we
did very recently is anyone remember how that goes?
With enough confidence to shout out what the
derivative looks like when I'm looking at this
modified entropy with respect to the probability
piece, OK?
Now, this may be a. Somewhat like the expression
to expect you to to shout out, we'll just go term
by term and looking at its first term with a
constant factor of minus R that comes along for
the ride. We know that the derivative of peace of
mind with respect to peace brings in the product
of Delta Delta like some of our eyes and pulls out.
The people term then pushing through the product
rule to find derivatives to the logarithm brings
whatever pie that cancels out that pie and leaves
just one. There's a similar. Product or Delta IC,
and some of the pullout becomes a factor of Alpha
and the last term, a Delta IC, which with the
Silver III gives us beta our times. E.K..
Just rearrange to isolate the remaining dependence
on the probability peak divide through by R. We
have a minus one. We have plus. Alpha over R and B
R cancels out of beta, use the term. So we are
left with. Taking the exponential growth sides
piece of cake is the exponential of these three
terms, a minus minus one minus alpha over. Minus
the AK, which I divided up in that way to.
Right, as a ratio of three exponential.
Exponential at lightning speed, the times decay
for. Microstates or the microscopic responded to
this occupation probability.
And then you find just to find that overall
exponential of quantity, one minus alpha over are
in the denominator to be some other parameter said.
We can break things a little more compactly in the
traditional way, the probability piece of cake it
is, there is this one over Z times, the
exponential of the speed of times. So we now have
in place of the parameters alphabetically started
off with we've changed terminology to work in
terms of parameters, Z and data. And we fix this
by demanding that the two constraints we started
off with are satisfied. First, the.
Conservation or the well defined property of the
probability that it adds up to 100 percent. Means
that the sum of all these terms. Has to equal one
one over Z was independent of the microstates I
from one to and so we can just rearrange that some
multiply it through by said to say that. This is
the sum overall microstates of this exponential
factor e to the minus two times the energy for the
microstates. Which. Is the definition of the
economical partition function. It is going to be
the foundational quantity and the canonical
ensemble will be able to drive things like the
residual energy, the entropy and so on from it. At
the moment, it is still.
An expression that depends on an as yet unknown
withdraws multiplier data, which becomes the
energy in the microcosmic approach for the overall
system, depends on that conserved total energy. We
know that the multipliers that we put into the
modified entropy have that similar that same
functional dependence on the fixed mycological
energy of the whole RF system. So the second
constraint. That's something over the energies of
all our of those replicas gives us that fixed
total energy leads to a kind of complicated
relationship between data and that total energy
beat up hearing in a ratio of two songs over all
of these microstates. Fortunately, we don't need
to extract in terms of energy total.
What we have what we need to do is extract the B,
the dependence of the entropy itself, which we can
do by plugging in the of the equation. Twenty nine
that we now have for. These probabilities in terms
of these the multipliers, Souleymane.
The interest of time wrap up just with. This last
gap here where there is a
healthy way of doing the calculation, which is. To
just insert the probability so it's not going to
fit on the screen at once, only insert this. When
it was times you didn't mind the speed of energy
for one of these two factors of probability that
show up in the expression for the entropy, we.
Recently computed, so you will steal some of my
pie. And then consider the launch of this one over
Z, if the minus beta time's energy, that depends
on I am using the usual manipulations of log's. We
have. The longer the product is the sum of the
logs or whatever it is, the negative said the
negative cancels with that. Ah, so we have on our
blog Z. With the Selm over just peahi. That's
something we know goes to one second term is going
to have the log of the exponential of minus V the
times, the longer the exponential is just its
argument. They would be the times negative for.
Is our data with the overall positive sign that we
have the some over the remaining. With the
energies of. Each micro state by. And what we saw
in equated thirty one just above here that this
some of our times, PI times is just that total
energy left with.
Said. Plus, the remaining factor, Zubayda. Times.
The total energy of the system of our replica, so
not quite enough time today to. Reach the goal of
removing all information about that, he Beth.
We'll recap this and wrap it up on Friday, which
maybe nice to take a few days off and then come
back to this and see if it still makes sense on
Friday morning, if there are any questions to
shout about otherwise. I will see you later this
week.