OK, the bells are ringing, so let's start to get things set up
and in focus.
The attendance system number four today is
seven two, seven six, three
one.
Welcome to the end of February.  The days are
getting longer, though it's not obvious when the
weather's like this.  At least the projector should
be more visible in these conditions with less glare. Are
there any immediate questions from last week before we
pick up where we left off and continue on this
week.
Let's go through a quick recap to.
Remember where we were and where we're headed.
For.
February.
So we have been looking at.
Ideal gas is through the economical ensemble.
Which is the experimental setup, the situation
where we fixed the temperature in the protocol
number of the particles in this gas. And the.
Energy levels are a starting point for statistical
analysis of many political systems.
Turned out to. We define that. In terms of the
voyeurweb. In which this ideal guest is. Can find
his style. We are taking to the. A Cuban box
belonging to the three sides, both sides in three
dimensions. And. From those energy levels, the.
Compute the canonical partition function.
And see how they differ or distinguishable.
Versus indistinguishable particles.
Short order, and so the canonical protection
function for indistinguishable particles is just
in powers of a single particle. Protection
function, and this differs by effective, in fact,
will compare to the case where the particles are
indistinguishable. And this leads on to. The same
results. For the average internal energy that can
be distinguishable, indistinguishable pieces, both
of which are three halves times the number of
particles times the temperature. But different
entropies.
Reflecting the different number of microstates
that we can have a smaller number in the
dismissable case. The three havstein plus 10 times
war could be over. The cube of the thermal
wavelength, it depends on the mass of the
particles, their temperature and plank's comes to
take part in the indistinguishable case decreases
to five heads,
plus a similar ratio now and again, factor being
subtracted and disinterment. Led to the so-called
Gibs paradox.
Tried to go through slowly and carefully on Friday,
looking at.
The. Different behavior that results when. Yes,
it's either distinguishable or INDISTINCTIVE, the
particles are mixed or allowed to be exchanged
between two phones through the sequence of steps
show. In these three squares, finding in the case
of insatiable radicals.
That the. Mixing was reversible, and the
activities of all three of those stages were.
Exactly the same.
And this. It was, at least historically, the
origin of paradox, and folks believed that the
sort of mixing of particles was always going to be
reversible. And we went through the mathematics
where the distinguishable case.
We found that. The process was irreversible.
There was a definite increase in the entropy going
from the initial separated subsystems to the
combined system where they were allowed to mix and
and quality of handwaving arguments that. The
final individual interviews would be the same,
would then require a decrease in injury from that
combined system to the final set up, which would
contradict the second ballot for the Debix by
being more careful about precisely how these
attributes are calculated. We were able to confirm
that there is, in fact, no paradox here, and the
entropy continues to remain the same as the wall
between these two subsystems is reinserted in that
final step. And that is where we ended up on
Friday. As you go through carefully, this three
step procedure in these two different cases of
distinguishable versus indistinguishable particles,
illustrating the different behavior that results
just based on the information content about the
systems that we can access in principle. So we are
going now to turn to a slightly different topic.
So this is the last call for questions about what
came up last week, and especially in the context
of this thought experiment of mixing particles
between systems that we separated.
Not hearing any. We have this next topic, so we'll
be able to zoom in on. Now to make it more legible.
Gets back to the starting point for this ideal gas,
it's and the fact that when we were first.
Constructing the precision functions and figuring
out how to sum over all of the possible
microstates of these systems, we saw that in
addition to the fixed temperature and particle
number that always characterise systems in the
canonical ensemble, there was dependence on the
volume within which this gas was contained. And
this introduces in addition to the. At the usual
temperature of the number that were used to the
volume as an additional control forever or
something that we can imagine experimentally
manipulating, changing in some way, which will
cause some response of the. Behavior of the system
coming through its partition function and
generally through the
particular energies of the individual, microstates
that enter into that petition function from which
we were able to derive. All of the. Observable is
of interest in the canonical ensemble, so we
didn't see this sort of thing earlier, even
microeconomic ensemble is the magnetic field
strength age for cinema systems. That was a
parameter that we could imagine in experimental
set up, take our system, expose it to a larger,
stronger magnetic field. We don't want it to feel
get a different behavior as a consequence. But if
we focus now on the ideal gases.
Even though this dependence on the volume dropped
out of the internal energy.
Average internal energy being just three halves
empty for both distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles. Dependence remains in
both cases for the entropies. For both types of
particles, and in particular, it is. Entering as a
ratio, the volume divided by the cube of this
Somodevilla wavelength. Which brings together a
particular combination of programmers, thermal
deviling wavelength, we can remember what right
down the whole expression of this recall is
proportional to one over the square root of
temperature. So that ratio of the over land cube
is then proportional to the times. The three has
power of temperature. And if.
The volume and temperature are changed in such a
way that this. Constant product, the volume times
temperature of the three have power is constant
then with the particle number also fixed. We see
that the overall entropy of these systems is
constant even as we change the volume and the
temperature.
This is going to be significant when we analyze
the damage cycles coming up possibly later today
or tomorrow. The latest. Processes in which we
change the control parameters of our system but
leave the entropy constant in some way, are known
as entropic, which is just a construction based on
the Greek word isostatic means equal. So these are
processes that leave the entropy equal from the
beginning and the end. When? We imagine making
changes to control parameters like the volume and
the temperature. We've already seen these sorts of
changes, the control parameters, for instance, the
canonical ensemble. We had the temperature being
defined as the change of entropy with the change
in the conserve energy in the canonical context
was considered. So the response of the entropy to
a change in the conserved energy and already in
the canonical ensemble, the heat capacity which is
showing up in your home due Thursday, is another
example of this sort of change, in that case, the
change in that energy with respect to temperature.
With the volume fixed. Here. Motivated to some
extent by that heat capacity, just slid off the
screen there, we can think about flipping the
roles of Temperature Boy and.
And. Defined in that way, the pressure for an
ideal gas, which.
We'll get into a bit more thoroughly later on, is
connected to some changes. Imagine taking some
ideal gas in a container and talk to you about
thinking of that ideal gas inside a building. We
try to change the volume of that building by
squeezing it into some smaller space, the small
box. We feel a force opposing our attempts to
change that volume. The force is arising from the
pressure of the gas as we try to change its mind.
And specifically, we define the pressure to be the
change in the internal energy, the drive quantity
of one somewhat due to infinitesimal change the
volume with the entropy caps fixed. So the fancy
terminology that we introduced this pressure is
the isotropic response of the internal energy to
the volume of the ideal gas.
And the. One.
Possible cause for concern about this sort of
definition or discussion in general is whether you
may depart from. The defining conditions of the
economic cycle, if we are to talk about changes in
volume or, for instance, changes in temperature
and the heat capacity. And similar to the similar
concerns could have come up when we introduced the
temperatures drive quality, a case where we can
get around this by supposing that when we have
some process that changes the. Um. Characteristics
of the system we are considering in particular is
temperature of volume, internal energy. We can
analyze such a process still within the canonical
ensemble. I am treating it so, viewing it as a
change from one canonical system with a fixed
temperature and particle, no. To some other
economical system. Again, all of these enfolded
equilibrium. With differenced. Temperatures
defining difference in global systems and then
considering the process through which we
transition from one of these large scale systems
to another.
So as a. The first example of this is the ideal
gas we have. Since just last week, this condition
for the continental ideal gas, regardless of
whether the particles in this gas are
distinguishable or indistinguishable. That is this
combination, the volume times, the three heads
power of the temperature is some possible call for
convenience, C, that the power we have so that I
can rearrange this equation and we get the
temperature being related to this constant C times
the volume to the minus two thirds power, dividing
three by the volume two thirds power of each side.
And when. The temperature and volume of this
relation. The entropy is constant. We have.
Isotropic.
Process.
And going back again to what we drive last week,
you can insert
this relation, this condition for the entropy of
the process to be constants into the internal
energy as a function of the particle number and
the temperature.
That now becomes, in the case of entropy, a
function of particle number and the volume being
raised to the power of minus two thirds, then
plugging this expression into our new definition
of the pressure, along with the pressure for life,
you'll get us all to a head in with the substances
that the unenlightening.
Algebraic manipulations. The point is that by
expressing the energy in terms of the conditions
for entropy be are satisfying the cause of entropy
condition that defines the volume. And given the
result, that is minus three C of the two and is a
constant factor that comes up front and then the
derivative of the power minus two thirds with
respect to the Z factor of minus two thirds or
whatever, the same B to the minus two thirds,
which cancels out some factors and. Rearrange
things to have the remaining arbitrary constancy
in that with this. Remaining power leads by two
thirds in addition to the one of people out front.
This.
See times minus two thirds. Bill is still the
temperature and overall, we then find that the
pressure for an ideal gas is the number of
chemicals times the temperature divided by the
volume of gas, which, if we multiply through by
the volume, gives us a famous expression of is the
ideal gas law. It says that for ideal gas, the
product of the pressure and the volume is equal to
the product of the number of times the temperature.
And. This ideal gas law, if you check out some of
the textbooks that were referenced just at the
very beginning of the course, you will sometimes
see this introduced as the definition of the ideal
gas. An ideal gas is any substance that obeys
small. We've taken the opposite approach started
from microstates, the macroeconomic side, like
microscopic dynamics of these systems and built up
to the equation state rather than going from the
top down. I realize I just referred to this as an
equation of the states without defining what
exactly that is.
So the ideal gas law is a relation between the
large scale properties of the system, the
macroscopic qualities of it, in this case, the
pressure, volume and temperature that the internal
energy we've also seen is directly related to the
temperature as another
large scale property of the system. So the states
that this is an equation of is really a way of
saying that it is a relation between these
macroscopic properties of the system. Which is
part of the reason I've been referring to
microstates throughout the module so far that the
state's been discussed here, are not the
individual microstates corresponding to the
disposition of all in degrees of freedom in the
canonical example? Rather, the.
Collection of large scale properties like pressure
building and temperature that define what's called
the thermodynamic stage or the macro stage of the
system.
So.
Rather than depending on the detailed information
about all of these all and degrees of freedom,
this macro state is characterized just by the
large scale behaviour of, in this case, the ideal
gas. And as such, historically at least.
The initial scientific explorations of gases,
fluids and systems in general were focused on
these Makarova states that could be observed and
manipulated with the kind of technology that
existed hundreds of years ago. So historically,
those sorts of experimentations of systems of
gases, fluids with well-defined volumes,
temperatures and pressures were studied well
before the mathematical development of statistical
physics,
the famous example being all the way back before
in the sixteen hundreds. The physicist Robert
Boyle experimented with changing the temperature
of a gas station to the pressure on the gas to its
temperature fixed and measuring the volume that
resulted from that. An experiment that could be
done in the sixteen hundreds in finding a relation
between the pressure he was using as a control
parameter in those experiments and the volume he
was measuring and finding that those two
quantities were inversely related to each other,
or in other words, that their product was
constants so long as the temperature of the gas
under consideration was also constant, which
started from the ideal gas law. We can see is. A
direct consequence, though, as this came first,
historically, it became known as Boyle's law, at
least in England and France, and share his name
with a French physicist. I did similar things
about 20 years later. And.
Building on the sort of. Observation,
observational discovery that the pressure and
volume related in this way, more than one hundred
years later, various other relations between the
properties of. Thermodynamic states of gases were.
Discovered in the late seventeen hundreds of early,
eighteen hundreds. For instance, all of which not
named after subsets of the scientists who were
exploring these ideas at the time. So, for
instance, holding the pressure constant and
varying the temperature of the gas, and scientists
were able to measure again that the. The volume
varied in this case proportional to the
temperature. In other words, the ratio of the
resulting volume with the varying temperature was
itself a constant. Which is another aspect of the
ideal gas law and turning this on its side and
fixing the volume, looking at the pressure and the
temperature, gave a completely analogous direct
relationship between pressure that was measured
and the temperature that was put in to the ratio
itself was a different color since the volume
fixed. And this last one here. Oh, God, no. We've
already seen looked at. How the number of
particles in a gas could change at constant
pressure and constant temperature, depending on
the volume and obviously related to coming up with
the. Number two hundred twenty three of particles
in everyday substances. And based on all of these
violations that were being discovered over this
time period without necessarily knowing
mathematically where they came from at the
underlying level. It was possible to combine all
of them into the ideal gas law, which was done in
the 18 years, that was the empirical statement of
the ideal gas law as instead of relations, that
gases were observed to behave without necessarily
knowing why. In a few decades after that, in the
middle of the eighteen hundreds, there were
independents derivations showing how physical
physics could.
Produce all of these different religions and in
particular produce the ideal gas itself along the
lines that we've seen in the past. In the past
week. So there are two
lessons, two to say about this sort of historical
development.
First, being that there was a.
Tight connection between a lot of these
experimentations in the sort of idealized behavior
of gases as an abstract question and the kinds of
industrial engineering and.
It's called.
Industrial developments, including designing
engines and machines like that, was happening at
the same time with a more practical focus, trying
to build new machines to. On. To do work in
different ways is part of the industrial
revolution, so a dialogue between sort of pure
mathematical understanding of the physics
underlying. The systems that play really
contributed to and benefited from all of the
experimentation and exploration being done in the
engineering side of. Industrial development in the
Industrial Revolution. The other. Aspect of this
to emphasize is that the 18 50 is the derivation
of the Gastar from ideas of statistical physics
was really the start. Get kicked off a long
running debate about the extent to which the
statistical physics, the idea that. We can
understand the behavior of substances because they
are built up of a large number of atoms and
molecules that debates covid starts through this,
this result in particular the results of research
showing that making that assumption or
hypothesized. That atoms and molecules were at the
basis of gases and and other substances could
reproduce the ideal gas law, but it didn't resolve
the debate about whether those atoms and molecules
really existed, which kept running throughout all
of Boltzmann's career and up to and beyond. The
demonstration started with how Brownian motion can
result from statistical physics. On the situation,
following the development of the ideal gas on the
leader, eighteen hundreds was a bit analogous to
the situation string theory that I mentioned in
our first class meeting, where we know in
principle, at least these days, that string theory
can describe the new laws of physics, both general
relativity and quantum mechanics. But it's unknown
whether it's the only way to do so and how
seriously we should take the idea. That everything
we see is really made out of these fundamental
strands at a extremely microscopic level. There
may be other explanations that have been being
considered, and that would seem and that's
analogous to the arguments going on one hundred
and fifty years ago about the existence of atoms
and molecules and whether they are truly
responsible for the large scale macroscopic
behavior. Of gases and other other substances. So
that is that's a bit of a extended commentary from
me and also the end of the unit for introducing
ideal gases and before diving into the next unit,
which. He's going to use these IP addresses to. To
do work engines or cool substances in
refrigerators, apologists for a minute and ask if
there are any questions about any of the ideal gas.
Fundamentals that we've gone through over the past
week from the volume dependent energy levels to
this definition of the pressure and the ideal gas
more.
So it sounds like we are content to move on the
phone and in cycles, which will start by. Putting
the pressure was just introduced on a more
familiar framework, since I'm assuming. You see,
the previous modules were familiar in everyday
life, the intuitive connection between the
pressure and force and the connection between
pressure and work coming through force and some of
the classical Newton's laws of motion from those
from the 16 hundreds where these concepts were
being developed. So the. The definition of
pressure, which is just an earlier today as
isotropic response in the internal energy to a
change in the volume is not obviously related to
to doing work. I did. Talk about squeezing a
balloon into a box is an idea.
Connecting the pressure to a change in volume,
sort of a force on the volume of the system to
change it thereby.
Extracts pressure. And what we can do to make this
connection a bit more explicit is by stepping back
to just considering rather than a full statistical
ensemble, just a single object at some position in
three dimensional space, some latitude, longitude
and altitude that some force acts upon at that
same position. And the the work done by this force.
Is a definition you may well have seen before, it
is how much? The energy changes due to that force.
Directed along the displacement of the object, you
mentioned some. Trajectory of an object moving
through. Three dimensional space and we exerts a
force on it. At some point in that trajectory and
the a product of that force in the position. Is
going to produce a change in the energy. Of the
object that is defined as the work, that's the
infinitesimal definition of the word which
generalizes to a light integral to the trajectory
of the object. Of the other product of the force
and cell times, the resulting displacement.
So just to give you an example, to check that this
all works out, we can start with this object at
some height above the ground, let it be stationary
to start with, and then drop it and let it fall
under the force of the Earth's gravity. Which is
just directed downward, the Z direction, so zero
in the X and Y components and the negative,
sometimes G in Z components, the negative side
indicating downward force as opposed to upward the
masking, the mass of the object and the mass of
the object. And this. Given the strength of
gravity near the surface of the earth, nine point
eight meters per second squared.
With the initial kinetic energy of this object
being zero starting from rest. As the object falls
downward parallel to the south, the work that is
done on it is going to. Increase in temperature of
some.
Kinetic energy that upon hitting the ground,
starting from a height H. Is going to come from
this line integral, introduced to both the force
and the displacements in this case in parallel, so
the entire product becomes a simple product. You
have minus M.G. as the. That component of the
force and then you have to integrate over the
vertical distance that the object falls is
integrating from its initial height H down to zero,
the ground zero, which is minus H. Your product,
then, is the best times, three gravity times the
initial height. And if we. Plug that into the
expression for the work as a change in the energy
from its initial value of zero. We find that the
final energy of the object is just energy age,
which we can relate to the momentum of the object.
Again, the only non-zero component is that
subcomponent. And rearranging find that the
momentum is direct, a downward portion of the mass
times, the square root of two times the initial
height. So the classic result of classical
mechanics that connects to the idea of work as a
force in the project to change its energy. Now, we
want to generalize this to statistical physics, we
have some number, a large number of objects in a
statistical ensemble of specialized. We'll be
talking about the economic ensemble still and
specifically ideal gases and particles in the
canonical ensemble.
So we define the work done by a force. To me, the
change in the internal energy of the system that
drives quality, that is specifically due to that
force and the way we will tell in general whether
a change in energy is due to a force or not is
precisely through that connection to the volume.
It's going to be the volume of the gas that is the
control parameter being changed by the application
of the force and doing a similar. Simple
calculation to the case of that single falling
object we can consider.
This settlement covid from one of the references
in the lecture notes where we have. A of gas and
some fixed temperature with some fixed number of
particles in the system with some initial volume.
And we imagine that one side. Out of the box to
find it, this boy is a movable piston that has a
surface area any and by acting on this piston with
some force, we're able to push it into the box,
decreasing the volume by that surface area, times
the displacement of the Pistons and try to exit
the change in volume. Is the surface area of the
boom times, the amount it moves, the negative sign,
reflecting that the volume is decreasing? Well, I
think I just said out loud all of the words here,
except for the condition that change in volume, we
can demand that this process does not change the
entropy of the gas.
And that allows us to connect this process, this
force in the work done by it, to the pressure that
we defined earlier today, the end of unit for.
Where there will be some change in the energy due
to the decrease in the valadier with a fixed
entropy and that change. In the energy is due to
the force that we have applied to change that
volume and is therefore the work. That's. You're
defined to be the change, the energy due to an
external force.
Set that aside for now, looking at the.
Product of the sports times, the displacement of
the piston that it causes. We can relate the. Work
the force, which depends on the displacements,
then also appears in the change in the volume. So
replacing this. Differential expression with the
overall change in energy and the overall change in
volume, both of those dependent. On the
displacement of the piston, and we end up with the
pressure being identified with the force per unit
area that is exerted on the system to change the
volume of our gas, which is essentially
reproducing. The. Classical definition of pressure
as a force divided over some univariate. And if we
rearrange this equation. Fifty seven. We can
express the work in terms of the pressure and
change the volume, so taking this intermediate.
Expression. That depends on those general
qualities multiplied through by the change in
volume. You see that if we demand constant entropy,
we have the work as the change in internal energy
equal to the negative of the pressure times and
change the bottom. That negative side, we can
check all this sticky back to the example we just
did, changing the hour, decreasing the border
specifically. So a negative change avoiding. It's
something that we have a sense it's going to
require pushing on a in meeting resistance and
putting energy to work into the ideal gas that we
are considering. In the south. So that is the way
to remember the presence of this negative sign.
And this relation, in fact, holds even when the
entropy is allowed to change, so this expression
generalizes, the work is always going to be. Equal
to the negative pressure times, changing the world
in general, but in the case of. A process that is
not isotropic would the entropy is allowed to
change, it will no longer be guaranteed that this
change of is the only way that the energy can
change, that there will be other contributions to.
The internal energy of the gas that are not coming
from the force that is being imposed change the
volume and therefore not part of the work as we to
it.
And thinking at the time will make a couple last
comments for today, first that in.
The next few sections, so starting tomorrow, we're
going to be interested in using the gas to do work
on its surroundings so there's extra burdens. So
rather than thinking about us pushing on the
piston to do work on a gas and increase its
internal energy, we're going to want to talk about
using the energy that is in that gas to somehow be
harnessed and do work. Surroundings are driving a
truck that can turn into a new video or perhaps
coupling that to an axle that will allow a car to
to drive, move forward or backward. And in the
case where we have the gas that's doing and its
surroundings, the change in internal energy is
going to be negative, that work is going to be
negative. We would want to see positive change in
the volume, but we're going to have to give pretty
careful track of the negative signs which
distinguish between whether. This gas in our
system is too important and its surroundings where
the work is being done to that gas.
Finally, if we recall the ideal gas law in the.
With the pressure. May well depend on the volume
and temperature, so that is an expression for
pressure we provide for an ideal guest here today.
As we make this change in volume, we can expect
the pressure to change as well. So. More generally,
if we always fix the particle no and consider a
change. In the volume to extract the work, we will
have to not just multiply the constant pressure
times somehow to change the body, but actually
integrate over the infinitesimal changes of volume
that each lead to a corresponding response in the
pressure, integrating from some initial warming to
a final volume that integral of pressure times,
the volume differential is going to give the
overall work of that process. So that is a good
place to start for now to cope with heat as
another way of changing energy tomorrow morning.
Are there any final questions before? Wrap up for
today.
If not, I will start shooting things down here.
Move over to my office hours in case any questions
about the homework due Thursday. And if I don't
see you there, I'll see you back in the other room
tomorrow morning.
What
role?
So.