Well, about time we get going once more.  I suppose
we won't have to deal with the issue of too much sun
causing a glare on the screen today. Though,
overall, I would have preferred that to walking in
from Wavertree in this weather.  Let's see...
Several things are going wrong at a technical
level at the moment. So the last person in this
room yesterday didn't plug in that little microphone.
So I hope that those who are connected remotely
can hear me through the built-in one sticking out
of the table.  The printing system also went down
yesterday. So we'll have to use my digital paper
here to keep track of what's going on, and look at
what that six-digit code for you is today.
So the magic number is six two five five one four
What I've put up on the screen is the tail end of what
we were talking about yesterday, wrapping up. Unit
three on the canonical ensemble, which I did rush
through a bit at the end just to get to that, to
bring in stopping points of wrapping up that whole
unit. And the particular one thing I forgot to
mention at the time was that in order to. Have a
non-zero value for the symbolic high temperature
limits of the indistinguishable entropy, which is
the slogan plus one, when everything normalize by
and for the purposes of this plot, that number of
spins is being set to fall. And you can check that
compared to the log to one quarter log, five is
about two thirds as large, matching the numerical
value shown here. That doesn't affect the. I mean,
qualitative message to take away that just by
changing our assumptions about whether the
particles in a system are distinguishable or not,
which is to say by adjusting our assumptions about
how much information is available about those
particles in principle, independent of whatever
technology we might have to distinguish between
them, if in principle, in any way they can be
distinguished. There's there are clear effects
both on the entropy as well as the internal energy
of that system. And that will cause we will
continue seeing similar things as we move on into.
Some of the more traditional playgrounds for the
physical POSIX, but before doing that, I'll ask if
any questions have come to mind. Now that you've
had a few hours to think about what we looked at
yesterday, especially that bit at the end. That
was a little rushed.
And up here in the room, Moore was connected
remotely. We will.
Move on to a second application of the canonical
ensemble. So, again, fixing the temperature
through a thermal ensemble, fixing the number of
particles and considering an.
Bit more length and more detail the. Topic of
ideal gases and what ideal means is one of the
objectives to start off with specifying the
systems to. To consider in this unit, so it's a
bit more a bit less trivial application compared
to just the speed systems to keep things.
Reasonably simple to start off with. We will
specialize this focus to ideal gases that are both
classical and non relativistic and I'm not sure,
given the. Different sets of modules that you may
have taken before now, how familiar all of this
terminology may be. So just to review it and feel
free to ask for
further elaboration if if you wanted the classical
systems just means that we are ignoring any
effects of quantum mechanics or classical is not
quantum. And that's easy to say. It has some
subtle consequences, one of which being that you
can imagine. We can specify both the position and
momentum of every particle in the gas with
arbitrary precision, which is not the case.
Quantum mechanically and I guess implicit in my
use of three vectors for position and momentum is
the idea that we'll be looking at these gases in
some three dimensional space. And not relativistic
particles, similarly, that we ignore effects due
to relativity, both special and general.
In this context of Agassiz, this means that the
particles in this gas are moving relatively slowly
where the relatively is taking a comparison to the
speed of light. Three hundred million meters per
second, which means that the energies of each of
these particles is just going to be given by the
expression that came out of Newton's laws of
motion all the way back in the sixteen hundreds.
But the energy is. What happened V squared B is
the velocity of the movie is the momentum. So we
end up with energy use for each particle that have
the momentum squared of that particle, the product
of those three vectors divided by twice the mass
of the particle, which we. We can assume is now
zero and it turns out that having a relatively
heavy mass is equivalent to particles moving with
speed, small compared to the speed of light might
be massless particles. And finally, ideally, Gas's,
which is the the big one that comes in, that the
title of the unit just says that these particles
in this gas are not interacting with each other.
In other words, the total energy of a system of
any gas particles and molecules we think of.
Absolutely. The air in a room is just the sum over
the energies of those individual particles with
their individual momentum. So how does a factor of
one over two and all the particles have the same
mass? And then to sum over all of the moment to
squared, so that is the statement of the system
will be considering. Are there any objections to
the classical and non relativistic terminology?
Having well, there is one more piece of
information to specify about the system. In
addition to the gasping and thermodynamic
equilibrium, what we will be assuming from now on.
And he fixed temperature. We will be assuming that
the gas is in some volume, a box that again for
simplicity, will it take to be a cube and the
three dimensional space, the total volume that is
L cubed, where L is the length of that box on each
side. So given the specification of the system and
in particular of the energy of that system, the
starting point for an analysis of the kinetic
ensemble is to determine the canonical protection
function, some overall microstates of the
exponential function, the Boltzmann factor. That
depends on the total energy of that microstates,
something overall and particles normalized by the
temperature. And this. Computing the summer
requires. Figuring out what the microstates are to
some over and if we. Did the intuitive thing and
just said that. These momentum three vectors for
each particle, we assume can be.
Determined with arbitrary precision so they can be.
Viewed as a triple loop continuously, very real
numbers, that is problematic in this context,
because real numbers, as we know, are an
uncomfortably infinite set. And if we have a set
of microstates, then essentially, by definition,
it is impossible to count. Those microstates
through this discreet, some over them estimation
would be ill-Defined if we were to assume that all
the men were continuously variable. So to avoid
that issue and recover a well-defined. Economic
competition function for statistical analysis, we
need to it's called regulate the system or
sometimes called regularizing the system for those
who prefer extra syllables. What we can say is
that rather than having those moments of being
continuously variable, we can posit that the
momentum can only adopt some set of discrete,
quantized values that we further assume depend on
the volume of the box that they are contained in.
Now.
Is to be specific, before going on to commentary.
What this does is takes that momentum three vector
and recasts it as. A. Triplet of integers, X, Y, Z,
with some dimension for every factor that carries
the dimensions of the matter, that attaches them
to these integers.
The. A key feature of this factor is this constant,
which is an age with a slash through it known as H
Bar or the reduced Planck constant. Which converts
those units from that inverse length normalize by
PI to units of momentum. And.
If you have seen quantum mechanics before him,
they will recognize this as cauterizes quantum
mechanically. It is the particle in the box
problem that is the starting point for a lot of
quantum mechanics modules. But for the purposes of
this module, we don't have to assume quantum
mechanics or any knowledge about it, we can take
this as an island, which. In fact, it's similar to
the spirit in which Max Planck introduced his
constant and a similar sort of hypothesis more
than a decade before quantum mechanics was was
really formalized. He saw that. Regularization of
the sort had to be required to avoid.
Nonsensical predictions from considering certain
physical systems and just to make sure that the
meaning of this equation forty seven is clear can
write down the energies that result so. For a
given. Integer vector k corresponding energy is OK
is just that momentum over to M, which brings in a
factor that each of our squared pi squared over to
and elsewhere and that factor then we enter
product of. X to Y. And casette
and. If I just write that Cowslip Prefecture, each
Achbar Square pipe over to that now as some script
E!
You can. Check that this makes sense by.
Considering what possible set of energies are
possible with this onsets, so all energy is have
this overall pretty factor of the these cases are
not negative integers, and if all three of them
are zero, but the energy is zero, and if one, two
or three of those cases are one, then the energies
of SCRIMPY times one, two or three. So what comes
next in the list of energies?
Shout it out when you. I have an idea.
I can't quite hear what's coming next was.
Indeed, you can have four when any one of those
key squared or any one of the cases, two squares
before and the other two are zero sum, so there's
a five and a six when we have two. And one of the
others will go to the others. The one what comes
after six.
Exactly. There's no way to get seven, we have to
have two of those caves being to get four plus
four with zero or plus one.
And once, of course, we get to nine, then one of
those kids can be free, the others can be zero or
one or one plus one. We can have a four plus four
plus four kids, 12 and a nine plus four kids, 13,
nine four one four 14. And.
Nine. It's the. After that, from nine for one, we
have to jump up to nine for four or 17.
Right. And so on. So there are gaps coming from
this. Disorganization where?
These three individuals cannot add up to. Certain
integers. That's exactly what it was. It's just
the devil in those etcs. So. These numbers don't
include seven.
And then.
15, 16.
So this is giving back, giving us back a bit
closer to those systems that we had in the
previous application where the energies were
falling into discrete energy levels.
Though we have just seen that the energy gaps
between the levels and the system are not constant,
and especially as those integer cases go to larger
numbers. The big gaps between accessible energy
levels will start to to grow.
We'll skip some of these into spaces in this.
Basic unit. Each R-squared. Types would never
cheat and elsewhere.
Another difference with that system is that these
entities can grow without bound, even for a finite
number of particles, and so there's still an
infinite number of possible moments and possible
energy levels. And even for a single particle in
this box, that would be an infinite number of
energy levels. But these are now countable,
related to subsets of the positive, not negative
integers. Which means that our some accounts,
these microstates is a meaningful medical function,
giving us a well-defined canonical protection
function, and even though it was a bit counter to
the spirit of the statistical physics of large
collections of particles, we can start by
considering what the protection function would be
for just a single particle in this gas, in this
stupid box. Where the microstates are, then we sum
over these possible non-negative values of the
integers, k is causality running from zero up to
infinity, plugging in. The energy written down
above and dividing it by the temperature to get a
dimensionless quantity that could go in the
exponential, so distributing the exponential of a
sum into a product of exponential. We can
rearrange these infinite songs. We always want to
be careful when doing so, because sometimes bad
things can happen in this case, the independence
of the moment in each of these three spatial
dimensions. Allows us to distribute the sums over
Kidwai kids at. Without. Running into any problems
and we can recognize that each of these three sons
that are being multiplied together are completely
identical. So we have a single sum over some. OK,
from zero to infinity, and that overall sum ends
up being cubed for this single particle.
Next, that's what we do with this song, is
actually simplify it by the sense now that our
system has been regulated or regularized, we can
go back to working with continuously varying real
degrees of freedom that are. You need to work with
now that elements of invented calculus and we
could motivate this by. Considering this factor,
each party squared PI squared over to him
elsewhere, times the temperature that appears in
these energies. So if we.
Bringing in some knowledge about the domains where
relativistic physics and quantum physics come into
play. We can. Recognize or take his input that
place, Constance, this bar is far smaller than all
the other numbers that appear in this expression
in particular, I mentioned earlier that if that if
the mass of the particles gets too small. Then
relativistic effects become important. So this is
our assumption of non relativistic particles means
that.
This is a fairly large number, if the temperature
is too low, we will eventually have to worry about
quantum effects or assumption that. There's
passage classical ensures that the temperature is
relatively large compared to calcium. And finally,
if the volume of this box. Is too small. And we.
Also run into quantum effects or just not have
enough particles to justify its statistical
analysis in the first place and. Recognizing that
this function are sending over.
Is then going to be extremely small numbers for.
Any of these non-negative integers, hey, at least
when those are small enough to leave this
exponential factor non-negotiable. We can't
replace these discrete integers with a smoothly
varying. Continuous real number and go from the
discrete, some coming from some of the microstates
to end integration over that smoothly varying.
Real parameter will look cat to distinguish it
from the integer K, so each of the three songs
appearing in that single particle partition
function become an integral minging to this K
ranging from zero to infinity of that same
exponential factor. And in this case, that squared
which. You can change the. No amount of
integration to make things look a little more
gorshin just by bringing in the factor of two.
Thanks to all the functional attendance in here,
just being on the powers of have squared. Coming
from that exponential.
And given that we're working with real variables
again, now that we've regularized the system and
have things we'll be able to find, we can convert
back from this. Dimensionless real parameter came
add to the momentum that are related to it by the
same factor four times over. So in the end. Each
of these sums into your case, it's converted into.
And integral to the full range of momentum. And we
end up putting this or taking the cube of this
integral to account for the momentum in all three
directions. There are three factors of. Now over
to a high bar looking up front that the integral
over the full three dimensional space of momentum,
so the three integral over the volume of this
exponential function, converting back to the. In
her product of these three vector momentum. And a
similar process of multiplying together many
different integrals takes us from the single
particle competition function to the. Protection
function for people and particle's. As just like
those different components of the momentum, all of
these particles are independent and not
interacting with each other thanks to considering
ideal gases. And if we assume that we can
distinguish the particles from each other, every
single one of them is going to bring in. The
factor of. Eligible by age two times is three
integral. So we have in total and a little bit
more to the power of three nd and then an integral
over three end components of momentum. The
exponential growth from a sum over all of those
particles labeled by the lower case and here.
And I think I copied and pasted going in there
that.
Is that some shidduch? Being there, if we have.
Where it should go up to the overall end
accounting for all of the particles in that gas, I
will fix that notation in the version of lecture
notes online later on today.
That was just meant to count all of the end
moments coming from the particles that we can pass
to the upper limits on that situation should not
have gone to infinity. What we can do is. Actually
carry out. Any single one of these integrations
before multiplying them all together, that's just
an ordinary kid grow over. In particular, inner
product of the momentum for the corresponding
particle and the corresponding component. And this
is, as I mentioned, when we reintroduced it, just
to get an integral that brings in a factor of Rupi
times, the coefficient multiplying P squared,
which is one over. The inverse of twenty over a
factor of two, three times that three factor L
over to my age and bringing things all together.
We can simplify the notation by. Replacing.
This complicated square root of a ratio of the
mass of the particle times, the temperature
divided by two PI squared, calling that one over
some lambda t h. That depends on the temperature.
So this is.
A step taken for notational convenience where?
We've introduced what is called this to. Is. The
thermal deploy wavelength.
As best I can pronounce that French name rudeboy
where. This wavelength that. I guess we don't have
to worry too much about the interpretation of this
factor, as
it turns out, if you.
Go through the exercise of inserting units for
recounting for what all the units are on each bar,
the mass of the temperature. This comes as the
square root comes out to have units of length. And
is reflecting essentially the.
Wavelike behavior of these particles in the box
coming from quantum mechanics, essentially
measuring how much space each particle is is
taking up, given the temperature and given to the
mass of that particle. All we can have to worry
about the quantum mechanics here, we can just
treat this as an additional inconvenience, ending
up with this overall. Protection function for an
essential particles that.
Comes in as just the ratio of the total length of
the box containing those particles divided by. The.
Thermal wavelengths, another quantity with units
of length to make this event dimensionless no
reason, the power of three and four of three
special directions X, Y, Z and all and particles
in the system if we redistribute that. In Cuba, we
can recall that the volume of our covid box is
allocute and can rewrite this as the ratio of that
volume to the different wavelength lambda cubed.
All of that raised to the power and for the
particles in the system.
So that is. The partition function, the ending of
the derivation of the starting point for any
statistical physics analysis of ideal gases and
the canonical ensemble. So apart from the typo I
had in, there were the individual steps of the
argumentation in what we were doing to derive this
unobjectionable.
And not hearing any objections, I will give you. A
few more observations before we go on to actually
drive things about this ideal gas is one thing to
note is that in addition to the temperature that
gets wrapped up into the DeBois wavelength, Lambda
T h and the number of particles in which we should
expect to characterize any statistical system
analyzing the chemical ensemble, there's also
dependence on the volume of the gas, which is
going to persist in some of the quantities that we
derive. A lot more to say about that later on this
week.
And one of the comment to put in here is, again,
without some reference to the work we were doing
yesterday, seeing how. Physical predictions
differed, if we could if we assumed that we could
distinguish between different particles in the
system or if all those particles were
indistinguishable. We should see what would happen
to the protection function if we were to have
indistinguishable particles convention, just as an
aside, that.
Quantum mechanics will also require
indistinguishable particles to the assumption that
we can say, look at the particles of the gas and
put labels on them. It may be. Too small to see
here. Why don't you zoom in on the assumption that
we can. Label the particles in the system, say, a.
And be it distinguish between different labelling
of sets of particles with identical memento. That
is something that is only possible in classical
systems. And there's another consequence that
arises from. Our assumption or simplification of
dealing just with classical, non quantum. Ideal
gas is for the time being.
And. Given that. Setting where classical physics
allows us to.
Impose labels or apply labels to different
particles doesn't require that it is possible to
apply these sorts of labels. There's no practical
way to do that for TV.
The nitrogen and the water molecules that are
opposing the atmosphere in this room, there's no
way to label a particular molecule, molecule A,
molecule molecule B and tell them apart. And the
absence of those labels, then the two states that
we have here with a given volume temperature for
the system are in fact the same microstates rather
than two distinct ones in the case with those
particles are indistinguishable.
So zooming back out, we can think about what
consequences this has for those storms over
microstates that give us our competition function.
Where we've seen that if we have two particles
here, there is a factor of two difference in the
number of ways of assigning momenta to the
particles that are being labeled when they can be
labeled.
And if we generalize this to. Three particles and.
Look at the various ways those three particles
with pretty momenta could be labeled and the
distinguishable case. Where we assume labeling is
possible, you pretty easily see that. There are a
few more possibilities if we label. Particle A
corresponding to come into one that more to get
the back of the screen.
And we can label the particle with momentum to
call that B and the final label C because the
particle with momentum P three and similarly. Swap
those labels and see just the same way we swap
labels and be. In this illustration. Or go through
the possibility of first labeling. That's particle
with momentum, P one s, B, the other two as A and
C.
Or similarly with the third and final possibility,
so the overall number of possibilities of six, we
can see pretty easily just three factorial.
There's. In general, within particle's, there are
and ways of choosing the label for the first one
in minus one, ways of choosing a label for the
second one and so on, until that last article is
its label is uniquely determined.
And what this means is says is that if we assume
particles are distinguishable, then we will count
a factor of 10 factorial times more microstates
compared to the situation if those particles were
indistinguishable and all of these labeling was.
Just collapse down to a single microstates rather
than in factorial.
So. If we. Repeat the derivation of the partition
function.
We can recognize without reviewing any more
detailed calculations that
the overall factor of squared for every micro
statistic and a single case is just one to come
along for the ride of going to discrete integer
momentum and then coming back to approximate those
by continuous integrations. So we will end up with
that same expression, the volume over the cube of
the word wavelength, always the power in with that
fixed factor of whatever and factorial to correct
for the overcounting that we did in.
The earlier.
Work based on the assumption that particles were
distinguishable.
So.
What we can write down as a conclusion to this
calculation.
Before diving into getting some predictions out of
these parties and functions, is just the
recognition that the. Patricia, function for
indistinguishable particles is. The single
particle partition function refused to empower.
Which is this factory and factory, two times the
production function for indistinguishable articles
is that I compared to the whole related to single
particle production function and one to the power.
And now, based on the. Machinery that we've built
up over the past week or so, we can take these
precision functions and use them to. To make
predictions, compute properties of the large scale
behavior of these gases and targeting just as we
did, and for those spin systems yesterday, looking
first at the internal energy and the entropy of
that gas and the functions of the temperature and
of particle number, as well as the volume within
which the gases contained.
So. We went through the work previously of
relating these observables to the partition
function through that HUMBOLDT'S free energy, the
negative temperature times, the logarithm of the
production function. And if we look at this
equation, gifty one on the top of the page here,
you can see that this logarithm is going to. Break
up into two pieces of logarithm of the product
being distributed as the sum of her logarithms,
this power of three and over two comes down out
front to join the temperature. We have the log of
everything in the parentheses, EMC squared,
squared, and then whatever factor that Vectorial
brings a relative negative sign in to cancel out
the overall negative sign. And we just have the
temperature times, the logarithm of an vectorial
factor,
putting this in the expression for the average
interval energy as the temperature derivative of
the free energy divided by the temperature, which
is just that logarithm, the only place where the
temperature is appearing. In. The logarithm of
this partition function. It's going to be. Right
in that three halves in Lord T squared, we can
break up the remainder of this logarithm to
isolate all of the T independent pieces at
logarithm within Petronius, also to independents.
And the derivative of the logarithm is one over
temperature. So we end up with that whatever
temperature canceling off the second tower of
temperature coming up front. So in the end, three
has a. is the internal energy which we can
interpret as every single one of those and
particles in the gas introducing on average. A an
energy and internal energy of three 1/2 times the
temperature, which is. Fairly remarkable compared
to the complicated function based on the
microscopic momentum of each of those particles
that we started off with just a few minutes ago,
the start of today.
To get the entropy and turn have the relation
between. The Entropia and the difference between
internal energy and free energy normalized by the
temperature, so plugging in this three hands and
feet and dividing that by the temperature, we
start off with an overall factor of three and then
divide up the temperature out of this expression
up here. Leaves us with these two terms that
involve logarithms.
Putting the thermal the wavelength back into this
complicated ratio gets us back to that same ratio
of the. Volume over. The Broadway by Cube that we
had up in the equation 50 wanted to start off with.
Where the blame is coming in, thanks to taking
note that we have pre factor up into the.
Into the argument of the war. And with the log of
L squared to the prehaps, power is cubed is the
volume and similarly for the wavelength, and we've
now seen that scene, what to do, and we have
logarithms of the factorial of large numbers just
plugging in. Sterling's formula at the.
Leading a couple of terms employed in business and
neglecting any terms that are logarithmic and the
more smaller that pops up here and we can combine
these two logarithms that come with that three
factor and into a single one in terms of all of
that volume over end times. But thermal wave
length and then the factors of three thousand plus
and add up to five has an overall.
And.
The next step will be to repeat this process where
the case of the particles, it may well be useful
to return to that on Friday, looking at the time
at the moment. Can.
For the next few days, checking that all of these
steps are clear and can be reproduced in the scan,
the comments will wrap up with to finish off today,
is that. In this ratio of volume over 10 times
that from the different wavelength can actually
interpret the denominator there as the volume
being occupied by all of the particles in the gas.
And we will see later on when we relax our
requirement that the gas be classical and allow
for all the mechanical effects to play a role,
that those effects will start to become important
when this volume occupied by the gas starts to
become comparable to the overall volume of the
container. So I'll stop. There you go for the rest
of your day. Hopefully will dry out now. Any final
questions before I shut things down this morning?
Take care. See you again on Friday.