OK, just about able to get things set up in time
for the top of the hour.  The first thing to set up is
that magic number for today.
Here it is: four eight three
five two five.
Now that is up there for you. Are
there any questions left over from last week?
Brief recap on the 14th of February. Welcome to week
three of Statistical Physics.
Last week, we finished going through the
probability foundations and went into the like on
some levels they have tried. Just way this kind of
stuff, I cringe a bit more pleasurable, it seemed
to be on Friday. And what we focused on specific
to report last week was this concept of we more
famous conceptual quantities in statistical
physics, which we have have seen now both. In a
general definition, that depends on the suburb of
microstates, of probabilities of those microstates
or specializing to micro canonical ensemble.
Interpreter David.
We are all of these probabilities are equal for
every micro state in the system, the entropy just
reduces to the logarithm of the total number of
microstates that this micro economical system can
have at the micro economical system. Is the.
Ensemble that's generated by the illusion of a set
of particles subject to conservation of energy and
particle, No.
Those are the conditions defining the biker
canonical ensemble, and later this week, we will
address those to a different set of conditions
defining the canonical.
Give an interview, Russell. The second law. Of
thermodynamics.
The statement that the Entropia.
Does not decrease. As time goes on, the engineer
actually increases. So the amount of entropy in
the universe really in a closed system can never
decrease, needs to increase as time goes on, which
provided. A more general definition of
thermodynamic equilibrium.
Should be the. Situation.
Or the context where the entropy of the system. Is
maximised.
So.
Taking the derivative maximum entropy observed it
so much that it's not fitting on the screen.
Hopefully I can spell that out, jump back to the
actual place in the lecture notes that we were
looking at last week on Friday, where we have gone
through the process of maximizing the entropy,
modifying it by adding a multiplier to account for
the requirement that the probabilities all add up
to one hundred percent when some of the old
microstates of the system
from that maximisation of the entropy, for the
canonical example, were able to derive the result.
Now that into a dynamic equilibrium, the
probabilities for each microstates in the micro
canonical ensemble is a constant and is therefore
equal to the inverse of the total number of
microstates in order to satisfy this constraint of
probability. So that's where we are. Are there
questions about. Any of that?
Where we are going from here is to continue
driving quantities in the canonical ensemble. We
started off with entropy is the first the most
famous derived quantity. But in this micro
canonical framework, that's. Leaves the conserve
energy and particle no as the fundamental defining
quantities. Also, the temperature itself of the
system becomes the quantity that we derive based
on the most fundamental and defining quantities of
internal energy particle and throughout the.
Remainder of. And this is this module as a whole
will just be working in equilibrium, which is
where this definition of the temperature is well
defined, where we can expect the temperature and
all other derived qualities to be functions of
those conserved energy particle numbers and the
temperature that we derive. We'll be. At the
fundamental level, a function of energy and
political no. So what what we will do, rather than
going through a long duration of what the
temperature might be, is simply state definition
and then try to see try to make some sense out of
it and see that it behaves or doesn't behave the
way that we are used to a temperature behaving in
everyday situations. So the definition of
temperature is the microeconomic sample is always
the thought of Librium. Is this T to the inverse
temperature? Is the derivative of the entropy with
respect to the internal energy. With that fixed
particle. No imposed. So. It's been just a minute
or two to try to make sense out of this. We call
that the. Microeconomic entreprise, dynamic
equilibrium is.
They're just awarded a number of microstates, this
equation. Is that derivative with respect to
internal energy? More are the number of
microstates fixed number. So in words, if we say
add a bit of energy to the system, we can expect
that to change the number of microstates that the
system can access, that can cycle between
environmental equilibrium with some probabilities.
And the change in that number of microstates is
then pushed through the logarithm to define a
change. Entropy and the ratio of change. The the
number of microstates that become accessible with
this change in energy is the inverse temperature.
So. If we were to say that adding just a little
bit of energy to the system would cause a big
change in the number of accessible microstates,
the big increase in entropy, then we would have
this large positive number is universal
temperature that would apply on the temperature.
So we can.
Intuition for that by thinking that low
temperatures, the system is very sensitive to a
small amount of energy being added in, whereas in
the opposite limits, if we were to add in a small
amount of energy, a small increase in the entropy,
we would interpret that as a high temperature
system. Already has a lot of thermal energy, is
not so sensitive to a little bit more being added
in.
But all of that. Discussion is obviously very
handwaving.
And I won't bother to read any of the job of try
to. Make this all a bit more concrete and less
abstract by turning to the usual system and spins
in a line in a magnetic field, defining the energy
of the system is minus H to the strength of the
magnetic field times. The negative of the
difference between the. A number of things pointed
up, combined with magnetic field, which is in flux,
and the number of spins into a lot of you're at
minus.
No.
But we are going to need to do more to figure out
the temperature of the system is figuring out how
the entropia. Of these and spins depends on the
amount of energy that they have, which in turn
depends on the number of microstates batteries and
Spitzkoppe access, we think of the amount of
energy. So we will see that
each different value of energy strictly defines a
different microbiological system with a different
number of accessible microstates. And the way that
that. That number of accessible microstates
changes defies the entropy in the derivative of
the interview with respect to that, changeability
gives us the inverse temperature. So that is the
first computer functional forms for the total
number of microstates, which we can then turn the
crank and get the temperature out as a function of
energy. The fundamental variable in the mind
canonical.
Now, we have to do that is count the number of
states that we have for a fixed amount of energy,
it may be worth building up to this by considering
a few simple special cases.
I can't remember if we've looked at this already
in the past, can anyone shout out what the lowest
energy configuration would be for these and
dispense with that magnetic field pointing out?
Exactly, it's just wrong. It's expensive to spend
all day doing it the end plus is the number of
spins pointing up a like with magnetic field that
brings in a negative energy. So the energy
response to this is zero for the lowest possible.
Energy is just all capital out of this spins
pointing up so any little and plus equals and.
And. Building on that, what would be what would be
the representative configuration of spin's would
be next lowest possible energy?
What would that look like if I were to draw it?
And the rate of this. Boxier.
Was that.
So they're all in the same direction they want,
that's where we got the lowest energy, what we
want now is the different system that has the next
lowest energy. So one of.
One step, one energy level higher than what we
call that grandstanders.
And why exactly so. Any one of these can be
pointed down and that brings in is now and minus
one and minus one. So instead of. The lowest
possible energy with minus and H we have.
And one gauge plus gauge from that one spin that
is into alignment of the magnetic field. Which
ends up being minus 10, minus two times H.
And now we can see what is written in the text
above here, that in order to count the number of
microstates for these systems, we have to figure
out all the possible ways that pairs of spins can
slip while keeping the energy the same. So, for
instance, in. On the right here, I could just as
easily control one negative, the one down putting
spin in that position. So flipping the third spin
from upside down and flipping the fourth standard
for the upcoming repairs to be fixed. There are.
And possible ways of choosing that one down or
pointing spin. Out of the. Total number of spins
that we have, so the total number of microstates
is that impossible ways of choosing which spin has
worked against the magnetic field in the Alos
energy case. Those conflicts are possible with
that same energy, so people the micro state is the
single one that is written down here with this
minimal energy, and we can recognize that this is
just the number of ways I could choose one that
would want to expand out of the enterable. And
there is a typo in this equation, 43, where I want
to have these labels aligned with e0, and it would
appear this should really be. Yourself and minus
the number of microstates that. Respond to this
energy with some number and minus is expense,
expense opposite to the magnetic field is just the
binomial fact is that choosing and minus spins out
of the total, which because and plus plus and
minus equals and is exactly the same as choosing
and plus spins out of the total. And in both cases
it is just the total capital and factorial divided
by and plus vectorial over in minus factorial and
minus being.
And minus and plus, as we've seen before.
Now we have the total number of microstates. The
next step on our way to the temperature is to take
the logarithm of that and then take the derivative.
The complication is that derivatives of factories
are. Inconvenient. So we go through a little
extended exercise here to recast the aspect
horribleness in terms of a nice continuous
function, and at the same time, this would be a
way to express the. Factories here in terms of the
fundamental conservative qualities, the energy
particle, one of which we want to fix and the
other which we want to take a derivative with
respect to. And the way to do this is to model or
interpret the spin system as a random walk. In the
interviews that these inspectors have, so whenever
we imagine any spin to the system taking a step
and the correspondent random walk in the energy
space of the system, well, there are two
possibilities to speed up, along with magnetic
field or down into the one with. If we considered
the energy brutalized by the negative image is to
make things dimensionless, then. We know from the
energy we've written down already that when this
bill points up. This is quantity X, we'll consider
the length of the walk is going to increase in the
following way and plus we've increased by one in
the total number of spins in the system and will
increase by. So the overall increase in X is to
minus one equals one, whereas the other case has
been reported down and we added it to the system.
That total number in would still increase by one,
but it doesn't stay the same, and this X would
change by zero minus one, which is negative. So
every time we consider adding a spin to the system,
this position of the walker and the random is
based. Either takes a step plus or minus one. So
it's a. System and steps of equal length, and
because we don't impose any preference for weather,
the next thing going into the system is going to
point up or down. We have equal probabilities for.
The walk to take a step in each of those
directions, the language that we looked at this
time last week, that's just probability P. Q is
equal to one half of stepping in either direction
up or down in energy.
And we know in this system, in this context, that
every one of the two, the power and possible walks
or possible configurations of these spins is
equally probable. So the overall probability that
our work ends in a configuration with a particular
value in plus and the corresponding energy event
plus or minus is just the number of those walks
with that fixed number of steps in the positive
direction divided by the total number of possible
configurations. Which is what's written here,
division, by the total number of possibilities and
the number of ways that you can, plus positive
steps of the energy out of the total number of
steps. And we can recognize from the equation
three that despite the little factor is just the
number of. Microstates we are interested in
probably the number of microstates is to the end
times, the probability of ending up with a random
walk.
And plus steps in the positive direction with the
energy we are interested in.
Is this approach clear so far? That's not so, we
just keep doing the same thing that we did in
fiction one point five and hit this with the
central bureau.
We know that the central limit theorem relates the
probability distribution for this and that random
walk in the energy space of the this system. To
the mean and variance of. The single step in that
process is spin the title, put it up or down, if
we average over those two possibilities, I should
say, sum up those two possibilities with equal
probabilities. We get the case because they have
the material and the variance is exactly the same
as we had in that unit, one variances for
particular, but of half, that's one plug that into
the central limit theorem. We find that the
continuous probability distribution for reaching.
Index energy.
Age is this Gaussian function around? X squared
over two times, the number of steps with the
overall normalization factor out front is always.
The next step is, again, building on what we did
and the appropriate foundations, taking this
probability distribution and extracting an actual
probability from it. Easiest way to do that. So
that can be a formula that we have to integrate
over some interval in the continuous X, the energy
of the system in order to extract the probability
from the distribution. The simplest approximation
to that integral is its central value.
We're. The over by this age is next, it is this
two. And plus minus 10. So the simple counsel
approximation to the probability is central value
of the distribution of the interval multiplied. By
the width of the interval. And that width of the
interval here is the distance that the ball
travels with the energy, adding another spin to
the system. The change, if we have a stand up
there has been pointed down, is just one.
So then. With the. Expression we had at the end of
the previous page that.
The total number of microstates is two of the end
times, this probability that we want to end is one,
the probability becomes the central value in that
distribution, which is just to the end, multiplied
by the distribution that we have. Already.
OK, many steps that just not done. We now have a
continuous function for a number of microstates of
this system as a function of the total energy, and
we just need to take this derivative with the
number of particles fixed. So.
I can go ahead and write down the logarithm of
this expression, you're going to do this in the
easy way. The logarithm of the product is the sum
of the water and the logarithm of the exponential
is just the arguments of the exponential to each
and everything else is. Independence, he will drop
out of that derivative. So what is the derivative
that we have in the end?
Yes, because I. That was the previous one, which
is now fixed.
This is one over the temperature or written below
the temperature with this approximation of margin
to bring the central element to bear is negative
energy squared divided by a.
So does this temperature for a spin system, the
excess?
I see you shaking your head in several ways, it
does not see it's not completely crazy.
One. One thing that does seem suspicious about
this is that in the case where the energy goes to
zero one, obviously divided by zero is something
problematic. The temperature seems to diverge.
When there are roughly equal numbers of upward
pointing at government expense in the system, what
may even be more confusing is that whenever the
energy of this system is positive, some there are
more stimuli against the magnetic field that there
are with the magnetic field than it is positive.
Each good as positive is positive or negative. So
we have a negative temperature coming out of our
definition.
And. We can check that's what's going on, there is
actually, yes, we have a system that has has more
speed to the line against the magnetic field and
we try to increase its energy by putting in
another piece of energy, that same handwaving
argument we went through before. We eventually
find fewer and fewer micro states so lower and
lower entropy as the energy increases. So the
limit there is actually. If we were to consider.
The. Maximum energy configuration of this system,
so instead of all this goes around. Parallel to
the extreme external feel, we have the bottom line
against it. The energy is plus and age so positive.
And if we were to. Try to add another piece of
energy, but we find that we can't. This is the
maximum, so there is the change. No change in
microstates is no fine if we were to go down there,
if we were to start from the next to maximal
energy positive and minus two times each and add a
piece of energy that we would see the number of
microstates decreasing from 10 to one, it's
exactly that decrease. That's.
Corresponds what produces this negative
temperature. We will call natural systems those
where this does not happen. So this unsuspended
system is one natural because there's an upper
bound on the amount of energy you can have, which
it is not standard in most physical systems.
In most natural systems, we can assume that the
number of microstates increases with more energy.
So adding energy to the system makes additional
microstates accessible.
And that is what we will restrict our attention to
specify that the majority of the spin's are
aligned with the magnetic field so that the energy
is negative, the temperature is positive. Just one
last remark we can see here. Is that because we
have a non-zero minimum energy that we wrote down
on the previous page of these notes? There is also
a. Not zero minimum temperature. Which is just.
Equal to the strength of the magnetic field when
the energy takes the value that you found. So
there are some things here, but there are some
aspects of this temperature that. Do better
expectations, at least when respect switch to this
natural regime and specifically the expectation
that you will think about is what happens when two
systems with two different temperatures are
brought into thermal contact with of exchange
energy with each other before diving into that?
Are there questions about the microeconomic
definition of temperature for this somewhat
response system? We've looked at so far
is part of the problem. So the temperatures are
coming. Just to stand up and just as soon as you.
Yeah, so the temperatures are coming out of the
microeconomic approach is not exactly what we're
used to talking about in everyday life and in
particular in the school system, we can't set that
temperature to zero the way that you could imagine
thinking of an absolute zero. So probably not
today, but tomorrow, certainly we will start
seeing the canonical approach where the
temperature is actually the three parameter and
can be set to whatever we want and. That that is
motivated by some of this microeconomic weirdness
and. That's actually the historical origin of
these names, the canonical is an English word sort
of means ordinary or standard. And when James was
developing these statistical approaches, again, I
think physical systems back in the nineteen
hundreds, you want to be standard, ordinary or
canonical ensemble to be the one where the
temperature behaves when we're used to the
microscopic cases, then. Some of the underlying
dynamics that relate more naturally to
conservation of energy, but less naturally to more
educated, experienced. Will reiterate that
tomorrow. We do see what the canonical approach is
and how it differs from microtechnology, it is the
first let's try to rescue some everyday behavior
from microeconomic systems unless there are
professions.
The. Setup here is going to be a bit. Similar to
what we were talking about when we encountered it
in the second half of the year, we start off with
two isolated microeconomic systems, A, B, each of
which has its corresponding energy. And as we've
seen, the energy and the particle number together
discovered a corresponding temperature to a TV.
So. Focusing here again on the natural positive
temperatures for either these spin systems or
general micro economical systems, setting aside
the possibility of having. A negative divergence
temperature. This is. The generic case, that is.
Of interest in everyday situations and then having
taken these two initially isolated mitochondrial
samples, you bring them together to form a
combined ensemble, allowing them to exchange
energy, thermal contacts. This will change the
amount of energy about the amount of particles
that are in each of these two boxes. And if we
then we isolate.
These two subsystems, they will generally have.
Different energies called it a prime rib prime and
then correspondingly different temperatures. And
the question is, how do the final temperatures to
crime and to be crime depend on the official
temperatures today and.
What we expect is a net flow of energy.
So the exchange is going to have a definite
direction from the Hodor system to the cooler
system if we put. If we imagine putting two
systems together when it's hot, when it's cold,
say an ice cube and a cup of coffee, then we get
to the ice cube that the whole system to heat up
and at the same time cool down often by exchanging
energy with. So what we can do based on
microeconomic approach is. Definably this energy
flow, a Delta E for each of these systems may be
just to be the amount that the final energy after
this heat exchange differs from the initial energy.
And just for simplicity. We will suppose that this
change in energy is relatively small. Compared to
the overall energy scale, that is not a necessary
assumption and. I'm debating whether to put a
problem on the homework, looking in a different
way of doing this energy exchange calculation that
doesn't require doesn't rely on the assumption of
small energy. But one thing we know from the fact
that even the combined system of C is like
canonical and isolated. From its surroundings, the
total energy. In these two subsystems together,
there has to be concerned, which is to say
whatever energy flows out of this debate has to
flow in the system being. So we change the energy
industry, subsystems is equal and opposite. No. To
get the temperatures, we need the entropies, we
need to take their derivatives with respect to the
energy.
And if we assume that the entropy as a function of
energy is continuous and infinitely differentiable,
which is generally the case away from our call
phase, transitions will set aside for now and come
back to probably after the term break, then we can
just expand. The entropy of the final system is a
series around the entropy of the initial system,
plus this change in energy.
Multiplied by the derivative evidence of the
response of the entropy to the energy at the fixed
energy that we were expanding around. So we can
write this in terms of the initial temperatures,
disability, so be.
And that is. Fairly trivial, so just remembering
that the.
Derivatives. That appear in the state expansion or
just the temperature we have then? The final
entropy.
Is to leading order, neglecting effects that come
in is the square of this relatively small energy,
the initial entropy, plus the change in energy
divided by. The temperature of the derivative
becomes of whatever temperature factor.
And what we have already seen is from the Second
World, from the.
As we go through this process of bringing systems
together, putting them in terrible contact, let
them change energy and then be separating them
total energy of those two systems, whether they're
isolated or combined. Can never decrease as time
passes, so the final entropies that depend on
those final energy use need to be greater than or
equal to the initial entropies.
There's a bit of a calculation that could. You
don't here just to show that there is equality
between the entropy of the. Combined system where?
No contact is not allowed me to set some systems
or just considered together another entropies ad
as extensive as an extensive period of. This may
be worthwhile to check that. If we go through this
calculation, something over all possible values
for the distribution of the total energy between
these two systems, we end up with exactly the sum
we saw last week for the total energy that
combined system. For now, we will come back to
that sort of issue a bit later on. We'll leave it
as a sufficient result. To say that or to
acknowledge that the final entropies have to be no
smaller than the initial interviews.
And then.
Inserting.
The leading order killer expansion that we got
here. Into this inequality to squeeze onto the
projector while I read it.
No, that s a crime as. He did Prime. Is to bring
order in the energy flow.
SFP, a plus delta over T8.
SBB.
Similarly, Delta Ebbe over TV, and this has to be
greater than or equal to the initial Entropies S4
system, plus the intrepidity forces to keep, which
means there are some simplifications that we can.
See, with the result being.
Guilty, a 30 a. Still to be over, TV needs to be
greater than zero and that
conservation of energy.
Which is the statement, Delta
is negative, Delta in the. We can get rid of one
of the. One of these in here is People Out of
Control Factor.
Of Delta A.
Times now, the difference between the increased
temperature and we started off with an systemis
minus the increased temperature. We started off
with the System B, which is what we wanted to find.
So.
That is the. Ultimate result of the second law of
thermodynamics gives us more heat exchange between
two systems that are brought into contact. And if
we set aside for the moment the possibility that
this expression will be used in quality and we say
that the. Product of these two terms, the energy
flow and the difference in the temperatures has to
be positive and there are. Two main possibilities
in both terms are positive or negative, and the
negative sides can select if this difference in
temperatures is negative. And we need to have a
negative flow in energy. So what does that mean?
This factor is negative when TV is less than a
third of the inverse, whatever, TV is greater than
the impersonality a. Which means that when A is
the core system to start off with.
That is right. Sorry, B is smaller. Temperature
this to be a small body temperature in. System,
they see that the universe is inverse differences,
negative, so is the hotter system at the same time
filter a. Has to be negative, so energy is flowing
out of the system into the cooling system, as
everyone would expect. And for a natural system,
the energy so out of the water system reduces its.
No microstamping, this is entropy reduces its
temperature.
Which brings down the temperatures of these two
systems closer together. And the. Same thing
happens that the two factors are positive in that
case, which is largely the one over TV. So the
temperature system is initially smaller than the
temperature and system be. And the positive flow
in energy means the energy is flowing into the
system and out of the hotter system.
And then finally, there is the possibility that.
Both terms were one of the other term is zero. So
if the energies are equal. We have. No energy
flows in the special case, that's when the
temperatures were equal before we put these
systems in the contact, that thermal contact has
no effect, the energy to stay equal throughout it
as the systems are brought together and we
separate. So at least with respect to the natural
regime of spin systems or other generic systems,
then this micro canonical definition of
temperature, despite its weird features to look at
the example we went through, does behave as we
expect for your spin system and. As. As advertised,
we will now be shifting into the canonical
ensemble where. The temperature T.L.. Is the
defining fixed quantity that characterizes the
system, you avoid some of the weirdness of the
underlying canonical system. We'll leave that for
tomorrow morning, because I'll start with you and
just wrap up today by saying if there are any
questions about what we went through with the
temperature of the water column,
which paves the way it should, and in some cases,
at least it should.
I'll see you tomorrow. I almost forgot to mention
that this being week three of the usual week three
mini questionnaires online on canvas, if you want
to get any feedback about how things are going so
far with this model out of
is about.