I'll start recording and deal with the
magic number for attendance monitoring. It's a new
one for this afternoon compared to this morning:
One two five
oh seven nine.
I got one report that the number this morning didn't
work for someone, I let the folks in
charge know that there was a glitch. I suspect
the only advice they might have would be to make
sure that the app is updated to the latest version,
that that's still problematic. And that's what it
is at the moment. This is just a pilot this year
to work out those sorts of problems going forward.
So just to talk about. Programming, the computer,
programming, the bits, I'm not going to make the
assumption that anyone taking this module has done
any computer programming in the past. So if you
have maybe a bit.
A basic reminder today. To.
And keep your face covering out of the mike.
This first part of the computer project is going
to. Apply computing to carry out some of the
repeated experiments we've been discussing in
lectures, so this case and generating random
numbers or putting that in the context of random
walks that we didn't quite get to this morning
will come up on Monday instead. And the idea is
that we want to.
Simulate or carried out with a computer. Random
experiments that. We can then analyze
statistically, and this gives us the ability to
fairly quickly and easily generate hundreds of
thousands or millions of experiments and see how
the statistical properties behave and how that can
be mapped onto physical systems of interest and.
The to sort of build up to that, there are three
parts to the exercise. The first to go through
some of the computing tools, use and apply it to
that random walk situation will be our next topic
in life on Monday in the first. Step two, that is
figuring out how to deal with random numbers in a
computer, given that computers are not random,
they do what you tell them to and any sequence of
numbers that they produce is going to be
completely deterministic and reproducible given
the same conditions. So. The best that of these
computers available is the classical physics as
opposed to quantum physics can do is what is
called pseudo random numbers.
Which is what is typically used and what it means
is that. It's a program or an algorithm that.
Needs the computer to generate a sequence of
numbers that are. That half the property so
loosely speaking, that if you know the first and
minus one numbers in the sequence, there is not
enough information in there to be able to predict
the next number and number with any high degree of
confidence or probability of success.
So that is to say that the sequence looks random,
even though it's physically can't be because it
will go beneath the surface of a computer program.
All of these numbers are being encoded into a
couple of bits of the binary representation of. Of
numbers or data at each bejamin, a collection of
information picks a value either zero or one of
two possibilities. Stringing together a lot of
bits you can describe to to the inpower pieces of
information, so. The traditional standard single
point decision for computers has thirty two bits
to say, an integer value that can represent all
the non-negative integers from zero up until a
number that is famous enough to have its own
Wikipedia page, its links from the PDF of this
demo. It's about four point two billion, I think
two to the tower. Thirty two minus one. So given
that this is the simple case, just considering
none of the stories that are going to be generated,
the sequence of integers after those four billion
in some numbers in that sequence, every number
that was accessible to that computer would have
been sampled and you would have to go back and
start sampling them again.
By being a bit clever about the switching up the
order in which things are simple, you can.
Extended, we are not extending number of numbers,
extend the length of the sequence that is
available before it starts to repeat itself.
Exactly. But you can't take the limit of an
infinite sequence. Eventually, that sort of
repetition will happen, at which point you will
know the next number of the sequence based on the
repetition that can be for. And the. The standard
algorithm that is used by default in Python, for
instance, is called the wrist twister, which
twists itself these two to the thirty two or even
two of the sixty four minus one possible numerical
values in order to come up with a sequence of
numbers that doesn't start repeating itself until
there are about ten to the power. Six thousand
numbers in that sequence, which is quite a few, if
you were able to generate with this algorithm, say,
a billion numbers every second gigahertz sampling
rate and it would take ten to the power of five
thousand nine hundred ninety one seconds to see
this repetition of a single sequence which is
vastly longer than the age of the universe. So the
practice this is a sequence of numbers that looks
random. And can be treated as essentially random
in this computer project board and the scientific
research more generally.
And.
Let's see what.
Yes, I go through. A couple more pieces of
information before hopping over to looking at some
actual accountability to talk about what is doing
and why, one of those being that.
Given this. Random pseudo random number generator,
p orangy. The typical. The. Function that is
provided by any given programming language,
whether that's Python or had received Fortran Java,
Russ, the Obama is going to provide random numbers
drawn from a simple distribution called the
uniform. Probability distribution, which. Has this
property defined here that.
The probability for a random number usually
generated between zero and one is constant between
zero and one. So there is equal probability of
getting any real number that can be resolved by
computer precision in that interval and the
probability is zero for all other real numbers. So
it's a kind of critical intervention to plot the X
uniform distribution.
So zero to one where specific magnitude of that
one is just set so that the integral over so
probability is one hundred percent that's required
for probability distribution. And so this is the
simplest thing to do, but it's also a bit more if
you're just grabbing. Ran evenly, distributed
random numbers from zero to one. And the question
is, what can you do with those particular if you
want to sample some less trivial or more
complicated probability distribution? So the
method. Get to explore this project in the Devil,
for that matter, is known as Inversed Transfer
Upsampling. And this is the. Picture that the
skull is what it is doing. That's come up with
some verbal transformation effort, that's
Rhapsody's real numbers, which presumably to some
other range with some of the more interesting,
essentially by default probability distribution.
And then. In order to. Preserve the property that
the probabilities continue to add up to 100
percent. There's a relation between the. Interval
of the Transformed. X's and the probability
distribution that they follow, which can be
manipulated to solve for their distribution in
terms of the inverse function of that
transformation from the uniform numbers between
zero one two year olds, X, which is. The origin of
that name in verse transform sampling distribution
defined by the inverse of the transformation that
takes the numbers from. The uniform distribution
provided by the computer to something more
interesting to work with. Oh.
That, I think is. Plenty for me to just sort of
throw out there and see if there are any immediate
questions about. I think the details or the
purpose of any of that and.
If not,
I'll see if I can hop over to. The.
Programming. Demo from.
It's linked to the Akinmusire.
Which provides a place to check out some of these.
Ideas and play with them yourself in practice. See
how they are they can be implemented in Python. So
this is a. What's called a python notebook, so a
way to collect some explanations and Python code
to be run and looked at together, since I'm not
signed into Google on this particular computer,
while I am able to edit all of the code in here. I
won't be able to save those edits. You can see
changes, which is should also be the case for any
of you, if you do have a Google account, you can
go into this and save your own copy of this
notebook, play around with it, see how it works.
See if you can make a break or make it run any
more efficiently than I have set up.
And.
Just to comment a bit on.
Why we're looking at iPhone in the first place,
out of the probably hundreds of programming
languages that are floating around in the ether,
it's one that is very widespread and
pretty functional and especially is easy to use if
you aren't already familiar with it. It's designed
to look kind of like everyday speech almost.
It's a way of translating what we want the
computer to do into a language and the computer
will understand. And there are because it is
widespread, there's lots of tutorials and
information out there. So a search can often
resolve any questions that that may come up. It's
also something that you can run various places
online, including the Google Collaboratory, as
they call it. If you. Don't want to have trouble
getting Python set up on a device you have access
to and you're free to.
If you don't just want to listen to me talk this
afternoon, you can pull up your laptop or film and
follow the links here and play with yourself as I
sort of summarize what's showing up here. And just
to get started, because this is being recorded for
anyone who may want some of this background for
the computer project offline. The starting point
with Python is. That language was sort of designed
by principle in order to be fairly small and
self-contained, but have lots of add on packages
that provide extra functionality for anything that
any users might need and to deal with. Sampling
lots of random numbers and repudiating them. There
are a few packages that are useful or crucial to
have so collections of special functions related
to mathematics, things like a square root function,
a separate collection of functions and utilities
related to random numbers in each of these.
Packages are modules is just loaded with this
special keyword importance at the start of the
Python code. And then there are two. Larger scale
packages that are developed by the community and
provide additional functionality for numerical
computing. A lot of things like matrices or higher
rank Tensas numerical integration, fitting
routines. And much, much more, as well as a.
A library for applauding, especially scientific
planning based on mathematical
or format, medical purposes, things like image
manipulation and we will use is just plodding
histograms, whines, fits and that sort of thing.
So importing all of those with a special keyboard
that lets us refer to them. OK, so you do have to
sign in.
Which.
We'll see.
If I remember at. My password for Dubow.
Any questions, will I deal with this delay?
I'm signed in, so let me connect to the cloud and
run this code on Google servers, you know, just
print it out here, the version of Python numerical
python at matplotlib currently being used by the
cloud server. This code is now running on.
And then immediately jump into the inverse
transform sampling that.
Shows up in the. Computer project assignments
where we want to. Start off by. Initializing the
pseudo random number generator with your
particular input, that's called a seed, we are
given this seed exactly the same sequence of
random numbers will be produced by the random
number generator after initialization. And those
sequences will be distinct from the sequences that
are produced with any other value of the seeds.
This allows both. The calculation to be exactly
reproduced either by me at different points of
time or by different people in different places at
different points in time. And then the.
The random routine that is part of the random
package imported in the previous block of code is
what it's going to. Provide one of those random
numbers uniformly distributed between zero and one.
So in this example, ought to sample the
probability distribution P of X equals X over to
ranging from X going from zero up to two so that
the probability of up to 100 percent. So we want
to take this
to something that looks more like that is some
small
sample, which numbers with greater probability and
smaller numbers and knowing that
this is the probability distribution we want to
end up with from. This relation at the on screen.
Makes it. Quick and easy to do what the. Required
derivation to figure out the transformation that
we need between those uniform random numbers and
facts, so we want to generate. When we generate
each uniform, random distribution and edit things,
we want to take it square root, multiply by two,
and then that will give us these random numbers X
following this different distribution that we want
to produce. And that's what's being done in this
line. You get that random, uniformly distributed,
random, you take it square roots multiply by two
in. What's going on in here is what's called a
forward, which is one of the fundamental aspects
of computer programming. Just tells it tells the
computer to. Repeat some set of instructions, some
number of times.
Python, these loops and other logic blocks are
indicated by the. Number of blank spaces at the
start of each line, which is a lot different from
some other programming languages that use curly
braces to separate them off. You may have seen in
the past. So it's these three lines that form the
instructions that are repeated by this form before
one is defining some horrible eye that varies
across the range from zero up to in samples, but
not including in samples, which is set to be one
hundred thousand. We define an empty array called
debt for data and initialize to running subs that
will just add up. All of the. Random numbers and
the squares of those random numbers that appear in
this forward. So with that set up, this is this
code is repeating one hundred thousand times the
process of generating this random number that
should obey desired distribution from the universe,
transform. And then added the number to the
running sub and heading the square of the number
two, running some. For the square where. There's a
little python trick at the end here that
I should explain, that arrays are like they say on
the 10, they are a list of numbers which can be
accessed with these square brackets by specifying
the location of the number that you're interested
in getting in a python, you can give minus one as
the very last elements of that array. The idea is
that zero is the first element. One is the second
two or three, four and so on. At the end wraps
back around to zero. So when you add in negative
numbers, you start going the other way around from
the back to the front. So that that is minus one
is just exactly the number that was appended to
the end of the array in that previous line.
So if I were to write down on the board in
mathematical notation what this corresponds to,
this veve, which is my shorthand for vacuum
expectation value is the particle physics version
of the expectation value. You want to see that
looks kind of like those some over all of the
repetitions of this experiment. Exactly. The X
that is being produced through that transform. And
then after the end of the for loop indicated by
the removal of that indentation, that sum is just
divided by the total number of.
So we hope that some of her are going up to and we
divide it by one over in.
And because we.
No, assuming for the moment that we have managed
to generate any success with the correct
probability distribution this year, it because
there is no
activation to the true meaning of the early
distribution. Similarly. So the squirrel running,
sometimes it's just the same arithmetic estimates
for that, so I swear. In each case.
And then you can see. How well, a hundred thousand
samples reproduces the known or the easy to
calculate, mean and standard deviation of this
non-trivial probability distribution scale is the
computation which we can do if there's demand to
check that the true meaning that
to a little above the point. In the distribution
because of the greater problem is that we didn't
see the larger exodus.
What is there to make it visible around the screen
and the standard deviation, the square root of the
expectation value of X squared minus the square of
the expectation value of X is reached over three.
So that point four seven. And with these hundred
thousand repetitions of that experiment with the.
The estimate of the median of standard deviation
from the lower class numbers is correct up to.
Five significant digits in the mean three or three
significant digits. In the standard deviation, so,
well, less than a percent
inaccuracy and better than percent level of
precision, and it took just a few seconds to run,
so we had another zero on computer. Repeat this
with the four million samples. It's wrong already
and gets even closer. That's what used to be point
for seven or nine, overshooting the standard
deviation is not one four seven one undershooting
hit by a smaller amount. And that's the sort of.
Exercise, it appears. In the computer project
itself. And I guess I've left it open as a
question in the demo so far,
even though we're getting the estimate for. The
median standard deviation, reasonably accurately,
to make sure that we really are generating these
numbers with the desired probability distribution,
which we can do similar to the way we talked about
with modelling on Tuesday, you're repeating an
experiment a large number of times. And by looking
at the outcomes of that experiment, we can infer
the probabilities of those outcomes or more
generally, the probability distribution. So this
was the reason why. We saved on one hundred
thousand to a billion. Samples in this array,
which we're not actually using beyond that, is the
running samples that would have sufficed to look
at the way the standard deviation. But having
every single one of those 10 to the five data
allows us to plot a histogram of those data and
see how they are all distributed. Which is where
that plot live, what we've called Kielty for short
comes into play to make things quick and
reasonably easy. All we need to do is call the
highest function, and it provides to produce a
histogram with the data we want histogram a number
of beams that we want the data divided into. And
this density tells us to normalize it so that the
area of the histogram is one, rather than being a
full count of the number of events in each of the
bands. So the blue
columns of this plot that are all next to each
other are. Those hundred thousand outcomes of the
repeated experiments in each each bin, the number
of outcomes is being plotted and then divided so
that the. Total area that is shaded blue is equal
to what if I were to change this to false and we
run.
You see that there are a few hundred up to a few
thousand outcomes in each of these bins and
Instagram is just showing how many outcomes are
falling in. Each range of the sex acts is going
from zero to two.
And on top of that histogram.
In the same set of accidents I've used matplotlib
to define a function in a kind of Python style,
and in particular that function is the. Have the
distribution down there after.
To where?
Is he going to he's in this library is to define a
set of X values that X is this is a an array
function from ignorable, that what it's doing is
creating an array that holds every value from zero
to two insteps steps and zero point zero one. So
there are two hundred elements in that array, zero
zero point one zero one or two, three and so on.
Which we could. Pretty to check out that it is
being produced correctly.
There it is. Two hundred elements from zero up to
two, but not including two and then.
This next line defining why to be half of X is
smart enough to figure out the size of that array
and make Y be an array of exactly the same size so
that it can then be plotted with a red line and
shows up like that in the plot that I've shown
here live in The Notebook. With that function that
could save to disk or to submit with homework,
despite
a different function provided by that volume. So
that is a simple example of inversed, transform
sampling. In Python. And think I've been talking
sort of continuously to the wall, this is
something online and available for you to play
with at the expense of having a Google account.
And it's also something that you don't want to
deal with Google.
It is possible to. Grab the source code for. This
demo from.
Something I thought I had linked at the top here,
the repository for.
This module, this is all the stuff that we were
just talking through, getting up to the Instagram
and inversed transparency and so on, you can make
sure you can run this yourself and modify it to do
whatever you might want. But are there questions
about the practicality or. Even the motivation for
any of the aspects of things we've gone through
this afternoon.
I'm looking at the time and thinking that this bit
about random walks we will see in the lectures
next week and it may be at this point more useful
to actually switch back to the stuff we were.
Going through this morning.
Here we are, we had these.
Small experiments of spinning wheel five times and
trying to figure out from a. Approximate
expression for what kind of return on the beds we
could expect from that game in. When I was writing
down all of the exact probabilities of winning
either none of those five statements or all five
of them, I did probably for the first time,
neglects to actually plug in. The numbers that are
appearing here may be useful for the annotations
that are put on canvas later today to record. I
have fear of what these numbers will be. Part of
that there's about a three or four percent chance
of not winning any one of the five spins that all
black spin of that roulette wheel. And that number
rises to about 17 percent to win a single one. And
then about 30 percent to two, so even though the
total probability factors are decreasing, the 19
of the thirty seven is decreasing two factors each
number 37, the number of possible ways that this
outcome could be achieved. It is growing fast
enough to. Well, more than compensate the decrease
in individual speed, probably in particular, that
10 is almost the enhancement from the point over
three six point three two oh, it's just about
reflected by that factor of 10. Then on the other
side, we go down 30 percent,
back to 14. Over to. Just three percent chance to
win every. Spin of the wheel and those six numbers
pop up on the next page in the lecture notes
plotted as these direct green circles on this plot
that is actually to be. Exact calculation that we
did this morning, going from below five percent to
a bit above 30 percent, as we noted, how little
skewed toward a negative gain so that.
The House, the long term abortion spins, will
always come out ahead of anyone who is playing
their games. Now, the
other six points on this point are coming from.
The computation that we just wrapped up with,
which is in fact a numerical computation to this
point, I. Produced using some
sort of. Ended up this morning just with a glance
at the extraction of unified probabilities from
the distribution that the central government gives
us. This is some. Government function around the
limit of five times the building or repeating that
relentless spinning experiment five times. And the.
One question that we. To the lead or I didn't
explicitly state this morning was what exactly
Beltagy is. Where they can be read off from the
work that we saw that the dean of. Winning a spin
in this game is a return of 10 pounds, so. But
this is the difference between the first one spins
versus spins is 10 pound gain for Delta Beltagy.
So the integral here is going from. The central
value. The amount that we gain if we win w spends.
The interview five times brought that to five
pounds above. Which might be easiest to.
By checking what this figure looks like, we
computed the.
Yeah, I computed here. No function for.
That total gain from winning W spins out of and
total, which is.
Do you need 10 from every spin that we win, the
losing five for every spin that it's played that
ends up with? Depending on whether we lose all
five spins, we get negative twenty five from that,
if we win all five plus twenty five. And these
boundaries, those she said WS plus or minus five
are exactly the vertical lines being shown on the
spot. Absolutely. Quickly enough evidence not
showing up. Of the not even the.
Dividing this range.
Around each of the outcomes in numerical python
doesn't provide. A routine to do with the
integration of the sort, you can even simplify
that by making the approximation that the Scotian
probability distribution is roughly constant
within this very small range. Relatively small
range, and then that is gorgeous because the
central value of the game are interested in
multiplied by 10 with the range rather than
writing down the 12 probabilities that come out.
You can actually.
Look through or at least pull up module's. Lecture
notes, click the link in here to what the python
code that I actually already had opened a
different tab.
This code here is doing exactly this computation.
And looking at the time, I don't think there's.
Much time available to go through it in any detail.
What it is, is translating the mathematical
manipulations we've done this morning into the
language of Python with some fairly extensive
commentary to explain. What is going on if I look
at this? While Python code and copy it all, say,
into
a new notebook.
And see what happens when I blindly run that
without even looking at things.
It is a missionising connected to with the cloud
and. It is complaining about to have the number of
spins here set up as an input argument. To run in
Linux terminals and set to use if I just set that
to five here will hopefully be happier. It takes
zero seconds to run.
It say exactly how much point zero point eight
nine eight seconds. And it reproduces not only the
six numbers that
I just wrote down here. Point oh three five seven
one six nine three two zero and so on. It also
keeps that constant approximation. Probability is
to gain or lose up to twenty five pounds. It does
the numerical integration with that routine. I may
be able to quickly find. If I search for.
The search for integration, this is.
A feature of the Google Fiber series that the
documentation pops up, I imported integrated from
a scientific platform package similar to numerical
Pythonic, only a bit fancier and more capable. So
this is sorry, that was it's back again some of
the documentation for that integration routine.
Doing a quadratic approximation to the.
Probability distribution and coming up with. The
numbers showed here and plotted on this plot. They
may look familiar and checking how.
How much error these approximations introduce,
checking that the six probabilities still add up
approximately to one with no better than percent
level precision,
and I can see that they are all reasonably on top
of each other when plotted visually. So. That I
think will suffice to. Wrap up that little example
in elections with the straight dogs, you effusions
of random thoughts, that one day I think I'll stop
talking there, just give one last call for
questions about programming or anything else
before we get to have a weekend.
But enjoy the weekend and see you again Monday
afternoon.