OK, that recording should be under way. And
today's number is... not that one left from yesterday,
but eight four five, three one five.
All right,
let's pick up more or less where we
left off just at the end of yesterday. So welcome
back. Are there any questions about anything going
on so far in the course, what we saw yesterday or
the project or remainder of the material.
So office hours are Mondays and Fridays,
Mondays at five, right after the lecture we had
yesterday and Fridays at 10:00 right after that
Friday morning lecture, and I will head down to my
office, which is in the theoretical physics wing,
and also try to stay connected to the room, call
for anyone who isn't able to be here in person for.
But
I of that. Right where we left off yesterday,
we'll wrap up random walks today and see in more
detail how they generalize. So yesterday to get a
first look at this random process that can be used
to model all sorts of things, we've. Cut it down
to the simplest possible random water, there was
just a walker who can go in one direction or the
other along the line, so single dimensional,
random walk probability of going in one direction
at every step, probability to which is one minus,
be going in the opposite direction. And after some,
the calculations found simple expressions for what
we're interested in, the final position of the
walk and the scale of fluctuations around, or the
variance in that position that depend just on P. Q
and the total number of steps which we can
rearrange in terms of a drift velocity and the
diffusion constants that describe how the
probability distribution for this walk or for any
walk in general, both drifts as time goes on and
also the same time spreads out or diffuses. So
while there is a.
A well defined expectation value that can we can
look at, it's drifted out as long as the water
gets longer, longer, with more and more steps
being added up in the sky in the process. At the
same time, the probability of finding exactly that
expectation value is dropping. And the.
The scale of fluctuations around that expectation
value is growing with and should have put up here,
this is a reminder, the characteristic dependence
on that square root of described by what's called
a law of diffusion. So from these two quantities,
the diffusion, constant and velocity, it is an
interesting question to see. How the scale of
fluctuations are behaving compared to that
expectation value when given the option of
dependence. We've just reviewed and saw yesterday,
we can almost write that down off the top of our
head. But to put in the full calculation for this.
Random walk with a fixed step at each point in
time. You saw the those fluctuations in the
numerator. In this ratio, so relative uncertainty.
Looking at the scale of fluctuations divided by
renormalize, by the drifting expectation value in
the case where he is not equal to has that
expectation, Diamond is not motivated by zero,
expectation in itself was proportional to end and
the two P minus one. So if we plug those in. We
have. To.
Q.
Can pull out.
Won over in times. The remainder of stuff that
depends on the details of the walk, we would
define the probabilities of stepping in either of
the allowable directions and related the number of
steps to the total length of time that the walk
takes. And up with that. Velocity for each
timestep of the total time, 90 times that same.
Somewhat messy factor, which is disproportional to
one over square root tea. So this ratio of scale
of relative fluctuations ends up going to zero
with one over security as the water gets longer
and longer. Approach that large and limits. There
are many steps all being added together in the
same sort of way that we saw for the central limit
theorem, which is.
Not necessarily what we might have guessed just by
looking at in particular this plot on the left
with the Lodrick velocity. It does not look like
the fluctuations are vanishing relative to the
expectation values. The highest point in that
curve and the of the only reason that's looking at
this part rather than doing the actual
mathematical calculation, what a excuse us is just
a trick of the eye. And considering times that are
not sufficiently long to suppress the particular
combination of P's and Q's that are showing up in
this case.
So
the conclusion of this is that even though the
probability distribution is spreading out around
that expectation, at most times, that drift is
always going to win, which is. I mentioned the
start of this exercise we could have. Forecast by
remembering the law of diffusion that is on the
scale of fluctuations, grows proportional to the
square root of tea, while the expectation values
proportional. See, so the ratio is just that one
over square root of tea and dependent on the
details of the steps and probabilities that we
impose for the particular grand walk. And this is
useful to know because it is very general, which
we can see by applying the central limit theorem,
which we saw last week, was where we stated, I
should say, last week was a very general limit
theorem applicable to all random processes where
the mean and variance for each of the single
experiments that's being repeated many times,
those mean and variances are finite. We train the
variable. So.
The connection to the central limit theorem to
consider. Is the way I think I mentioned yesterday,
each step in that random walk becomes that random
variable. It's independent, it's identically
distributed, and once we add up all of the steps,
we're still fixing that length to be one. The sum
of all the steps and the random walk is exactly
the same quantity s for which we.
In terms of which.
We introduced the form of the central limit
theorem that is relevant to. She you to work, and
we saw there that the overall probability
distribution for the length of that random walk or
that some of the steps depends only on the
characteristics of that underlying single step
process. Those characteristics being the mean and
variance where you saved the letters new and sigma
for the single step. It is a single step we can
very easily compute what the mean and variances.
And you may have already done so in your head.
Does anyone have an idea for how to go about
computing? I mean, just of that process of taking
a step farther to the left minus one was probably
a cue or to the rights one plus one the
probability.
This is before. It's the usual definition sum over
all the possibilities and the outcome sets that
walk length of times the corresponding probability.
So the walk length with C plus one to go to the
right probability, T minus one to go to the left
with probability. Q And that is putting it to
being one minus P, you get to P minus one, which
just so happens to be the expectation value for
the total supply divided by the number of steps.
So the fundamental definition is behaving as you
would expect and similarly for the expectation
value of XY squared. The only difference here is
that minus one squared goes to four equals one. So
instead of minus two, we get plus Q. And those two
possibilities always add up to 100 percent
Firewalker stepping only to the left or to the
right. So then it's just the process of plugging
those in to the variance. The expectation value of
the square is one and then the square of the
expectation value is square that for P squared,
minus four. Plus one.
Which is just for three times when minus P
distributing that negative sign.
Which again, when I was P is for P, Q, which is.
Scale of fluctuations in the total SNEPP length,
also divided by N. So from the form of a central
bureau that was written down. A few pages earlier,
the notes and is essentially reproduced here. We
have to do is plug in this for Q, where Sigma
Squared appears in the probability distribution
for the summer, we call called X for the total
lauchlan. And similarly to minus one. That's where
the need for that single step process occurs, and
then it's easy enough to rewrite that in terms of
the.
The diffusion constant, the. B squared was four P
Q we computed earlier and that drift velocity.
Which was. Just. Make sure I don't drop any
factors.
I did drop by a factor of. The Delta teams that
are canceling out. With this and we're actually
delighted to be here, I'm tending to one that is.
This is in this particular form. So then the drift
velocity itself is exactly that. In T minus one.
So we have the probability distribution for the
final position of the war just as a normal
distribution, which is precisely what we're
looking at in the possibly we. Discussed yesterday.
And what this means is a general.
Outcome to take away is that whenever the. Central
is applicable, so whatever that means in terms of
the single step process are finite, we can
identify. Drift velocity as related to the meat of
that single step process and the diffusion
constant. He's connected to the variance of that
single step process, and upon adding up all of
these individual random processes, we end up with
a smooth, normal distribution for the position of
the water. At the end of its log is a function of
the time that the law takes. So that establishes
precisely how general matlab diffusion is. It will
apply. So the. Scale the fluctuations increasing
proportional to the square t the probability of
diffusing away from the expectation that it's
going to be the case whenever that central limit
theorem is applicable.
And if we. Look at the final form of the
probability distribution. Expressed here, you can
sort of read off the kind of behavior we were
seeing, the response that as.
We look further and further away from the peak of
this probability distribution, which is the place
where the negative factor in this exponential is
the smallest, right, where the numerator is equal
to zero as we get further away from that. In order
to. Achieve the same probability of oral arguments
to reach a given value, this. Denominator dividing
through factor X minus velocity quantity squared
also has to become larger. In other words, at. The
peak is becoming broader and then the overall
multiplicative factor is just there in order to
keep the overall probability integrated of all
possible values equal to one hundred percent. As
required by its definition.
Now, we'll just wrap up by saying that. It is
possible for the central in the film and the law
of diffusion to break down, and that will be part
two of the computer project where the first part
you're going to look at a slightly more
interesting random walk where the step lengths are
not fixed to across the valley, but are drawn
randomly from a probability distribution obtained
by the transform sampling. And then in the second
part of the project. So the first part, we draw
those variable step sizes from a well-behaved
probability distribution with a finite mean and
variance. The second part, we look at a more
complicated distribution where. The central limit
theorem and more diffusion will break down. So
that is it's getting everything in place for work
on that computer project. Now, there any.
Questions about.
Any of the stuff we've seen so far wrapping up
with these random box?
Because at this point, we're going to
move to the second unit and in particular dive
into the sort of core focus of this module as a
whole, which is the concept of statistical
ensembles, building of this community foundation
we've so far in terms of. Collections of large
numbers of repeated experiments
drawn from some distribution with an element of
randomness that collectively give rise to a
well-defined, smooth behavior governed by its
central limit, involve large numbers when there
are insufficient number of degrees of freedom. In
the system, so we're going to start off with
another round of definitions and showing where
this more physical concept of statistical
ensembles and thermodynamics in particular from
the real connects to the probability spaces and
random processes seem so far.
So. The basic perspective is. Connecting to the
definitions we started off with last week, the
experiments that we're going to consider in the
context of thermodynamics are simply taking some
collection of degrees of freedom of particles in
general for short and just look at the arrangement
of those particles as they evolved in time subject
to certain constraints. So we the state system or
equivalently the measurement that we are
interested in performing on that stage at a given
time. It's just defined by the arrangement of
these many underlying degrees of freedom. So a
concrete example.
Which is one we will. Look at a few times in a few
different perspectives. This system is. To suppose
there are degrees of freedom are what are called
spin's essentially arrows that can point either up
or down. So this likely the simple right of what
you were just looking at. There were only two
possibilities. This has some of the same
mathematical features. As simple coin for the
experiment, the final breakdown they represented
the state for as it spins here. To just have some
pointing out, some pointing down, if I were to
label those heads or tails, it would be the same
sort of state that we would get from flipping a
coin here or call it the configuration of these
spins and the. Total number of possible
configurations is just the total number of ways
this and spins.
Can each independently be pointing either up or
down? So two possibilities for each and spins,
which in this case of equals eight us that
backwards because it is two possibilities for.
Each of the US spends.
Starting to get that backwards in the case of any
of those eight. Two of the eight is two hundred
and fifty six possibilities.
If we then. Let the system evolve in time and look
at it again at some different time, too, as
opposed to T one, we will get a new state or two
that is in general different from a legal one, but.
From either empirical observation of physical
systems or Gerda's theorem, we know that there are
certain measurements on the state that would
always produce the same outcome, even as the state
changes over time. And that was an outcome that is
always the same for different states, is what we
know as the conserved quantity. The obvious
example we're hopefully familiar will be
conservation of energy inside a closed or isolated
system that is not in contact with any other
system. It can be considered just if they hold the.
When it is considered as a whole, it's total
energy has to be conserved, so the same as a
measurement on. And the possible states that can
be produced by the time evolution of our
collection of degrees of freedom.
Probably familiar, and you may know that it can be
rigorously proven through his first theorem.
Something that you won't go through here, you
might see in a field through the group theory
module. But because. Statistical physics was first
developed before his theory, this conservation of
energy was merely an empirical observation that
was. Taken to be a fundamental law of the universe
known as the first law of thermodynamics. So this
first law sounds impressive. It really is just
energy conservation or equivalently, the statement
that if an energy of some system, which we can
call a capital, will make changes, then this
change in energy must be compensated or accounted
for by an equal and opposite change in the energy
of some other system with which America is in
contact, which we will see in the context of where
we will apply that to handle heat engines,
refrigerators and other similar cycles in the
framework of the economical ensemble. But before
we get to canonical ensemble, we have to define
what an ensemble is in and of itself. And that. In
order to do so, we can start thinking about
conservation of energy a bit more concretely and
getting back to that speed system that follows the
same mathematics and sticking points, we can bring
in energy by supposing that these things are each
representing the magnetic dipole moments of some
molecule that can interact with a constant
external magnetic field, the strength we will call
H where the strength of the magnetic field.
Really just has to do with the energy that it
contributes to interacting with any one of these
spins. So we have a.
Magnetic field oriented upward with that strength
age, and I'm assume that this is this field is
pervading this whole box that I'm drawing, and if
I have this upward pointing spin that is parallel
to that field.
We're going to say that this contributes energy
age to the.
This is negative if you want. So there is a
negative energy.
Coming in from having a spin, a line with the
magnetic field, if there is similarly the spin and
she aligned, pointing opposite to that magnetic
field, the energy that it contributes as well is.
Depositary.
We have then some number of spins pointing upward
and the remainder point downward, total energy of
that system. Is negative eight times the number
pointing upward. What's the positive age from the
remainder? And spins minus those and plus upward
pointing spins, which we can rearrange into.
That same.
But a minus eight, minus three to plus minus and.
Somewhat similar to the length of the random walk
that we were looking at previously, just because
we've defined simple systems that have the same
mathematical features as these new coin flip. So.
If I looked up the. State that I came up with on
the previous page, and just as a reminder, six
upward point expense and two pointing down.
The energy of that.
Representing the state would be this minus age
factor with two times six is 12, minus the total
number of students is eight. So that is minus four,
which is less than zero.
And that the negative sign of the total energy is
just a reflection of the majority of those
standards being pointed upward, aligned with this
metallic field that's bringing in that negative
energy.
So.
The interesting. Or an important consequence of
defining this energy is that since it is conserved,
there's now only a fraction of those two to the
eighth or two hundred fifty six states that are
accessible.
So.
If we look at the total number of states with
serious energy, not zero, but.
Minus four H.
How many of those two hundred fifty six states
would have this energy that we are going to see or
demand is conserved from connection to legacy or
everyday experience, empirical observation?
Can anyone tell the other what computation I would
need to do or just the answer to the total number
of those two hundred and fifty six states with
this energy?
So that is binomial coefficients. Eight to six,
which is a factorial over six factorial.
Times two. So the six Vectorial cancels out
everything below seven. So it's eight times seven.
Over to four times seven is twenty eight. So the
fraction. Of allowable states with a conserve
energy. Is that twenty eight over two, fifty six,
two, five, four and seven sixty four. So it's only
about 10 percent of the states that would be
accessible. To assess that once we impose
conservation of energy. And once we recognize that
energy is conserved.
We can also. Looking beyond the simple collection
of two state spins can talk about the energy use
for molecules in the container, which. It's
another standard example from dynamics that would
come back to you from several perspectives
repeatedly in this module where you can write a
simple expression. For the energy of these these
molecules by. Assuming that they are small enough,
we can approximate them as a point particle where
we ignore any size that they have or any structure,
the spin or angular momentum that they may have.
So that reduces the energy to just a computation
of kinetic energy. The velocity squared for each
of these molecules times, the mass that we assume
is the same for each molecule and we can rearrange
in terms of momentum. He's the mass times velocity
and the energy that is the sum of all of his party
calls for the momentum squared, which is a free
vector in a container in three dimensions divided
by this overall factor of one over two times the
mass. So whether we're thinking of spins in the
field or a bunch of molecules bouncing around a
container, we have the perspective that the time
evolution of any of these systems is is the Kaspi
process. And was the system probabilistically
adopts the sequence of states? Drawn from the
total outcome space of all of the configurations
of spenger molecules or in general particles. That
out of which it is composed, so rather than trying
to apply Newton's laws to follow the motion of all
of these ten of the twenty three molecules, which
would require writing down the power, twenty three
initial conditions and solving ten hour twenty
three differential equations, which is not
practical with any technology. We just. Say that
with each tick of some clock, the system with 10
to 20 free particles is adopting one state after
another after another, which is.
Exactly the set up that we went through and the
Probability Foundation's over the previous week.
And then you sort of form a connection between
this statistical view of physical systems and
those early foundations is this definition of
statistical ensemble that was introduced by a
physicist named Gibs in the early nineteen
hundreds. So that one hundred twenty years ago now
where the statistical ensemble is that same set of
all states that we defined in terms of
probabilities.
That's so the several states that the system could
possibly adopt through its time evolution and each
of these states has a corresponding probability of
being adopted by the system, are only going to
consider non-zero probabilities. So we say if the
state has no probability of being adopted, it's
not a possible state at all in the first place.
And we can recognize this connection of states
with probabilities as the probability space that
we were working with in that first year that.
And just as another piece of terminology, because
each of these states that. Our system of interest
can possibly take you specified by its microscopic
degrees of freedom, the particles that are
bouncing around and producing the large scale
behavior going to call them microstates, which
will eventually be contrasted with macro stage
with the states or quantum states, because there
are lots of different types of states with
connections between them that will come along in
the next few weeks.
So. The. Requirement for probability space that
the. Some over all the possibilities of all of the
states add up to one is now just the statement
that the system must be in some microstates at any
point in time, and the probabilistic sampling of
those microstates. It is going to define the
market, determine the behavior of the system that
emerges and is observed over those long timescales
with many steps and many states being sample.
Now, bringing in the fact that there are these
conserved quantities like the energy. You saw that
imposing that conservation restricts the number of
states that have a non-zero probability of being
adopted, which means that the statistical ensemble
defined as the sets of states with the
corresponding probabilities. Depends, which is
characterized by the particular quantities that
are conserved and the first example that we will
look at through this whole unit is what it's
called for obscure historical reasons, the micro
canonical ensemble. So it's a fancy name for a
simple idea. All it is, is that statistical
ensemble, a set of states that a system can adopt
where the energy is conserved and the number of
degrees of freedom. Is conserved, which because
degrees of freedom has a lot of syllables, what is
call that particle? So it might be economical
ensemble is the first example of a statistical
ensemble that will see really conserved quantities.
Characterizing it are the internal energy and the
particle. No.
And. The. The fact that. The energy in particular
is conservative, means that any system delivered
by the microbiological ensemble has to be isolated
in the sense that it's not in contact with any
other system with which you could exchange energy
or particles. So the thought of handwaving view of
a micro canonical system that we could have is a
bunch of particles in a box that is floating in a
perfect void in space and unable to exchange any
energy or particles or information with anything
else than we and the rest of the universe. So
impermeable walls around this collection of
particles through which none of the particles
themselves or the energy or radiation can travel.
If we think of this picture of particles in a
sealed container, we can make the approximation
that if this room were to be sealed off from the
outside world, so no one was coming in and out. No,
no noise, no able to leak in or out. That should
be. Described by a microeconomic ensemble, and we
do have some intuition about roughly how that
system should behave, and in particular our
intuition is that the. Behaviour of the states
that the system adopts over time tends to be
smooth and fairly uniform. So the usual suspects.
The particles of this box to be roughly evenly
spread as I. Sketched out just by unthinking
assumption here, rather than being all
concentrated in one corner of the room, and
similarly, if we did find, say, this room in a
state where all the air was concentrated in the
lower back right corner, you would expect that
states not to be typical, but all the area to
expand into the rest of the room, filling that
vacuum and producing something like what we feel.
Were the molecules forming the air? Have no
visible railings, no gusts of wind going through,
no big shifts in time.
So that intuition is. What we can have in mind
with this concept of thermodynamic equilibrium
where. It's really an axiom or hypothesis known as
the regarding hypothesis, that these physical
systems generically evolve towards the dynamic
equilibrium, the sort of stable state that
persists over time on human timescales.
Which we can.
Translater, move from the handwaving intuition.
I've been walking through towards a statement
about mathematics and probabilities by
mathematically defining what thermodynamic
equilibrium means, at least to the microeconomic
ensemble through these probabilities that we have.
Introduced for each states that are thermodynamic
system could possibly adopt. So with the
definitions that we have for micro economical
system, we'll make up the total number of
microstates in America called Capital M.
So the system is in thermodynamic equilibrium. If
and only if all of those probabilities are equal.
So that means any individual state has an equal
probability of being realised by the system
through its time evolution. And in particular,
because these movies have to add up to one and we
know there are some of them that are all equal, we
can immediately write down what the probabilities
are. They just one over so that the sum adds up to
one hundred percent. So. This. Conex, I guess it's
it may not be obvious how this mathematical
definition connects to the intuition I was going
through earlier in terms of what we expect for the
position of all the air molecules in this room.
And much of the remainder of this unit and indeed
the ability to connect the mathematics to everyday
experience, what does this mean? But before diving
into that, one thing to keep in mind. Is that
equilibrium, the steady state is again an example
of state being used in two different ways. The
overall large scale states of our system is steady
in the sense that it is in the delivery of it is
not showing any large scale changes, but. The
microstates being sampled by the system are
constantly changing from one moment of time to the
next.
So rather than being in a single micro state, be
this equilibrium system, which is the terminology
I should use instead of the states, it probably
simply adopts all of the possible micro states
with equal probability through its time evolution.
So. That initial section was largely a matter of
introducing definitions for statistical ensemble,
like a canonical ensemble and equilibrium. Are
there any questions about that before we wrap it
up for today?
Just in the last few minutes, I'll take a little
take a brief look at the next topic that will be
our focus on Friday, which brings in one of the
famous derived qualities that I'm sure you've
heard of is not necessarily mathematically defined
in this way before, which is entropy. And the
second of all, the dynamics that do that, the
entropy of a closed system is always increasing
and as time goes on. So we will drive that
probably on Friday and if not shortly thereafter.
But. What we will do
this is a preview, is a definition of entropy
based on the probabilities. That show up in our
microeconomic ensemble or indeed any sophistical
ensemble. And you will want to use. It's quite a
bit of entropy to characterize some of the
equilibrium in a way that more closely connects
via the mathematics that we are working with these
probabilistic sample states compared to that every
day intuition. And just as well.
The initial connection is our expectation that
quantity is. Derived from the behavior of the
microstates of our system are going to be stable
over time, even as various different microstates
are probabilistically adopted.
And.
The argument here is that we know in the macro
economic cycle these two quantities that are
absolutely stable over time, those are the
conservative qualities that characterize any
system governed by the right, kind of like on
ensemble, namely the energy and particle number,
which we should then expect to be able to express
entropy as a function of those two conserved
qualities. So that is. Yes, the. Forecast for what
we will. Do what we would go through next time. So
with that, I'll give one last call for questions
about probability or statistical ensembles. And if
there aren't any ill start wrapping up the
recruiting, shutting things down and see you again
this time in a few days.
It.