Should now be underway, just a minute late, as there
was another round of technical difficulties with the printers.
Hopefully I have successfully transferred the
six digits for this afternoon's session.
Seven, six, six, seven, five
three.  So with that out of the way, welcome back to the Friday
afternoon.  It's become sunny and warm but there are still some
fun things we can do here.
So.
This week's tutorial, we talked about Sterling's
formula, which will need some focus adjustment.
How did you all get on with that?
With Sterling. And before me that she's named.
You want to part of.
The.
Derivations in this problem, my last week in
particular, driving these bounds, we were able to
do it in person last time. Do you have any. Going
beyond that to. Find that. Do you buy that or what
the values of any of these? As yet, unknown
consequences may be received in this full series
for the vectorial of a large number of workers,
only it's logarithm.
That's true of.
Too challenging, especially, he says, since I left,
it is optional war analysis and the. Version of
this problem that I initially uploaded to Canibus,
which I've since fixed a few typos in there,
including at the bottom of the page here. This is
of the power. Negative one was incorrectly.
Sean, the initial version as negative a switch is.
Fairly obviously incorrect. You make you change
your variables to Y equals eight times X and then
just do the integral to the minus Y y.
Something something's important to society for
potential.
It's.
Here, so would it be worth going through some of
these steps that we didn't get to last time around
in driving?
Sterling approximation and powers used to allow.
There does seem to be. Objection, saying that
you've only done this work on your own. Is it time
to repeat it, live here to pick up with the.
Equation at the bottom of this page where there
was an unfortunate typo that. In the initial
version of the fix would have. Caused some.
Difficulties with manipulating this equation.
The idea of the manipulation to do here, so taking
it for granted that we've shown these vials and
confirmed that the meeting turned into an
approximation, is a walk in.
In order to derive the full expression with the
facts or to plan included, we need to.
Stop what is about to start looking at the actual
calculation of N factorial, which. I'm sure you've
seen can be related to the Scherba function, that
is. Further generalizable to complex numbers
related to rebudget, a function, the first step is
to. Consider just interest for any particular
positive.
Ensure that the game of function plus one is equal
to N factorial in the. Trick suggested here was
manipulating this simple, definite integral.
Integrating from. Zero to infinity, minus eight
times X is one over a year, and the manipulation
that. Proves productive in this context is to take
the. Derivative with respect to a of both sides of
that equation. So. If we do that on the left hand
side derivative with respect to a interchanging
freely with the integration over X brings down a
factor of minus X plus the exponential on the
right hand side, that the derivative turns that a
B minus one into one over A squared again with a
negative side that we could cancel out. And then
repeating this process in the second derivative of
the derivative of the first derivative, we bring
down another power minus X on the right hand side
of our minus to the negative signs. Keep canceling
out on each side of these equations. And if we
generalize to the tenth derivative, so.
And derivatives, with respect to a gives us the
relation between the integral role that we play
off with the gamma function and plus one. And just
the product of all the powers that come down on
the right hand side of that vectorial times, this
arbitrary, constant day to the power minus and
plus one of eight to one, it drops out and we end
up with what we wanted. Now.
That's just the first step in the actual
derivation of Serling's formula, the next one
being to.
Stipulates this interval for the gamma function in
particular, looking at it back up here. Trying to
expand this 50 grand in some sensible way, so I
showed the picture last time arguing that. This
function is approximately a gorshin. Around its
maximum value, you can see that if.
The X is very large or very small, that
exponential factor is going to dominate the
overall integrated and I guess the the next step,
it was just that I can't remember if we discussed
or not getting to the second page. I was to show
that this factor in the category in which we can
revive as a single exponential has its maximum and
a particular value, which is just a matter of
taking derivatives of that integrated. So.
This overlay of some calculations taking that
derivative of the A. we have two terms that we
want to set equal to zero to exercise this
function. And cancelling out come back would be by
the sex those two terms and end up being taxed on
our in from the derivative of the sex and times
extra power and minus one procedure at the end,
which immediately implies that An equals X at this
extreme second derivative is just as easy to
compute and evaluate against at the extreme gives
a negative result after several cancellations.
Which confirms that extreme that we have is indeed
a maximum, which is not a surprise, and we looked
at the plot of that function last time around. And
this justifies expanding the war, rewriting the
Interbrand in terms of fluctuations around this
maximum. So at the maximum when X equals and this
new variable Y equals zero and small Y is going to
correspond to the small region around the maximum,
that actually contributes to the integral going
over the integrating over this exponentially
suppressed function. So we can approximate. In
fact, we know very well by expanding. It's
exponential in terms of and so why small compared
to an.
Itself involves first expanding the water that is
within the exponential.
Which. We can.
Do you think the usual power series, logarithm of
one plus a small number is small number itself,
minus the number squared two and so on?
Off the screen. X-Men is next to two plus executed
over three positive signs off to infinity. That
gives us some cancellations and a suspicious
looking and again, bias. And it's already
reminiscent of Sterling's formula trying to drive
what's left over after that truncated expansion of
the order of the small number Kud Y squared away
over in one of the accused. We can insert all of
this back into that exponential. And bring out the
cost in terms of why. So that's the more than my
spin is at the end of the end, minus 10 in what's
left of the. Integral is precisely what was
promised in the.
Problems with that last time. Which is that factor
is going to play in that. Gives us the usual form
of Stirling's formula that you may have seen
before.
So hopefully walking through those steps pretty
quickly out of the. What's going through the
argument here is a decent balance between filling
in and sticking points that you might encounter
thinking about this on the or at the same time not
duplicating that effort that you put it on your
own. The generalization that I'm still exposed to
this whole series, these corporations A, B and C
suppressed by larger and larger powers, is
something a little less. Carmen. This is something
you may not actually have seen before. It sounded
like.
You weren't able to find any candidates for the
values of those A, B and C that. Correct. And you
have a. Result. They want to shut up.
In the interest of time, I'll go through this
stage of the.
The calculation is a little more quickly. It's a
fun one, and there was the last time that having
derived this usual form of service for the to play
and times, this had to be a factor. We can take
that is taken as given. That's the approximation
can be expressed in this form of an infinite
series. And apply that to the relation between, in
fact, where you live and plus one Vectorial that
is really you defining property of the factorial
as an operation, which is to say. Plus, one factor
is and plus one times in factorial and both of
these materials. They are on the screen now. We
can hit with.
For one, keeping some number of shows here up to
order one over into the fourth. So on the left
hand side of this equation, everything is in terms
of influence, one both in the prefecture and in
the series expansion itself. And on the right side,
we're expanding in factorial. We have that just
factors in except for that overall and plus one.
So a fairly straightforward arithmetic to do, to
isolate, say, those powers of one hundred and
whatever and squared one over and you won't get
all of the square roots and the exponential either
canceled out or what remains is this combination
of one plus one, the return to the power, then
from the terms in parentheses and plus the half
from the square roots. Celebrity players and so on,
and we have to do that is. Express both the series
in the square brackets, expanded in terms of one
over end plus one to some power in terms of.
Powers of one president and similarly for this
factor. That one plus one and two and a half. Also
needs to be expressed in terms of the powers of
whatever. You may recognize that.
Expression for the exponential. Is the limit of
them going to infinity? What I want to listen to
the end suggests that this is the latest one going
along here will be relevant. The first stage of
things is, you know, in terms of expanding the
powers of one over plus one. Law enforcement
squared law enforcement is just the simple
application of the geometric series pull out the
leading power of and in the denominator.
Everything left in the denominator is a small
number of one race versions of the series, and we
can expand. In this case, we have one plus one
over N so we're expanding in terms of negative
whatever and whatever squared minus here and so on
up to that same border, whatever into the fourth
at.
Here to the other side of that equation for the.
Other factor, one over one, plus whatever happened
to the power and plus a half. The.
Easy ways to address this is to, again, convert it
to the exponential of the law and do that same
sort of expansion that we did in the previous
derivation of the route, buy, in fact, to expand
the law that overhead is a small number. So here
I've kept up to order one over into the fourth,
which would keep into account that it's being
multiplied by a factor of power and from the
overall power front. And then just rearranging
gives us an exponential of a small number. And
actually, for any number of the we know is just.
It's so serious that we can truncate after the
first term up to this order, whatever, and to the
fourth. So bringing everything together, we have
both sides of this equality and plus one Vectorial
is a plus, one factorial. Both sides have ever
expressed in terms of how or whatever, and we just
have to match up all the coefficients of those
equal hours on each side of this equal sign. So
power one over zero, that's just one one times one
is one that equals one on the other side, which is
correct, but not so useful for determining the
coefficients of the series at the one over end
level. There's just this term here times that one
this term. They're telling us that it equals a
again, self-consistent but useless. But if we look
at the.
Four terms proportional to whatever and squared
have we have this one of the 12 times when we have
B minus A times one on the other side was just B,
which can only be true if that day is a 12. And
there's a similar. Rehearsal for the whatever and
human turns we're here, we need to account for
costumes. Including this eight over 12. In
addition to the terms of in. Whatever, and you'd
already multiply by one. Coming up, with
cancellations on both sides that may be equal to a
over 24 or two hundred eighty eight, so the
ultimate results for Sterling's formula is the.
Potentially familiar prefecture to high end times
and over all to our end times, these power
corrections one plus one over 12 and it's one over
two hundred eighty. And then the next trip is a
native son. I forget about you and to you. There's
a clear procedure to compute as many of these
terms as we want just by expanding. More Mexican
insurance to appropriate orders and matching the
powers of one over and that appear in the
definition of vectorial.
So hopefully that was
amazing, too, to see what might be more relevant,
the statistical physics than this derivation of a
classical formula is looking at applications of
Strongs formula and maybe addressing the question
of. Do those corrections that these computers
really matter?
We have
this expression for an vectorial. That's
expanding and plugging that into the logarithm
that is going to give us.
Expression usually stop with placidity sequence of
corrections.
When half offered to buy end and then the
logarithm of this whole series.
That can come into play.
And.
It's an easy enough exercise to fire a pipe down
and plug in numbers into both sides of this
equality. There is what I've done in this table,
just for some representative, the illustrations
that if we look at, say, just an equals five.
Two terms will we typically truncate statements
from what we've done so far, electrodes are off by
thirty five percent. So it gives us the right
order of magnitude, but this is the.
Direct computation by.
A significant amount, though, adding that next
correction, the. Close to one half of the
logarithm too tight end immediately gets us within
one percent of the correct result. And all of
these approximations become more accurate as the
number of degrees of freedom going into these
factorial increases. So. Already for any one
hundred homes is still tiny compared to 10 to the
power 20 30 that we have in all of this. It
becomes challenging to print out enough figures to
see any discrepancy between the result we've
computed and the direct computation. Even that, in
my mind, is in is 99 percent accurate. And if we
get that in that war, they're going to buy and
whatever and then and squared terms. In addition,
additional war in.
Then we get to the point where. The approximation,
especially the computation to what is said about
11 significant failures have to go out to one part
in the or tend to be 11 to find the difference
between the two.
Actually.
This hints at another use of Sterling's formula,
which I made.
Currently on.
Screen here, I'd be able to get set up before. We
started.
Look at the Python code that.
I used to read the numbers we've been looking at,
which.
Somewhere.
This for any five, you see that? Thirty six
percent off just from here, like I said, getting
better opportunity for several significant figures
matching as we get through the full computation.
But if we consider, say, seven equals five
of.
So two thousand and ten to three
million. See this code breaking down, it's not
really a complicated code, it's just plugging in
these formulas and evaluating them for
given end of interest. Forty four thousand the.
Python computation of the log of and factorial
precedes by first trying to compute the factorial
head and then trying to take the log of it, but
already for the second end of
the keyboard,
already for kind of one hundred and seventy one, I
think is where that factorial.
Overflows the available floating point numbers
that are available that are offered by modern
computers, so one hundred seventy degrees of
freedom in this vectorial is about the upper limit.
We can handle about 10 to power. Three hundred
seven.
Whereas just the simple expressions that we have
from Sterling's formula, I have no problem.
Computing numbers as large as 10 of the 10 under
the 12 at some points will be roundoff effects in
and of itself that even though and factorial, is
unmanageable without some special care. The
Serling's formula approximation, the computation
of Morgan Vectorial flows through without any
particular challenge.
All their applications. I don't want to spend the.
Full time on this. To
do one other discussion, going back to Unit two,
that's introducing the microeconomic ensemble and
in particular the entropy, in this case for a STEM
system, which is a direct computations of the
entropy would be if the external magnetic field
were zero and every single one of the two of the
power and possible microstates were accessible
with the same sort of energy in the approach in
the. From that considered how that would change if
we demanded that the energy remain zero in the
presence of a magnetic field and we found that the
resulting entropy was the logarithm of twice the
number of quite experienced, minus twice the
amount of. Of that number of people with
experience, actually, and we've been told they're
going to try to computers back to where it was
instead, just try plugging in some numbers, for
example, with eight spin's seeing that the entropy
decreased from the log to the eight two hundred
fifty six down to seventy.
Now, if we try to hit this with try to address
this with Stirling's or what.
That gives us a way to approximate these facts,
horribles that we
saw. Sorry about that
the former cop tried to grab.
So in this case, we have and is equal to twice the
number of opportunities to be paid. Interest. In
this case is going to be the one with them of the
binomial factor for, say, two and choose evidence
which.
Did that computation already on this page, still
more than two, eventually minus twice Walkerville
factorial, which are usually a function of
Stirling's formula, would give us to and more to
end minus two in. I was twice and once again I was
in, so. Although the linear terms cancel minus two,
plus two, and indeed, if we break up this
logarithm to allow them to a with them than the
two and log and cancel the two and log in and we
are left with. To end times, the one or two, which
is exactly what we found.
Or the case where that sort of genetic field was
equal to zero. So this is a case where our usual
approximation to Sterling's formula is a bit too
overaggressive and doesn't distinguish between the
doesn't reveal the decrease in entropy that we can
expect from removing a large fraction of
microstates from the accessible set. What we need
to do in this case is retain that logarithmic term,
at least take that out here to keep from having to
stretch it out while I talk. So we have all of the
cancellations we just went through at that to add
more to that. In addition to that, the moderate
level. We have the lawn of the square root of two
pipelines to N minus the minus twice the water in
that square root, which is water to paint itself
combining those lines out. The two and four, we
end up with the decrease in entropy that we
expected rather than that for two and to for the
case of all microstates of the spin system that
decreases by the logarithm of the square root of
pipelines. And so the direct calculation for this
to end equals date back to. That gave us the more
70 that's now being approximated by eight ball to
minus the lawn of the square root of four, which
is again within one percent of the true value.
So in addition to confirming that the entropy is
decreasing, that negative sign is microstates are
made inaccessible. We have a precise prediction
for exactly how much it computes, which require
that.
Third. Term in the Sterlings formula for the. And
there's lots of other fun things that could be
done with Sterling's formula. One example is to go
back to the vandervoort in one dimension to big
step sizes that would consider in the one where
you can show that as the number of steps in the
walk increases to infinity, the probability that
the water returns would start a position
infinitely many times is one hundred percent. And
that follows from following Sterling's formula to
some of the combinatorial factors that it was in
that calculation. The same thing holds true in two
dimensions. Where the random walk with the big
step, like their response to choosing a direction
down, left or right during the step in that
direction. Which defines a let's call lattice
positions that the marker can can be held, so
rather than doing just left and right with even
sized steps. It's also possible to go up or down.
And in this case as well. So all the spaces in
there are meant to be equally spaced. And the fact
that they're now deceased have to my artistic
abilities also in this case, there is a 100
percent probability that the walker will return to
the starting position infinitely many times as it
takes steps to realize the three dimensions, that
same probability changes from one hundred percent
to zero percent. And that is also the result in
all higher numbers of dimensions. We imagine the
threat of water exploring some. Higher dimensional
levels, possibly in an abstract space of points
rather than physical space. There is a sharp
change from one or two dimensions to free and
higher in terms of.
How possible is it possible for Walker to return
to the starting place and how frequently does that
I will stop going on about Sterling's formula with
that? We still have a few minutes remaining, I
guess some discussion, at least with the homework
assignment that's now due in less than a week. And
just to comment on some of the questions that have
been posed here, some of the inquiries I've
received about that and see if any of you have any
further questions that would take a look at this
assignment or if you haven't looked at this, can
be a chance to. Go through it to some extent and
make sure that everything that is being asked is
clear.
So the question that came in had to do with this
first problem about the. Movement of oil spill and
in particular, the question about. Whether the.
The spill itself. Can be modeled as just a one
dimensional process, or if the larger spreading of
the spill on the surface of the water needed to be
taken into account. So.
In practice, if we. Imagine if some oil spill has
time. John, in addition to drifting, we might
expect that spill to spread out over a larger area
in not just the direction it's drifting, but. The
whole. Two dimensional plane available to earth on
the surface of the ocean. But essentially, what we
are doing in this problem is a simplification, and
this is projected over that drift in the final
direction just onto the single line. That
separates the location of the first from the.
Protected area that we are worried about reaching
and not just the Griffin diffusion of the spill.
Towards the protected area in that whole dimension,
this can't be justified a bit more precisely than.
By going through the problem just to.
Suppose that, well, it is an accurate
approximation of the. Before edge of this rift
remains parallel to the boundary of this marine
protected area in two dimensions. But we can't
take it as a given or as long as us that this is
the one dimensional problem, that.
Post for us to to deal with. And in this first
question. The many questions make it more
straightforward.
Looking at. Systems of the microeconomic ensemble
is.
Even from that microbiological behavior, the
temperatures entropies and the process of heat
exchange systems with various temperatures
according to triple contact with each other and
leave the last two questions actually touch on
reforecast in Unit three. So derivations and
elaborations left out of the lecture that was
driving the.
Fluctuation in response, relation between heat
capacity and the fluctuations of the energy around
its value, the canonical ensemble, and certainly
looking at the high and low temperature expansions
for the interval and the internal energy and the
entropy of a system of indistinguishable spins of
the gas, which is where we wrap up Unit three on
Monday. So. Are there?
Any aspects of these questions that are unclear
just needed to read into the balance and all
should be started at the athlete in terms of
religious? Yeah, so the specific terms that are
requested
is the screen.
In these expansions for the last two parts of
question four on this specific about how many
times to keep, so in this middle part of this, the
two leading troops, which may include any
volunteer constants, that does not depend on the
temperature, that can be one of the few of them.
And then. In the last part, there's just the one
leading term in high temperatures and two leading
terms, depending on whether we're in city that has
no plans to retire.
Yeah, so that is the small parameter that we will
be expanding in, depending on whether it's the low
or high temperature, it's being pursued. So that
is the small parameter that organizes what turns
into something. So just like we were doing today
in terms of hours of over and.
So I want. Go on to say anything more about that
assignment, if there aren't further questions
about.
Take a look at three things now or wrap up and
move on into the weekend and see how you get on
with that.