Okay,
I'll keep doing both Zoom and Stream Capture
recordings to see which works best. Turns out the
ones yesterday didn't really work at all, but
fortunately that seems to be an issue with the
equipment in the other room 210 rather than. A
personal curse for me, this document actually
seems to be functioning the way it's supposed to
be recordings and in fact, the projection itself
should turn out better today than yesterday,
should be able to zoom in and out and even focus.
On what we are looking at in the magic number for
the. Flight attendants will check Second System
edition
this
year.
So knowing that
and having just met at the end of yesterday, you
get at the beginning of today, there's not need to
do too much recap. There's not enough time for
information have to fail. And there was one point
that there was one little tidbit that I actually
forgot to bring up and talk about at the beginning
of yesterday morning, what the motivation and the
big picture for statistical physics that actually
had to do with the Nobel Prizes that were awarded
just last autumn, which I don't know if any of you
kept track of that, but half the Nobel Prize went
to a couple folks, secure a bit of a class
Hofferman for work on climate modelling. And the
climate models are actually reliable, predictable,
which is one of the big applications of
statistical physics in modern day research with
some relevance to.
To society and to us and the other half of the
award actually went to a jury of your peers who.
Was awarded the Nobel Prize for conceptual
breakthroughs in the treatment of complex
statistical systems, in particular systems related
to the interactions that we'll be getting to
toward the latter end of the term. All of those
applications which are sufficiently cutting edge
to. The analysis by Nobel Prize are not going to
pop up in this class and that code two zero three
nine seven nine, which did not go.
The chat window.
I might be able to design some tutorial problem
once we get into those interactive systems that
will connect to some of the stuff, Super Easy was
working on things. These are called spin classes
that.
Rely on non negligible interactions, which is
exactly the opposite situation of the negligible
interactions. If you look at four for most of this
term, which is in in place of formal recap, just
that reminds us of the importance of statistical
physics and also its role in the emergence of
complex phenomena from fairly simple underlying
fundamental processes that we have to model
sarcastically with elements of probability. So
going from these individual atoms or other
molecules of the particles, objects in our system
that are bouncing off each other or even just
passing straight through each other. We come up
with the. Complex emergent behavior from a very
large number of those objects with 10 to the power,
20, 30 being the relevant number, Avogadro's
number appearing in sort of everyday scenarios,
everyday situations built on the underlying ADLs.
And we went through then a few formal definitions
to build up the probability of foundations. The
key one being what is the top of the screen here?
The introduction of measurements. That is a
mapping that to apply to the state of the universe
after some manipulation or some observation that
allows us to control the set of outcomes that we
are interested in. So when we roll the dice, the
measurements is what allows us to predict the
outcome of that. The stuff the goes onto the
numbers one through six, ignoring the situations
where the guy ends up on the stage in the corner
or a cat comes by the. And why can't we map out
the one to six? The measurement process takes into
account all of those possibilities and just gives
us a number that we can work with and treat as an
event, some subset of all of those possible
outcomes that the measurement defines. And we got
to at the end of yesterday, the the mapping. Of
events in this event space, the set of all
possible events from the subset of outcomes into
the real numbers between zero and one, including,
of course, the probabilities of those events occur
from zero percent up to one hundred percent. And
yes, the question came out, how much measure
theory is it relevant to this definition? And
really there are the two properties coming right
below that after what we stopped last time that do
play an important role in. Defining the
probability measure as a well defined probability
that we would talk about in everyday life, the
first of those being that if we want to consider
probability of well before moving out, I should
ask you three questions about anything that came
up last time, both just as well as the
mathematical content and always feel free to jump
in if any questions do come to mind. But
this is sort of. We are in some of the rooms to
switch to the schedule, so. But I was on. If it
wasn't here yesterday, were to a psychiatrist and
SWAT start
moving on with. These probabilities that we have a
probability of two events, this event occurring,
the probability of more than a six and two from
that roll of the dice. Then the probability of
those two events occurring is the sum of the
probability of each of those probabilities to
probability of six. So that hopefully is simple
and intuitive. And then if we consider the
probability of. All of the individual outcomes
being defined by our measurement that we impose.
The probability of that entire outcome space, when
the event space is equal to the outcome, space has
to equal one, which is to say that if we do an
experiment and measure something on it, we demand
that something happens.
And this is.
Again, including that measurement to project the
physical universe onto. Nice, well-defined
mathematical numbers, but if. Something happens
that doesn't appear in the outcome space, then we
should just as well say that nothing happened in
the first place. There was no outcome to to be
fortified with this probability. And then the
overall probability space is the combination of an
outcome space that incorporates both the
experiment itself and. The measurements that we do
upon it to extract these random variables, the. A
set of events, the event space that we are
interested in talking about and then the
probabilities that are assigned to each of the
events in that event space. So make this concrete
with a relatively simple but still somewhat
general or generic example, imagine that we have
an experiment that can produce only one out of 10
possible states.
So how states have maybe one and the relevant
states is this capital will make a set of all of
the states. Now, if only two of those states were
identical, then by definition they would produce
identical outcomes for all the measurements that
we would do. So
having Omega equals Omega J for J implies that the
measurement result is the same on both of those
states and the Gollan and make a J and the
contrapositive that logically follows from that.
If that statement is that if the two measurements
are distinct, the states themselves must be
distinct. But because the the measurement function
in general is not a. Unique isomorphic function
that maps a single state onto a single measurement,
the. The reverse direction of this relation does
not hold if we have two different states, we can
still have the same measurement on those two
different states. So the space of possible
outcomes, A, which is far off the bottom of the
screen there,
a, the outcome space we can label by the outcome
of the measurements on. Each of these large end
states of the universe, some of those measurement
outcomes will be the same for different states. So
the city will have some size that is smaller and
that can be no larger than the total number of
possible states that we are considering to be
finite at this stage. And in general is much, much
smaller. And getting back to that simple example
of rolling a die.
We know that the outcome space is just the six
numbers, one through six that can come out on top,
whereas the whole state of the universe is keeping
track of things like where that is ending up after
we roll it.
So the two indices on these lawmakers and these
exes, the outcomes of the measurements are not
necessarily mapping out to each other, but we can
set aside the states themselves and worry only
about the measurement outcomes going forward
where.
We can choose the event space to be a collection
of each of those individual outcomes, each
considered in isolation, and then all of those
isolated outcomes combined together into the set
of events, which is then just equal to the total
space of possible outcomes. And because we've
constructed this event space so that all of the
possible events are mutually exclusive of all the
others, then that each of them has a distinct
probability. So the probability of. And with this
event of Alpha will just hold that a little
reduced piece of alpha for all of the possible
outcomes of Alpha and then. The two requirements
to have a well-defined probability space are that
the probability of any two events or any two
outcomes occurring, alpha, beta, four different
alpha beta is just the sum. Of the individual
probabilities for each case and then the
probability of the full outcome set in this case,
the full event space is again the probability of
any of those outcomes occurring all of the sudden
from one to N, and that has to add up to one
hundred percent just as a statement that something
happened in the experiment that that we did. The
six sided die is the simple example that you can
use them to put a. A simple concrete understanding
on some of these abstract, generically checkable
mathematical definitions. So we want from the
assumption that this this guy is fair, there's an
equal probability of ending up with any of the
outcomes that we've defined for measuring the
number out on top. That is enough information to
actually compute the six probabilities for getting
those numbers out one through six.
And probably this is a question, what are these
probabilities, something that you could just tell
me immediately without having to think about it.
So go ahead and shout that.
And here that. Fair just means that each of those
probabilities from one to six is equal to the sum
of key.
And what is?
It is one over six and. That hopefully sounds
intuitively obvious, the probability for giving
each of the six sides it's following from
precisely this condition on probabilities in
general, the sum of Alpha. Going from one to six
of Palitha is just six feet, and that has to add
up to one hundred percent. So pee is then this,
that one over six from the assumption that this
guy is fair.
And we can also, again, we saw the example of the
coin four times as a single experiment with some
space where we wrote down with 60 elements getting
four heads, two heads followed by two tails, two
tails, followed by two heads all the way to two,
four tails. And we can hear
do that same sort of calculation to.
Figure out the probabilities for each of those
outcomes from assuming that the coin is fair.
Does anyone remember how many outcomes there were
in that setting, there were 16 and each of those
outcomes then as a one out of 16 chance of
occurring. And if we instead of taking the whole
event space to be the outcome space here, we're
showing we.
The power of these definitions to apply to
somewhat different of different circumstances we
can consider instead of the individual outcomes
for heads or tails to heads or tails, UTSA heads,
each of those has the probability one succeeds we
can. Considered different sets of events that
might be interested in in this case, looking to
see when we have equal or different numbers of
heads and tails coming out of those four tosses as
a single experiment.
So.
Was. I heard someone. Saying either the answer to
this question here or a question about it, what
are the probabilities that we're getting the two
events in this event space? So probability of
getting an equal number of heads entails the
probability of getting a different number.
That's. Three directly. Yeah, so there are six
ways of getting two heads and two tails out of
that 16 possibilities, and then it happens to be
that all of the other outcomes and the outcomes
based A have a different number of hesitations. So
we can take the shortcut of recognizing that the
probability of getting different numbers is 100
percent minus that three probability, which is
then five. It's just for. Reference right down, I
guess, on the side here, the.
Six.
Outcomes in the first event, in this two event
space where.
These are all the ways of arranging those two
heads and two tails in. Any order coming from
flipping a coin four times?
So those are the. And the simplest possible
illustrations of. The definitions that we are now
through. Are there immediate questions about any
of that
continue or will wrap up this first sort of
definition section with a slightly more elaborate
example that will come up a bit? We'll build upon
a bit later on in this unit, which is looking at
roulette and without advocating any gambling, we
can think about the possible outcomes of spinning
a roulette wheel, assuming it's fair where with
this wheel has is thirty seven pockets that each
column with a numerical label from zero up to
thirty six. Eighteen of those are colored red 18
or colored black. The numbering is not in a very
obvious pattern there, but even in our numbers
that are called red, black and then pocket zero is
singled out, at least in this particular standard
European set up as the single green pocket in the
roulette wheel. The idea is if we spin this wheel
and roll all around the outside of it, eventually
that slows down. It falls into one of these
pockets randomly. And we can think about both the
number that is leaving that pocket as well as the
color of the pocket, which is. The colors
automatically specified by the number.
Hopefully the.
The focus on that projector is good enough that
you can are able to read off numbers around the
outside of their.
Enables them briefly to get a closer look at it
with the actually functioning that in this room
rather than yesterday's equipment. So considering.
Back out to the.
We were there all sorts of event spaces that we
can consider based on the outcome space A which.
At this point, I guess you can tell me straight
off the top of your head what the outcome status
is.
Here is the exact plan. They're.
There is a number going along with or sorry,
there's a cover going along with each of those
numbers that you can take to be implicitly
specified. And then the corresponding.
Probabilities. Again, coming from something over
these thirty seven.
Possible outcomes with the event space set equal
to that outcome space that some of the
possibilities as one. And the assumption of a
roulette wheel. Use any for whatever thirty seven
probability to each of those outcomes, and then
again, we can do. The same sort of. Construction
of a different event, space that doesn't map
exactly onto the outcome, space can look at the
colors. Corresponding to those thirty seven
possible outcomes and break those up into an event
space with three different events where the ball
ends up in some pocket with a different color, red
or black or green. And you can tell me. The.
Probability of having that. And up into a red
pocket by that sort of distributive property,
probability is just going to be the sum of all the
different pockets around there that are colored
red, which is one three. So on and not all numbers.
And thirty four is the last one. And Tom.
Because I've already told you that there are 18 of
these, so you. Can tell without having to support
you that. The probability of. Ending up with the
ball in a red pocket. Is 18 of the thirty seven,
so slightly less than 50 percent. It's the same
for.
The probability of ending up. In the black market,
which is the sum of the probabilities for two and
for up to.
Thirty five. And finally. The probability for that
rocket is the remainder. These are a mutually
exclusive set of events that end up covering the
whole outcome space about the event space itself
being equal to that outcome space.
So we'll come back to do something more
interesting with that roulette wheel in a bit,
just to wrap up the definition section of the
course here mentioned that. This process of
assigning probabilities to events essentially is
modeling in general, and what we've done in the
three examples of coin tosses, dice rules and
roulette tables is by assuming all of those
processes are fair, reduce the symmetry between
the size of the dye, the size of the coin or the
pockets in this roulette wheel to immediately
determine what all the probabilities of the
possible events are.
More generally, if we don't have those cemeteries
to rely upon, we can just repeat events time after
time and empirically observe how often these
events occur. That's an empirical estimation of
probabilities which gives us.
Results within a certain confidence level by.
Collecting a sufficient amount of observational
data from repeating the experiment, which is
disconnecting to the next topic, involves large
numbers where
it's really tells us formally how we are able to
infer probabilities just from repeating
experiments and measurements a sufficient number
of times so that any questions before moving on to
that law of large numbers.
So charging forward to keep the same. Simplified,
but still sort of generic situation with a outcome
space that has a finite number of elements that
the label by the measurement outcomes except one
going up to this exact little end, or there are
then in probabilities piece of alpha, all of which
are between zero and one. And all of which add up
to one without necessarily all being equal.
And we can. Generalize this notation in a way that
also applies to. Accountably, infinite sets of
outcomes from experiments and measurements where
instead of something explicitly over output from
one to end, we say we sum over all of the outcomes
X and our outcomes. It's a sum of the probability
of that X occurring, and that has to add up to
that 100 percent sum outcome happened if anything
happened at all.
And from the sort of notation we can define the
mean and the variance which are properties of the
probability of space space itself. So the
probability is that map these events, selections
of measurements onto.
Percentages from zero percent to one hundred
percent, where the mean is given by the expected
value or what I'll probably call it by having the
expectation value of the possible outcomes in the
outcomes space, which sum over all those possible
outcomes, X in aid of X weighted by probability of
that outcome to occur. And the variance is a
similar expectation value shown by these angle
brackets here that simply mean do that same
weighted sum computing this quantity X minus the
mean mbewe for all of the outcomes in the space
weighted by the corresponding probabilities. So,
yes, here there is a general definition of
expectation value simply being the function of
those outcomes weighted by the corresponding
probabilities.
And that expectation value is a linear operation,
if you multiply it by a cost and see that cost can
be pulled out of the wreckage expectation value
operation. And if you look at linear combinations
of two possible functions of these outcomes, F and
G, the expectation value of that linear
combination is the combination of the expectation
values. So.
I'm. Making assumptions could be wrong that these
are things like meat and dairy are things that
have come up before in other molecules and we can
check from the definitions. Toward the top of the
page, that's the standard deviation, the square
root of the variance has a simple expression in
terms of the expectation value of X squared and
the square of the expectation value of X. So if we
start from definition of variance, both as the
expectation value of.
But I'll start calling fluctuations around me the
difference between each outcome and the mean
outcome, that quantity squared and then take the
expectation value of that. You can simply expand.
That square and then apply the fact that the
expectation value is within your operation to.
Start getting something that. Looks familiar where
I've used the fact that this meeting is a kelson
property of the probability space to pull it out
of all those expectation values. The expectation
value of the concept is just the concept itself.
And because we have that new itself is an
expectation value of the individual outcomes, we
can rewrite this as two times the expectation,
value, expectation, value, and where is the
expectation value squared and you end up with. The
expectation value of the square minus the square,
the expectation value, so sigma itself is the
square root.
That's the difference
that is still on the screen, which.
Again, I assume it's something that is familiar.
I see some civilians saying that is the case.
So what we are going to do based on. The set up of
this new way of writing
outcome, spaces and spaces, means and variances is.
Generalize that example that we had of flipping a
coin four times, you will define a single
experiment that consists of repeating some of our
experiments, some number of times. So are four
repetitions. And we make the demand that each
repetition of the original.
Fundamental experience is independent of the
others, and in each case, we perform the same
measurements to get the same. A set of problems
with the same probabilities in the space and time
that.
New outcome, space to be B, so B is the outcome
space, if we repeat the original experiment to
give some space A some number of times. So based
on that definition, if we still have that original
outcome, space of X one up to X lowercase and.
Some of the representative events that show up and
B, if we fix our schools. For the politicians. A
single outcome in this new event, space be. Is
this New Orleans Excuse me, is just going to be
poor outcomes from that original space. So just as
when we were flipping a coin four times, we could
have, say, heads, heads and heads all in a row.
Or since we're generalizing this, to have some
number and possible outcomes of the original
experiment gets repeated. We could start off with,
say, how Trump, for the first repetition won in
the second forty two in the third and then won
again in the fourth.
And all sorts of probabilities, or I should say
all sorts of possibilities, each with their own
probability. So I guess I can ask you at this
point. Knowing that the size of a number of
elements in that set is this lower case m how many?
Elements are we going to have in this new album
space be?
To Bill. That would be something like that if we
were flipping a coin and those two possibilities.
Now that we were able to get up to four point
forty two and an.
Yeah, so with R equals four, there are four
possible outcomes or being multiplied together,
and if we go back to that general and we have a
product of any possible outcomes for that first
experiments, that first repetition and possible
outcomes through the second repetition and
possible outcomes for all are of those repetitions
so and multiplicative factor. So our
multiplicative factors of M. So each repetition of
the experiments brings in multiplication by the
total number of possibilities. And the.
Even when the size of the. So fundamental, the
underlying original event space is finite once we
repeat the experiments of a large number of times
and large are, we see the size of the space of the
possible outcomes really rapidly growing,
exponentially growing in that. That number of
repetitions and.
Now. Try to keep some of that on the screen, we
can think about the probabilities of all of these
outcomes. Are all of these events in the larger,
repeated experiment outcome space be based on? The
probability is that you've assigned to the event
space for the original underlying experiment that
gets repeated. Where?
We can define the expectation value for each of
those repetitions, so that little parenthetical
label or has that mean new and variance sigma
squared? And again, just talking about four
repetitions for simplicity.
The probability of any of the individual outcomes
and be considered as an event by itself is going
to have. Each of these labels, so you could
combine the first repetition of the second
repetition and the third repetition in the fourth,
and that again multiplicative breaks up just as
the total number of outcomes multiplicative
depends on the outcomes in our space. A, as the
product of the independent probability of getting
that outcome by the first replication times, the
probability of getting the outcome accepted and
the second repetition. And similarly for x axis of
evil, in the third and fourth repetitions where
the individual probabilities are coming from an
outcomes based A. Which is now being related to
the much bigger conspiracy by. The assumption that
all of the repeated experiments are independent of
all the others.
And what we can now define probably another
familiar concept, is the arithmetic mean? As
opposed to the true meaning of the probability
space that requires exact knowledge of all of the
outcomes and all probabilities in that space, is
arithmetic mean is what came up at the end of the
previous section? Are we talking about figuring
out probabilities by repeating an experiment some
number of times this averaging over the possible
outcomes that are observed?
And that's the key point, is that this arithmetic
mean is a random variable. So it's a measurement
that we can perform in that appears in the open
space. B.
Where we simply add up the values of the
measurements for each individual, repetition
average over the number of repetitions and define
this arithmetic mean. X bar with a given number of
repetitions that is set in advance and so for.
Each element in that repeated experiment out of
space, we would get a slightly different estimates
or empirical observation for this arithmetic mean,
but we do expect that the arithmetic mean is
related to the true meaning of the distribution.
Particularly of the. Distribution, a single
experiment, distribution that we can have an
easier time getting a mathematical grip on. And
there is a relation that can be proved rigourously
as. That number of repetitions goes to infinity,
given the assumption that the variance. Of the.
Original experiments without consent is a is
finite in the footnote, there is just a note that
the second part of the computer project is going
to focus on what can happen if that assumption
breaks down to the variance is is infinite for a
distribution and looking at the time.
And debating whether there is enough time to go
through the little denervation, establishing this
equivalence, and I think that might actually be a
nice thing to start off with on Friday rather than
trying to squeeze it in in the last couple of
minutes. So just do one more poll for any any
questions that have come up in the course of today.
Any word on how many strain
that's notation I've seen in various places, but
that's sort of a shorthand to fill in the space
available. Not anything really crucial. So just
using the it's called the no sign to refer to here
the number of elements in A or B.
This is not universal, but also I'm not the only
one who has employed that, so to you ask about do.
And.
With that, I will. Shut down the recordings, you
say, thanks to those of you who have not been able
to make it, but have told me that you're unwell
and they're joining you because it's all about
class, that we can tell who's here, who isn't. And
I appreciate you kept in touch about how things
are going. So
hopefully as the spring progresses.
There
will be less. Illness going around.