So we've got the recording underway, and it's just about time
to start.  Are there any immediate questions from
earlier in the week before we get going?
While you're thinking about that, this is today's
magic number for the attendance system:  nine eight eight
one one zero.
There was some interesting discussion on the Canvas site
about whether the law of diffusion we saw a few days
ago, at the start of this week, has built into it an
assumption of large N, like the central limit
theorem. I think that it does, but I didn't prove
anything. If there are no questions about that or
other things, we can catch up a bit with what we
did on Tuesday and where we are now.
the micro-canonical ensemble
we saw earlier this week after wrapping up
the random box, which will see again in different
guises with the introduction of statistical
ensembles.
As is the particular example. Of the capability of
spaces we defined.
The. First unit for the force where. Is the key
idea behind this identification is that.
The time of ownership.
Of the degrees of freedom particles in this
ensemble. Our as leader, probabilistically, simply.
It's.
All of the possible spade's.
In the outcome space for this probably only space
and.
Even as. The ensemble, the system is probably
probabilistically sampling all of these states,
there is stable, large scale or long term
equilibrium behavior.
Which.
In that equilibrium state, which is what we're
considering in this model, is sophistical
ensembles are characterized by conservative
qualities.
The example we are looking at first is known as
the micro canonical ensemble, where these concerns
quantity is.
Our. The energy. And the heard No. We're
conservation of energy, given the name, the first
law of thermodynamics in an isolated system. So
this is a picture that got blown up to its full
page by the printer to serve as a sort of mnemonic
for this microeconomic ensemble
characterised by we have some particles of degrees
of freedom in the system. Your picture is a beaker
with a cap of the show that all the particles are
trapped inside, can't escape, can't change the
number of particles, and there's also some
insulation shaded it around. The outside
of this drawing illustrates the conservation of
energy, a possibility for the system to exchange
the energy with its surroundings, with the other
system. So we're going to pick up from there if
there are no questions about what we saw before.
Some of the qualities that we can now derive from.
Statistical samples of the microeconomics ensemble
in particular
zoom back in focus. Starting with the Entropia,
which is. One of those ideas was.
They may have popped up a lot in popular culture,
everyday life, and is sort of the synonym for
chaos or disorder. Here we get entropy as a
mathematical property of statistical examples
where this initial definition that we wrapped up
with on Tuesday is. A generic definition of
entropy for any physical ensemble, not necessarily
the micro canonical example.
In terms of the probabilities piece of pie that
each of the possible micro stages of the system
has to occur as that system probabilistically,
examples microstates involving over time.
Again, as always, in this course, in thermodynamic
equilibrium.
Now.
Well. The reason note here that. Because we're
imposing from an equilibrium, we can expect the
entropy to be a simple function of the
conservative qualities so specialized to the micro
canonical example is entropy, although it's
expressed in sort of a not intuitive way in terms
of because the probabilities should in some way be
related to that sort conserve energy and particle
number, which we can start to derive by plugging
in the expression for this piece of by. In the
Michael Canonical ensemble, in some of the key
political, does anyone remember what that
expression was?
One over, and
that's what it is. There was a hyperlink to the
equation that appears and is the number of
microstates in the system, every single one of
them is equally probable in the micro particle
sample. And hence those equal probabilities are
just one. And so that any of them add up to one
hundred percent. So that's the entropy is the
negative of that. So overall, microstates of this
constant probability, whatever, and. I'm so
supportive of whatever happened, so OK. None of
that depends on the micro state we're in. This is
just a cost factor that can be pulled outside of
that situation. So the sum of I was just counting
one from one to add to that is a factor of 10 that
cancels out with the whatever over. And we're left
with a negative log. Whenever any of the
properties of the walk, we know that that is the
logarithm of the number of microstates. And if you
were ever to visit Vienna and start wandering
around graveyards there, you would see this
equation with slightly different terminology on
Boltzmann's gravestone. This is Boltzmann's
equation. The entropy is the logarithm, the number
of microstates that was one of his best punchy
contributions to the physical physics and also put
it on his gravestone when he died and. So as the
number of accessible microstates goes, this
entropia grows and eventually diverges. And this
is. Maybe a more intuitive way to connect the
mathematical definition of entropy that we have to
sort of every day terminology of entropy as a
measure of disorder, the more microstates there
are with a fixed energy particle numbers and the
more possibilities there are of arranging the
degrees of freedom, the larger the entropy, which
we can see corresponds what we will see. Some of
these examples coming up, how that corresponds to
less ordered, less special and more generic
microstates for our system. Now, of course, we
said at the top of the page, you would expect
entropy to depend on the conserve energy particle.
No, it's not obvious how those appear in the
microstates. It turns out to be they do all of the
conservative quantities and the number of
microstates are interrelated. So we have to
specify the system and its details in order to
come up with what precisely those interrelations
are. So. One quick example is. If we have a spin
system introduced earlier this week. Each of which
can point either up or down, and it is in a
magnetic field to define its energy, all of that
magnetic field is turned off. We want to find the
entropy that's avoiding them. So here we just need
to count the total number of microstates, for
instance, which.
Something we did on Tuesday is remember that
results. Right down here.
So, yeah, two to the power in.
The total number of microstates for and spins the
conflict to the values and as a blog we have been
involved to for the Intrepid, still a mystery you
that grows linearly with the number of spins that
field is off. We can also so when there is no
magnetic field, all of those could be and spin
states have that same energy equals zero. We can
also ask if we have a non through a magnetic field,
but still require the same fixed energy in the
micro canonical ensemble.
What is the entropy in that case? So it's the same
procedure figuring out. How many microstates there
are?
You know, the.
This is also something that.
You may have seen it a saw the same calculation in
a different context. So maybe I will just. Mind
you, that the silk, the way to get energy is zero
when the magnetic field is non-zero is to have an
equal number of students line with the magnetic
field compared to those aligned against it. So
half of the spins have to be and plus, along with
many other people, contributing a negative energy
to the total. And therefore, if we have capital
and spins and we want to choose the case and plus
of them to be oriented up there are. The binomial
coefficient in use and plus ways of doing that in
those different ways of arranging the spins to
have zero errors used, the microstates that this
microeconomic system would have, which if we know.
Since we know that. Total number of spins is now
twice and plus we can. Rearrange this binomial
factor as to add plus factorial over. And plus
Vectorial, and then the Vectorial, the two and
plus minus and plus, which is just ten plus for a
second factor. Plus, Vectorial, the denominator.
Which the Lord breaks up into.
One of the numerator minus, take that count to
twice the Lord.
Of the Vectorial in the denominator. So it's
obvious to see. From this expression, if this
entropy is more or less than. The case where there
was no magnetic field at all to the end, states
were contributing, what were they to the entropy,
if we consider this the simple case of an equals
eight? Then.
We have. Two of the power eight.
This is two hundred fifty six, so it is zero and
all possible microstates are at play, the entropy
is that more to our eight to fifty six.
H.S, non-zero.
It's easier to look at this fraction with the
entropy is. The board of two influxes cattle,
which is bait and expand that vectorial and cancel
out the full effect within hours of Vectorial the
denominator, I'm left with just the other power
for Vectorial, the denominator four times to the
state and six of the three is to seven times, five
is thirty five and two times thirty five is of 70.
So the total number of microstates has gone down
by. Probably a factor of for. And the entropy has
changed here by.
Of course, on the border, which you will see a bit
later on, is.
I has some interesting behavior because it limits.
That was on the screen while I was writing it. So
we will. Revisit some calculations, and that's
where possibly a tutorial, possibly next week. For
now, just based on this definition that we have,
we can build up some more.
Details or characteristics of the. And one of the
main features of the Entropia of a period way to
categorize observables is how the entropy behaves
as the system becomes larger or equivalently, we
take two copies of the same system and imagine
considering them as a combined system with some
subsystems. So we saw the general growing that
with the number of microstates logarithmically.
And.
Mr. Consider. This in a more general context than
a specific number of things. We can picture these
two school systems, each put in its own box to
emphasize that it is a micro canonical system not
allowed to exchange other particles or energy with
anything else in the universe.
So that the energy and the number of these two
systems is characterizing them and also.
Assume that there is a. How's the magnetic field
to get to produce this energy that is the same for
both of these isolated systems when it comes to.
And then the energy has the same form and then
just the number of spins in each system align with
or against that magnetic field.
And. Just for the sake of using different
variables for these two different systems, we'll
say that the probability probabilities in System
one.
I have that same piece of mind for each of their
lawmakers that I microstates. And there are in one.
Of those microstates, and we'll call the
probability system to Kucik, ranging from from one
over the total number of microstates in that
system. And if we look at these two systems as a
single entity with two subsystems that are still
isolated from each other and still in the same
magnetic field with the same energy in order to
determine the energy of this. Combined system.
Make the subsequent one plus two. Always do is
figure out the number of microstates. And someone
else to in terms. Of the number of individual
microstates and one and then to 12.
This is. Reasonably straightforward, because
whatever the system one is in some microstates by
the system, two is completely independent of it
and can sum over all.
And two of its microstates and then the overall
sum over all.
I microstates and one brings in the power factor
of them two for each and one each want to be a one
microstates, which says the words that the total
number of microstates is the product of the
microstates in both systems. So it was that quick
argument is clear.
I don't see any objections to it.
And.
We also.
Are not supposing here that the analysis I'm doing
here is actually not assuming that statistical
equilibrium, it can be applied more generally than
that if we go back to that initial definition of
energy, sorry, the initial definition of entropy
in terms of probabilities.
The entropy was the sum.
Over all the probabilities of this combined system.
The U.K. and Borg.
So we need to figure out as a prelude to this
calculation what exactly the combined entropies.
The combined probabilities are, since we're
keeping these two subsystems completely
independence, the probability of that system, one
has stayed on, I guess. Subsystem, too, has states
how big is the pay is just the product of the
individual probabilities.
Which we can check quickly, is well defined
because, again, at that independence between these
two subsystems. If we saw over. The product of
those states at one time, there were two in this
combined system. That's just the product over each
system independently and sends the probabilities
of System one don't depend on the states and
system to break up the system into separate sums
for each subsystem. Overall state of the
probabilities, which we know by the definition of
probability, is just. One in each case. Which is
to say.
Matt.
Well defined by the probability piece of junk that
adds up to one overall of the data and one, two,
microstates of this microeconomic system, and we
can do that same procedure. Breaking up this song.
Over, I think, those two subsystems into.
Two independent studies and at the same time did
break up this. Logarithm of the products we know
is the sum of logarithms, so we can have.
The. First term, it is P times, Q Times, the one
with rearrange that.
Like still calling the. Probabilities survive from
such as the one outside of the some of the
microstates and subsystem to. And similarly.
The case when we have the second term.
So hopefully that was not too quick just now,
broken up these sums into separate sums or for
each independent subsystem in the same way as
before, and this allows us to spot the same simple
probabilities that add up to one of those two
cases. Whereas we saw that the. Somewhere over
microstates of Pewaukee inequitably culotte to.
Was just the. Individual entropy from system one.
That first term, plus the individual, that system
to. So we've derived from the basic definition,
the result of the entropies, when we add up to
independent subsystems, just add together to form
the entropy of that combined subsystem of the
combined overall system when the two such systems
are independent. This is the definition of an
extensive quantity. The energy and the number of
particles are the easier examples to use to work
with. If we take two systems with two particle
numbers and one then to add together, a particle
is just the sun. The entropy behaves the same way,
which was not guaranteed optimal result from. This
calculation, based on the definition and could be
contrasted to what are called intensive quantitate
is
an example of which is the temperature of two
systems, two systems with the same temperature,
and look at them as a combined system of two
subsystems. I don't expect the temperature to
double. I expect to see the same independent of
the size of the overall system. And then, of
course, there are quantities that are neither
extensive nor intensive. For example, the total
number of microstates which turned out to be the
product of the microstates, the two independent
systems is not constant, nor does it grow
addictively the way that the entropy does.
And of course, everything becomes simpler if we
were to assume for a dynamic equilibrium. We would
have the Entropia system just given by the one of
its microstates, and in that case, the
probabilities for the combined system as before,
add up to whatever the total number of microstates
each that there's some over and what time them to
give 100 percent. And then the calculation would
it be called. Even easier, the combined entropy
and just by the properties of the water, the World
Cup into the some of the original to entropies.
So that extensive property is one feature of
entropy, but maybe not the most interesting one,
or at least not interesting enough to describe it
as a law of nature. What happens?
Or what we can generalize that same set of two is
now in addition to taking those two subsystems and
bringing them together in a combined system, we
will allow them to exchange energy particle number
with each other. So we'll call that through
contact. Where we have those same to. Subsystems
in the magnetic field that are now brought into
thermal contact that have the possibility of
exchanging energy. With each other now, the
overall system, the total energy one plus the two
and one plus into. Is still being treated,
microeconomic energy is concerned for that total
one plus two and similarly for political No. But
the individual interviews, you want to get
themselves change basically by swapping energy
between themselves, so a bit of energy can be
given up by subsystem one. Shifted over to some
system, too, so those individual energies are no
longer conserved and the individual subsystems are
no longer psychoanalytical for that reason. But
economical ensemble requires that cost of energy
and. So if we call this overall system. It's the
capital Omega, with no further subscripts, we can
tell immediately that it is not the same as.
That's system one plus two. We were talking about
it in the context of extensibility subsystems work
at independent each individually microeconomic
level and the entropy just on attributes of those
independent subsystems, typically at.
In order to. Appreciate that this. New combined
system of mega is not the same as the collection
of those two independent subsystems. We just need
to count the total number of microstates. And see
that it is not the same as simply being a product
of. The one time that two of those two original
systems.
And in this calculation, we do have a important
remaining tool, which I actually paid. The set up,
which is that conservation of the poor energy, so
we know that any microstates of this combined
system will make. Has to have a total energy.
We're capital so that in one of these two
subsystems that are now account contact
contributes some lower case energy, each one to
that total. The other subsystem has to contribute
the remainder capital, the minus lowercase E one.
Now, if we fix those two values in every case, in
one, then the remainder will be minus one. We then
have the combination of two independent
microeconomic ensembles that we computed to have
the total number of states simply a product of the
corresponding microstates with those values and
energy in each of the independent subsystems. So
this is. That said, repeating the same calculation
we did earlier with the independent subsystems,
but now. The key is that there are at least one in
many more ways of distributing this total energy
among these two systems. We know that it's
possible to have the case we considered before
that case even equal to the capital E. one. We
started off with that is when it started off with
know that subsystem can take that energy capital
if you want, it already did. So from that
particular case, we already have all of the
microstates. And if someone wants to. That we
considered earlier on, we had the system of two
independent subsystems considered in combination.
But in addition. We have to keep track of these
situations in which system?
Omega one has energy other than one. So the total
number of microstates for that system Omega.
Starts off with the product and one time step two
and we had for. From those decisions to subsystems,
we started off with having their initial values of
energy and then in addition to that, there's a sum
over all the other possible values of energy that
we were all the possible ways that the systems
could break up the conservative energy amongst
themselves. And this stuff is just counting a
number of states that are all one negative numbers.
So we know that the sun is also not negative. So
the total number of member states is at least as
large as the. And one times and two that led to
the extensive interview on. And this economy holds
only when there is no other possibility than
having the
energy and system will be its initial value, which
is to say that the two subsystems individually
made MicroCon behave in the same way as it could
have exchanged energy in the first place. So in
full generality, without even specifying the
details of these systems, you can say that the
energy. Of these two systems, nothing but the
entropy of the two systems that have got into
trouble, contact is at least as large and
generally larger than those two subsystems when
they were independent and isolated from each other,
which you might recognize as the second law of
thermodynamics. The statement being that when
initially isolated subsystems are brought into
thermal contact, the entropy can never decrease
and generally almost always increases, except in
some extremely special cases when that thermal
contact actually has no effect. Even though the
systems are able to exchange energy,
their details prevent them from doing so in order
to satisfy the first law of thermodynamics.
So the second law of thermodynamics, which is.
Again, another question related to entropy that I
imagine you've seen in less mathematical contexts,
it is it's possible to do more general derivations
than taking to systems, bringing them together in
terms of content and allowing them to exchange
energy if we picture that process going on in time.
This has the implication that the entropy never
decreases the increases as time passes under any
circumstances.
Which we can actually make use of. To the. Find
more generally what we mean by dynamic equilibrium
as compared to a statement about probabilities and
the souls equation. Here it is. That the
probability of each micro state of the macro
economic one is equal to the inverse of the total
number of microstates. But because entropy. Is a
non decreasing quantity under any circumstances.
If we consider its time evolution that.
That not decreasing property is going to call for
any statistical microeconomic or not including the
one that. Including ones that we will get to in
coming weeks. So the entropy.
Is. Always decreasing, is that a function of
whatever qualities are considered for this
ensemble and.
We want people to be able to be the state where
these qualities have some stable value. They have
to depend on the on the conservative qualities. So
we define thermodynamic equilibrium to be the
situation in which the entropy of the ensemble is
maximized. So we have some we can have some
generic picture or intuition of. Doing something
to systems that bring together a lot of energy, as
we just consider this, can leave them out of
trouble and hard to analyze with the.
Tools and techniques for developing this course,
but as time passes, we expect them to approach and
recover their equilibrium in this new situation.
Two systems that are now allowed to exchange
energy. And as the system goes through that
equilibration process, the entropy is. Never
decreasing, it is either constant or increasing.
And once some of the people that it's reached, the
entropy that saturated whatever down it is allowed
to to reach with a finite number of microstates,
which physical systems you always have. So then
the saturation of that maximum entropy corresponds
to the phenomenon of an equilibrium without having
to specify precisely what quantities are conserved,
precisely what sophistical ensemble are
considering. So that was sort of a long process of
argumentation based on physical intuition rather
than mathematics. Are there any objections to that?
Not hearing any what we can do just to wrap up
this section and possibly report. Today will see
is show that this new and more general definition
of equilibrium reproduces. And the. Condition we
had earlier in that equation, my team with a
microcephalic ensemble where all of the
probabilities for all the microstates are equal to
that equilibrium. So the way we do this is
consider that entropy and its generic form, then
some over microstates of plock. And then subject
to this maximization process, to the three
constraints implicit in the Bible canonical
example, first, that the probabilities are
probabilities and add up to one with some degree
of microstates, and also that we conserve energy
and conserve part of the number. And it turns out
that it's only the final constraint over. The
probability of something up to 100 percent that
needs to be taken into account in this
maximisation through. A method of war crimes
multipliers, which. Pretty sure you should have
seen in previous novels, or perhaps not recently,
perhaps some time ago, so might be worth reviewing
at least briefly. But the idea is that. In order
to maximize the entropy is subject to some
constraints in this case, the sum of some of the
probabilities equals to one. We define a modified
function in this bar that depends on everything.
That depends on as well as this additional
parameter lambda code. That multiplier and what
this multiplier is multiplying is the quantity
that implements this constraint when the sum over
P equals to one, its quantity in parentheses
vanishes. So that whenever we have found. And
whenever we oppose. This condition on the
probabilities we automatically get back, recover
equality between this modified spark and the
emotional bond that we are interested in and in
particular.
If we consider the derivative of this modified
entropy with respect to the large multiplier, once
we impose the constraints that also banishes.
Which means that in the extreme of the modified
entropy, it's going to remain an extreme one of
the. Actual entropy that we are interested in the
case when land is equal to zero. So.
With that set up, the.
The maximization process simply consists of
looking at the derivative of that is modifying the
image on the screen some way with respect to the
probability that we want to. Two constraints. We
want to find the value for the probability of a
generic MicroTech that maximizes the entropy with
this multiplier, imposing the condition that the
probability. Is well defined as up to one hundred
percent of the microstates. So if I copy this down
at the moment, then I can get rid of that sheet.
We have a similar.
Piece of I have one piece of it. Plus, Linda, I
just remember I used to buy that old stone like
this one,
and now we can.
Just to pose the
identity written up here, where a derivative of
probably a piece of eye with respect to. The
probability piece of cake is going to vanish
overnight, it's not equal and it will be one
whatever equals K, that's the Honaker Delta
function that we encountered briefly last week.
And we can pull it through in this. Some of the
derivative will pick out the Kathee term in that
sum over I.
And give that Delta function so. Acting first on
the piece of up front, because the building like
so negative Morgan piece of.
Similarly, acting on the board with derivative
keeps that piece of iron and brings over a. One
over piece of the building,
that is. Pick over pick, which is one, which is
one. And then. The final term is even simpler,
which is pick out the delta, I came from the
derivative of peace, the value of peace, OK? Which
is going to be one for the one term that some of
that is equal to the probability, T.J., we are
interested in. So overall, we have. Negative all
play minus one slam dunk, that being so equal to
zero to get the extreme. Of this modified and
which is to say that this piece of. Is the
exponential of India minus one, which with this
constant parameter lambda is just a constant and
that imposing. The constraint that we have, the
some over all of these equals, one immediately
tells us that this is one over the total number of
microstates. So we have. We we have derived what
initially we had to state as a definition of
thermodynamic equilibrium to maximize the entropy.
We find that all of the probabilities for the
microstates and the macroeconomic ensemble. Are
our people so equal probability for every micro
state in this microcosm ensemble? So given the
time, that's where we will wrap up, so I thought
we might get the temperature today, but we will do
that on Monday instead
of the fact that temperature is not. Inherent in
the micro example, but it provides on the same
footing as with some high tech companies in an
unusual counterintuitive futures. This afternoon
we have a tutorial. So my plan is to go through
the remainder of that computer and then I'll
answer any questions that have come up about the
computer project that's due next Thursday. And if
that doesn't tell the time, I have more computing
stuff that we can look at
all of those. So see you then.
You focus on what is really focused on this be. So
my office would to walk back there right now if
you can come along with
a book or just for.