All right, let's get things underway this Friday morning,
approaching the end of February.  It may be that
all the news from Europe has distracted all of us
over the past few days, but it's probably best to
persist in what we have to deal with in front of
us for the time being.  Of which, the first thing to
deal with is the magic number for the system
today is seven eight four, three, four, zero.
And let's catch up
with where we got to go earlier in this week
and where we're going today and over the coming week.
So for this day a few quick logistics notes.
First homework assignment is due next Thursday,
3rd of March.
May well spend some time looking at it and making
sure it is all clear to dig to this afternoon in
the tutorial, among other things, like wrapping up
that discussion of Serling's for more and then
also fix the typo. I noticed in the lecture notes
on Tuesday where they sent over and particle's had
incorrectly written that as it sunk from zero to
infinity, which is only valid in the limit of
infinite particles. Now. That sun came up in the
context that we are working on now of the. Ideal
gas.
They analyzed through the framework of the
canonical ensemble. The statistical sampling
probability space that we get with the temperature
and particle number fixed of that particular non
relativistic. Classical.
And you'll us. In a container, a box of Boliva
allocute.
On your side of the boy, you in turn. Produces.
Discrete energy levels.
For us to analyze coming from the discrete moments
of. Each bar pi over L. Times the vector of
non-negative integers.
So. What we're looking at their.
Which is what I had on the screen to.
Custody, the focus and the brightness of the
protector today is driving the canonical
competition function, the starting point for
analysis of economic momcilo. And as we did with
spin systems on Monday, considering what the case
of distinguishable and indistinguishable particles,
finding out that these differ by a factor that
counts the number of possible ways of
distinguishing a set of particles with all of the
momentum, the resulting energy is the same is the
simple fact of any factorial leaving the
competition functions. For the discreetness, would
indistinguishable, indistinguishable cases, so are
their. Questions about. What we've gotten up to
and what we are going to pick up on that today.
So we began that. So given the economic
competition function that we drive to, the next
step is to gain
predictions for the large scale macroscopic
observable features of these ideal systems, in
particular focusing as usual on the internal
energy systems, the same quantities we looked at
in the case of spin systems. If that first
application we canal, for example, at the end of
Unit three on Monday, we went through the
derivation of that energy and entropy and the
indistinguishable case to the more complicated one.
Where that Helmholtz free energy is a convenient
repackaging of these partition functions, taking
the war, multiply them by the negative temperature
and then taking derivatives of that free energy.
Give us both the internal energy and the interview
that internal energy boils down to something quite
simple. Three 1/2 times the number of particles,
types of temperature, everything else in the
protection function is independent of the
temperature drops out of the derivative. And
plugging things into the entropy, we recover.
Another term coming from this expression to be
derived based on the free energy relating to all
three of these quantities. So in addition to that,
three jobs and the energy we have, the.
Contribution to the HUMBOLDT'S free energy itself.
Bringing in some remaining dependents can
approximate with Serling's formula. We talked
about at some length. In the tutorial. Ending up
with an injury of five hands and time plus end
times, the longer this ratio of the volume of the
container times and times, the cube of this
thermal double, the wave length that we define
which. We can. We may see where you can trust me
when I say that this is or can be thought of as a
way of associating a light scale with each of
these particles at a given temperature. That's.
Can be interpreted, that is the amount of the
volume occupied by these particles and in
particular the ratio of the total amount of oil
available divided by. The amount of that volume
that is occupied and I went through reiterated
these things that we have already done in some
detail, just because if we move on to the next
stage of repeating this analysis for the
distinguishable case, we can actually just
essentially write down the answers from the
indistinguishably case. We go back to the relation
that we had that was just a factor of any
factorial difference between the supervision
functions. And we can see that this point
factorial that's contributing to that second term.
Again, we have goals for energy in the industry
for the case. So all that remains, if we remove
that to get to the of the case is. A slightly
complicated expression. So I ask you to shout out,
just copy down from the previous page,
that first term, the innocence of the case,
carries on to the distinguishable case without the
one over in Vectorial. That's.
We would be would be introduced if we had to
identify a lot of these distinguishable
microstates adding up to give us the protection
function of the free energy. And now. Something
interesting happens. Moving on to the energy this
year, boy in Vectorial with three by team is just
part of these t independent terms that don't
affect the energy coming from the places that we
derive from the chemical ensemble. So the
derivation with distinguishable case is turns out
to be exactly the same as that for the
indistinguishable tree energy and then moving on
to the entropy. We have this. Relation between
these two terms, we see that the difference coming
into the Helmholtz free energy is going to carry
through into the entropy PACULA. We don't have
this log in Vectorial factor to expand out anymore.
We're just left with. Three have in plus and Lord,
the over the thermal cube, which, not surprisingly,
is what's written in these equations. Fifty two
and fifty three for us to check the energies are
unaffected by it, whether or not the. Particles in
this ideal of gas are distinguishable, but the
entropies do have a difference, reflecting the
different amounts of information that we have in
principle about the system, depending on whether
or not we can distinguish the particles that
compose it. So.
In one sense, this behavior of the entropy
equation. Fifty three is a bit like we saw for
that same system as the first example at the end
of Unit three. There is a difference in the
behavior of the system, depending purely on the
information content that is available in principle
for that system. We also had different energies
and.
The if we want to boil down, this is a brief
remarks for you to think about if you are so
inclined. The reason the energy is come out the
same here, but came up differently in the case of
Spain, systems has to do with. How the
distinguishable and indistinguishable micro states
are connected to each other in this case, I guess
we just saw that every indistinguishably
microstates maps on to and vectorial
distinguishable microstates independent of the
energy of those microphages from the different
ways of labeling the particles that we're three.
And you saw that the the number of distinguishable
micro states varies depending on how many of the
spins are pointing up or down. There are many more
micro states with roughly even numbers of up and
down point expense compared to the extreme cases
with the maximum of the minimum amounts of energy,
like the grand stage, where in both the
distinction center in this case, there's only that
single grand state. So the.
That no mapping distinguishable in the same
microstates all to each other in the ideal gas
case that's independent of the energy. Just that
simple act of vectorial in all cases that we can
bring side of the partition function. But for the
spin system, the factor vary with the energy
leading to, in that case, a difference in the
internal energy, depending on the information
content, which we do not cover in the ideal gas
case. And as the a couple of final remarks. So
looking at these two expressions for
distinguishable and indistinguishable energy
entropies, which is fifty three,
if we want to think about the energy, is
quantifying the amount of information that we have
about these systems, the amount of different ways
there are
a sign of the system to microstates, you would
expect that in the case of many more microstates
it would be a larger entropy. And we can confirm
that despite the the difference in this linear
term here, just because there is also this factor
in showing up in the war with another end out
front and that in the end is created and for any
reasonable number of particles. So subtracting off
and again from the extra linear term we have in
this case does give us the expected relation.
That's just a possibility that leads to larger
entropy
and. I was sort of driving to the other
observation earlier, looking at the. Interview for
the quintessential case where we have this log of
the ratio of the total volume of the container
divided by this end times, different length cube
that we interpret as the volume of the container
that's occupied by the particles in the gas. And
if that.
Occupation fraction happens to drop below one.
That the second term here is in times of log of a
number between zero one would be negative and
indeed as the temperature approaches absolute zero,
this boy wavelength.
I should probably. Record. Here, for reference,
was a nice place for it.
So.
The wavelength is.
Two pi squared over.
And he. What would that? To the square root, so as
the temperature goes to zero, the wavelength
diverges to infinity and so the argument to the
logarithm approaches zero. So the entropy appears
to diverge to an infinite negative number, which
is problematic if we think of it as. On a count of
the number of microstates available, depending on
energy. What's going on here is that this is
exactly the regime where our assumption that the
collapse of gas is classical is breaking down. So
we did that in a few weeks. So certainly before
the verdict sometime in March. So. Those are the
basic observables, internal energy and entropy for
ideal gases of both dismissable and
indistinguishable particles. Are there questions
about the derivations or conclusions being taken
away from these expressions?
The next topic is. Something known as the Gibbs
paradox, which is. Not terminology I particularly
care for, because that's we'll see, there is no
paradox in the end,
but it is one of the important topics in
statistical physics that illustrates some of the.
Ways of thinking about these collections of large
numbers of particles, the ways that large scale
physical behavior emerges from microscopic
dynamics, and also the dangers of sort of
qualitative physics based argumentation with
insufficient appeal to detailed mathematical
calculation, which is probably the case for a lot
of so-called paradoxes in modern physics. They
arise if you try to work by analogy and. Every
argumentation and show to be or not an issue upon
going through the detailed mathematics, so the set
up for. Looking at the Gibs paradox, which is
related to something called the mixing energy is
to.
Repeat the same sort of. Thought experiments that
we did a few weeks ago when we. We're considering
biochemical systems and we wonder what would
happen if we took two micro economical systems,
put them into verbal contact that allowed them to
exchange energy, and then we isolate them. And we
saw that energy flows from one of these systems to
the other unless they had the same temperature.
And through that process, the second law of
thermodynamics was we actually derived a simple
form of it so that the entropy never decreased.
And in general, increases, though, in that
calculation, we had to be careful to account for
all the entropy after we isolated the two systems,
keeping track of the fact that. Once the systems
had been allowed to exchange energy. In the micro
political setup, we had to. Some over all the
possible distributions of energy after the storm
contact has been made and then broken. So we're
going to generalize that same approach to the
economical systems, these are already allowed to
exchange energy with their surroundings that form
a reservoir that fixes their temperature. What we
will now do is take two economical systems and
bring them into. Contact in such a way that
they're allowed to exchange protocols and then
after they have exchanged those particles reach
some equilibrium, we separate them. We can think
about this either as removing a. Wall separating
two identical boxes or to make it slightly more
every day.
Situation we can think of, this is opening a door
between two rooms that we will suppose have the
same temperature tea and just for simplicity, we
will also formulate this.
Canonical ensembles of ideal classes with the same
number of particles then and the same volume V as
simple as possible case that we can construct for
this thought experiment, see temperature, same
volume and the same number of particles. And like
I have to zoom out a bit. They have all three
stages of this process on the screen at once. We
start off with these two systems, A and B, that
have that fixed temperature or energy issues with
the environment. Upon removing the wall that
separates them, we have the combined system, see?
Norman. We are going to be interested in. What
happens to the entropies, say, S.B, at sea as this
process proceeds after allowing political exchange
in this new system with twice the number of
particles, twice the volume, still the same
temperature? Assuming there is a large thermal
reservoir around the entire system, that
temperature will be three isolates, the systems
reinsert that wall. That in between them, we still
expect the second law of thermodynamics to be type
to be obeyed and the entropy never to have
decreased. So.
As we just saw in the. First part of today's
discussion, the entropy is dependent on whether or
not the particles in this gas are distinguishable
from each other and just as we did for the
duration of the entropy.
We start by considering that case,
indistinguishable particles.
Rachel.
Is to some extent the easier system to consider
because there's less information to keep track of,
which is the total number of particles as well as
the.
The volumes of the systems that they are contained
within the boxes contain gases. So if the gaps
here are. Simple calculations, but they are
calculations is trying to get in. Talk to them
myself rather than. Asking. What do you expect?
What we have for that first stage with two
identical ideal gases and with the same
temperature and in volumes, the boxes with the
same volume, we have twice the contribution from
that in this case of the entropy, depending on the
number of intersexual particles and the volume
they're contained in. Which you look back a few
pages ahead. That was five halves in for the
interview. The initial case was that and the board
of the over and. Then cubicle. Which.
Is the easy calculations to.
Down here, and they want to compare this initial
interview from before the two systems are brought
into while we're allowed to exchange particle's.
With the entropy of the combined system after
particle exchanges allowed in this case, we still
have essential particles so we can refer back to
the results of the derivation we did for the
entropy. In that case, we just have to involve
them in a container that has twice the volume. Of
the two that we started off with. Instead of
reading. Plug this into that expression. It's five
1/2 times the total number of particles, 210.
Eight to end times the law on the ratio of twice
the volume. To be over this to Ed. The boy,
Wavelength Kyun. Which boils down to five and plus.
To that, she was canceling that ratio.
And we come back with exactly the interview we
started off with. And that is consistent with the
second law of thermodynamics, entropy does not
decrease. It has just the same which.
Engaging in some of that qualitative physical
argumentation I work against is what we would
intuitively expect if we have two identical
systems, two identical rooms, open the door
between them, you don't expect anything very
dramatic to happen. This is reflected in the
entropy here as well as the energy. The more
trivial
we separate in the systems now is more complicated.
Because when we close that door or we insert the
wall that you have, you don't necessarily know how
many particles are going to end up on each side of
that barrier. What everyone here is going back to
the starting case with there were in particles in
the left and the right. But there are.
Obviously, and other possibilities where. Anywhere
from zero particles could have ended up on the
left hand side of that barrier, which we argued in
Dettori over the past couple of weeks, is unlikely
and should be expected on the basis of the equal
probabilities for all microstates. Similarly, we
don't expect all to enter the particles to end up
on the left hand system that will make it a crime.
But those are still possibilities that are still
valid, microstates that will contribute to the
entropy and have to be kept track of. So.
The total number of microstates involve something
over all possible ways of dividing the particles
between the two separate boxes when we compute the
partition function and. For this, he's to be
separated systems. This is the tricky part that I
shouldn't rush through. And I will emphasize that
performing this song over all of the possible
microstates that we can get from all the different
ways of dividing the particles between these two
systems has to be done at the stage of computing
the partition function, because the entropy then
is the derivative of the free energy, the log of
that partition function. And we need to make sure
that the entropy captures the log of the sun,
which is not the same as something else. So. In a
general case, if some number of new particles end
up in that we separated parts of the left, this is
still a big problem. Then we know how many
particles are in the other box. The total number
to N minus this new that is the left. So the
contribution. To the partition function from this
case is the. Total number of ways of selecting
those new particles.
This is the indistinguishable. Partition function
for new particles, which is given by. The new
power of that ratio be over to places like Cuba
that we saw before, normalizing Ivy, whatever new
factorial, indistinguishable ways of selecting new
particles. So that is. The. Number of
possibilities on the left side, left hand box
after the separation. We have to multiply that by
the. Number of microstates, we have the different
moments in the
we separated box on the right, the make to be
prone to put it all together, we have. News
canceling out in. The product of these ratios V
over Lamda could and he was just the total number
of particles. And the power that that factor is
race to and then a combination of factors that is
looking a little bit like if I know your
coefficients.
Just missing the overall factor of two in
Vectorial, this is a complicated expression, but
it is just one term in the overall sum for the
petition function of the three separate systems at
the final stage of the experiment. We have to take
these.
Partition functions, that's new for the cases of
all the particles, all the possible ways these two
particles can be distributed between the two
systems, some of those. And I have gone ahead here
and replaced this. Whatever the product, the new
factorial times two and minus factorial with the
binomial coefficient divided by one over two and
factorial. That it's just a simple mathematical
identity. So the overall entropy after we
separated these systems. Is and given by the three
terms that come from taking the log of this
product, the three factors which in particular
involves this log of a sum of many binomial
coefficients. Which is not the easiest expression
to move to work with and as. We forecast in the
tutorials of the past two weeks in which the Gibs
after the Gibs paradox, his name also derived some
ago in the 70s for large and. We have seen that.
The entropy interpreter, the total of microstates
for dividing a certain amount of energy or a
certain number of particles into two. Subsystems
that have to add up to that same fixed amount. In
this case, too many particles is very nearly
saturated by the single case in which these energy
or particles is divided roughly evenly between
those two subsystems. So this was the reflection
of our intuition that it's much more likely to
find many particles in a ordinary looking smooth
distribution compared to a special unusual one,
even though. All those different microstates have.
Probability is given by the Boltzmann distribution.
So they are equal probabilities whenever those
entities are equal, there are just many more ways
of arranging. Particles when they are divided
roughly evenly and therefore many microstates to
pick up on. So this complicated expression. For.
The final interview that we are after can be
simplified by considering just the case in which
the. Two and particles are divided approximately
equally between those two subsystems or to take
the approximation to its limits instead are only
the case in which. That division is exact, you
sort of previewed or forecast, by the way, to the.
Drew. The thought experiment on this page, even
though the six particles that we have an
inclination to draw are not the largest number
where this approximation will become strictly
valid. But in this case, the calculation is easy
and it just boils down to the single possibility
for the number of particles in each system. In
fact, we don't even have to calculate observe that
once we have declared that the same number of
indistinguishable particles end up on either side
of the room, we separate the system to a private
domain to be from then something over all
microstates that those particles have at the same
boy v. to teeth gives us exactly the same
protection function. Hegel's three energy and
entropy as the original systems before we
separated them. So at the end of this process of
allowing two canonical systems to exchange
particles and then re separating them as had no
effect on the entropy, the final entropy
trajectory is exactly the same as the initial
entropy. Which we already computed was the same as
the entropy combined system. And this is where
there's a danger of oversimplifying.
Let's say that we didn't need to do the math at
all, we could just say that. OK, opening and
closing the door between two identical rooms is
not going to have any effect on the rehearsal
process that does not increase the total entropy.
Of the universe. The concept of reversibility is
connected to that if some process increases the
entropy, but it can't be exactly reversed to get
back to the original states, that would require a
reduction in entropy, which I suppose we will see
in more detail now if we switch our focus from the
individual case to the case of distinguishable
particles where the calculation is. Now, almost
the same. Looking at. The initial increase in
those two systems, A, B, and what happens when
they are combined into this system, C with twice
the volume and twice the number of particles
instead of plugging in. Expression for the entropy
interchangeable particles we just have to use for
some. Equation for the civil case and the only
places that differ are five haves and three haves
and and the presence or absence of a factor in the
logarithm. And it is the. Second feature that
turns out to matter in this calculation of the
linear terms cancel out and this difference, as
does oil dependence on. This morning and. Deployed
wavelength. But we have here is no longer
effective end to end, cancel out the fact that the
two of the log that carries through and we find
that upon the first stage of this thought
experiment, removing the wall and allowing
particles to be exchanged between these two
subsystems in the case of distinguishable
particles, that produces an increase in the
entropy by this two and more two factor that.
Straightforward to compute based on her own work
today. So this positive increase in the energy
already level with a Delta mix, this is known as
the mixing entropy, essentially the increase in
number of possible microstates that we have to
account for when two gases of distinguishable
particles are mixed together. So this is also.
Essentially, what we would expect from the second
half of the interview is not not only remain not
decreasing, it has actively increased. But if we
go through the repeat the qualitative argument of
say that we expect an equal number of particles.
To end up in either of the two would be separate
the systems which this war has been put back in
place, that would be problematic. Because if it
were still the case that the initial to final
interviews were equal, then after increasing the
energy in the.
In the process of combining the systems, we would
need to decrease the energy to get back to that
starting point, which violates the second law, so
that that argumentation is what is called the gibs
paradox, which is maybe not entirely fair because.
Even as Gibbs was presenting this thought
experiment 150 years ago, you showed how there is,
in fact, no paradox. And. The explanation is.
Not the most complicated one is just the one where
you have to keep track carefully of how the
mathematics is proceeding, rather than relying on
intuition that, say, opening a door or involve
with two systems should be a reversal process with
no change in entropy.
And. Everybody knows mathematics, the fact that
the particles are now distinguishable means that
even though, as we've seen, we can expect. The
receptor in the system to be dominated by setups
where the particles are divided roughly evenly
between the two sides of the barrier, that is no
longer enough to establish that the final system
is identical to the initial system. Precisely due
to that distinction, we can tell we can label all
of the particles in that initial system, calling
them, say, A, B and C.
With lowercase letters and then in order to get
back to. Precisely the same microstates that we
have from these two initially separate systems up
here, you would also need to require that the same
sets of particles ended up on the same side of the
wall, which is not always the case. It is just as
likely, even with an even separation of the number
of particles to have different labels on different
sides of the wall, and all of that does have to be
accounted for in. The nasty sell over all the
possible microstates.
Even though we can still expect even numbers.
In particular, one of the possibilities that we
now have to sum over is, in fact, A, B, C, D, E, F
and so on, or ending up where they started off. So
that is. One contribution to the final entropy,
there will be many, many others that have really
large numbers that guarantees that the final
entropy will be created, that is not equal to what
we saw with. And if we do that calculation, which
is not really edifying to work through, we find
that the second law of all is obeyed. The entropy
is never decreasing and is always in general
increasing, not decreasing time. So the. There are
a few things to wrap up a few comments to. Make
about this to wrap up for today. Well, first,
maybe I should ask. The arguments, it's clear why.
You can. But into worries about a paradox, if you
were not sufficiently careful to enumerate
microstates and go through the mathematics that
really defines the entropy as opposed to.
Argumentation based on everything, intuition.
It's something to think about as well. Later on
today or over the weekend.
But this example also provides is another
illustration of another situation in which the
behavior of systems differs only due to the
intrinsic information content that they have. So
depending on whether or not we assume that the.
Particles in these two ideal gases we considered
are distinguishable, that each particle can be
labeled as labels can be tracked as the system
evolves and samples its microstates, that behaves
differently from the case in which those particles
are indistinguishable. It can't be
pulled apart in principle. There's no way of
attaching a label to them and saying that one
particular particle is distinct from any other.
And in particular, in the case of the sociability,
there is this positive mixing entropy when two
systems are allowed to work, when they are mixed,
they're brought together to exchange particles.
And that is in contrast to the case of the
individual distinguishable particles, which
behaves a bit more like you might expect from
everyday intuition. That argument of No.
Big effect coming from opening the doors to the
rooms or reversing that process by closing it
again. If we had of mixing between. Different
gases are distinguishable particles that change
could be coming from this positive mixing entropy.
Guarantees that the process itself cannot be
reversed. Doing so would imply a violation of the
second quarter and the take away message from here
is that the the second rule always wins. If you
think you find a way around it,
you should be skeptical of any claims to that
effect. So the process of mixing essential
particles, because it produces that increase in
entropy from the form of this mixing entropy, that
is an irreversible process. And the system cannot
be taken back to the starting point, even in
principle. Or perhaps we could have gotten here by
considering a different qualitative physical
argument that if we take, say, coffee cream and
mix those together, there is no way to
spontaneously separate the cream from the coffee
and get back to the initial stages by the time
evolution of the systems in the. Attempt to
separate those would require putting in a lot of
entropy to filter things into the two different
types of particles that have to mix there. That
even is a.
It's not quite a fully distinguishable article.
It's the case where we have two classes of
particles that are distinguishable between the
different classes within each class, but it is
perhaps a way of remembering the difficulty of the
physical picture of mixing entropy and mixing is
hard to do. So.
Given the time, it's not going to be worthwhile to
move on if the next section, so next week we will
start looking at pressure on the states and build
from that into thermodynamic cycles more generally
based on these ideal gases analyzed to sample
the sector. Your chance to look at the homework a
bit and talk about some of the. Nothing's really
changing. At the end of last week's tutorial, the
Instruments formula, the which obviously played a
significant role in the approximations brought to
bear on the process of mixing it to Eigil gases.
Are there any final questions before? We break for
the few hours. Before that, it was a real.
So I hope to see you all again this this afternoon.
Have.