Well, I'll go ahead and get that recording started.
Then get the usual attendance
monitoring issue out of the way. The number is
Four eight two
six eight three.
Welcome back to the second week of physics, are
there any immediate questions from the stuff we
went through in the first?
Well, the more times people think of any just a
quick recap of some of the main things with
hundreds of
civilians, the floor. And. Starting from a
foundation in probability theory, last week, we
developed two main results that start to show in
broad terms how this sort of snooty behavior that
we expect from everyday experience with systems
like the air in this room with lots of molecules
and atoms all bouncing around emerge from the
stick, has the dynamics of those underlying
degrees of freedom. The first of those results was
that of large numbers.
We focus on the arithmetic and we have that
reproduces the true meaning of life, liberty,
distribution, more generally,
the law of large numbers effectively states that.
Averaging over a large number of repeated
experiments.
Or those repeated experiments can be many
independent degrees of freedom. We've yet to
arrest. That's reproduces the true expectation
values. Seen on that large scale. And building out
that the central bureau.
Dictates that.
The collective behavior of those many degrees of
freedom is a normal distribution, so the ocean.
Behavior.
Bajrang in probability. Distribution.
For a large number of degrees of freedom.
And particularly this probability distribution
patterns. Only on. The individual.
Means and variances.
More of those on the line.
I should keep an eye on this issue on the screen.
For those underlying degrees of freedom. So we are
still collecting behavior is emerging from the.
Sarcastic or capitalistic behaviors of these
underlying degrees of freedom, and we saw in the
tutorial that. Looking at some type of code. This
is much larger than one.
Can. Really set in quite quickly this large scale
behavior described by the central limit theorem.
Even in around five gave you a good approximation,
for the example, we looked at their. Already.
So a final call for questions about those topics
before.
And another model will be blah, blah,
blah, blah. No, and this language, which Paul. Yes,
we call hard numbers for our purposes. That's what
we've seen here, basically. And again, we're in
this module not quite so much into the proof
underlying that, but we went through that quick
and easy operation, making assumptions of what we
will be interested in is the application to these
physical systems. And I guess that's if there are
any more questions as a good segue way to the next
physical system that is sort of on the agenda.
Getting back into the lecture notes here, which
is pushing towards an important topic known as
diffusion, diffuse the behavior, but looking
specifically at processes called random walks and.
I guess the idea behind a random walk is kind of
what I would tell you, have some objects and
individuals of Walker who randomly chooses the
direction or length in which to walk. Now, that
sounds at first glance, maybe that's.
Simplistic or uninteresting, the power of random
walks comes from the ability to model all sorts of
stochastic phenomena around the box, not
necessarily in the physical space, but possibly in
more abstract spaces. One example you can walk in
a space of energy is that a system of particles
can have and considering just a simple system to
start off with. Where? If this happens in here
about our processes, which then walks are an
example of, that's something that we will also get
back to somewhat later in term, we can set that
aside for now. Let's consider in this section just
sort of the simplest random walk that we can where
our water is moving only in only one block and is
moving only in steps with some fixed length. The
only element of randomness in this law is which
direction along this line the water moves. So
maybe the water and we'll say, what's the
probability that we'll take a step with a fixed
line to the right and with probability? One dance
to your cue. I'll take a step back to the left,
get back where I started.
So we can equivalently see that we assume that
each of these steps is happening one after the
other and sort of regular tick of the clock, so
the total number of steps is going to define it
for the length of time in which I'm walking either
to the left or to the right. The total length of
time t is just any number of steps, times that
caused tick of the clock for each step. So.
Just thinking of the random. A representative
random walk with six steps where. And then used to
first take a step to the left and the step to go
right back to where it started, another step to
the left and then another step to the right in
Afghanistan and a few more steps to the right.
Give me some distance, two steps to the right to
where I started the call that plus two. And if I
had done everything the other way around, would
have ended up two steps to the left of the
starting points. Call that negative to. The
starting point is zero, and just adding numbers to
the final position of the walk for each step that
is taken. So.
One of the some of the power random walks comes
from the combination of likability with the simple
mathematics in this case, there are two
possibilities the probabilities here that add up
to one. So. The. The probabilities that come out
of these random processes are. Similar in some
ways to the very first example of something that
we came up with in the first day of this term.
Belaboring the questions of this guy here. We know
that with an equal six steps, the total number of
possible locks is to that power. Six, there are
two possibilities, just like flipping a coin at
each of the six steps that is taken. And the
difference with flipping a coin is that there are
unequal probabilities potentially of going. Either
to the left or the right.
So that, first of all, I did two steps to the left
with four to the right would have occurred with
probability of the four and Q which is what, minus
to the two. And similarly, the Steffanie going in
the opposite direction at each stage would have
had T squared off by to the fourth, which
immediately generalizes one and step one with our
steps to the right. Probability is the power our.
Due to the power and bias, are the total number
just being. To the power, Ms.
So.
This is just mathematically a slight
generalization on the process of flipping a coin,
but we will see that there is a lot we can do in
the simple case, in particular in connection to
the central limit theorem. So the. Observable
expectation value will be interested in analyzing
is the final position where the walk ends after
that time t or those steps which you can recognize
as the same sort of song that we dealt with in
that let example at the end of last week, in the
context of this problem, you're just adding that
the outcomes of each of these and identical
processes. In particular, what we. What will
determine is the expected value for the end of the
war, as well as the the various the spread, the
scale of fluctuations that we can expect around
that average value at the end of the year. Water
taking those steps.
And I just wanted to mention that the expectation
value here and this very is I will not use.
Variables, variables unsuitable for those oil
reserves, those for the mean and variance of the
single step, that is the fundamental underlying
process being repeated many times to build up this
random this random process.
And sort of based on those definitions, it's easy
enough to write down the final position of the
walker in terms of. The number of steps that it
takes in total and number of the steps that go to
the right, we call a lowercase R to keep them from
being mixed up with a number of repetitions that
we had. Earlier in the course.
So. This break down despite opposition. Is going
to be. Plus, one hundred a number of steps taken
to the right. We added minus one with a number of
steps taken to the left, which is all of those
other and minus our steps out of the total
rearranging that. Just because two times more
light is an. And in particular, if we
just check the two examples that were in the
previous gap within. Equals six, equals four. We
ended up with a final position of plus two, which
is the V eight minus six and similarly for. The
example would be reverse on the left and right
steps, head to the right and forward to the left,
the final position after that block was minus two
or two steps to the left of that starting point.
So we can recast the probability as a function of
X for this final position, just with the
probability piece of ah, of taking a certain
number of steps in the right, which. That is a bit
of a simplification that does only hold the
special case and not in more general situations
where we might consider having the length of these
steps very.
So is the the set up does not necessarily pay off
clear at this point?
So let's add in the one final piece to.
Build up the probabilities of taking our steps in
the right that we will use to analyze the final
position of our land and water afterwards. OK, so
in addition to discounting the probability of
taking the particular set of sequence of steps
randomly chosen left and right, we need to count
up the number of different possible ways of taking
those steps in any given order. So.
Hopefully, it is obvious that the order in which
the steps are taken does not matter all the way up
to the white person and probably back will keep
bouncing around that starting point before going
the few steps out. And we know that counting
possible ways of choosing our steps to the right
steps total is the binomial coefficients.
And she was over.
Which we can expect to show up. In the full
probability of. In combination with the P's and
Q's of stepping to the left or to the right, so.
Going back to. This example with.
And of six and final possession packs of four.
How many steps to the right? Is that going to be
to end up at X equals four after six steps?
Five year.
Sort of like five steps to the right and take that
last one. To the left and the opposition for more
equivalent leave, since the order doesn't matter.
Could have left that single leftward step on the
second to last position, more in the third to last
position. More on the way at first position in the
step seven six. So those are the six ways of.
Choosing the. Five steps in the right with
probability to the fifth single step to the left,
the probability cube and.
So. Right here. That is six steps we've counted
out here, is that in?
There it is on the screen for you that and she was
our the coefficient here to use five, which is
just six and a generalization. For the probability
of the step with our steps to the right and minus
our steps to the left, is that binomial
coefficients? And she was for. I'm probably of our
steps to the right of the people are in queue and
minus our steps to the left.
And at this point. With the probabilities defined
for all of the events in the outcome space, the
process of competing expectation values is
basically straightforward arithmetic, which.
To run through that reasonably quickly.
As a reminder, the expectation value for any given
function.
Called. Of the degrees of freedom, either step to
the left or right or the number of steps to the
right is the sum over all of the.
Possibilities in the open space will be events of
whatever investigations of weighted by the
probability of each of those events and we assign
more. So we computed that P are just off the top
of the screen there. And looking in.
The value for. X was all the way back here next
year, two times ah, and my list ends with some
over overall. Two times more like this than. Times
the probability for taking our steps to the right.
Is exactly two times this expectation value of
power to the power of one.
Minus 10 times the sum over all of those
probabilities, which because they are
probabilities, you know, just to one. So the
expectation value of X has the same form. As the
expression came up with the boat simply related to
the expectation value. Of our times to understand
that same relationship between the final position
of the war and the number of steps taken in what
direction?
So the same.
Amputation goes through the.
Square. The object was expectation value. You're
taking that from.
So here, if I expand that square, I get four times
the expectation value of our square.
Minus four in four and then plus. And squared with
the sum of the probabilities, that adds up to one.
So that is now the expression for the expectation
to use the powers of that final position that we
do in terms of the number of steps to the to the
right.
So given that the task is now the computer. These
quantities that we have expressed, the objects of
interest in terms of an. Easy way of doing that in
general is. From a bit of what are call generating
functions, where we introduce a parameter theta
that this function we define depends upon, that
will eventually remove by setting that is equal to
zero.
After we have the latest derivatives of this
generating function to the objects that we're
interested in, so having said that, I realize it
sounds a bit abstract. So the example here is
going to make that seem a bit more straightforward
that we've chosen. The dependence of dysfunction
on theater in such a way that the derivative with
respect to theater just goes through this tangible
some. Deflater. Of the better times, the
probability for each are. Which is a fairly simple,
primitive. It's more.
That same exponential function, the probability is
constant, comes along for the ride and at the end
of the day. So inflated to zero in this expression,
because this is some of our. Of our times, the
probability. Which is just the definition of the
expectation value of.
And that after having gone through that process,
we can just see that every time we take a
derivative of this general information with
respect to the data, we bring down another factor
with no additional effect so we can pretty much
immediately write down. The result of taking in
derivatives on the real. This power to the power
and that same damage factor times the cost and
probably. And then seven zero at the end. The sun
over our. Are the probability or. The expectation
value of our solar power at. So. In the case of.
This random walk with a six step plan, because
it's really the final position of the walk that
contributed to the simple number of steps in the
right direction. The right words direction.
If we plug in. The form that we had in. The
previous cap for probability of taking our steps,
so the interviews are one, the confessions for the
number of ways to take our steps have a total
probability of stepping to the right based on our
ability to speak to the left, to reduce the amount
of our power can actually recognize from the case
the reason that this cover is what it is called,
the coefficient. It's counting the possible terms.
Of this binomial factor they used to power at.
So.
There is the buttermilk formula that you've seen
before, the recently E-Plus Beach, the power and
is equal to the sum of two and of exactly the
binomial coefficient times in our higher power and
minus high. And here a. Includes both key to the
other factor in the E to the power data, to the
power after.
And just be is just to them so you can relate from
the definition of imputed for probability of
interest. We can find a generate functional
degenerating function is just this binomial factor
race to the top of the power number of steps being
taken by the small.
So far, so good. We're getting close to the end,
so I appreciate there are lots of steps in this
calculation. Let's see if.
Some nice. Results once we get through the last
few steps and get back to the central level, so
not knowing that to find these expectation values
of powers who are in this set up, we want to take
derivatives of the generating function, which we
have. Found to be this simple. Look at this
derivative is an easy one to take. It's just the
Powerwall.
So we get that same factor, not the power and
minus one, and then the chain rule brings in the
derivative of each of the theta respect to Theta
is that same? You can see the times people are
going to set it equal to zero at the end, which
has the nice simplification of setting this factor
that appears in generating function to the sum of
probabilities of going to the rightful people,
after which options which are up to one hundred
percent. So setting theta to zero, this whole
factor drops out to one, as does that factor. And
all that remains is in times P. So it would be
expectation, value of the number of steps that we
take to the right is the total number of steps
times the probability of stepping to the right,
which hopefully makes sense.
It's a bit more
work to to take additional derivatives and.
Take the second derivative that's operating on
this whole factory here. So the first thing we can
do is take the derivative of that, either the
theta factor, which is just itself. So we
reproduce.
If I read it carefully,
you produce exactly the first derivative as the
first half, but then there is also a hiding still
within. This final factor, so we have now two
powers, the minus one to down.
Plus, Cuba is now raised to the tower in minus two,
and there's another factor of the fate of Peter.
At the end, she said it equal to zero. Well, let's
set it equal to zero right now. That's at least
one.
No
one, so that remains.
Is that same MP now
added to nine? We got to
that factor of the that comes along for a ride as
a positive factor that you did, it also goes to
ones with pee and and minus one times pee in there
and then a bit of.
Manipulation. Just bring up the factor again and
of out front, but we have left is one for that
term. And then. Plus and
minus.
And we can recall that P plus Q equals one is that
one minus two equals Q Express that as end times P.
Multiply by the quantity in dispute again. Plus. Q
And that then.
Is R-squared the. The expectation value of the
square of the number of steps taken to the right
to given these probabilities, P and Q.
So. Now that we have all of the ingredients. It's
running down the. Relations we had earlier, the
expectation value for the final position was twice
the expectation value or minus. And so again. The
expectation value for. Went to men minus.
When should we pull out that overall factor then?
Incentives to be minus one child, they're just to
check
and then. So look at the variance in the final
position of the random walker. We have both. That.
Expectation value of X squared, which
is topped back with the two previous page and
these three terms coming in, so. Four times
R-squared. Minus four times the expectations for.
Plus N squared.
To subtract from that.
The square of.
The expectation value of X. She is going to be.
Four times expectation value per square. Minus
four in. The expectations are. Plus squared, so
that's a few of these at least cancel out what we
left. Just with four times this variance
of power between. Now plug in from above.
With the expectation value of R-squared. And
squared, P squared, plus thinking, Q expanding
that. Dr.. And then the expectation value per
R-squared. In that end, where you square, that
cancels out he's only the single term.
For each other, all those cancellations. Which is
why I should not.
So. These are the. Results we were going after the
expectation value proposition of this very simple
random water model, six walks the fixed length
either to the left or to the right to vote on the
line.
In the book, the expectation, value and the
appearance of the final position are related as
they should be added to the number of steps that
are taken or the amount of time that the law is on,
as well as to the probability of walking to step
in to the left or to provide each individual one
of those repeated experiments that is going on.
And you can see in some of the special cases that
if the probability of stepping to the right is 100
percent and every step goes to the right that he
has won, the expectation value of X is exactly an
after and steps and there is no variance around,
no fluctuations at all around that outcome. The
same sequence of steps is always taken with
probably one hundred percent, and if say the same
thing happens, we always go to the left. If P is
equal to have we get back to the experiment of
flipping a coin, then the expectation value.
Vanishes and zero, but the scale of fluctuations
around it.
Would people a half inch equals a half the cars
now that factory before was expectation of that
variance in the final positions at the start of
the walk after Insteps is growing. Exactly. And so,
on average, the step the walk always ends up where
it started. But because there's this random
fluctuations and the. Sequence of steps that can
be taken there is greater and greater probability
as more and more steps are taken for the war to
end some distance further and started once.
And that's spreading out of probability. Is no
more formally diffusion.
I. Recasting these results that we got in a
slightly different way, we can connect to a very
similar result. It's known as the law of diffusion
related to that. Process of fluctuations spreading
out around the expectation value that I just
described. So.
Well, before diving into that, are there any
questions about the waters, the arithmetic
derivations we just went through? For the final
results that we reached.
Sing, Everyone's happy, let's recast them in a
slightly different way by replacing that any
number of steps with the total time. Of the walk
divided by the time interval taken from each step.
What this does. If you play in that ratio to your
identity friend, we find that the expectation
value for X is directly proportional to the time
that the walk lasts. And this concept,
proportionality is some factor that depends on the
probabilities that we can call. A velocity
and drift velocity, we've chosen this name just
because the velocity tells us how far a walker. No,
it was a half hour drifts. In after time and
specifically that the drift velocity is just. A
function of.
The parameters of the what probabilities, number
of steps and type of takes and it's inside tells
us whether the walker is drifting on average, the
expected value to the right or the left. Based
exactly on which of those elementary steps is more
likely. And similarly, looking now, the standard
deviation of that final position. The square root
of the variance that we can plug in that same
ratio T of the Delta T for factor that appears in
this expression for the square root of four
identity is two Times Square Root. And Q And now
we find a standard deviation that was proportional
not to T, but to the square root of the amount of
time that this random walk persists. And this is.
The law of diffusion, the. Standard deviation of
the final position of the walk, which we can think
of as the scale of fluctuations in the outcomes of
repeating these walks over and over again, or
equivalently, you can think of it as the
uncertainty in that final position for any
individual. What is proportional? To the square
root of the time that passes during this process.
Because of the proportionality, it's called the
diffusion constant and the standard deviation
itself, uncertainty and may well be referred to as
infusion. So it's quantifying the scale, the.
Overall distance around expectation that we can
expect a given war to end up in this diffusive
process. And so in the calculation, we did a a
computer, a particular result for the diffusion
colistin, that is specific to a very simple case
we set up with a fixed step length on a line.
And this picture here is. Illustrating. How? The
resulting probability distribution and we may not
get to a judge tomorrow morning is behaving as
time goes on in the case that. P and Hugh are
equal to a half. So this was one of the special
cases that we checked.
In equation 14, we saw the expectation value for
random walks of this sort of equal probability of
stepping up and the expectation value ending up at
zero. And we can see the symmetry around the zero
that not only is ending up at the starting points,
the single most likely probability. We again
extract probabilities from probability
distributions by integrating over an appropriate
interval. It's also the result of. Integrating
even function over these probability distributions.
The interesting thing happening in this figure is
that even though the distributions are always
peaked around that starting point zero, as time
goes on, the probability distribution spreads out
further and further. So this line here is the
shortest amount of time where there's the greatest
probability of any starting point. But as time
goes on, there's more and more probability of
finding the water farther and farther away the
tails of these distributions. Compared to right
around the starting. So is this spreading out of
the probability that we're finding the water or
finding the outcome of this random audit process?
We can model for brainwork that. Is known as
diffusion.
And the.
Knowing the particular distribution cost for the
brand long process. That would be the specific
cell phone we consider we can compute the.
Probably intervals which are often no one will say
what he said, but three said, depending on the
integrated probability of finding a walker within.
The.
That region around the expectation now and the
characteristic dependence on the size. Of those
intervals, for a particular amount of probability
for finding the location of the water steadily
grows as the random process goes on for longer
with the square root of two.
So that is basically writing in words in
mathematics, the picture in this picture and
generalizing these next figures at the same,
spreading out a diffusive behavior is also
presents a non-trivial case. So it is not equal to
zero or equal to zero or one. The same behavior
happens the. If P is not equal to half that, we
have unequal probabilities of going to the left or
the right, then that drift velocity. The drift was.
To be minus one, at least, proportionality that
you one that is not a non-zero. So in this plot on
the left here, where he is equal to four point six
and there's just a slight preference for stepping
to the right compared to the left, you can see
that the single most likely. Final position for
the water at the peak of this probability
distribution instead of the. To the right, as time
goes on, it is clear to see that same diffusive
spreading out process where the probability.
Finding the water in some region around Eppy is
steadily decrease in order to say the same thing
in the other direction, the amount of distance you
have to look around that most likely execution
value in order to have a. Particular probability
of firewalker is steadily increasing.
And the same thing is happening on the right. Even
though it's a bit harder to see we're here,
there's a hybrid philosophy of taking a much
higher probability of stepping to the right. 99
percent. So it's clear to see the peak very
quickly drifting off to the right. But at the same
time, it is spreading out around each of those
peaks and tomorrow morning when we return, we will
look into more detail about precisely how that
spreading out around the peak. Is in play with the
drift and the peak of probability distribution
itself. So a lot of mathematical manipulations
today, hopefully.
Behavior that we are now seeing from the simple
random process, pretty straightforward. Are there
any questions before we wrap up, Dr..
I see folks shaking their heads and I just
come over there and I'll see you again tomorrow
morning.