In terms of recordings, it's interesting, what I've
seen is that Zoom recordings are better quality
than the university's Stream Capture system and they're
also about four times smaller files, which shows
what you can do with lots of programmers working
for you. To start with some of the boring stuff while
we wake up
the magic number for attendance checking
is one oh
three oh eight four and let me know if that's too small
to actually see.
And as we get going, are there any media questions
left in your mind from earlier in the week?
So quickly recap what came up at that time, so.
Maybe before recapping a couple of logistical
notes that the first part of the computer project
assignments, it is now up on canvas.
Available for you to work on. And this afternoon,
we'll look through some of
the Python programming background that will be
useful for that, those who may or may not have
done any programming before. And there was also on
that poll I had run during this week, just a
couple of requests for a to print paper copies of
the notes. For those of you who prefer paper, the
end might not have easy access to a printer. So
rather than trying to juggle that. Here live in
your. I just left them in the box. Outside my
office, which is one twenty three, the theoretical
physics wing, so those of you who requested those
printouts can just come by and pick them up
whenever it's convenient for you. They're just
sitting in the hall for you and getting into. The.
Actual physics and mathematics we looked at
earlier this week to be two main points, to recap
very quickly that the essence of statistical
physics is bringing probabilistic processes,
holistic methods.
To tackle the practical problem. Of handling
systems with many degrees of freedom, many the
objects in these systems.
Where many is something of order tend to be. Tower
twenty three or more. And then we went through a
sequence of formal definitions for these
probabilistic foundations.
We are going to be developing and applying, in
particular defining. Outcomes. Of experiments to
be. Roughly equivalent to the states, I should say,
the outcomes of measurements can be treated
equitably with the states that results from doing
experiments in precise ways that we define and
then subsets or sets of outcomes.
Give events to which we can assign probabilities.
And based on that, we got to the. Concept of the
law of large numbers
can have to be careful to keep the paper actually
on the screen up there where we have the idea of
defining an experiment and repeating it some
number of times from which we can monitor the
outcome is used to define things like the
arithmetic mean is the average value of the
outcome of interest as the experiment is repeated
other times, which has some connection to the true
meaning that is defined for probability
distribution itself. So another call for questions
about any of those topics before moving forward
with this idea to establish this connection
between arithmetic means and the true means of the
distribution.
Where? The key thing to consider is what's.
Pulled up in this box, which may turn out to be a
little small for me to do the deliberations. So
what we're looking at here is essentially how this
arithmetic mean fluctuates around the true meaning
you within the expectation value that is
considering this object as a random variable for
all of the outcomes in the outcome set in space.
Of the experiments and the measurement that we
have in mind to define the outcomes themselves.
And.
What we can do to. Tackle, this is a little trick
to bear, which is.
Slide margin over here just to.
Simplify things. We note that if we rate. The
summer over, these are repetitions of the
experiments of view that use a constant within the
expectation values. This is just our times new.
So if we bring out the overall one of our squared.
The cost factor being squared. Within that
expectation, value can be pulled outside. And then
you're left with that sum over all those hours. Of
that. Exaro minus mu, or if we pull out that one
over, we get our view that we can turn into
another factor of that. So we have parentheses
within parentheses. So we are now sending over the
fluctuations for each repetition around the mean.
And that some as a whole gets squared. And then we
take the expectation value of that whole kind of
complicated object that we can now expand and
simplify it. And by extension, I mean. That. I
would just right the square of the sun as the
product of two repetitions. Of the song with.
Difference, independents. Variables, counting the
outcomes of your going over. So that is just what
it means to square Aselton two factors of that
sound multiplied together and see why we have
introduced a few lines up the page, this little
relation, which
is.
A.
Something that we will take is given just saying
that if we multiply together two sets of
independent fluctuations around the mean value, we
can expect that when the indices on those
fluctuations are the same or we just have a single
set of fluctuations that squared those
fluctuations squared, give us the variance of the
distribution from the expectation value. But if
those two sets of fluctuations are different, then
upon something over all of the outcomes of the
definition of expectation value, we're going to
get lots of noise fluctuating around. These means
that on average, the expectation value is going to
cancel out an advantage so we could get zero. In
that case, when this I and J are different and
that can be wrapped up in this product, Delta and
Delta IJA, which is just one one equals zero. And
on different. It's something that I expect you've
seen before in other models
and I have. Written things here in.
Such a way that this can be immediately applied.
One more step in between, which is just noting
that the product of two songs is equal to the
combined sum of all of the Independent.
Combinations of the two seats up or something easy
to see in case of multiplying two by four together
and then generalize to arbitrary sums by adduction.
And that lets us right. This product has sold over
an hour, and that's. Of.
The corresponding factors.
So we then have the product of the two
fluctuations within the expectation value, which.
Gives us.
The expression written in terms of the variance
sigma squared and.
And. The.
Honaker, Delta, Delta R. S insists that Delta R. S
is zero whenever R is different from S and one
equals s.
We can rewrite that some of our this as just the
sum over. The set where our equals dolto are,
which is one if you some have won our times, is a
factor of our enumerator canceling out one of the
two factors of our and the denominator and that
stayed on the screen reasonably well. So what does
this mean? That the fluctuations of the arithmetic
mean around the Trumaine are the variance, which
is a constant property of the probability
distribution divided by the number of repetitions.
So as long as that variance is finite. In the
limit of an infinite number of repetitions, this.
Complicated expectation value is going to zero as
our. Goes to infinity.
And from this. Because we chose with some
forethought to square the fluctuations in the
expectation value that we consider, we know that
the definition of the expectation value is the sum
of all the terms being considered weighted by
their probabilities in the distribution. With the
square, all of those terms are now negative, so
there are no cancellations. So if that sum of non
negative terms equals zero, that can only happen
if each individual term in the sum is itself zero,
which is the statement of the law that as we take
the limit of all of them to infinity, everything
in those parentheses which fell off the screen.
That's the argument of those parentheses at zero,
which I can rearrange just to say that the
arithmetic mean is equal to the true meaning with
a sufficient number of repetitions. Again,
assuming that the variance is finite of the meat
itself exists to be defined.
And now. So part of the programming exercise is to
verify this numerically and also see the approach
of the arithmetic mean to the truth. And that is
hopefully. A clear arguments going through the.
Mathematical calculation about whether questions
about the individual steps or the meaning of what
we have produced here in this comment box.
And not seeing any said the law of large numbers
aside arithmetically, is approaching true based
upon repetition of experiments and just do a quick
generalisation of the probability spaces that
we've been considering. You said before. That's
what we're talking about. Generally, we talk about
discrete sets of outcomes for simplicity. We roll
the dice, see what number comes out on top. There
are six possibilities. The entire framework
generalizes to the case of uncharitably infinite
conspiracies, things like picking any number on
the line of real numbers. The one where. The
number of possible outcomes is continuous, and if
there are uncountable infinite number of possible
outcomes, and in order to relate those outcomes
and the corresponding sets of the matter events to
probabilities, we have to be a bit more clever
than just taking the individual outcomes,
enumerating them and assigning the probabilities
without accountability. We have to consider
instead the distribution of probabilities as a
function of the continuous variables that we have.
In this case, just considering a single real
variable for simplicity generalizes to any finite
number of variables. You get this multidimensional
integrals square. The way that we connect these
probability distributions to actual probabilities
is by associating the probability with some
non-zero interval around the region of interest.
In. In that variable cheer, X is a real number,
and that probability is computed as the integral
of the distribution over that interval. And so
there's this just completely analogous
generalisation of the expectation value back in
the case of. Finite items that we remember that
the expectation value was given by the sum of all
X in that space of F of X, that means if F times
the probability of X here is that that probability
we have. The integral over the probability
distribution where whenever I ovid's to the upper
and lower limits from the political on, just
assume it's over the full range of possible values
for. For that independent variable X in this case
here, the entire domain and as an example, the one
of the requirements on probabilities is that when
going over all X started to go off the screen of
it, they're going over all X, and that outcome
sets the probability itself has to add up to one
hundred percent, which now becomes an integral
equation. The integral of the probability
distribution over the full domain is one. So if we
specify specialized to particular functions, F of
X being powers of X, then it's straightforward to
get back the mean of the distribution, the
expectation value of X, just the integral of X
times X. And then the variance, as we do here, is
still the difference between the expectation value
of X squared minus the square of the mean
expectation value of X new square.
Within X Square is that same integral over the
probabilities weighted by X squared.
And that's the briefing aside on that
generalization, which becomes relevant when. And
start looking at the central limit theorem. So
assuming that everything about this is clear, feel
free to shout out if it is not,
you can apply it to that central limit theorem,
which is is so called because it is central to
probability, not because there are two things.
Anything to do with centers of distribution,
anything like that is to say limit theorem that is
of central importance and it shows up in many
different forms for many different situations.
What we'll do is just define a particular formula
central with your statement that is going to be of
interest to us, which.
Starts by considering this random variable X for
the sum of all of the.
In some number of independent random variables, so
this is. Inspired by what we were talking about,
the last large numbers, repeating some experiments,
some number of times, each of those repetitions
can define a outcome X, which is an independent
random variable with the same meaning and variance
that, again, we assume are finite. So a number of
identical random variables that we sum in order to
define this as a result. So the S itself is also a
random variable associated to the end repetitions
of the underlying process. The experiment just the
way. We talked about earlier and then we just
state that the. The probability distribution for
this test we can treat as a continuous parameter
and the limits of a large number of repetitions is
given by a Gaussian distribution,
which is to say it is exponentially weighted
around and times the meaning of each individual
random variable X. So I mean you. Normalized by
end times, various. Of that individual random
variable. With this overall factor out, front is
required to ensure the usual condition that's
integrating over over the sole domain of real
numbers for X adds up to one hundred percent.
So.
Again, there's no mathematical statements of one
equation. Are we still sitting here? Two, the
probability distribution. And then there's also
the question of what does that mathematical
equation mean and why does it matter? And.
Essentially, there are.
Two important implications coming out of this,
this mathematical statement, the first of which
being that when we consider this large number of
repetitions, which shortly we will identify with
that large number of particles that we have said
thermodynamic systems, the overall collective
behavior of all these particles is the smooth
function. That's just the normal distribution that
can be defined without reference to any individual
properties of those individual particles, apart
from the mean and variance expectation values
governing the probability distribution as a whole.
And maybe even more remarkable is that. That
collective behavior, in addition to being
independent of the details of what each individual
particle is doing at this point in time still only
depends on the details of those individual
particles in the form of the mean and standard
deviation for the individual random variable.
Without. And worried about. How they might be
interacting or interfering with each other.
And back earlier in the week, the. Talked about
Roulet as a somewhat less trivial example of a
probabilistic system compared to flipping a coin
to roll the dice. And we can use that same
Goulette example. To see in practice that. The
large and the large number of repetitions in which
the central limit theorem is fairly well defined
doesn't necessarily need to be so large in
practice. We you're talking about 10, 20, 30
molecules in the statistical systems, but the
central limit theorem itself can become
remarkably accurate even when that number is much
smaller. Order a few, order 10, some, just as a
quick reminder of that left, we all we have thirty
seven pockets, 18 red, 18 black or green, each of
which has the corresponding number that determines
what color is. And a game that we can play with
real is to place a bet on whether or not the the
ball that we will end up in a red color pocket or
black for pocket after we spin the wheel of the
ball around, actually settles into one of those
pockets. And if we guess the correct color, we
could get back twice the money that we put in.
Otherwise, the money goes to the house. And just
to please concrete numbers on this, we can say
that we five pounds each spin the real. And then
we would get back 10 whatever, take out a total of
10, whatever deal ends up on the we bet on,
otherwise the money is gone. And from that, we can
define the gain. As a function of the number of
spins of the roulette wheel, that number of times
that we do this bets and as a function of the
number of those times where we win. So the first
thing to write down, just a reminder, what is the
probability of winning or losing any single spin
and maybe just to.
Checking that from the same page, can I ask you to.
Tell me what. Those probabilities.
But.
Glossed over the detail here, in addition to the
amount that we built, we are bidding on black. So
winning corresponds to a ball ending up in a black
pocket after the real.
But which there is a well-defined probability.
What is it?
It is exactly that
and we know that the probability of losing is
every other outcomes, so not only about ending up
the great pockets, but also in that single green
pocket. So there are slightly. More likely to lose
than to win, which was the case in any.
Gambling set up, the house always wins in the end.
And for each of these possibilities, we can gain.
Some announced that its possibly negative if we
lose, the game is being defined to be the net flow
of cash.
And as we place these bets, so what is the game if
we win?
Lieutenant.
But he was 15, so it's the amount we receive minus
the amount we spend. So if we spend five, that's
that minus sign. And if we receive twice of five,
when we will, we get a 10 and I can see where 15
comes out of there by having those two numbers
here with the definition, is that minus sign that
takes it from ten minus five to plus five. But
there's a similar game. That can be defined. The
slightly, slightly more probable situation that we
lose.
What that game would be. You bet on black and the
ball ends up in retrograde.
Well, that's exactly.
We always get that fire back goes out of our
pockets, so it's a negative number and then we
gain nothing
from that. Walk right down the corridor, gain
after. Waiting times in hospitals so that in times.
To regain the function. Of.
W.
So. This is the.
Winnings from the wins, minus the number of bets
that have to go in for each of those and spins. So
is be one shot at what? That would be as a
equation, mathematical function.
To on Tuesday night. Oh, yeah, that is. Exactly
what it is, so we've put in that fire for this
global scale. That's the two times five is ten.
That's the factor of two. Exactly. So the winnings
are. Ten pounds for win, which is twice the. Five
pounds, and that goes in for each pet.
So that is. What we would get out if we were to.
When The York Times out of ten spins of this
roulette game and the next ingredient to bid is to
figure out the probabilities of winning those 30
times, for instance. So we have to keep track of
the number of different ways we could win the war
times and total spins. And because we don't care
about the order of those occurrences in which we
want, the total number of possibilities is.
Exactly, defined by the binomial coefficient. The
fraction the number of possible ways of choosing
W. events out of the total set of events, so.
We give them a wipe down. Yeah, if we set and it
was five, something small enough that we can. Go
through these calculations, my head without too
much. We have six probabilities overall for
winning either one of those spins, all five of
those spins and all four possibilities in between.
And you can.
Consider maybe a simple case is the overall
probability of losing all five states, so winning
zero, that subscript here is the number of wins.
And then if you tell me the probability of winning
zero spins out of.
The total fire that we're doing, so losing every
single one in a row.
But
it is exactly that. So.
The probability of losing a single spin you
computed up there, you just have to repeat that
five times in a row each time with that same
probability. And if you go to. Winning a single
one of those since then, what we do is we bring in.
The probability of winning. One time. And. Losing
the other four, but then because there are five
spins and we could win. Any one of them. There is
a factor of five that comes along to keep track of
each of those possibilities, we the first or the
third, the fifth and the others. And we can
recognize that five and generalize the whole
situation at this point to
the. For instance, with W. winds, there are inches
w possible combinations where. Probability of
winning is that 18 over thirty seven. W power.
And. The probability of losing its 19 over 37 in
all of the other spins and miles from that
equation. It's easy that you keep writing down the
general pattern. Probability of winning two is
five, Tchoupitoulas, 10.
18 or 37 square and then another 37 to the power
three. You can win.
Three, four or five. There are 10 ways of winning
three, five ways of winning for a single way of
winning five. The military is coming in.
Winning. Two, three, four, five.
Spins and losing.
All of the others in this case is 19 over thirty
seven to the power is zero this morning. So that's
the exact probabilities and the wind along with
the corresponding gains. Of winning these all the
possible outcomes of five spins of what we bet on
black with five contests that we win, that's the
entire setup. And now we can bring that central
limit theorem to bear and write down the
probability distribution for gaining some kind of
some game after those and spins. So just to repeat.
The definition of the word would be the same, the
probability of the central limit theorem, it gives
this probability distribution of one over a square
to PI and various times the exponential of
fluctuations of the game around in times that mean
square normalized by. What is and times the
variance and the exponential. So all we need to
figure out is the mean and variance for that
single round of this experiment we're repeating of
betting five pounds of black and skipping the
roulette wheel.
Mr.. Illustration.
You can write down that mean again, but
considering all of the possible outcomes of that
single spin of the roulette wheel and the
corresponding probabilities.
Remember that this was X squared her back a
discrete outcomes. So we are studying the outcomes
and probabilities, which are exactly what we have
computed previously. So we have what we need the
gain if we win these five,
the probability of winning a single spin is 18
over twenty seven to gain. If we lose, it's minus
five probability of doing so, 19 over thirty seven.
And that is better even I can do in my head. It is
a mean of minus five of the thirty seven, but I
can't do my hands put that into digits just to
keep and keep track of what the rough scale is
about. Zero point one three five. So as expected
the.
The main outcome of this game is for us to lose
money and then. We can do a similar calculation
for. The expectation value with X squared, that
feeds into the various.
Is anyone willing and able to shout out what this
might look like? Even if we repeat the individual
steps for the.
In the interest of propping up the few remaining
minutes, you say that it's the same process of
selling over all of the two outcomes in all of
that space and here instead of.
Reading those the corresponding probabilities by.
X. We just by X squared. So five squared is twenty
five and minus five squared is also twenty five in
particular, plus twenty five is the negative side
scan sonar, which we can see eighteen plus
nineteen is thirty seven and twenty five. Is that
so. So. If I have space left to write down the
variance, it is the expectation value of the
square. Twenty five minus the square of the
expectation value, which is. Five over thirty
seven squared, which is quite close to twenty five
barbarically, four points.
Ninety two, so if we put this into. Probability
distribution from the central theorem that comes
out to be this one over square root of two times
twenty four, forty eight to the one that is forty
nine ninety six point and.
In the. Exponential of gain minus has me so plus
zero point one three five. And squared. With
another factor of forty nine, ninety six and and.
Basically run out of time for today, and this is
something that may actually be useful to wrap up
in the Detroit of this afternoon, look at
programming is given this kind of.
Probability distribution with some fuzzy numbers
in there. We have to extract actual probabilities
from that. We do that by integrating over
appropriate regions. So
some small Beltagy around the game you're
interested in and.
And this numerical integration is exactly the kind
of thing that computers were built to do, so we
will revisit this along with other aspects of
computer programming in a few hours. And we could
be just wrap up now by seeing if there are any
quick questions about what we've gone through
today. The law of large numbers to probability
distributions of a central theorem.
Saying, I'll let you go and see them all again
later this afternoon.