All right, that should be the recording started, so let's get underway.  Welcome to Friday morning,
for which we have the six-digit code
two five seven six two seven.
And to give you a chance to
catch up with what we're doing on the grand-canonical ensemble.
So, it is the eleventh
of March.
Some of you may have seen that feedback and
solutions for the first part of the computer
project, I was finally able to get those back
to you earlier this week.
I think this afternoon, the tutorial will talk a bit
about some aspects of those solutions. It's a
tricks for. We're someone. Relevant aspects of
them for part two, which is also available for you
to work on due in a couple of weeks, 24th. Of
March, I think.
It was a. Range of performance is part one of the
computer project, the average was about seventy
three, but there was a big standard deviation on
that 73 percent. So divide that by two to get the
marks out of 50, then standard deviation of about
twenty three percent. So that's sort of what I was
aiming for, making the assignment. Relatively
challenging, at least for someone who does not
feel discouraged if the headline Mark looked a bit
low, go through some of the tricks for that part
of things. And a quick look at the second part of
the tutorial this afternoon. Before then, we will.
Continue developing the script multiple. Not
sellable. Are there any immediate questions before
we dive into that other down to the. Stuff we did
earlier this week with wrapping up the
thermodynamic cycles, introducing the economical
sample or any aspect of the computer project.
I'm not hearing any.
Quick reminder that after.
Wrapping up the presentation of some of the cycles
on Monday, again, something a bit more in the news
for you this afternoon, we move on to the third of
the three statistical samples that we're focusing
on in this module. So we started off back in
February with the microeconomic ensemble
probability space that describes the states the
system can adopt as it falls in time subject to
the constraints of conservation, energy and
conservation of particle. No, we could have gone
from there to allow these systems to exchange
energy with their surroundings, form of a thermal
reservoir that, instead of fixing the energy of
the system, fixes its temperature while still
keeping the particle number the same. They know
we're sort of filling in the other side of that.
Developments looking at the grand economic
ensemble, which allows the system to exchange both
particles and energy with its surroundings, the
surroundings are now treated as a particle
reservoir and they fix, in addition to the
temperature, this chemical potential view that we
defined on Tuesday. So the great ensemble is
defined by. Six chemical potential and temperature.
Where that chemical potential.
We define to be in negativity at times, the
response of the entropy to a change in the
particle, no, with fixed energy.
And we saw that this is. Less than zero, it's a
negative number in natural systems, which was our
choice to interpret the chemical potential, it's
leading to a flow of particles or regions of high
chemical potential, chemical potential analogous
to the flow of heat from regions of high
temperature to low temperature, and then to put
the economic ensemble on a formal mathematical
footing. We essentially repeated the. Trick that
we introduced when developing the economical
ensemble. Proposing that it's political reservoir
consists of many replicas of the system of
interest itself, and our goal then is to.
Breakdown.
Probabilities, for example, involve the
equilibrium on the basis of this nonsense or its
political reservoir and then show that all the
details of this nonsense are irrelevant and even
unknowable in the great canonical approach. So. We
have to come back to the lecture notes at that
point to. Just catch up with the final stages of
interrogation. We are imposing a dynamic
equilibrium by modifying, by maximizing the
entropy subject to the grass multipliers that
incorporate the constraints of the ensemble, the
conservation of energy between the system,
systematise reservoir and similarly with the
particle. No. And we got down to expressing the
three parameters that appear in this.
Maximization process, the sense of the expressed
is a function of the other two parameters, both of
which we related to the total energy part of the
number of the system, plus its reservoir, which
gave us a fairly simple expression for the overall
entropy that depends on the details of our onsets,
the number of replicas of the total amount of
energy and the number of particles and from the
entropy, our definition of temperature. A The
schedule allows us to relate the remaining
parameters data again to the temperature and
chemical potential that we're interested through
half of that on Tuesday, finding that this
parameter beta is the inverse of the temperature.
I deliberately stopped in the stream so that we
could review all of the set up and remind
ourselves why we are computing and how we are
computing all of these qualities. So if that recap
did not inspire any further questions or need for
clarifications.
Move on to the final pieces today.
And the. Wrap up this last derivative of the
entropy to find the chemical potential of our
system in terms of beta and give those. Across
multiple parameters coming in through the
maximization of the entropy, given our. Replica
trade consoles, and this is a similar calculations.
But what about just swapping all the respect to
energy for derivatives with respect to the number
of particles? We can. Right down.
TR.
Recalling that the lollygag of Z G depends on both
speed and gave us of expanding.
The derivative with respect to enter into
derivatives with respect to beta and gamma.
Of that log.
And then still with the latest fekter. Times, so
the energy is independent of the party. No. We
just have that energy times in the end. As always,
I'm keeping I'm getting some subscripts here just
to reduce the amount that I need to write the
derivative at the end with respect to them is just
Gaila. And then we have in the game at the end.
As before, this is
these derivatives of the mortgages that we
computed on Tuesday on the previous page, they're
the same as noted above. Minus E for the
derivative, with respect to the positive and the
derivative with respect to Gamma and the of this
sector of honesty. At the end of the end. Times
minus the. Let's give a. The end times in.
Plus, the way to defend.
And then I pulled out negative signs incorrectly
here.
It's minus seven minus and. Given the and so it
simplifies
those two terms, cancelling those two terms
against any negative, the possibility is, given
the times, the temperature, if we can now relate
to gather and data directly from the results from
Tuesday. So once the dust has settled and all of
these cancellations have been applied, we find the
same relation between this parameter data and the
inverse temperature that we had for the canonical
example. And then this new ingredient, we actually
got together coming along with the constraints on
particle exchange between the system and its
particle reservoir is related to the ratio of the
chemical potential to the temperature. And just as
in the case of the canonical ensemble, this is
what we were after. We have expressions for the
MicroTech probabilities. In terms of sense of that
gave a lot of which refer in any way to any
details of that particular Izibor, so we know that
this particular reservoir is presence to make the
temperature and the chemical potential
well-defined and fixed for ensemble, but beyond
its presence in its will fixing those quantities,
I know information about that reservoir is
relevant or even doable in the great economic
approach. And if we look at just our system of
interest. Every aspect of it can be expressed in
terms of the fixed temperature, tea and chemical
potential, you as promised by that. Picture we
looked at earlier. And having host family dynamic
equilibrium, we have this expression for the
probability for. The system to adopt any given
microstates will make us supplied with a given
internal energy supply and protocol number and
survive, both of which are now allowed to
fluctuate as the system exchanges. Particles and
energy with its surroundings. We can see that.
Thanks to one of the features of the chemical
potential mentioned Tuesday, the fact that it has
dimensions of energy, which is the same as
dimensions of temperature units, the arguments of
the exponential factor here is dimensionless says
it has to be.
And this is. Essentially a generalization of that
troublesome factor that drives for economical
ensemble to include. Now the. Role of the chemical
essential you.
Adjusting the probabilities for different
microstates with different numbers of particles
and again continuing that close analogy with the
canonical ensemble. All of these probabilities are
verbalized by this one overzealous subsidy factor,
which we can identify as the accountable form of
the protection function, which, as we first saw
for the economic, is the fundamental quantity from
the. Ensemble that characterizes the system at the
basic level from which all aspects of the system
that we're interested in can be derived, and we
found in the course of our calculation on Tuesday
that the specific form of the screen canonical
production function is the sum over all of the
microstates of the system of the same exponential
factor, both in terms of the inverse temperature
and the temperature itself. So it is minus.
Quantity of energy, minus types of particles, all
of that normalized by the temperature. So that is
the end of the long form of construction of the
canonical ensemble characterized by these
microsleep, probabilities and projection function.
So we can now go on to do some interesting things,
seeing how we derive quantities based on this
foundation. Are there any questions about what
we've done so far in order to obtain? This basic
definition.
Like I said, much the same way that the
construction of the grand ensemble was done so far.
Mirrors our work on the economical example, we can
continue in that vein, looking at the same sort of
manipulations of the petition function that proves
useful for the canonical ensemble.
Which in particular?
Revolve around the logarithm of this screenshot of
a petition function, the same object that we saw
popping up in terms of replicas as we were going
through this derivation of.
The relation between the temperature of the
potential and the multipliers we saw that the.
Derivatives, with respect to those parameters in
Indiana of the law other than that of this grand
non-competition function, played a central role.
And.
Now that we have seen that the can be defined
completely independently of any that's for that
large. Particle reservoir. The reinterprets. Those
sorts of relations to look at some of the basic
sets of commodities like the energy and the
expectation value of the internal energy and now
adding to that, the expectation value of the
number of particles. So even though both the
internal energy and the number of particles in our
system are allowed to fluctuate in the Green
Kalikow approach. The expectation value is for
both of those qualities. Are building materials
that.
Followed so they depend only on the temperature
and chemical potential now with deliberation about
the reservoir and the basic definition of any
expectation value. As we've seen many times now is
this sum over all of the microstates of the
quantity of interest, such as the internal energy
weighted by the probability that we found for the
course of the microstates now expressed in terms
of the partition function in this exponential
factor. Similarly for. The average number. And
we've seen already that. This sort of some over
microstates of energy, a particle, no, we by the
probabilities is. Related to derivatives of the
logarithm of that great medical protection
function. Just the way that the entropy, an
internal energy and the canonical example were
related to the speed energy, the.
Voyeurism of acknowledgeable protection function,
so the analagous quality in the grand canonical
approach is known as the grand canonical potential
defined in essentially the same way as the help of
three energy, the factor of negative temperature
times, the logarithm of the screen canonical
protection function. Which allows us to. Rewrites
both the partition function itself and the
probabilities in a somewhat more compact form. So
in writing this relation equations. Seventy five.
Justin tells us that the petition function is the
exponential of the negative of this great economic
potential, the temperature inflated that into the
equation, 70 for the microsleep probabilities
gives us an overall exponential factor. Looking at
the difference between. This potential internal
energy and chemical potential Times article no,
again, although the normalized by the temperature.
Just to highlight the similarity between this
incredible potential and the Helmholtz free energy
case, I'll mention that
some of the resources for this Vijayawada may
sometimes see this quantity called the Landfried
Energy is the highlights of similarity with the
Helmholtz. And continuing on to develop this
similarity, we can expect that derivatives of this
potential are going to be related to those
quantities of interest that we will want to
compute for any given system in the economic
approach. The simplest one of these to consider is
looking at the derivative with respect to the
chemical potential. So. Reading this in terms of
beta.
The. Phenomenal potential is the water level of
the patrician function divided by negative data.
So that is.
What this derivative refers to and then.
Going through the chain rule for the derivative of
the law, it will become a factor one over. ZG. And
we call them that. The protection function,
something overall, microstates we can move inside
the cell and just apply it to the exponential
factor negatively, the Times, Microsoft Energy
minus new Times Microsleep particle number. So
that derivative of the exponential is just
bringing down a factor of positive Balewa times.
And so by the Betas will cancel out. We will be
left with the sum of the particle number for each
microstates weighted by the same. Exponential
factor.
Which we can recognize. As. The negative.
Go ahead. The call that the microsleep probability
is over 70 times the exponential factor that we
have.
She just barely fits in there, so this is the
negative sum over microstates of times like this
in our ability or in other words, the expectation
value of the party with No.
For the system in the medical approach.
So that is accounting for one of the.
Quantities of interest that we will want to
consider for any given system be analyzed through
the economic cycle starting. Next week.
Most likely. The other qualities are the average
internal energy and the entropy. Which we can
expect to be related to derivatives with respect
to the temperature rather than with respect to the
chemical potential. So. Going through the.
The delegates calculation that we looked at that
three for the canonical ensemble. We can
anticipate that just collecting the temperature
derivative of the logarithm of the opposition
function itself is worth doing in advance.
And this is, again, something of a. Welcome back
to right in terms of the temperature below
plugging in. The relation between. Temperature
derivatives, an inverse temperature evidence that
we drive toward a black.
We can expand the war with the partition function
the same way as above and move that derivative
with respect to make it all inside. Some of her
microstates.
That involves so that is, again, just the
derivative with respect to. Data of our usual
exponential factor, which is now going to bring
down. The negative quantity immodestly in.
So that cancel out the negatives have a of squared.
And then something over on microstates, Eastby,
minus you and Savi.
Exponential. Factor remaining, which is. The
expectation value of the internal energy system
overall, microstates of Eastby Times piece of.
Minus the constant chemical essential plants, that
same expectation value of the. Particle number.
All of that divided by. T squared reprovingly
multiplied by it being a squared. So then putting
this result into the full derivative of the great
potential.
We have just a trivial derivative of the
temperature with respect to temperature is a
negative log of the protection function.
Then minus two times the derivative of the log of
that subsidy. With respect to temperature, which
is exactly what we computed in the first half of
this gap, this difference between expectation
value is divided by two squared. So can you really
write down the answer for. This derivative of the
great economic potential negatives, more of the
petition function. Minus one factor in temperature
at times. The. Expectation value of the internal
energy of the system.
And then plus that, better times, chemical
potential, new friends, the expectation value of
the particle, no. Or if we recall that. The
economic potential by this negative negativity.
Times the wall of censorship, and we can rewrite
this expression as.
Fire itself with not a potential.
Which will be divided by team to get the law of
Senshi and a similar division, Bayati is present
in all the other terms. In other words, this
combination of. Real economic potential, energy
expectation value, political expectations that is
related to 10 times the partial derivative with
respect to temperature of the ground about the
full potential itself, which is written a bit more
cleanly in the text on the next page. If you
multiply through.
We'll get to that location in just a bit. What we
have now is the final basic quantity to drive in
the economical approaches, the entropy itself.
And just as we did. In the economical case, we
have a general expression for the interview as
this product of microsleep of times, there was
some deverall microstates, the negative sign and
we just need to insert.
Because I probability probabilities for the
grandmotherhood Wythenshawe that we computed at
the beginning of today and trick here again is to.
Just do that substitution for one of these two
factors of the probability. So you keep the
negative sum over all microstates. Of those
microsleep, probabilities times the logarithm. Of
the probability itself, and I'll just right here
for reference. But over the weekend on the
competition, a function of the to speed up Eli
minus. And so we have. Applying the logarithm to
that factor, a negative log. That's G. And along
with the exponential of negative, better times,
the internal energy for. Because they make it so I
mean, plus the times, new times, the corresponding
particle, no.
And recalling that. So over all probability, this
has to add up to one. With this mortgage factor
being a constant that some just gives us a new one
coming along for the ride. So we have more of the
petition function, the song over is weighted by
the probabilities is again, the internal energy
expectation value with the overall factor of.
Positive on the. Negative signs cancel out and
then similarly, the storm over the particle number
for democracy weighted by democracy with an
overall negative sign of the times, new times. The
expectation, Don, for part of the longest. Which
is exactly the negative of the derivative we have
just computed of the great potential which is
attached to the temperature of.
Devi. Team.
Over the past few pages, we have derived. A whole
set of interconnected relations between that great
potential that. Packages are the partition
function or basic starting point and the general
set of. Derives qualities that we tend to be
interested in computing for. And if you insist on
the mechanical approach, the entropy, the internal
energy, expectation value, the expectation value
of the particle and the relation between that
great potential and all three of those qualities
that we get by multiplying.
The situation up here through by. The temperature
right here on the left hand side here is the
negative entropy is beginning to realize that this
is the great economic potential itself.
Up to plus factors of the expectation value, the
internal energy and minus the chemical potential
times the expectation value of the number of
particles. So these are the results that we have
some time driving. Are there any questions about
other aspects of those derivations or the meanings
of the results of relations that we now have for
the grand canonical ensemble?
Hands are shaking, so we will wrap up this. Kind
of for the governments of the ensemble with just
one last application of particular, this last
relation between all three of these large
quantities and the economic potential, and then.
Possibly start getting into. On the first
application of the draft document sample that we
will be doing now that we have all the pieces in
place over the fall as it developed, we can.
Observers from the final equation, seventy-nine
collected in this box here that. We now have.
Extended into the earlier connection that we had
in the canonical example relating the free energy,
the internal energy and entropy. Which back in
previous units. Give us a. Full expression for
that first law of thermodynamics, which describes
how. Any changes in the internal energy of our
system have to be compensated by corresponding
changes in the political order. It is in contact
with. So just as a celebration of simplification
for the remainder of today, we will drop the
expectation values on the internal energy particle.
No, just reading them as the in, though, keeping
in mind that these are the large scale properties
of the macroscopic system. So the thermodynamic
observables rather than. The. Fluctuating internal
energy, the number is and supply corresponding to
individual microstates. So the first law of
thermodynamics that we. Drive last week related
the change in this internal energy to two factors
that we define as heat and work. The heat
exchanger, thermal energy from the system and its
surroundings was expressed as the temperature
explains the change in the entropy of the system.
Breastwork. We identified as the change in energy
due to the application of force was the pressure
of the system multiplied by the negative change in
volume caused by that force. So decrease in the
volume at fixed pressure increases the internal
inertia of the system.
We now have the ability to exchange particles
between the system and its surroundings.
A new variable that the entropy can depend on, the
particle number is no longer fixed and if we
consider in general expanding and the change in
the entropy. In terms of these three parameters,
the internal energy volume of the system, such as
the gas or the particle, no. We pick up this
verbal expression for how changes in each of those
three qualities relate to the overall change in
entropy through the response to the entropy, to
the corresponding quantity with the other two held
fixed. So the derivative of entropy with respect
to energy, fixing the volume of particle number.
Similarly. With the change in volume and the
change in political level. And we saw. Several
times now previously, with this response of
entropy to the internal energy is nothing more
than the inverse temperature. And at the start of
this unit, we define the corresponding response to
the entropy to change a particle, to be the
negative chemical potential divided by temperature.
And this last person with that is left here and
derivative of entropy with respect to volume we
can relate to.
Usual thermodynamic properties by. Stepping back
to the case, the first law of thermodynamics with
a fixed particle, no.
That is given as one of the conditions on this
partially.
And the other condition that the internal energy
is fixed is that is change. It's zero, and that
relates. The heat and the work in this case, the
fixed part of a no fixed internal energy and
rearranging this. Infinitesimal expression. You
find that the. Be attributed to a change in the
volume. Again, with fixed internal energy particle,
no, it's given by the ratio of the pressure to the
temperature, and so we arranged to move to the
other side of the equation, divide it through by
temperature and by changing the volume. So this
issue of pressure and temperature in to that final.
Partial derivatives you had written down at the
bottom of this page here and then rearranged to
isolate the change in energy by multiplying
through five the temperature that is appearing in
the denominator of every term of the right hand
side, we recover the previous form of the first,
the networks that we derived, canonical ensemble
change in internal energy. Is related to the heat
exchanged with this round? Plus, the mechanical
work that is done on the system by the
surroundings and then the new term is the chemical
potential times change in particle number,
sometimes referred to as chemical work, the change
in energy that results. From a change in the total
number of chemicals in our system through exchange
with the surroundings.
You can again see the role of the chemical
potential and its dimensions of energy leading a
change in the pure number, the number of particles
to change the overall energy of the system. So
this is a further generalization of that, first of
all.
They called the generalized thermodynamic identity,
which provides an easy way to either remember or
redivide of relations between.
Six of these. Macroscopic properties of the system,
the temperature, chemical potential, energy,
entropy, avoiding the particle numbers. If we
imagine fixing any two of those qualities, we come
up with a relation between the other four. So as
an example. If we fix the particle number and the
volume, then this equation of the General Assembly
identity collapses back down to the definition of
the temperature, the very first derived quantity
that we. Introduced all the way back to the so the
second and third terms vanish by fixing and fixing
while you're left with just a change in energy
equal to temperature. Times change entropy, which
we can rearrange to identify the inverse
temperature as the response of the entropy to a
change in energy with everything else fixed.
Is. Swapping things around so that only the second
term can be identity is not zero. So fixing the
particle number and considering isotropic
processes that keep the entropy constant, we
recover the definition for the pressure that we
introduced in. Unit four, I believe we can get all
the gases, the negative response to the internal
energy to change the volume for fixed particle
number and constant intravenous. And the new
relation that we now have from the general, that
is if we continue considering isotropic processes
with constant entropy and now a fixed volume, but
allow the number to change, we can get a.
New way of looking at or understanding what the
chemical potential means in physical terms, that's
just as the two examples above that we've already
seen you find the chemical potential is the
response in the energy and we change the particle
number if we keep the volume of the system fixed
and also require that the entropy remain constant
in this process.
Now, at the start of this unit earlier this week,
we argued that if we add particles to a system, we
can generically expect the intricate system to
increase. So qualitatively at the hardware level,
with more particles, there are more ways of
arranging those particles. More microstates has
more energy, entropy or more information. So
generically, if we. Increase the number of we
expect the country to increase and in order to
keep the interview fixed when adding particles,
you would then need to adjust the energy of the
system to cancel out. That increased.
Decrease the entropy by a corresponding amount,
cancel out the change we will typically get from
increasing the number of particles. So what that
means, in short, is that limit the number of
particles increases. For isotropic process, we
need to decrease the energy.
So that was pretty primitive here that we have not
related to the chemical potential is going to be
negative. So this is. Just a.
New way of looking at understanding of the.
Results that we discussed where we had the
potential to introduce a introduced on Tuesday
that it is in generally negative quality for
natural systems with positive temperatures.
And that is. Sort of the end of the formal
introduction of the grand total ensemble. So a
good place to start for today. Just to recap what
we have done, we finished going through that
replica trick, seeing that the details of the
particle reservoir fixed the temperature and
chemical essential for the great canonical
ensemble are irrelevant and unknowable and then
derived by introducing the chemical, the
derivative of the logarithm of the partition
function and related derivatives of that economic
potential to the standard set of divided
quantities that we tend to be interested in an
average particle, no average internal energy, and
the entropy which led us to this generalized to
the identity, the generalization of the first law
of thermodynamics, to the canonical case in which
the particle number is allowed to change along
with the internal energy and potentially the
volume.
So this is a last call for immediate questions
about what we have gone through today in. And as
you consider those on this forecast, the next step,
which will be applying all of this formalism that
we have spent the past couple of classes
developing to the case of quantum field cases, and
it will be just a bit more build up to. Work
through those applications starting on Monday by
looking at. The definition of quantum statistics
and how this differs from the non quantum or
classical. Systems that we have been considering
up to this point in the module, so that is what we
can look forward to next week. I have office hours
now. There are questions about the solutions to
part one of the computer project or the feedback
that can check through that, which also will look
through briefly in the tutorial this afternoon. So
obviously, I'll see you all there. If not, I'll
see you on Monday afternoon.
Yeah, so.
Stop the recording.