All right, welcome back to Friday afternoon, the end of the week,
at least for statistical physics, and the start of
the end can be the six-digit number for this afternoon:
four seven seven seven five eight.
And it seems to be
warm of these days that leaving that window open
isn't going to make things too cold in here. We'll see how we
get on at this point. There are about three
things in the bag for this afternoon. And the idea
is I'll just go straight through them in this
order. Starting with a quick look at the computer
project, solutions for feedback on that first part
and a quick look forward to the second part of the
week's. That the. Not a trivial exercise that we
got started last week with the mixing of two
different types of otherwise indistinguishable
particles and the resulting mixing entropy when
the systems are combined and separated, and then
that everyone outside knows the new and exciting
tutorial exercise on different sorts of
thermodynamics cycles, a bit more practically
useful than the current cycle.
And of course, this is far as an opportunity for
you to bring up any questions, have the topics but
the others want to know more about, I have this
bottom on the screen, very focused and.
Not hearing any urgent questions coming up,
make a few quick comments about the solutions to
this first part of the computer project, probably
just looking at the plots that we have dispersed,
exercises calling the. Particular type of function,
random, random, to generate the security number
many times and then manipulating those results to
check the average standard deviation of a fairly
trivial uniform distribution. Maybe the
interesting thing about this is that when we look
at how the fluctuations of our estimates for. The
meaning of that uniform distribution from the law
of large numbers. The fluctuations around the true
Analytica mean.
Can be computed by repeating that estimation many
times and then checking that. The difference
between this estimate from the law of large
numbers and the true meaning, it's closer to.
Proportionately to this one, overall, the number
of repetitions somebody.
Numerically verifying something that you saw in
class, namely that. The. Number of repetitions
times, the deviation between the arithmetic mean
and the true meaning is a constant. And in
particular, this counts. It turns out to be, as we
derived in class, just the variance of the
distribution in this case, what, twelve point
three that's plotted on. But as the solid orange
line compared to the numerical estimates and the
number of repetitions being used in this analysis
increased by a factor of ten thousand the.
That should be a consequence, as are increases
from ten to one hundred thousand is just bouncing
around within 10 to 20 percent of the expected
value. Exercise to sort of looking at a
non-trivial distribution related. To that uniform
distribution by the arc, Simon. Inversed transform,
sampling this exercise was. The easiest one for
most folks, it's another computation of the exact
mean and standard deviation of this non-trivial
distribution, and some of you could check that. So
the probability distribution you can derive.
Random variables distributed, according to their
cosign, that the limits. On the range of. X is
looking at this kind of stuff, what I needed to
have the integral over probability distribution
itself add up two to one snippet of X, the X
equals one, given the limits of minus six to six.
And this is an automatic consequence of. Setting
up this distribution through that inversed
transform sampling already released to the uniform
distribution where the probability. More
critically, it adds up to a larger percentage of
these inevitable transformations, preserve that
total probability. So that's. The basic properties
of. The probability are satisfied by any
distribution obtained through the sample. And as I
said, this was the. Exercise is the easiest for
most folks who got a nice agreement between the
cosine of X that solitaries line and the
normalized Vistaprint. Running from minus six to
six. With a million samples that can be computer
generated in about five seconds, this facility is
exercise three, which was the more challenging one.
And maybe the main challenge we're talking about
here in person is just the amount of computing
time that it is going to be done over there that
some folks reported needing to invest in order to
come up with this part of the. Diffusion length,
as estimated from the ballpark numbers, the
arithmetic mean of the diffusion line for ten
thousand samples for every and the number of steps
in the walk ranging from a single step walk. All
the way up to walks of five hundred steps. And the
trick that helps this competition run a bit faster
in about 20 seconds on my laptop, 40 seconds on
the clock. Is hinted at in the demo, which is to
note that if we go through the trouble of
computing this final points, ten thousand
different marks, each of five hundred steps in the
first four hundred ninety nine steps of that five
hundred step will give us ten thousand four
hundred ninety nine steps already lied about. And
the first steps are all the hundreds of works that
we need and all the way across here. Now,
obviously, this has the. Effect that. The five
hundred step walks only differ from the four
hundred by the Knights that walks by that last
single step, which is part of the reason why the
data in blue are. So smooth in this result and
ignore those correlations was the time to be in
the exercise that allowed it to run in the 20
seconds as opposed to 20 minutes. How do you have
to.
Fit this comparison on the screen.
So the. Far to the left here is the same one we
were just looking at figures out its focus again,
where we ignored the correlations between all of
these lots of different number of steps and just
use the five hundred step walk as the source of
all the shorter walks. If we repeat that, the cost
of one hundred times more computing than what we
can see by having them side by side like this is a
greater amount of. Sarcastic scatter around the
fit. So getting this to the square root of N.
That.
Hide the fact that the data points in blue are
bouncing around.
To a greater magnitude above and below that, if I
wanted to write about. Zoom in on. The
uncharitably bought the plot showing uncorrelated
results. Mr.. Make that a bit clearer to see the
effect of those correlations and smoothing out
that behavior. So if we were being.
Very careful about estimating uncertainties in
things like the coefficients of these and
predictions for physics, we might want to worry
about those correlations. That's. Something that.
We don't need to tell a lot of effort into you for
the purposes of this exercise, just confirming the
expected security independence is sufficient for
our purposes.
And.
One other comment is that. If you want to look at
this difference between correlated, uncorrelated
results in more detail, a nice way to do that,
which I have set up today, is to. Look at what he
call the residuals of profits. So take the
difference between each data point and the Fifth
and the corresponding value, and I plot those
versus then you'll see results that sarcastically
fluctuate. Ground Zero saw some data points are
higher than the feds, some are lower than the
average. And the scale of those fluctuations is
going to. Decrease as the number of repetitions
are increases and it's going to be larger than the
Oncolytics compared with these smooth correlated
results where the fluctuations that we get for
five hundred steps in the war are going to depend
almost entirely on those that come out for
that stuff box. So those are all the.
I had to say about that first part of the computer
exercise there, any questions? About that. Before
just a quick walk through the next piece of that.
The.
Yeah, so in the PDF that I have on the screen here,
I copy the
companies that were used. This is an example I
found that I used to produce the American response
and the plots that I was showing. And this is also
on the Candace page, linked from the same
discussion where the solutions themselves are long
from. So it may well be worth spending 30 seconds.
Whether you can find all of that.
Sloane.
Two factor authentication is part of the reason
they have so upset the student, beaten up the
immersive reader.
So this should be what you see on canvas.
From the stream, there is an update on the
computer project on the bottom of here, we have
the link to the PDF and at least my model python
code. That is not the only or necessarily the best
way to do things, but gives an example of how all
of these numerical results and figures were
produced in the stated amount of time
printout just to keep an eye on both sides, asking
you to work on all of these missiles.
So that is. Where you can find all of that and.
Further questions about. That part one.
Also, just a few comments and a quick walk through
now, part to highlight a few things, not go into
an exhaustive discussion of everything that's
going on.
So this is a continuation of the project that is
going to. Build on what you've done. One to. Bring
things to bear on a slightly more complicated
situation, so we're still looking at random walks
with step sizes that are randomly chosen from a
particular distribution and. In this case.
Rather than starting from the transform, taking us
from the uniform distribution to the distribution
of interest from which we'll build up the works of
what analyzed and to start off with defining. That
distribution, which is known as a commercial
distribution or personal wealth distribution or
Brainfeeder distribution, depending on what
textbook you're reading, what Wikipedia article
you're looking at.
But this is is an overall normalization factor,
one over five times subcouncil parameter B.
Times the. Fraction one divided by one plus. The
ex Overbey squared, and this rages over all real
ex positive and negative, it's an even functional
around. Exit zero is it depends on the square root
of the square root of X.
And.
The maybe the best way to. Did some intuition for.
This distribution is just to look at it plotted
for a few different values of the parameter of the
compared to the normal Gaussian distribution with
a with a sigma of of one so that Gaussian
distribution is the solid black curve in this plot.
And then the other three curve's. The red dashkova
hyping the solid green curve with the peak fairly
close to navigation distribution and then the
lower and broader.
Got a blue curve are three different realizations
that Kosmaj distribution with different values,
black has to be either a half, one or two. All of
these cases,
the most noteworthy thing about these
distributions is that for a sufficiently large X
in magnitude, so plus or minus X often for the
edges of this plot, we see that even in the case
of a small B, where the peak and the probability
distribution around X equals zero can greatly
exceed the peak of the Gaussian distribution.
Eventually.
Even after all of these distributions following
the election were sufficiently large X. The
Gaussian distribution is the lowest of all, and
any cautions against distribution is going to have
probabilities at large acts that are larger than
that of the distribution. Which is. Easy to
appreciate simply because the distribution. Eataly,
minus X squared is decreasing exponentially in X
squared. There is the distribution of the driving
down by this factor of one over X squared. So an
exponential suppression is always going to beat
any polynomial suppression for a sufficiently
large values of X. And what this is known as or
referred to are tales in the distribution. It's a
statement that the probabilities for. Large
volumes of excellent details of the distribution
far away from connecting with zero.
The probability of those and the disintegration is
greater than or fatter than that of the normal
distribution.
And in the course of the. First exercise in this
part of the assignment, which is the fourth
exercise overall. We'll see some of the features
of that coherence distribution, which motivates
the. Introduction of generalized diffusion length
and the following final exercise. Maybe I should
start on its previous page three by picking up on
the discussion of these battles in the course of
the rest distribution, which. Mean mathematically
that there is a lower probability for rare events
far away from peak to occur. Compare it again to
the normal distribution. So an illustration of
what this means in practice is what I initially
put up here at the top of this page comparing two
different random walks in two dimensions. So here,
in addition to randomly choosing the step size,
you also randomly choose a direction, the plane
for the water to step. And that's not just to get
something visual to to look at
the. Figure on the left here, the step sizes are
being chosen from a national distribution.
And if we trace all out the path of this random
water to take its steps, we see that as randomly
choosing different directions in step lengths to
proceed in this two dimensional plane and filling
in. Some portion of that played around with the.
Border. Ten to 20 units from that starting point
at the origin, zero zero.
And.
I'm sure you've already seen the contrast to.
The other men to walk on the plots where the
planes are drawn. But the to Lorenz distribution,
rather than the actual distribution and the. Fat
tails in that distribution are caused by
occasional steps that have much larger sizes than
anything seen in the case, so that the scale of
the accidents has seen by a factor of 10. Even
with that. That Zuma out some of the individual
steps are far larger than anything that is
produced by a U.S. distribution with any
probability.
In this situation, it turns out to be necessary
for reasons the seeding exercise force, you define
a generalized diffusion length rather than looking
at that L2 in the first part of the computer
project, the distribution is also theta.
You mentioned that in the case where the mean is
zero, which is the case for all of these
distributions that are even around X equals zero,
if we set Theta to two, we would recover just the
usual diffusion length standard deviation as
opposed to here L2. That was part of the first
part of the computer project and the ordinary log
diffusion that this elsom that is proportional to
the square root and for walks and steps for the
distribution. The only valid values of theta are
data from zero to one. So it has to be a positive
quantity and the portion of its distribution, this
generalized, if you like, that still define if
Theta is ever. One of the larger. And the question
then is, how do you pay for this distribution of
these journalists, if you like, severity with the
number of steps to walk, so give him some.
Exponents Alpha.
Which in the case of ordinary diffusion,
corresponds to. The square root circle is a half.
Whatever the law of diffusion.
Satisfied? And final exercise for you to do is
figure out Alpha for the distribution, see whether
it is a half. Larger than a half produces, but
it's a super supervision that's similar to the
system up here, but we can also have halfa still
positive. That's more than half the produce and
subterfuge of random walks. That's. Move away from
their starting point much more slowly than
diffusion. Would forget. So they've gone on, I
have got to wonder about all of that, the media
questions before you get to work on this next
assignment, the knowledgeable.
There are a couple of weeks left to play with that
you can now. Return to your problems more
explicitly and starting with the one we got part
of the way through last time around, looking at
the mixing entropy for the simplification. We
assume that all of the particles of these gases
are indistinguishable apart from your color, red
or blue. And you want to see how the entropy of
these systems various through the three stage
process of starting off with the initial
separation due to. Different containers with all
the red particles are going to take it all the
particles. So that was interesting challenge the
lectures, elections and two
more is there. And on that one, there is just two
as.
This volume divided by.
And then upon removing the wall separating these
two systems of law, but it was a part of this mix.
Last time you computed the entropy, that combined
system was not shown in these figures and saw that
it is equal to an initial review by the courts to
avoid the ratio. Plus, your positive mixing
entropy that we to do to add more to the. And it
depends on the volume. And then we ran out of time.
And left it as something for you to think about
what happens when the ball is reinserted, that
combined system is re separated into two systems,
which you can assume have the same number of
particles, but in general will have red and blue
particles now scramble together on different sides
of this wall.
So if you have any luck finding an expression for
how the interviewee behaves in that.
Final stage where the ball has been inserted and
the right of the particles are all scrambled.
Sounds like the.
Almost intractable. Which motivates going through
it here and now in person.
Let's see
how much time to spend on this. The first step
that is even being mentioned in this problem is
that we just need to compute this partition
function of that final system once this law has
been reinserted. So. To go through that very
quickly, this is always a.
It's based on the civil protection functions. So
that's where that
ratio of.
Particles come from a wall to the single particle
protection function for everything else you wrote
down in class was just the sheer the volume of the
particles in
several different wavelengths and then for an
indistinguishable from the. So that this is the
one.
Partition is just the single market opportunity.
However, it is divided in different ways of living.
It's probably the single. Indistinguishably posted
in the. System of particles.
The case will probably be solved, at least one to
the end is just as important for the same the
girls. So the question now is, if we have these
two separate containers with a mixture of red and
blue particles.
What is the overall function for ximo
for difference in this initial gases? We have the
red particles in the container particles in what
container particles were a container of particles
of the right container. So if we suppose that
there are new particles in the left container,
then for factors to multiply together. So for
those particles, that horrible times, that's a
particle vacation function. So.
We want you to know that our assumption is that
there are in total particles in each container.
One is very important with this container. So
one to see this all, it's more defined by the
remaining red particles in the right container. We
know there are a lot of those
in the particles, a total of four of them left in
the.
And there are things like this new container
is
in that.
So those are the four factors going into the
petition function for any particular number of red
particles in the container, which determines all
of the other particles are distributed among those
containers. This can be simplified.
Fairly directly, just by. Seeing that. He has. How
is it you can correct me on those terms so we the
two factors at the end two, but one of the factors
that were involved in so many
times,
both
what we want to end.
Calling
for
political.
Well,
see that the denominator here, that's just what we
have to do, right? This is one over
square Times Square by
you.
So that is protection for one particular
distribution and. We have to some this over all
possible numbers of red particles that came up in
the left container. There can be no particles
there, one or two or all of the particles. And
when something goes all the way up to the end of
that, you just disappear.
Which that is of
where.
It was worth
it to me.
Half
of the
square, which was given to that this fall, some.
As a result, more than seven years ago, so this
one is down to the final four when she was on.
So.
If you want to be in the final stage, play a
little trick to simplify calculations, it's the
same trick as we talked about last week. The
difference between the comparison to the interview
of the divine system,
one that came out, which is. The mother of the
ratio of. That story
just repeated the bipartisan policy, which was
last week. What we have right now, from the work
to the bottom, there is little.
As to the other side, this is one of the fairly
complicated.
Expression.
What we have is the final state
where.
And then there were politicians and over again,
this is all divided by. The
most popular politician there. Well, I don't want
to question.
Factor. So everything is canceling out except for
more
than a minus
or two.
Now we can.
So for your services, what was the bottom
line, is this
for real small?
Well, without the war support, it's useless to
try to minus two
plus.
To there, cancellations, anything except
school that cancels out that factor to zero.
So.
Once we reinsert the ball in the system and we
separate the combined system into two. Subsystems
with the same number of particles and scramble
colors, the entropy of the universe does not go
back to the smaller value that we started off with.
It also doesn't increase. It just stays the same
as it was in that combined system, which is in
agreement with the second law of thermodynamics as
time goes on
and is created as equal to the interview, which we
thought was certainly greater than the start of
entropy. So this procedure have been able to
confirm explicitly does not violate the second law
of thermodynamics.
So that is. All to say, you have to say about last
week's mixing entropy problem, unless there are
questions about it. A fun exercise you might do
going forward is with the next corrections and
formula and see if you can explain what happens.
Order, order, mortgage terms are preserved.
And it looks like there is just time remaining to
mention the. Final topic that I thought would be
the bulk of activity today, which is looking at
different thermodynamic cycles.
Beyond the cycle that we finish talking about
Monday. This is an example known as the auto cycle,
named after a German physicist, Nicholas Otto, who
spent about 14 years in the eighteen sixties and
seventies trying to figure out how to actually
build the machine that would realize this pressure
volume diagram. So let's walk through the four
stages of the cycle. And figure out. What it is
doing and maybe the best way to. Motivates the
four stages here is to reveal from the start that
this is an idealized description of how a petrol
engine works. So starting from this point, one man
and a boy you visible the gas in this cycle is
typically some mixture of air and vaporized petrol
that is compressed idiomatically.
To a smaller volume, you point to that compression
raises the temperature of this petrol air mixture.
At which point that high pressure, high
temperature, the spark is introduced to that gas,
which lights it on fire, it ignites the gas and
essentially uses that. The burning of this gas is
a replacement for an external hot reservoir of the
sort that Cardno had in mind. So rather than
waiting to exchange energy with an external
High-temperature reservoir, William. Ignite the
fuel, burn it, extract heat from it to drive up
the temperature and pressure at a fixed value for
the volume, and then once the pressure is up here
at its maximum point thirty, we use that pressure
to extract work from the engine. So. We allow the
system to expand again and also idiomatically with
the expansion at constant entropy that can do work,
extract power from the the burning of the fuel,
and then that takes us to this final stage where
we're back at the boy we started off with. But we
still have a significantly higher temperature
after having gone through the process of dumping
in a bunch of heat into this gas by letting it out,
fire burning it off. And this exhausts stage is a
similarly clever way of rapidly reducing the
temperature and the pressure at a fixed volume. So
what happens here is that rather than demanding
that the same end particles in the gas remain in
the gas throughout this whole cycle, those hot and
particles of the fuel are expelled to the
atmosphere as exhaust. And at the same time
they're replaced by an equal amount of tresh
cooler fuel air mixture so that the process back
to the starting points and repeats over and over
again, often several thousand revolutions per
minute, and the sorts of petrol engines that we
have on the streets nowadays, we thought it would
be in to be able to make anything quite so
advanced is what's driving our cars on. His
realization of this cycle had about two or four
percent efficiency and was about 10 feet tall. It
was a fellow named Dimler who figured out how to
actually. Shrink things down to the point where
the engines were movable, didn't have to be set up
in a specialized lavatory, which is why Dimler
does not want to be. Most established car
companies in that in the world. And given the time
it was just through the states, the tutorial
problems surrounding this obviously go and revisit
it next time around, zoom in a bit.
So we went through this cycle and did one last
thing to define is the compression ratio, which is
just the ratio of the larger volume to the smaller.
So something that is greater than one which is
relevant because the efficiency of the cycle
depends only on that compression ratio. The ratio
of the volumes at which the compression starts and
where it ends. So the task which you can think
about all over the coming week is to compute the
efficiency of a petrol engine compared to the
current cycle and figure out which one is most
efficient and how that efficiency can be maximized.
So you will discuss that next week. And hopefully
in the meantime, you can have some fun thinking
about how that calculation might go on. Any final
questions for today? Feel free to shout about now.
Otherwise, see you back here Monday afternoon for
quantum statistics. Completely different.
At
this
point,
oil
is.
Stop that recording.