I'm running just slightly late this afternoon, but we can
get underway now with the next six digit number
for this afternoon,
which does not have to do
with these mass densities.
Today it is nine eight
two zero, nine six.
And let's start, to see if there are any questions
about any topic we've been covering so far in this
module, Including the second part of that computer
project that's due next week.
I'll say that this is the last tutorial
before that deadline and we will have another set
of office hours Monday afternoon. And this is a
quick. Notes I put in the miscellaneous section of
the material on canvas, just a couple of links are
actually a couple of paragraphs that I downloaded
from relatively recent applications of anomalous
diffusion published in the journal Physical Review
Letters, which publishes short four or five page
papers looking at things like anomalous diffusion
in terms of how genes move around in DNA from
about 10 years ago, as well as a more recent
letter that.
Some supplemental material getting it up to 10
pages, but maybe of some general interest in how
it reviews.
Different contexts in which both sub diffusion and
super diffusion occur in biophysical contexts,
which is what these folks are working on, things
related to polymers, education, DNA, active
networks.
Motion of tracer particles in in cells, so lots of.
References there to. Applications of supervision
and substitution, specifically in biophysics,
which were considered interesting enough by the
editors of that journal that they commissioned,
Dave Schwartz, less technical summary of. How all
of this supervision and subterfuge have come into
play in actual physical systems.
That is just in the final miscellaneous section of
the budget materials for those who are interested.
And with that.
Out of the way and mentioned. You can pick up with
not this, but what we were doing at. Last Friday.
That up to steal the screen and.
As a. Reminder of last week we had. A bit too much
material to get through the time available, so
this tutorial problem on the auto cycle for a
petrol engine is something that we just sort of
tossed out at the end with the idea that could we
visited. Today. We're just as a quick reminder,
the engine has like the carbon cycle, four stages.
No, in contrast to the current cycle, rather than
waiting for heat to be exchanged between external
hot and cold reservoirs. What happens with the
auto cycle is that after the. The fuel, so the gas
is a mixture of air and vaporized petrol is
compressed to some small volume V two, it is
ignited and burned the internal combustion process
to crank up the temperature of the pressure very
quickly at that fixed volume. And that high
pressure can then be used to generate work or
power from the expansion cycle before. That
Högberg fuel is expelled and replaced with a new
cooler mixture for the cycle to begin again,
keeping the same number of particles even as
particles are expelled and replaced from outside.
The question was. What is the efficiency of this
cycle in particular in terms of this compression
ratio between the large and small volumes? And how
that compares to the efficiency we computed. Last
week for the annual cycle.
And one topic I was going to. Mentioned briefly
even before diving into this out of cycle was an
alternative way of representing these cycles, both
Kernow as well as other cycles and many others,
that
takes advantage of the set of. Thermodynamic
equations that we. I wrote down for some the
cycles to express. All aspects of the system in
terms of a different set of variables rather than
the pressure and volume. So we've seen a
reminder from just law books, both empty,
specifying both pressure and volume, determines
the temperature
of the volume and temperature determines usually.
Find the entropy is proportional to that volume of
temperature to the three taps power, so an
alternative set of. Freedom parameters that we can
work with. Let me see if I can. He with the finger
and the question on the screen there, through this
sort of pressure and volume, we can work with the
temperature and can see underlining the state as
well as with the interview and from those get back
and forth between pressure and volume
to temperature and entropy.
So I removed myself.
Which of these two are most traditional there on
which axis the entropy is actually treated as the
x axis temperature on the y axis of these
so-called S.T. diagrams? As opposed to PV diagrams,
if we.
Call the news cycle, we're in the TV diagram, we
have to idiomatic expansion into precious stages,
interweaved with two isothermal progression and
expansion stages. As a reminder, boy in for final
was like. That where.
Scott.
It's not the best. But the.
Those up 80 stages connected to two stages, so.
That's.
Was there?
And so Adams on the other two stages. And
in contrast to how tricky it was for me to draw
that diagram before we see the entirety of your
diagram for the current cycle, it's much easier to
draw those terms or processes with constant
temperature. So the idioms that we've seen with no
exchange of sheets have no change. And there's a
constant central issue which leads to the current
cycle just being a.
Square or a rectangle in the axis of.
Temperature and the. And.
Whereas in the case of PV diagrams, we had a of
radical interpretation of the work, and it's that
area closed
under the cycle, so.
Work integrated.
We move forward and back with the negative side.
So canceling out, that is under both of those two
lines and keeping all boys in between the call
that similarly
keeps deploying and entropy put on that x axis,
then we end up with each
others operating cycles. That's it would be fine.
So that's just an alternate representation of the
two cycles. That's the whole case. There would
be up not here, the TV diagram correspondents that
I've crossed onto this diagram. So for the other
cycle.
Hopefully is usable, we have again to idiomatic
compression and expansion phases, which
mean.
So there will be two council phases and then in
between then we have this constant volume increase
or decrease in the pressure and temperature. So
the heat is being pumped into the system by
burning its fuel. So that increases the entropy at
the same time as it increases the temperature. And
similarly, at the exhaust stage when he is dumped
out into the environment.
There is
a decrease in the temperature and the interest of
the system and entropy being pumped out along with
the heat, so integrating these PV and AC diagrams
will give both the heat and the work.
So just to be precise, before we get back into the
actual question, that was, is the Baltimore Sun,
yes, going from four to one is cooling down the
system. So decreasing its temperature and its
pressure at a fixed point, the small of
civil rights people.
We have a free choice of volumes and we have to
specify at least one of the pressures in order to
close the cycle, if we go around this in a.
Rigorous analysis and essentially what we have at
our freedom, there's.
The temperature of the Interreg gas, as we bring
it in, assuming that the cycle has been running
for a while so that the engine is as hot as it's
going to be, not overheating, so that fixed
temperature is going to be set by how hot the time
is, how hot the engine is running. And then we
just need to pump out all of the. Burns fuel that
is at a higher temperature from having been burned
and then replace it with the fresh fuel mixture at
the same temperature. We started off with, which
necessarily lowers the pressure while the fight
against the occupation and be fixed in temperature
correspondingly lowers the pressure. So. We are
able to analyze this in the same terms. As a TV
diagram, even though it differs from Kurnos
original idea that we have some large external
reservoir that is shifting heat into and out of
the system just through from contact. Instead, we
have ignition and exhaust as ways to speed up the
process and have engines that run at several
thousand revolutions per minute rather than taking
several minutes for resolution.
And what I should ask at this stage is, are you
already done with. The question of calculating the
efficiency of the auto cycle or should we take
five minutes to. Work out that seem to be. Working
so. That's a sign she paused for those five
minutes reporting to check in. At that point.
After 20 past.
That was the worst ever for me to check in, having
what still seemed to be part of work on Friday,
just it to another.
But about a five minute period for you to keep
working on this. Are there any obstacles that have
come up so far?
It's just a matter of pushing through the.
Computation can help you with it, at least for
another. Five minutes before. Another chicken.
And the recording and say that maybe with at this
point, see how far we got out and.
Able to simplify things.
In terms of
looking at the efficiency of general expression,
that efficiency is the net amount of work put out
by the system that works in from the surroundings
to break the cycle, complete with the bottom line
that comes in, in this case, in the form of
burning fuel. In addition.
Well,
interestingly enough, some of you that
saw on this panel, you have the three. Quaternions
to return. And your work so far, it seen that the
system is the negative of the work done by. How
are things going to have a positive quality
negative work from three to four since that's the.
That is the major change in the energy, which, by
the way, was key to the equation cycles. It's just
three times and
the change is positive. Then Scorpion's.
Nearly the same one, the compression faced three
different sizes because the work is being done by
this system, which is the positive change from
point one to point to
the ads and
also the new needs to be. And then because Putin
is going to change the volume is zero and a fixed
volume, there is no work being done. So this is
also
for change and energy.
Those two to three
is part of the
picture. So ever
since all these factors that have been cast, that
is just
on the almost by the estimates of two one by.
To pull that, he wants to go to France to have one
like this one's for.
And this, too, may well look familiar from
the past few minutes. Now.
No, no.
So that's the starting point for people who want
to help, aside from the large scale of regional
pressure and temperature, but we're going to have
to do the same so we have a seasonal space.
Whenever a burning fuel is pushed out into, the
demand has to be replaced immediately with a fresh
batch of fuels that no article statistics, even
which these particles they are, is evolving. So
that is an important condition for analyzing for
cycles through the canonical ensemble that fixes
the temperature. No. That insurance for was. And
that. In particular, it is also part of that
condition for constant intracranial.
That this country needs is proportional to just
that combination of the temperature when the of is
six. I mentioned that interview commission as it
is a useful way to simplify this, to get to the
promised result of this efficiency is to depend
only on that compression ratio of the one divided
by two to.
Rich. We can see that by applying that condition
of entry to both of the antibiotic cycles where me
Constance's will do that over here at.
Just because. In addition, here comes the boiling
water temperature, one, two, three,
two, three. And similarly.
For.
That's kind of the general rule.
So this is the second or full cycle one this stage,
as well as for that stage to be the for some
rearranging things, they have ratios to one to two
to four to.
What will prevent depression with your help and
also the same ratio that pops up from other power
stage just as the ratio of for
to three?
Or if I rearrange those equations
to one, which is the same. As to what was he did
through?
Let's see what we can do with this expression
later on this morning. Well, the bottom line is
since to one, all he wanted was to oversee this
whole factor in parentheses. This one, the
efficiency is one minus that ratio for over three
that we identify as the compression ratio to two
thirds. And that is the answer to the first
question. Keeping an eye on the clock to wrap
things up today on his charge ahead with.
Your comments about the other two pieces of this
problem, because the comparison
is efficiency is the problem. So if you plug in
rather than whatever depression version of the two
thirds for this speculative for which you three
other ratio tell the truth, then express the other
side of this numbers, the ratio between two, which
is less than one, the T cycle, which is two begins.
And it's easy to see where this inequality comes
from with teaching itself. The temperature before
the fuels is able to stop being smaller than two
three. So there
is longer and subtracting a larger number. For one,
you say reduce the efficiency cycle. Which is what
we expect, given what we saw was the theoretical
maximum. So the best we could do would be throw
the other side well, is less efficient, but much
faster to operate in an internal combustion engine.
But the last comment for today has to do with
maximizing the efficiency of this cycle, which you
can do by maximizing this compression ratio. So as
our goes to infinity.
There's a ratio of the boils over which this
engine is operating, it's become larger and larger,
the efficiency gets better and better, and there's
less relative amount of energy lost to wastage
compared to the amount that is converted into used
to work. So what we would want to do to make our
petrol engine as efficient as possible is make
this with compression and power stage as long as
possible. Which went into some practical
limitations, because as we compress the mixture of
air and vaporize petrol that is burned as fuel in
these engines, the temperature is steadily rising
through the ideal gas law. This is adiabatic
compression.
That's. Leads to larger temperature as the system
is compressed with no ability to exchange heat
with its surroundings, and if that temperature
becomes too large, then it is possible for that
mixture of air and fuel is being compressed to
spontaneously combust and start the ignition phase
before an actual spark is put in to ignite the.
The fuel is controlled by. Audio engineering, this
is called Docketed, and you have engineers
knocking in a car, that is what happens when it's
trying to work with a. Compression ratio we want
to repeat to that is too large. For these fuels to
remain stable. This is a just brief segment in the
last couple of minutes here to alternate. Form of
internal combustion engine, I need to zoom out to
get into the screen. That should do it. And what
we have here is a cycle.
Known as the diesel cycle.
Imlach.
And similarly to the auto cycle that describes a
petrol engine we have, adiabatic compression is
going from using, if you want to be to and
idiomatic powerplays. But instead of mixing the
air fuel at the start, the schools are concerned
about what what is compressed is actually just air
itself, which is not going to spontaneously
combust, at least not if the temperature is large
enough to melt whatever the engine is made out of
the first place. It is only at this stage. Mr.
Weebles, one, two, three and four. The initial
phase is now happening at a cost and pressure. And
pushing the system out to a larger point where
fuel is actually injected into the hot air that
has been compressed. Where it immediately ignites,
increases the temperature and increases the volume
at this fixed pressure and then. It's power. Out
of. Remaining expansion back to the point where we
started off with. So the efficiency of the diesel
cycle is going to depend on both the compression
ratio, the one. Review, too, as well as what is
called the cut off ratio, which is this. New
volume three divided by the two how?
This is putting the limit on how much how high the
pressure can be as fuel is injected to be burned.
So. We have an expression for the utmost
efficiency. Given a depression ratio of.
Existing cars tend to have compression ratios,
babies, so it's going to be almost is times for
children to get into this expression of the auto
cycle efficiency, what is now fifty six percent
efficient efficiently. What's.
In practice, so realistic cycles, psychosis is
ignoring things like fiction and other
inefficiencies, the people burning fuel, so the
other cycle legalistic deficiencies are usually
about 10 to 20 percent between two to three. And
you can find in the diesel cycle with a fixed
compression ratio. The efficiency actually tends
to be less than the other cycle. But because we
don't have this risk of spontaneous combustion, we
can get much larger compression ratios at work
around 20. So two and a half times the ratio for a
petrol engine is possible with typical diesel
engines. And in those real world examples, the
efficiency can rise from 20 to 30 percent all the
way up to 40 percent, which doesn't seem to be
showing up well on that screen. But. Is, I think,
the place to stop for today in light of the time.
I think over the coming week, both in lecture and
tutorial, we'll do some more. Connections with.
These more realistic real world applications of
all the food and concepts we've been building up
in time, gas related to solar radiation, and I
think a tutorial will look at the Einstein model
of a solid.
It's its capacity to some experimental data.
So if there are no further questions for today,
we'll have a week for statistical physics. Hope
you enjoy the weekend. It remains so nice and
sunny.