Okay, that should all be in focus, so let's start
getting underway for the second half of the first
part of this week.  And, as usual, I have six digits for you.
They are mostly eights today.
The number is eighty eight, eighty four, eighty
one.
Are there any immediate questions lingering from
yesterday afternoon?
I think we'll keep moving straight forward through this
introduction of quantum statistics so that we
can apply the grand canonical ensemble we came up
with last week to quantum gases. And just to
briefly recall what we got through yesterday, we
saw that two things have to be done to obtain
quantum statistics as opposed to the non quantum
or classical statistics that we've been working
with up until now.
The first of those is. Retaining discreet energy
levels for all the particles in the system, and it
turns out that that does not suffice to obtain
true quantum statistics, if we go through the
exercise of computing, the grand canonical
partition function, the fundamental object for a
canonical ensemble retaining those discrete energy
levels, we come up with so called Macksville
Boltzmann's statistics, which Maximilian Boseman
did a lot to develop in the eighteen hundreds well
before quantum mechanics was. On anyone's radar.
So the second more subtle issue that really
defines quantum statistics compared to classical
statistics is the way in which we organize and
account for the microstates that correspond to
these discrete energy levels, rather than the
classical approach that gave us maximum elements
of physics where we broke up this many particle
system into looking at each particle in turn into
something over all the possible energies that each
of those particles could have, and then correcting
for the overcounting that results when those
particles are indistinguishable. As they must be
in quantum mechanics, we turn things on his head
and looked instead at each energy level in turn
something over the occupation numbers. So the
number of particles that. Can occupy that energy
level and. These two approaches at argued are
equivalent when there is very little probability
of having multiple particles in the same energy
level. So if we have occupation numbers of only
zero and one with suppressed probabilities for
larger occupation numbers, or in other words, if
we have many more energy levels, then we have
particles to fill them in. Classical statistics
should be a good approximation to the true
behavior. And it's only when we are in the quantum
regime where there is a non-negotiable probability
of having multiple particles in the same energy
level. That. Clear differences arise and so far, I
appreciate I've just been telling you this result
in as motivation for building things up in either
by the end of today or Friday morning at the
latest, we will see on post facto that this is the
case, a regime in which classical statistics is a
good approximation to quantum statistics and the
regime in which they give different predictions.
So many questions having. Going through that rehab
to get back to our starting point for today.
So we are on the 15th of March and there is one
final piece of input about the world to cover in
the course of writing down Quantium statistics in
the form of actual grand canonical partition
functions from what we can derive and observe
levels of interest. And that is. A fact about
nature concerning the possible occupation numbers
for. The particles that exist in the world and.
Just to tell you again, this is not something that
you necessarily have. Seen before or need to
understand at a deep level, but a result, a proof
based on quantum mechanics and special relativity
states that. All particles in three spatial
dimensions like we live in fall into two distinct
classes that differ, among other things, by their
possible occupation numbers and therefore by the
quantum statistics that they realize these two
classes are called bosons, infirmities that are
named after. Physicists who were working less than
one hundred years ago, this statistics theorem was
developed. Around the nineteen twenties, nineteen
forty is based on empirical observations in
particular by this fellow Fermoy, a freelancer
named after a while, those are named after those.
And the difference between those and fermions that
its relevance for our work and sophistical POSIX
is that in the booth on a case? Any number of
identical bosun's can simultaneously occupy the
same energy level, so the corresponding occupation
numbers are any non-negative integers, we can have
zero particles in a given energy level. You single
those on that energy level to bosun's three
bosun's and so on, off to infinity. And just to
connect this to.
The physical world that we live in, we can mention
some examples of on that include pions in nuclear
physics, helium four atoms, the Higgs boson, which
is a bit bizarre, as it says on the tin, as well
as photons. So the quanta of light that. It will
be our first target for an application of the
green economic ensemble in the next few minutes
and.
What differs in the case of fermions is that.
Multiple identical fermions are forbidden to
occupy the same energy level, so instead of having
all non-negative integers, it's possible
occupation numbers, as we had proposed in the
first case, there are only two possible occupation
numbers for any given energy level, and those are
exactly zero and one. And this is something that
was first observed empirically in the early 90s,
hundreds looking at the ways that atoms and
electrons organize themselves in orbitals around
atomic nuclei. So we've come poly. So if you could
explain patterns in the resulting periodic table
of elements like supposing that only a single
electron maximum could be found in a quantum state.
And this was. Pretty quickly understood in terms
of accident statistics, the government can be
rigorously proven just a few years later and of
course, as this behavior is responsible for that
periodic table of elements, it is responsible for
all the chemistry, biology and us. So it is a
fairly important principle as things go. And as
this is, electrons are the famous example of
fermions. But other examples include the protons
and neutrons that form the nuclei of atoms that
those electrons are bound to, as well as more
exotic particles like neutrinos and even entire
atoms like Helium three, as opposed to Helium four.
Just to remind you of the difference between
healing three, healing for both of those have two
protons and two electrons, Helium three has only a
single neutron or helium four has two neutrons.
And it is exactly that difference that. I gives
those two types of helium, different quantum
statistics and therefore extremely different
behavior at in the quantum regime where. The
healing for kids can exhibit different phenomena
like those on site compared to Helium three and.
I appreciate it, just sort of telling you facts
about the universe, which may not be particularly
intuitive or easy to to understand. So I think we
have time to just motivate a little bit what's
going on with fermions that leads to this
different behavior, the requirement that no
multiple fermions can occupy the same energy level.
Is often in popular science, where some of you
might have seen these concepts of those kinds of
fermions before, they will say sort of whimsical
things like bosun's are friendly and like to
cluster together while fermions or standoffish
when they want to be by themselves. And that can
give the incorrect impression that fermions may
well be physically repelling each other. And that
is the reason why multiple fermions are not
occupying the same state. And that is not the case,
what is actually going on is the feature of
quantum mechanics. I'll try to tell you about this
qualitatively, tell a story about it rather than
going into the actual math and derivation. But the.
The setting is if we consider a system of
particles so governed by quantum physics and all
of these particles are identical and
indistinguishable, they can be at various
different energy levels. And because they are
indistinguishable particles, if we interchange any
pair of them, all of the observable properties on
the system have to remain unchanged. We got two
particles that we can't tell apart. We should be
able to tell whether or not we have done this.
The feature of quantum mechanics that is relevant
for the distinction between those of the fermions
is the fact that. All of these observables or
observable properties of a quantum system. Are
covered by the square of the quantum function that
really defines the system at the fundamental level.
So the technical terminology, this is called the
wavefunction for the system, and it has to be
squared in order to extract predictions for
anything observable.
The situation becomes sort of analogous to the
fact that the square root of one has two possible
values, plus or minus one, and it's similar in
quantum physics, in three spatial dimensions,
where there are two possible ways to have a
quantum function whose square remains unchanged
upon interchangeable particles. That function is
either completely symmetric under all of those
interchanges. So it remains unchanged or it is
completely anti symmetric. And any interchange
will bring in a negative side that squares to
unity when looking at observables. So those who
responded to the case in which interchanging
particles is symmetric fermions are that if you
symmetric possibility and just as in the case of
correcting for overcounting in classical
statistics, things become interesting when we
imagine that interchanging particles that happen
to be in that same energy level here, even at the
fundamental level of that quantum wavefunction,
there is no change in the system upon doing so. So
that.
The function itself has to be symmetric and is
unchanged when we interchange particles in the
same energy level, so it goes on a case that's
fine. All of these interchanges are symmetric
already in the Permian, in case you would require
a function that is simultaneously symmetric and
anti symmetric under indicating a pair of
particles. There is one such function and it is
zero, which is to say that there are
no quantum states.
That feature multiple fermions in the same energy
level, the function goes to zero whenever that
happens. So.
That is hopefully something a bit more memorable
to give some information about what's going on. If
you want more, there are quantum mechanics modules
for you to see what's going on here in more detail.
And why we only pick up the plus and minus one
rather than any complex phase, that's a feature of
special relativity and three dimensions and more
exotic behavior is possible in other dimensions.
And you just make sure that. The conclusion, the
take away is clear and maybe remember the quick
example we were going through yesterday with. Ways
of distributing to particles into five energy
levels, we saw that. When those particles are
indistinguishable, there are 15 possible
microstates, all of which are. Possible, which are
allowed in those on a case, and the quick question
is how many of those energy levels are allowed if
the particles are instead fermions?
Boscombe. Yeah, and there were five of those to
the 15 go to ten remaining.
So there was TEUs. Our lost. Those that remain
have particle numbers in zero and one and just to
be. Fully explicit, they take the form.
In the notation that we wrote down.
Hoopes.
So for.
And that is 10, so all accounted for the possible
ways of distributing these two particles in such a
way that there are at most one particle in each of
the five energy levels, that the one corresponds
to a single particle in the corresponding energy
level. Zero energy level with occupation number
zero. So now. Yes, check for questions about the.
Definitions of those items for me understand the
distinction between them. It will be in general
the case that. Hermione's have fewer microstates
than bosun's because of the microstates with
multiple occupancy are forbidden.
Not seeing any immediate questions, we will move
on to. Consider each of the Bozena confirming
other cases in turn, come up with the grand
canonical petition function for them and then see
how these differ from each other as well as from
the classical case. Where, of course, all of this
information about the quantum properties of
occupation numbers was not accounted for. Now, if
we consider the green canonical petition function
for a system, those boatswain's. This is called
Bose Einstein Statistics You. We are familiar with
Einstein already from discussions of Brownian
motion and the acceptance of statistical physics
and atoms earlier in this course, and those popped
up in the as the namesake of bosons. They were
working again less than one hundred years ago, so
gradually approaching the more modern day
developments in physics and the question now is,
given our usual definition for the grand economic
competition function that I have just repeated
here, we have to organize the some of our
microstates of. Our usual exponential factor and
involves both the temperature and chemical
potential, as well as the full internal energy for
each micro stage and the fluctuating number of
particles. We take that sum and we organize it by
considering each energy level and turn. And then.
Something over all of the possible occupation
numbers for each of those energy levels and in the
case of those bosun's, you just stated that the
possible occupation number can be any integer that
is not negative. So the natural numbers, including
zero, is what that terminology refers to and smell
ranging from zero one, two, three up to infinity.
So to start off with the simplest case of build up
from there, we can consider a system that has just
a single energy level that is not and the
corresponding energy of a particle in this energy
level is a capital E not.
And with a single energy level, with a fixed
energy, each microstates is given simply by the
number of particles that occupy that energy level,
the occupation number, in other words. And yes,
this gap is here in part to warn you or apologize
for some of the awkward notation that we have at
this point. So what is the total energy of. This
microstates Omega's alive that has an occupation
number and not that is the total number of
particles.
One of.
Yes, all I heard was big enough, which is. Equal
to the occupation number times, the energy of the
level being occupied and we say.
Sorry for having this location in which we have
the same symbol to Capital E for both the. Energy
corresponding to an energy level that is the
energy of any individual particle in the energy
level. And with the subscript I have, the total
energy for the micro state of mega sopi that we've
been working with Altarum so far, so we have to.
Be careful and keep in mind which capital E
corresponds to the energy level and which
corresponds to the micro stage. This is possible
if we go through things carefully and I will try
to be clear about that going forward. So. We have
the set up with a single energy level and. All of
the possible microstates. Are you surprised by how
many particles occupy that energy levels of this
occupation? No, and not for the energy that ranges
from zero up to infinity. They're plugging in to
the general expression for the great economic
competition function that we drive last week. We
have the particle number and supply for the
microstates is that occupation number and not
times the chemical potential. The overall energy
supply for the microstates is the energy of the
energy level and at times that number of particles.
So we can. Plug in the. Energy to the energy level
rather than the total microstates, and pull this
common factor of the occupation number out of the
exponential factor. Which we can recognize then as.
This exponential factor. The exponential of the
difference between the energy of this energy level,
minus the chemical potential divided by the
temperature, which is one over beta, the whole
exponential is then raised to the power of the
occupation. No. And this sum defines the geometric
series, one over one minus X is equal to one plus
X plus X squared and so on. So we can.
Essentially carry out the same analytically and
end up with just the fraction of one over one
minus the exponential factor of the energy in
minus chemical potential. That quantity divided by
the temperature.
And some of you are frowning because you may
recall that the geometric series only converges in
a limited range of X, so identifying this X as an
exponential factor in order to have a convergence,
non-competition function for the simple system
with a single energy level, we have to require
that this exponential factor be smaller than one
in magnitude. You can actually see that as an
exponential. It is always going to be positive. So
it is between zero and one and four natural
systems where data is positive. We also want the
overall exponent of the argument of the
exponential to be a. Negative number overall. But
only we can take the blood of both sides of this
inequality to see that negative data times.
Well.
That difference, in my view, is to be less than
zero. Well, the point about the negative side is
that both of these factors, when multiplied
together, have to be greater than zero with beta
being created in zero for a natural system with
the possible temperature. That requires that the
other factor in the parentheses also means to be
positive. In other words, the chemical potential
has to be less than the energy in this energy
level that we argued yesterday can be shifted to
be a non negative real number without loss of
generality. So this will this constraint for the
conversions of the Bose Einstein grand canonical
partition function is consistent with the
generically negative chemical potentials that we
discussed when formulating the grand canonical
ensemble. And we'll just have to keep in mind that
the protection function itself, even for the
simple case of a single energy level, is only
defined in this regime
where the chemical potential is less than the
energy of the energy level.
So I'll charge forward now with the generalization
of that geometric series in the case of multiple
energy levels. We get labeled by the subscript
Heilbrunn, ranging from zero to some countable
upper limit so that we can take to infinity if we
are so inclined. And. Thanks to still considering
only ideal systems, if not interacting particles,
it is pretty trivial to write down the total.
Energy and particle phone number for.
Any given micro state defined by the occupation
numbers for all plus one of these energy levels.
So this is, again, where we see some suboptimal
mutation that.
For a particular microstates, we have a total
internal energy supply, antiparticle number and
supply. The state is defined by the occupation
numbers for all of the energy levels that we have
and the total number of particles is just the sum
over how many particles are in each of those
energy levels. So the sum over the occupation
numbers. The total energy we also need to account
for the energy carried by each of those particles
in each energy level. So we have some overall plus
one energy levels. Of the corresponding energy for
each particle in the energy levels of Izabel,
which differs from Sevi. Multiplied by the
occupation number, the total number of particles
and the corresponding energy level.
And the next line we just plug. These two
expressions into the general result for. The
granting of legal protection function, the minus
beta times used by my minus of principly. There it
is on the screen. We have Solms over él for both
survive and survive. There's a common factor of
the occupation number for each generation level
that we could again pull out of both the energy
and particle, no terms in the economical
protection function. And then. For the energy term,
we also bring in the.
Value of the energy for his energy level,
something within the sum over all of those energy
levels with that overall factor of beer and then.
Out front, the sum of a microstates turns into a
sum over all possible. Occupation numbers for all
of these plus one energy level, so the occupation
number for the zeroth energy level similar to the
one we considered isolation previously ranging
from zero to infinity. Similarly for the
occupation number of the first excited energy
level. And so one zero to infinity and then sums
over all of those and said L up to the maximum
value.
Now, pulling out the summit, the exponential and
converting that to a product, the usual rules for
manipulating the exponential function. You can
write things.
In terms of this product over electoral initial
factors rather than exponential of a sum of the
terms. And then rearrange.
The terms in the songs to distribute the terms
that depend on not. To be summoned over and not
separately, this is. Thanks to that non
interactive nature of the particles, some of the
lead pull out the terms that depend on a one to a
separate cell and one in all the way through all
of these factors and in each case. We have a
requirement that the chemical potential be less
than the corresponding energy value in this energy
level, which allows each of these L'il plus one
factors to be converted to that one over one by
this ex through the geometric series. So we end up
with some.
Overall energy, we end up with the product overall
energy levels. Of. One over one month, exponential
factors where the exponential depends still on the
value of the energy in that energy level. So
looking back to
the previous page, when we had just a single
energy level, we had just a single factor of the
geometric series, one over one minus our
exponential factor. Generalizing to multiple
energy levels just requires generalizing that
result to involve the product of. Similar, though
not identical, factors that depend on the energies
of each level. But have the same form of one over
this quantity, one minus the exponential, so the
structure as a product of independent
contributions for each energy level is. A little
reminiscent of the classical approach where we
were able to identify and particle canonical
protection functions as the product of any single
particle non-competition functions up to issues of
overcounting in the case of indistinguishable
particles. Which become challenging to deal with
when there may be multiple occupancy for
individual energy levels. I want to highlight here
is.
That this sort of behavior is purely general, at
least of ideal systems, general enough that it has
a technical term, we say that the calculation
factor rises into a product over. The much simpler
calculation for a single. Incidents, either a
single particle in the classical case or a single
energy level in the quantum case and thanks to
this factorization, the full result in this case
for the economical partition function. Can build
up on the basis of much easier. Computations for
that single energy level that we started off with.
And I mentioned that this is fairly generic and
not interacting case, we actually could have
identified this already yesterday. We're looking
at classical Mexico Huelsman statistics, I'll
remind you. In this equation, 87, that the.
Economic competition function for classical next
for both six was the exponential of a sum over
exponential that depend on the energy level. So
doing the same manipulation of bringing that some
out into the form of a product over these
exponential gives a more explicitly factories form
for this classical partition function. Now we have
a product over energy levels of the exponential of
the exponential. That depends on the difference
between the energy of the level and the chemical
potential.
So.
This is a brief look ahead in a few weeks,
possibly even before the term rape will start to
look at not ideal systems in which interactions
between. The different particles can modify the
energy of a given micro state or energy level,
which. We can now appreciate the reason why. The
calculations become vastly more difficult in that
case, because we can no longer bring up the end
particle computation can no longer factories that.
Into a simple product of calculations out there
for single particles or single energy levels.
So Paul is here to see if there are questions
about factorization or about the result that we
have in equation eighty six for those statistics,
the grand economic competition function, that is
the basis for all predictions of systems of
bosun's.
And not seeing any. In the room, or mostly you can.
We have plenty of time to do the same procedure
for the case of fermions precisely because it is
effectively the same procedure.
And the. The result that we will get in this case
for the consciousness is that fermions is also
named after Fairmead, along with the English
physicist Paul Dirac. Come on. It was working.
They were all working around the middle of the
20th century.
So.
We again take the same approach of considering
just first a single particular energy level, that
same. Ease of knots with energy, not an occupation
number and not the only difference with respect to
the physics of on is that the possible occupation
numbers now no longer run over all non-negative
integers, but can only be zero or one thinks that
the exclusion principle, the. The fact that
multiple fermions are forbidden from occupying the
same energy level. And OK, with only two terms of
disarm, we don't get anything from writing it as a
song, you might as well just write out those two
terms. When the occupation number for this single
energy level is zero, this exponential factor is
just one. And the other term corresponds to single
occupancy, occupation, number of one that we pick
up that exponential factor and not set to one.
And during the. Same approach of plugging in. My
energies and particle numbers for systems of
multiple energy levels.
We have.
The exponential factor of this sum over the total
microwave energy use of L.A. Times and Zippel,
something over all of the energy levels, just as
we had before, and the. Particle numbers come from
a similar sum just over the occupation numbers
themselves. So this is. Very nearly the same
expression that we had for those Einstein
statistics. Again, the only change is the upper
limits observation of each of these. Now, one
comes over occupation numbers that no longer go
from zero to infinity, but instead in each case
and at one. So breaking up the.
Some of exponential is into the product of the
different terms for each of these different
occupation numbers, for the helpless one,
different energy levels. You see the same sort of
factorization.
We're now the factor that is being multiplied by
its that is being multiplied for each of these
different energy levels, ranging from zero up to L
with a different value for the energy. And the
level is just this these two terms, one plus the
exponential factor that depends on the difference
between the energy and chemical potential. So one
big change here coming from the different range of
summation is that we don't have to worry at all
about conversions for not applying energy network
series identities or just multiplying a bunch of
factors together. So in fairly direct statistics,
there is no constraint on the possible arguments
of this exponential factor, the way that there
were in the the Bose Einstein case. And also, if
we look back to classical Mexico statistics, we
also did not have to worry about the convergence
of these storms in that case. So both track and.
Classical bultman statistics can handle. Any
relation between the chemical potential and the
enemies of a given level?
And we are. Almost in the position to analyze
quantum gases that consist of either bosun's or
fermions, looking at the. Interviews, energy use,
particle numbers and eventually the equation of
states. But before we get into that. I promise to.
Justified, post hoc, some of the claims that I
made to motivate the different approach of quantum
physics compared to classical statistics, if we
can do, is by figuring out and analyzing the
so-called classical limits where. We expect I have
claimed that. The classical natural bowsman grand
canonical competition function can remain an
excellent approximation to quantum statistics. We
can. Imagine if we've done everything right, that
this should be the case, reflecting the fact that
physicists were working for decades or even
centuries without any hint that the universe was
governed by quantum mechanics. So in the
accessible. Domains of experiments that could be
done up until the 20th century, classical physics
was indeed an excellent approximation to the true
underlying quantum nature of reality.
So you want to figure out where this classical
limits should be or where the quantum physics
effectively reduces to the classical analysis that
we started off with? To see that all of these.
Of the claims that we have made are
self-consistent.
Well, the way to proceed is to turn that question
on its head and ask not where do we expect all of
these different economic competition functions to
produce the same results, but instead to ask where?
We expect them to differ, we would expect quantum
statistics to be needed. So that is in the case
where. There were over accounting problems in the
classical approach that corresponded to. Having
non negligible probabilities for multiple articles
occupying the same energy level, and this actually
connects to
something that we considered back in our
development of economical ensemble, as well as in
that first homework assignment where we looked at
classical spin systems, keeping these keeping
their energy levels discreet and considering in
particular the low and high temperature limits of
those classical systems. And the. Probabilities
that. The system may find itself in any given
state, and in particular the probability that it
may find itself in its lowest energy state, the
crown stage compared to. Energy states with higher
energies, so we saw. In class and at low
temperatures, predictions for years, like the
average energy and acknowledgeable approach as
well as the entropy, were dominated by those
ground states, the microstates with the lowest
possible energies. And microstates to the higher
energy levels were exponentially suppressed, which.
In the grand political context, we can interpret
as exponentially small probabilities for the
particles to occupy any of those higher energy
states or any of the energy levels with larger
energies. Or to put that another way, in that low
temperature regime. All of the particles want to
fall into the lowest energy level that is
available to them, to the ground state, which
effectively guarantees that this ground state will
have multiple occupancy. And the overcounting
corrections that we did in the classical case and
the resulting classical physics will break down as
a consequence. So the conclusion of this argument
based on work we did last month, is that the low
temperature. Should be a regime in which we expect
quantum and classical statistics to differ,
whereas in contrast, it is at high temperatures.
That we should expect both the quantum and
classical calculations to produce very similar
results, which is what we've been calling the
classical limits. I've got some statistics. And I
appreciate that the arguments I just went through
to motivate considering the high temperature
regime of quantum statistics as to the place where
that quantum statistics should look effectively,
classical is fairly qualitative and an handwaving.
If you want something a bit more detailed and
concrete, there is a derivation that can be done
based on considering the different wavelength and
the context of the equation of state. That's in
one of the sets of lecture notes referenced as a
further reading on page five. I see that time is
just about up for today. So. We will wrap up the
demonstration that high temperatures correspond to
the classical events on Friday. And just to
briefly look forward to that, the. Next up, we
will take on Friday is to consider the Grand Canal,
the collapse of oil at high temperatures. In the
case of all three of the different types of
statistics that we've been considering, the
classical Marc Saltzman case and the two possible
quantum statistics, that's.
Correspond to either exotic particles, supposing
science statistics or thermionic particles that
interact sophisticated, and we will hope to see
that they all agree in that classical limit. We
will have to be very careful in order to reach
that conclusion just due to some use in working
with the grand canonical ensemble at high
temperatures in particular related to the way that
the particle no, which can fluctuate in the great
approach, the way in which that particle no
depends on the temperature as a temperature.
That's the forecast for Friday. We will look at
that particular regime of the statistics we have
derived today. So I will see you then, unless
there are media questions about those on the
fermions or the resulting in differing sets of
statistics right now.
You had a few days to think about that and come up
with any questions to bring to me on Friday. I'll
look forward to seeing all that.