OK, the bells have rung, so it's time for me to get
under way, even though I'm still getting
everything in order today.  We can start with the
usual six digit code for this afternoon:
Four nine, three eight, nine
seven.
See if there are any questions about
the quantum gases we've been going through this week,
or anything else in the course so far, or even coming up.
There was a bit of discussion on the Canvas site forums
about historical developments of some of the
concepts we've been dealing with, in particular
entropy, and there'll be a bit more historical
commentary in the exercise I have planned for today,
but I'm going to somewhat violate the principle I
proposed online and give a lot of credit to a
particular individual for introducing a new idea.
But I won't give to that right away.
Instead of.
It's very briefly in the couple of minutes to
elaborate on some topics that came up during the
lectures, which might benefit from a bit more
background information, at least for those who
aren't already familiar with the. And the first
actually was when I was pulling up in my window
when it started.
Which has to do with the. Details of photons that
we discussed earlier this week, I'm not sure why
that the search, but.
I've collected a few visualizations of.
We used to picture those photons and in particular,
their connection to electric and magnetic waves or
electromagnetic waves, which may well be familiar
to some of you from previous modules, but could be
useful if you don't have a picture to guide
intuition as to why photons are waves like they
have a wave, like the frequency and how they're
connected to the. Electric magnetic fields and a
particular electromagnetic radiation that's just
trying to zoom in on one of these illustrations at
a time, because all the flashing at once may not
be easiest to understand the not going into any
technical details about this. This is more picture
to date intuition that we have electric fields
here showing is red and magnetic fields shown is
blue that oscillates in relation with each other
here. They don't have any phase shifts, so they
have maximum minima at the same point. And as they
oscillate.
That corresponds to a propagation of energy, the
form of photons you're going along this area off
to the right of the screen. Where the distance
between subsequent Mexico in each of these
oscillations defines the wavelength of. This wave,
which we interpret as the wave length of the
photon and the number of. That signals that.
The radiation dose through each second then
combines with the wave length to determine the
speed with which this radiation is propagating,
which Maxwell famously found to be the speed of
light to be able to identify light as precisely
these fluctuations in electromagnetic radiation.
The main points of figures that are collected on
this page, all the from the camp site later today
is the two polarizations states that were
mentioned in the lecture. For this, we have what
you get is certainly electric fields are
oscillating the vertical direction perpendicular
to the fields in the horizontal direction is
what's known as a linear polarization of light.
And there's a second one where. This picture is
just tilted 90 degrees outside so that the fields
are possibly in total direction, the way we had
field is inflated vertically.
What is another way of. Representing these two
photon polarizations is actually two.
On. Essentially. Interpolate between them as time
goes on each of these cycles. So that you did
point in the cycle. I could feel the same be
oriented on the portable axis this year and the
extreme volatility cycle, it gets around to the
vertical axis. So there's a picture of the
polarizations of tracing out the circle. That goes
along with the frequency of this wave, rather than
drawing that with my fingers, I can just.
The other two. Illustrations on this page, which
are linked to further discussions and.
During that interpolation of the electric
orientation, Qasm decided to desired.
Leads to what's called circular polarization,
which can precede that either in two ways,
depending on what you trace around. In a clockwise
or counterclockwise direction, as the cycles pass
passed, they still have wavelength separating the
peaks and electric fields and the clear
propagation in this case still always to the right
side of the screen. And here's a. Sort of like a
where treaty out the direction that the electorate
is changing with the figures and then the sun is
pointing in the direction of propagation for the
whole rest of time. Similarly, the other faiths
that we treat is the ultimate direction of
propagation and that the left hand pointed in the
direction of propagation I of propagation rather
than rotation. The two circular polarization sets
of photons is evolving linear combinations of the
linear polarization states. Provided those two
extra generous energy levels for. Any given energy
level that we any given energy, any combination of
momentum that we have for photons or will be for
any other mass, this particle covered by its
wavelength or frequency. So hopefully that is
useful and not just. Making things more confusing
for those who haven't. Seen. These details of U.S.
preventive radiation and its interpretation is
photons before. Are there immediate questions on
that topic? Yeah, with the words that you said
there was the energy that was not.
So. With everything else the same, those two ways
of sort of things are going to degenerate into
battles that they've brought in as an overall
factor to our calculations. Earlier this week. So
it sounds like it's cleared up. Might not have
presented so clearly
what other further questions about so-called.
You seem to be thinking about. Ms. We can always
come back to this.
There was one other. For Tom DeLay, the topic that
I mentioned in passing, that is sort of fun to
take a look at a bit more deeply than exercise for
you to go through this. I'll try not to take up
too much of your time in the tutorial, but that
connects to the cosmic microwave background
radiation and the particular mentioned in passing
that these sorts of measurements of the
temperature of the cosmic microwave background.
Provide evidence for the existence of dark matter,
which is ongoing research, trying to figure out
the properties and the fundamental nature of dark
matter, interpreted as some new set of particles
that are as yet unknown in fundamental theories of
physics. And a
quick reminder, this cosmic background radiation
is left over from. About three hundred eighty
thousand years after the Big Bang, the universe
cooled enough for the plasma of electrons and
protons to combine into neutral atoms and wildlife
to propagate its propagating for thirteen point
eight billion years since then, before reaching us
to form this sort of pattern. And what we didn't
go over and lectures was. How these patterns of
those complaints and rules are sorry, those are
the hot emails of the contractures, different
Bibles, one part in 10000 around the average
temperature. Those depend on dark matter through
the dynamics of the Spurtle universe plasma, which
is affected by precisely what particles are in
that plasma and how they're all interacting with
each other, going through those calculations,
which is sort of the module itself, leaves a six
parameter expression for
things like the behavior of the cosmic microwave
background. Indeed, all other cosmological aspects
of the early universe. This is known as Lambdas
Kvamme model, where
Lambda refers to what's known as Dark Energy,
which will be mentioned briefly in the lecture on
Monday. And KVAMME stands for cold dark matter,
cold, meaning that this is a non relativistic gas
of not interacting particles.
And.
I have printed out here the usual way, which I
have to zoom out the usual way of.
Mathematically analyzed those patterns of
temperature fluctuations in the cosmic microwave
background, which I think I mentioned in class, is
to look at the correlations between those
different points, which here are plotted on two
equivalents, horizontal axis, one being a multiple
moments and the other being the corresponding
angular scale over which we are looking for
correlations. So to take a quick step back to this
figure, the idea is this is the projection of the
entire sky on two dimensions. So distances in here
correspond to angular separations looking in one
direction and then another separated by some angle.
You can spin to fix that angle. Look at all
possible orientations and all possible
translation's the night sky. And the product of
the energy is coming in at those two angles, some
integrated over orientation's translation's gives
this simple angular spectrum that corresponds to
the vertical axis plotted against the angular
scales. So maybe the simple limit is a 90 degree
separation. On this plot, which is a dipole. And
then looking at.
Points that are more and more closely aligned in
their angle. Corresponds to higher multiple
moments in in that expansion. It's probably easier
at first glance to interpret this in terms of that
scale, looking at points that are two degrees
apart, half a degree apart, or even smaller
angular scales where. The line on this graph,
which is coming from
a few years ago, that still this.
This was based on the release of the first three
years of data by the Wilkinson Microwave Software
Program, which was in 2006 and provided the first
resolution of the second peak in the spectrum
power spectrum here, getting below the half a
degree and separation. The functional form of the
line that is being fit to all these data from that
experiment and the earlier experiments that were
mostly based on the earth that are high up the
balance or carried balloons to try to avoid.
Interference from the Earth's atmosphere.
Is precisely given by the six parameter
expression's. Michael, respond to that dark energy
and dark matter model of cosmology, of which the
key feature is the second and third piece in the
singular power spectrum being roughly the same
height, about twenty five hundred in these units
of Microtel squared. And to give a.
Slight contrast illustrates how that matters. But
it has to do with dark energy. This figure from
just a few years later, which is using a lot of
the same data with some improvements around that
third peak, you're showing two different
predictions for this angular power spectrum. In
terms of that multiple woman that's now, but that
is again plotted on a logarithmic scale, the
dotted lines are the predictions of the CDM, but
more generally, what is predicted if. Not
relativistic dark matter exists. And the salad
line is from it's called modified gravity. The
idea that dark matter doesn't actually exist,
there's some change to Newton's laws of gravity
that has to be taken into account in large
cosmological scales to explain. Explain what
appears to be. Dark matter and things like
galactic rotation curves, and even 10 years ago
from these data, it was. Very strongly confirmed
that the data themselves are following the we're
in agreement with the predictions coming from
hypothesising dark matter and strongly ruling out
modifications to gravity that can explain other
evidence for dark matter, coming from galaxies, a
galaxy, clusters. So this is.
Really, what gives us confidence that dark matter
exists and allows a lot of research to continue to
go into figuring out precisely what that dark
matter consists of and how it interacts with the
ordinary. Of particles and fields that we are
familiar with. So that was a brief
introduction to that ongoing topic in modern
physics research, new questions about it before I
give you something more interesting to actually do
yourselves.
So.
And in the spirit of confronting.
Observations or experimental measurements with.
Predictions, this case predictions from
statistical physics
think it would be fun to. Step back a bit to kind
of things we were doing about a month ago, Unit
three on the economic loss of. We started
considering a solid system that was formed of
these spins that.
Soon to be oriented either up or down and
interacted with the magnetic field of strength
given by age. And forming a solid out of these
spins, which will allow us to distinguish between,
well, that allowed us to make the contrast between
distinguishable spins that are at a fixed location
in the solid and indistinguishable spins that are
in a gas allowed to move around so that they can't
be told apart by observation, observation we
computed be distinguishable case. That the energy
of a solid formed of energy spins was this simple,
hyperbolic tangent function of the inverse
temperature data helps make the field strength.
Which we can put into our calculations for our
definition of the heat capacity to get a
prediction from. Statistical physics to compare
with experimental measurements, which are the data
points on this figure, which those data are. Can
you tell me about 50 years old now, but suffice to.
Cover the temperature dependence of the heat
capacities for several different solid materials
level women and diamonds, both in the low
temperature regime with the heat capacity. It's
got to be very small to be banished to the limit
of absolute zero and the high temperature regime
leadership capacities all approach some constant
limiting factor. So the first exercise is to check
with the result that we have for the energy, how
well we can reproduce. These data points actually
mentioned that experimentally it's much easier to
measure the cost of pressure rather than how to
bowl. So as you increase the temperature we've
seen in the context of actual gases, for instance,
that the volume pressure, although those will tend
to increase. So you have to exert more force to
keep the volume constant for if you exert the same
amount of force, you end up with a variable. So
the sudden curves out here are for the heat
capacity, a constant volume, even though the data
points are for the capacity and pressure. The
effect of those two definitions of heat capacity
is something that we could ignore, at least for
our purposes.
And maybe I can.
Just pause the recording now to be five minutes to
compute that acetate and see how it compares to
the data points that are on this plot, at least in
their qualitative shape of dropping to zero at low
temperature and increasing to subcontinent's at
higher temperatures.
That was my favorite time going on. How are you
getting on with this is actually motivation for
the legal problems still to come up?
Do you have a. Expression for the heat capacity
from this energy.
They just let go of the system. So
let's be clear
in the public
square, the problems facing the nation that shows
up with the camera there.
So I agree with that, except for the negative side.
Which.
Because there are two ways to resolve that, one is
by changing the variables to differentiate to
better. The other is by the chamber with the one
over temperature and ability there and the
argument that you're not. So I think you see now
an agreement, several.
What to do with this will be my first and
time.
We think about the looks, I'm sure, which is
building increased temperatures close to infinity,
then this heat capacity reduces to
mean something on live off the factors of
proportionality. That's hyperbolic. Cosine square
is a sum of either the better age plus or minus
that age as being opposed to infinity that
exponentially dominates and we end up with
something better over the cumulative.
To the square, which does indeed go to zero zero
exponentially quickly in the inverse temperature,
so that these degrees with the zero emission
limits of these experiments, we measure heat
capacities.
Although I'll mention that the functional form of
exponential attendance is incorrect, but at least
it's getting the right limiting value of zero.
It's the high commission that's available in
Europe where things are more interesting here,
hyperbolic, cosine goes to one. Catchable.
Zero is one, and then we have just in Times Square,
each square
one goes to zero, in this case quite dramatically
in the universe temperature, which is not what is
measured experimentally. And in fact, there is an
even bigger issue that these experimental
measurements were done without any external by the
field at zero. So I guess the trigger response is
that capacity is always zero, that what we can
take that as a model for the functional form of
the heat capacity. And so we're going to pull up.
While we're working on that, but wasn't able to,
was the.
We thought plot of what? Was being predicted.
For some reason, it's not.
That is updating itself, the capacity normalize by
and so part of the sea over in versus either the
age or the temperature over age. So it's a simple
function once we put things in terms of X equals V
at a time stage. This is just X squared over the
sides where she was zero at the height of the
multimeter limits and changing the variables to
plot things in terms of the temperature like we
had from that experimental data. We see a nice
drop off to zero that's just too steep being
exponential rather than it turns out the
experimental measurements are best fit by a power
T cubed because you go to work for. But the big
issue is that as soon as the heat capacity.
Increases to a little under point five per
particle. That's exactly where the. Hyperbolic,
cosine undersecretary's starts to die off and one
over. Temperatures square from the famous square
starts to kick in and push things back down to
zero. In this case, the quadratic equations,
rather than exponential hopping back to what we
want to match, it doesn't match. Not even
qualitatively in that high temperature limit, and
this is not entirely due to the simplicity of
modeling solids is just upward or downward extends.
Somewhat of a silly or unrealistic model, even
with more or better justified models of solids.
The predictions for the heat capacity obtained
through classical statistical mechanics methods in
classical models of. The solids were not
reproducing. He capacity's that the experiment
measured even as late as the 18th or as early as
the eighteen hundreds. This was a known issue and
a fellow named Einstein attempted to address. With
some inspiration from his solution to the
photoelectric effect, which was another one of his
breakthroughs in his miracle, 019 of thoughts and
addition to showing that Brownian motion can be
explained on the basis of statistical physics, he
took one of the first steps towards quantum
mechanics by solving or proposing a solution to
puzzling experimental measurements known as the
electric effect, which don't have time to really
get into here. And it's not really relevant to
statistical physics. But the take away was the
proposal that. Energy had to be quantize in the
context of the interactions of lights and sirens
and just a couple of years later.
At the insights that taking a similar approach to
quantize the energies could help to resolve the
disagreement between these experimental heat
capacity measurements and classical theoretical
predictions, classical here being not quantum. So
the idea is maybe just.
Appreciate it. Again, with the picture rather than
a bunch of words there. This is the basic model
for a solid that he proposed where he tried to
simplify things as much as possible. By focusing
on. The. The energies that are at play rather than
the detailed balance of forces that is being
pictured is holding at odds with the solid in
place. This is just around the time the ads were
no longer being a theoretical construction or
turning into something that people thought
actually existed. So building a solid out of a
bunch of atoms is a regular array leads to the
question of how the atoms are fixed to their given
distinguishable positions. And the simple way of
bottling this is to say that all of these atoms
are interacting in some way with the atoms around
them.
So that whenever one tries to move, sort of is
pushed back by the adults around it, that's the
jagged lines here can be thought of kind of like
springs that are pulling all of the adults in
position. And then it becomes a very complicated
exercise to try to model how those atoms are
interacting with each other. We're all connected
to each other and that's independent, not
interested in degrees of freedom. So the idea is
ignore all of the details of interactions between
neighbouring atoms and just focus on the amount of
energy that's stored in each of these oscillators.
The.
The picture of the cell that's being proposed is
that. These interactions with these friends can be
represented as degrees of freedom that have some
energy and as I was growing up with that, that
could affect your proposal, is that the energy
that these oscillators have by virtue of the
interactions between neighboring atoms is
quantized. In terms of conservation times, some
characteristic frequency that is the same for all
of the oscillators in the cell, and this is. Well,
the fantastic simplification, because now, even
though we're modeling lots of interactions between
neighbouring particles, if we look at the physics
of the oscillators themselves, those are not
interactive degrees of freedom. And we can analyze
them using the statistical physics methods we've
produced up till now particularly. We can start
already in the canonical example.
By. Fixing the overall energy that is present in
the south, it's going to be dependent on
temperature, will be solid as gas, whatever that
temperature is, if some amount of energy that can
be distributed among the and different oscillators
in the system. I mentioned in passing that the
oscillators depend both on the number of atoms
that there are, as well as how they are laid out.
So can this square lattice, there are two
independent possibilities for each atom, and that
could rise to three independent oscillators per
atom, three dimensional cubic lattice. It's also
three different lattice structures that have
different members of your neighbors. Things like
the honeycomb lattice that shows up in graphene,
for instance, has somewhat different counting in
this. Setting that aside for the moment and
working in terms of a fixed number of oscillators.
So that will be our end rather than the number of
atoms. They can go through sort of four step
process to get from the definition of the small.
In the microeconomic ensemble to capacity, as
usual, I've gone on longer than I expected with
the introduction of things today, so Will. Just.
They believe a lot of the detailed work for you to
work on over the coming week and dive back into
this just before the break. Next week.
Maybe even.
When they police say. We're just a complete
misrepresentation of the calculation at hand in
the microcosmic ensemble. We're fixing the amount
of energy which we divide into some number of
these quanta, each with units of mega.
And the first question is, what is the total
number of microstates that designed ISIS can have
with that fixed amount of energy being distributed
among a fixed amount of oscillators? So this case
is an integer counting the units of.
Quantize energy levels can be distributed among
all the oscillators and then from the total number
of microstates going through the same sort of
calculations that we've done over the. First of
all, to this cause, we can extract the entropy,
the temperature and energy and from there and
ultimately the heat capacity to be compared with
experiment. So. Just stop there. Get started in
the next five minutes or save this
free time over the coming week, in the end,
hopefully you should see a significant improvement
compared to. What we had from the system, but room
for further improvement will turn out to be
possible.
You may get into that. Once we start possibly next
week, so. Just wrap up the recording and leave you
with this problem for the next five minutes plus
five days, are there any questions about the setup
that we should clarify it before you? We'll get to
it.
One check of the work that she neglected to
mention is. It's comparing predictions with I it a
minimal three hospital system. We can set up.
Three atoms, each pair of them connected by one of
these oscillators. That's. It's simple enough that.
For the small.
Number of energy units can be checked explicitly
that the total number of microstates matches
functional form in terms of and hoc.