Well, the bills have rung and we're all back again for the
last bit of Statistical Physics for this week.
With the
new six-digit code two seven two seven five seven
And, yeah
the tutorial gives us a chance to talk about some stuff
beyond the main core of the lecture notes, some
stuff that may not appear on the exams.  It occurred to
me that those of you---either here at the moment or
catching up with this recording after the fact---I'm
not sure how
thoroughly you've gone through all of the stuff
that was posted to the "Modules" page on
Canvas for this module.  There is this article
from just a few months ago, November 2021,
talking about the title of "The Demons
Haunting Thermodynamics", which looks better when it's
spread across two pages side by side. But the work
we've been doing with the mixing entropy. The
Gibbs paradox in the general thought experiment of
bringing two systems together, letting them
exchange particles and seeing whether the
resulting change in entropy is consistent with the
second law of thermodynamics is the spots in this
module where. This particular article becomes
relevant and interesting in particular, if I can
zoom in on.
One of these figures here, I guess that is the.
Highest level of zoom, the cameras will let me do.
It's embedded screen share.
Which I guess will suffice. This is an
illustration of a concept sort of similar to the
games paradox and statistical physics, say similar
sort of thought experiments known as Maxwell's
demon. The idea being that if we have these two
ideal gases, so each of these screening, the
particle has the momentum bouncing around each of
two containers separated by a wall. The question
of the thought experiment is what if there were
some way for someone to choose which of these
particles moves from one of these points to the
other, depending on their properties? And the
specific properties that Maxwell considered was
saying there was even some device that. Could tell
the energy of any particle that approached it and
depending on whether that energy were relatively
high compared to those particular articles in this
case, because of that particle, absolutely nothing
to keep it unless there was already there. On the
other hand, if the particle energy were relatively
low, it could be the returns. This container on
the. It's a very big. So if that sort of process.
Could be implemented not necessarily by a demonic
creature or by some clever device or the rotating
door ratchet system that was sensitive to particle
energy using the particles to pass or be blocked
depending on those energies. Then what would
happen over time that we started off with? U.S.
civilians have the same temperature. As the higher
energy particles were allowed to congregate or
accumulate in the left volume, the average
internal energy that supported would increase as
its temperature super hot new gas that the
internal energy is directly proportional to the
temperature of the gas.
And at the same time, the opposite can happen and
the other supporting entities that are opposing
would all come lower than the average for those
two systems leading to a lower. Temperatures have
started from two systems with the same temperature.
This demon would cause a net flow of energy from
one of those systems to the other reason, the
temperature of one, lowering the temperature of
another, sort of the opposite of what we expect
from the second law of thermodynamics. So
violation of that second law. And now this, of
course, started off as a thought experiment in the
eighteen hundreds, which is why it features this
demonic entity controlling the. Passage of these
particles depending on their energy. But there are
ongoing experiments that do this sort of thing.
This is an illustration of. From about 10 years
ago, which rather than having. A bunch of
particles of gas between them, it had particles in
what was called an optical lattice, so shiny laser
beams across each other to create the potential
that particles could interact with. And those
particles were the optical lattice out in such a
way. They were a sequence of energy models for
these particles. This energy is represented by the
steps of the surface and the particles. Have
probabilities used to fluctuate, goes down the
staircase as well as at some points and by
imposing a. Opposing the voltage, what is shown
here as the square being put in place by that
natural steam in the provincial department all the
way down the staircase, whenever it happens to
fluctuate up the staircase, they quickly shifted
this block to the next higher set. So what happens
over time with this system is that the particle
cannot move down the staircase. It's blocked
whenever it fluctuates up. The demon blocks of the
new law, also the particle continues to accumulate
a higher and higher energy costs, higher positions
on this dramatic staircase. This is an
experimental realization that even as these
particles are being forced to have higher energies
in this system, that corresponds to a reduction in
the entropy of the system and raises the
possibility of violating the second law of
thermodynamics, the.
The solution that. You have a question, though,
the question is whether or not the second plane
actually is violated in his experience, the answer
to exactly that is not because that information.
Essentially, what is going on is that the action
of this quote unquote demon, the cross, the
procedure by which these blocks are put into place,
also is requires energy to operate and requires
information processor to monitor the energy of the
particles and adjust the water with energy changes.
If you add together, the entropy is not only of
the system, but also of this device, the steam
that is reducing the entropy of the system, the
overall contribution, the entropy coming from the
system. On the one hand, the device on the other
ends up in such a way that it can increase it as
time goes on. So I want to.
We'll go through any more details about that next.
Stephen is one of the funding thought experiments
to talk about in statistical physics related to
the sort of particle mixing processes that we have
been
discussing this weekend and last week. In this
article, as I said, is on the campus site for the
module, if you feel inclined to check out some of
the additional details that it contains, which
also bring up the. There is there are other demons
that have been proposed in thermodynamics history,
including the Pluses Demon, a theoretical entity
that knows the positions and momentum of all
particles in the universe and can thus predict how
the universe as a whole will evolve since the
point of a tutorial is not to. Listen to me talk
or rather have a chance to ask any questions that
you have. Feel free to shout them out, or if you
don't have questions, have something to work on
yourself. I have here. An exercise related to the
mixing entropy that can spend some time working on
to make sure that what we went through, the
example we went through in class is all clear and
in particular. I switch over to the project
briefly, um. When we did the political lexicon.
Thought experiment a few days ago. So this is a
reminder of how the stages are set up with two
nautical systems that are initially separated, the
walls separating them and removed, they're allowed
to exchange particles and then that wall is
reinserted, sort of wrote down the formal
expression materials during the focus, see? Can be
improved.
I guess the expression here is not of so much
importance. The point is that although we wrote it
down, we didn't make an attempt to evaluate it, to
confirm that reinserting this wall, separating the
systems at the final stage does indeed lead to
behavior consistent with the second part from the
entropy is not decreasing as we separate new
systems. So and of course, that was. Only
problematic for the case of distinguishable
particles who were fully indistinguishable
articles in the interview was just constant
throughout this process of removing the wall,
reinserting. But the distinguishable case, there
was culture of mixing in and the question that was
left hanging, that's. It's what happens to the
entropy as. The wall is reinserted, have a more
complicated expression to compute, so that is
through the. The two tasks for this particular
tutorial probably have a chance to work on that
today is. Trying to simplify the setup of. These
distinguishable versus indistinguishable particles
by supposing that. We have. As in the initial case,
two systems with each with particle's and within
each of these two systems, the particles amongst
themselves are indistinguishable. But at the same
time, the particles in one system can be
distinguished from the particles in another system
by some property. Here we are using the color to
do that. We. Color the particles initially left,
when you read those initially in the right volume
or blue, and after we go through that process of
removing the wall, allowing particle mixing
particle exchange and then reinserting the wall,
the red particles and particles, we can expect to
be scrambled between the two we separated boxes.
So in the initial state, we computed the entropy
in class five plus 10 times, the log of this ratio
of the volume to end times the cube of the thermal
deployed wavelength. And the first question for
this case, that is somewhat. Intermediate between.
Or. Distinguishable and indistinguishable
particles is to compute the mixing energy from the
combined system, the intermediate stage is not
shown in this drawing when all two of these
particles have access to the full volume of the
extent to be. So the starting point for that
computation is the protection function for that
combined system where we have to add particles in
this to volume. And.
And of those particles are indistinguishable
amongst themselves. So the overall partition
function. Starts off with the product of to end
single particle production functions. For those
two in particles and then has to compensate for
overcounting, just as we saw in the. Tastefully
indistinguishable particles. The only wrinkle here
is that we are only overcounting by this factor of
whatever and vectorial for the red particles times
one over and vectorial for the blue particles. So
whatever and vectorial squared, which is much
smaller than the one over tumin, actual, real that
we had four fully distinguishable particles. And
then once we have determined the mixing entropy
that arises when the wall is removed and the
system. The second task is to compute the final
entropy. So once the wall is reinserted and we
have mixtures of red of the particles on each side
or each of the two, we separate the systems. The
question is, what is the final entropy that we do
not attempt to compute in class? And in particular,
the question of whether the final entropy obeys
the second law of thermodynamics and ends up
larger than. The entropy of the combined system.
So I'll give you a few minutes to get started on
that. I'll check in again and maybe five minutes
to see how you got involved with. Computing, just
the mixing entropy in the.
Somewhat more straightforward parts compared to
the final entropy, then, depending on how things
are going, we will. See where they go from there.
That was the time to do a quick check in how
you're getting on, whether you have a result for
this first task or it's more time to keep working
on that.
It's.
Syncope is the difference between the entropy of
the combined system minus that of the initial
system. This. Anyone done with that calculation
wants to. Shout out to the result they got or. So
they want to say they want more time to keep
working on that part of things.
Is that. Sounds like we're still working, said
another five minutes time check, checking again.
And after that point, to pause the recording a bit
more promptly at this time.
Since we're back now to address a question and
I'll switch over to the projector from your Web
browser.
And to
add a little bit of confusion to. This picture
that we have here still zoomed in a bit more and
then each of these.
Two compartments that are separated by a wall. We
have the same temperature, volume and number of
particles.
On each side, the total value, what's the system
is combined. So in the divine system. We have that
going to be with two particles and then once the
system is or the systems are separated, that will
be inserted. Then there is just particles in each
box to avoid being so. I don't know why the. Focus
on the overhead projector is so bad, but hopefully
that clarifies a bit what? Shown here, this is not
letting me zoom in anymore. So it sounds like some
of you have moved on from the. Mixing entropy
computation to computing the final entropy. So.
You get another minute or two. I'll check in again
about the result for the first half. See if that's
worth going over on the recording.
And.
You all the recording is underway, I'll mention a
identity that may prove useful in that second part,
which is a relation between. The. Three binomial
coefficients, particularly relating binomial
coefficient of two, and she was then would be some
of the squares, the binomial coefficients for and
she was K for all K from zero to end. And then in
Europe, this tends to be known as the abandonment
identity.
Or Bannerman's Identity, which was published in 17
70s, about four hundred fifty years after it had
been derived by its Chinese mathematician, Zhou
Shuja, which whose name I obviously cannot
pronounce, I apologize for the butchering of
however it is meant to be pronounced properly.
This fellow came up with this identity that will
be useful in the second part.
No one system is no longer filling the screen, you
came up with that more than seven hundred years
ago.
Download the file. It would be a bit more. Well
behaved.
Yes, that is certainly more flexible.
Plus, the recording, again, for. Another few
minutes.
And if you do finish up with the mixing entropy in
that time, go on to that second task. Keep
yourself busy and just let me know how you're
progressing.
That is the final stretch for this afternoon and
maybe to. Get things wrapped up. I'll see you
again if anyone wants to shout out. A. The result
for the mixing entropy on removing the ball,
dividing the two systems.
Know.
So that's a complicated and more complicated
expression than I have I found
to and more to as this resource for the entropy
when we combine the system compared to the entropy
from the initial state when the system is
separated. It sounds like that was not what you
were finding. Let me go through one or two ways to
calculate this mixing entropy reasonably quickly.
It is possible to start from the proficient
function for that combined system, 50 logarithm to
find out the energy, the derivative of the energy
supply, the residual energy or the entropy. But
there's actually a trick that we can do by
inspecting this partition function carefully here.
The trick is to rewrite the zc as.
A product of two factors
will have to work on the one hand
and left over the other. There were, in fact, all
the other factors
related to.
And what we can do based on this way is recognize
that each of these identical terms is the.
Can I go with a function for an indistinguishable
particles in
two great. There are two factors, not a political
indistinguishable protection function, which is an
interesting result, already said that the once the
barrier is removed and the particles are allowed
to mix in this volume, they behave incredibly
independently of the other. And what we end up
with is, in essence, two copies of an
indistinguishable particles, one copy for the
particles, one be for the particles. The
corresponding entropy then is twice the entropy
for the particles in way to be a very powerful
class.
Size five has crossed
over in the first place. And here's.
All the is in place, if I shift the screen here a
bit to compare that combined entropy with the
starting entropy, what
was?
The Times, the signature factor of five, and it's
allowed.
Everything in the two in the Atlantic will cancel
out what is left is two and two that I claim was
my answer. So.
One possibly surprising thing about this result is
that it is exactly the same as the Fab Four,
completely distinguishable particles as opposed to
this case, or we have two sets of particles that
are in the same cells that are distinguishable
from the other sets. Compared to the fully
distinguishable case, both
biometrically are smaller, there are fewer
microstates exactly makes utility. But the
difference between them removing this wall and
allowing the predators makes. Ends up being
exactly the same, which is something that a nice
aspect of this documentation that I enjoy. There
is also a second way of doing this computation
that wouldn't rely on through our notes or
expression would be indistinguishable entropy or a
number of particles of the bullet. And this other
trick is a bit more generally applicable.
The approach is to recall that the Entropia,
in terms of the HUMBOLDT'S energy, is the negative
derivative with respect to temperature of that
free energy and Freelander yourself, like negative
temperature, climbs more of the partition function.
So putting things together
with all means
and if we look only at.
Differences between countries, which is what this
makes America, is that the purpose of liberty is a
linear alteration and it's an Zitter difference
between.
Two energy is.
This, the partition function system, partition
function, which if I combine those logs and divide
up this product, I use your product rule
derivative of T with respect to T is just more of
the lower the ratio of functions. Lots and lots of
balls of ratio's.
That's visible around the screen, part of the
simplification from this approach is that this
board of protection functions tends to be and is
in this case easily seen to be independent of the
temperature so that this whole second term
vanishes from the outset. And we just have to
compute the logarithm of canonical partition
functions. So we are. Given. The. Partition
function for the combined system. And if we can
know, we can figure out that provision for the
initial system,
if I showed this
this expression, I get rid of a fairly complicated
looking ratio. The combined system we have.
Square.
Times is changing over used to intelligence, and
that is the greater discretion whether to combine
systems going to have dual. Information for an
independent particles in.
In a volume V so we can have in the system and you
will have one factor of that from the system. Well,
that's one factor of the system, the loose. And
it's easy to look at the terms of the numerator
over here. It's like in factorial, the video will
accuse the factor of two of the square come in and
all that is left is smaller than on to three and
which is going
through the same result. The other needs
see how we're doing for time, which is already. So.
With this is hopefully inspiration or illustration,
just you can keep plugging away at the task then
of computing the final entropy, the especially
interesting bits of this exercise, and we will
check in about that this time next week or so
before then. I'll see you on Monday for the wrap
up of the current cycle and starting the grand
canonical ensemble. Hope you have a nice weekend
in.