All right, let's get things underway this afternoon. Hopefully the jackhammer outside
is not going to cause any problems for us.  It
seems far enough away that it's just a bit of
background noise. So, welcome to the final stretch
before the break.  The plan for this week, just
looking at where we are in the topics for the module, is
going to be to wrap up those quantum gases in the
grand-canonical ensemble, but hold off on getting into
the next and final big section of the module,
which is introducing interactions to the
statistical systems we consider. I think we'd
probably have time to start talking about that
later this week, but then after the break, we
would have to circle back and resume all of that
from the start to catch back up. So probably good to
put a bit of a break in the material as well as
just in the meetings. So what we are doing today, on
the twenty eighth
of March, is, first of all, checking to see if
there are any immediate questions about what we
were doing last week.
We dealt with the photon gas, the quantum gas of
Marcellus unprivileged, this seclusions.
Particularly.
Finisterre, the so-called radiation pressure that
even particles of light exerts on any containers
that contain them, and this gave us the equation
of state for the first time, gas, which are the
usual form that radiation pressure times. The
volume depends on the number of particles. The
temperature is like the ideal gas law with just a.
Numerical factor of the rebounds is a function
with argument four divided by that, we must see
the function of three coming in from the quantum
statistics of those Einstein counting the. Stuff
food arrived back in Unit seven, and I don't think
I emphasized enough last week that this expression,
which is PI squared over 90, Zyda three, is not
that far from one. So in practice, it is not easy
to distinguish the equation of state for a gas of
mass photons compared to the classical equation of
the state that was started to be established
empirically back in the sixteen hundreds Boyle's
law and was put on the framework of statistical
physics even in the mid eighteen hundreds well
before.
The. Connection between photons and radiation was
developed following quantum statistics and ideas
of those kinds of programs, and we're actually
part of the fourth. Sorry about that. Kind of
looking at this, we can just do a bit of mental
arithmetic that PI squared is 10 PI being a bit
more than three years apart. The fourth is about
one hundred. Zyda three. Something like one point
two to it's a famous irrational number, so 90
times more, that one also gives us something
around one hundred. And altogether this comes out
being that point nine times. And if you actually
put that into a calculator. And the precise value
so after. Wrapping up that the derivation of the
equation of state for the photon gas in three
dimensions, we turned to quantum gases at four
rounds and here we change looking at non
relativistic fermions, which is fermions that are
massive and huge. Mass is large compared to the
typical momentum of the energy are given by. The
classical relationship screwed over to AM derived
from the general Einstein triangle, the
combination of mass energy and kinetic energy. And
we also saw how all of the free energy levels are
degenerate from up and down spined states, at
least for a typical fermions like Electron's.
So a similar degeneracy to the full time and
tutorial attriting, but from very different
physics spin rather than pauperisation, and we
started working through derivations of the
particle, no density for fermions. So the average
number of particles and approach per unit volume.
That we found that we described as an integral
over the from the energies of this Fairmead
function.
I've left the cost of proportionality here, that's
in the notes, but the important thing for the time
being is. The. Similarity between the security
function and the average occupation that we looked
at to compare and contrast those instances, just
experiment with sticks and classical maps or
bowsman statistics. So which if we. To go back to
what I had on here is you. Test the focus for
today, you can see that as the temperature
decreases, that family function becomes closer and
approaches more closely, just a step function that
corresponds to.
Essentially, the probability of a level being
filled at low temperatures, that probability
becomes one for energy levels that have value to
the energy less than the positive chemical
potential that will come back around to today. And
once the energy becomes larger than that chemical
potential probability of a corresponding energy
level playing field crashes down quickly to zero.
So.
If we focus on that, the low temperature regime,
to simplify our calculations, at least for the
first pass through, then the simplest thing we can
do is approximates the security function just as
that step function, which is exact in the zero
temperature limit of absolute zero. And it's very
simple as these intervals quite dramatically.
That's still visible in. On what it does is cut
off the integral at the energy equal to the
chemical potential.
So that all of that exponential dependence that is
present at zero temperatures drops out and we just
end up with something directly proportional to the
power, three 1/2. So that's what we wrapped up
last week because of questions about.
This is the state of this calculation before we go
on to discuss a bit about what it means.
In terms of the media, I want to highlight the
dimension of dependence on the three halves power
of the chemical potential.
Since waking up at the top of this next page.
As well as, again, at the level of dimensional
analysis, independence from the temperature, at
least at low temperature, so we can appreciate the
temperature independence pretty easily just by
saying that this is a really good approximation to
a more general general result that could be
organized in the powers of that small temperature.
That is something you will have time to look at
and a bit more detail than originally planned
before the term break sets in at the end of this
week.
But independence of temperature is essentially an
approximation that we are making to this result by
placing that farming function with a simple step
function, the. Power of the chemical potential use
of the three hands. Is now governing the behavior
of this average density, so the average number of
particles is dependent on the chemical potential
and in such a way that. Can be appreciated from
dimensional analysis or from a more geometric. But
you're looking at things which gets to the.
Attempting to not quite succeed in draw on the
board
last week. And speaking of drawing on the board, I
realize I put on your six digit number for today.
So sorry that that is five seven zero.
So
we decide to fill in that blank
what we can think of at low temperatures just.
Is it not working?
Looking for something? When I reported some
problems earlier on, the generic advice was I saw
recently that we could see more trouble. That's
the level we're working at. It's not a crucial
issue for today. So getting back to the.
Dependents of the average, the density on this
three have power of the chemical potential. What
we can think of to motivate this, at least at low
temperatures, is a picture qualitative idea that
the step function approximation that we've used is
corresponding to the probability of energy levels
being empty or filled. So every energy level that
has a value of the energy is smaller than the
chemical potential is filled every one that has. A
energy larger than the chemical potential is empty,
so there is a cut off on the values of the energy
below, which all of the energy levels are sealed
and above, which all of those are all empty. So
the picture that I tried to draw on the board last
week with limited success is now replaced by this
printout I got from Dan Schroder's textbook
introduction to thermophilic. Several other
figures from there have also popped up and sugar
is using slightly different location. All these
names are the integer case that we have. What is
showing here are energy levels that depend on the
overall magnitude of that three vector case, X
squared squared plus case squared with the overall
chance that some of these energy levels depend on
the electrical energy, some constant.
Since when we looked at the possible of generous
use of those energy levels maybe a couple of weeks
ago now, the very start of this relatively long
date, each of the dots in this figure are those
possible energy levels, three vectors in tax. And
why is that? And the corresponding energy is given
by. The. Magnitude of the distance of the dot from
the origin, and by replacing or approximating the
integer X, Y, Z by real continuous has been to
simplify the calculations and integrals rather
than complicated sums. What we're doing is
approximating these cubes of discrete integer
points in this case based by the positive octaves
of the sphere that has this radius, payback's.
Remembering that.
The possible numbers of degrees of freedom and
values for today that we have in a typical
statistical physics system are something of order.
Ten to twenty three. If you do this exercise for
ten of the twenty three points filling up a cube,
you can convince yourself to take my word for it,
that the sort of rough bits around the edges of
this approximation where the sphere in Cuba are
not quite matching up are thoroughly irrelevant
compared to the overall volume of that cube. So
all of the energy levels that are picked out by
the step function are those that fit within that
tube. So they are
essentially filling the void, the volume of that
cube or the sphere with this particular radius
Cmax that is being set by the cutoff point in this
step function where E is
equal to. And since the idea is given by E
corresponds to where the overall value of Cmax is
like the square root of the energy. And then we
have again this cutoff point for the energy. You
pick up a sphere. We are counting over the field
energy levels within the volume of the positive
octave of a sphere with radius Cmax. Which is like
the square root of energy, which goes like the
square root of new volume of the sphere, is the
cube of its radius, giving us free powers of the
square root of MU or use of the three has this
functional dependence and hopefully the focus on
this camera will improve as I zoom back in.
You dealt with.
Stinking. Hopefully that's better, so that's the
kind of.
Dimensional analysis based arguments, you can
figure out the functional dependence of these
various quantities on the critical parameters,
temperature and chemical potential, just from some
considerations of the meaning of the
approximations that we're making in terms of what
this family function is and what it means, what it
amounts to when we talk about it as a step up. So
hopefully that discussion is not too confusing and
immediate questions about.
Not hearing any what we can do on the basis of
this argument is actually invert the result that
we found for that critical density. The average
number of particles divided by volume and extract
the corresponding energy that.
Matches up to the.
Square root of the radius of that sphere that we
were just looking at. So rather than talk about
how many particles or what particle density we
have to give, the kind of potential we can
consider, if we have a gas with gas, a fermions
with some particle density, what is the
corresponding chemical essential, which is use of
energy that corresponds to the. The region must
see the energy space that would be filled by that
density of particles. This value for the chemical
potential is known as the fairy energy at zero
temperatures. It is just the chemical potential
and at non-zero temperatures, we will see. Not
today, but later on this week. There are small
corrections that come into the terminology, but
this is essentially is the.
Shape of the region in the space of momentum and
all of these terminals are trying to fill at low
temperatures and they don't have a large amount of
thermal energy or equivalently, with all higher
energy, energy levels are exponentially suppressed
by that function and every transit systems that we
have derived.
So.
I'll just say in passing that. In the case of
these not interacting, yes, in civil war, that's
sort of the simple case for the of energy. The
ferry surface, as it's called, is just the sphere
of the sphere, and once we get into if we were to
get into more complicated gases, it firming up,
for instance, electrons and various sorts of
metals, we talk about what it does talk about and
watch those through the shape of their so-called
pheromone surface. No longer just a year with a
particular radius, but a more complicated object,
the behavior of which we can tell you a great deal
about the behavior of the corresponding the
without having to go through detailed calculations.
That's not even for this modulars they will peak
at. How these sorts of ideas play out in. Things
like material science and superconductivity and
investigations of crystals themselves.
Set that aside for now and having completed the
average particle density can go on to. If you're
the average energy. Was there are. Questions or
objections about.
What we've gone through so far. The. Only change
that we need to introduce to consider the average
internal energy density rather than the. Average
particle, no density is just an additional factor
of the energy in the same integral that we had
before. So. When we broke down, this had to go
with the cost factor multiplied by the integration
of that family function, the square root of the.
That was counting the number of particles that we
have in the energy levels that are available, the
every function essentially giving us the
probability that any given energy level with this
value of the energy will be occupied. Now, to get
the internal energy, we have to start over not
merely the number of occupied energy levels, but
also the amount of energy that they are
contributing to the overall gas. So.
That is the purpose of this extra factory coming
into. This next integral here whenever we have.
With some probability and occupy energy level
energy, it's contributing exactly that energy to
the overall average energy of our gas.
And with the low temperature approximation of that
primary function being the step function, this
integral is. Essentially just as easy to to
compute as that for the average protocol. We
started off with by reviewing today.
The constant increase factor comes on. For the
ride and the fairy function is one between ages of
zero, up to the chemical potential view and it is
zero for all, energy is larger than UCITS, if you
will. Just it just gets cut off at a maximum value
of the chemical potential. And. The integral of.
X2, the three halves, the X is. Just another.
Simple power function. So the to the firefighters
now divided by five halves and evaluated as equals
zero and equals. So we have now zero zero and new
to the five hands we can split up into. That same
view to the three House facts that are coming from
the volume of a sphere in energy space the states
are filling. So it's that same factor of two new
to the three horsepower.
Bring that one over half up to provide another
factor to get to the three heads, there's a five
left over with PI squared in each part cubed. And
then one additional factor of view that comes
along and. The reason for organizing things in
this way is that we can identify a constant factor
proportional to the average particle, no density.
So we have to.
The result that we had earlier, this three has
power to win you over three. I scored a five and a
three everything else. It's the same for. Firmly
on no density times, the additional factor of the
chemical potential.
Many campuses will cancel out because of the
policies that are now on both sides of this
equation and just end up with the situation, one
of three very simple relations between the average
particle number in the average, the energy.
If we were to find out that overall internal
energy by the particle number, what would just be
left is three fifths of the chemical potential,
which is that from the energy that we have just
defined. So if all of the fermions were occupying
energy levels at the boundary of this year, then I
do want to show that would correspond to energy
use of that very energy.
So of the boundary of the sphere, the energy is
just kind of the actual. And what we found is that
it was that low temperatures,
as we fill up that sphere, the average energy.
Coming from all of the particles, from what that
sphere is not all the way up to the feminine
energy, but a little more than halfway there on
average, which is, again, just coming from the
geometry.
The.
The geometry of the relations between energy and
momentum in the knowledge of Mr.. That we.
We are depending on the situation where these
multiple energy levels are restricted to have at
least one term, you probably should have said
earlier, given a reminder, that that restriction
is the key that needs things to fill up one energy
level after the next rather than all collapsing
down into the lowest energy level. The way that
Placidyl particles or exotic particles would. And
one. Important aspect of this equation, one of the
three temperatures is that, as we said earlier,
the average particle number is independent of the
temperature and there's no additional dependence
on the temperature coming in through this three
fifths of U. Factor. So the energy itself. Is
independent of the temperature and the positive,
even when that temperature is absolutely zero.
And even in the absence of interactions, we are
still considering its ideal gas of the track and
particles. So.
There is a behavior here for four males, that is.
Extremely different than classical particles or
gases of. All those islands, like little towns, we
consider, if you remember the. Expression be used
repeatedly when considering thermodynamic cycles
built on plastic about the masses we had in the
chemical and solvents relation between the
internal and the temperature equals three has
plenty to that. That temperature, absolute zero
energy of the system. Also vanish. This is also
the case. For the first time this year. Things are
a bit more complicated because in the grand
economic ensemble number of photons, there's also
varying with the temperature. And if we pull out
of the overall temperature, we had found that the
energy with the US is actually proportional to
temperature. The fourth power and varnishes even
more quickly as that temperature becomes very
small. And it's completely different for fermions.
We have a non-zero energy even in the limits of
absolute zero temperature, which is precisely
because. We have at least one me in each of these
energy levels. So organizing energy levels as as
we have labeling them with some integer labels.
Where the energy is always increasing as we go to
the values of this label, we can picture 30 year
olds selling their energy levels, starting from
the levels of the smallest energies that have the
least exponential suppression of that function.
The average occupation number and. Going up to
levels of higher and higher energies until they
fill that whole sphere downward by that very
energy is the tension.
So and that is independent of the temperature from
can't get any lower energies with all of the lower
energy levels already filled due to that post
principal. And this this is the contrast to
classical Masonic systems, which. Don't have to
worry about the occupation numbers for energy
levels preventing any more particles from moving
into that, they can just keep crashing down to the
lowest energy, but eventually varnishes. The
temperatures,
again, with. Exponentially suppressed
probabilities for any higher energy levels to be
occupied.
And I know I've been going on at some length about
that picture of. Fermions filling up energy levels
as a way of thinking about the behavior of these
gases, that low temperature. And that is because
it's very useful to. It's sort of intuitive
understanding beyond the formal mathematics of how
these systems are behaving and why we can see now
returning to a question that came up at the start
of our considerations last Friday, which is. Why
do we have the positive chemical potential in
these systems, whether on introducing the
chemicals actually six now holding our bodies in
general, negative on based on this definition and
the relation between the number of particles and
the entropy of the system? So just to briefly
recall that argument, which was a few weeks ago.
If we think of just a ordinary classical gas
without any of the. Any consideration or any
worries about public exclusion principles for
forming the input from pond mechanics, we argue
that as we increase the number of particles in
that system, we generically have ways of Organa
ordering. Those particles are organized within a
larger number of microstates, response to a larger.
And if you want to define the chemical potential
with the entropy fixed through this equation that
comes from generalized, some of the identity we
derived in unisex, you would need to decrease the
overall energy of that system, remove the number
of accessible microstates for those larger numbers
of particles to occupy. So in that way, the
increase in entropy from the larger number of
particles is compensated by a decrease in the
entropy from a smaller energy, and the overall
derivative is therefore negative, that energy has
to decrease the number of particles increases and
vice versa. That's how it works. Classically, we
went through that argument some time ago and
that's exactly what does not apply to fermions at
low temperatures because in that limit of absolute
zero. We are all of the families who have fallen
to the lowest energy levels and they can fill in
all the.
There is only a single microstates, not one.
They're all the energy levels up to the energy are
full of the energy levels with higher energies are
empty. And if we were to add particles, so
increasing the number of particles, we don't get
the classical increase in the entropy number of
ways of organizing these particles, we just. Push
up that energy a little bit more, but we still
have just that simple micro states where all the
new particles are filling the additional energy
bubbles up to be shifted to energy. So going back
to the general definition of the entropy. Several
microstates of probability of the system being a
democracy at times of that same ability to have a
single term in the sun, that is that has
probability one for the system to be in the single
part of the microstates. So we have one time
support of one, which is zero entropy.
Independence of how many particles we have in the
system,
but at the same time, because these additional
particles are considering adding have to pick up
the empty energy levels that are around that
fairly energy, each of these additional particles
is bringing in a positive contribution to the
energy. They're all landing, if you will, at the
edge of the former surface, the sphere in case
space. We add the particles just outside of it.
Push the sphere to make the bit larger to the
portion of the particles in each of these new
particles that are contributing approximately that
energy to the total energy, which is a positive
contribution, a positive contribution in the
particle number for the positive derivative here.
Unlike the classical case we considered earlier on.
So the.
The potential then becomes zero, and we may or may
not have enough time this week to go through the
demonstration of how the chemical potential
recovers, the expected classical behavior and the
high temperature limits. Where we get back to that
situation where we generically expect it to be a
negative.
Quantity in the classical analysis, that's.
Something will be pushing towards coming up to the
break.
So quick pause, 30 questions that have come up,
we're going through this justification for working
with positive chemical potentials.
Because at this point, we are in. The position to
complete the calculation of the equation of states
for this now Multiphasic from get us to the
relation between its large scale quantities that
governs its behavior. And the missing piece that
we need is, as usual, the pressure of this case.
So the response, the average internal energy to a
negative change in the volume, keeping the number
of particles fixed and also keeping the entropy
fixed. And we just went through an argument that
the entropy at least had this low temperature
limit is automatically fixed, it's just zero and
having only that one microstates. Available. So we
don't have to do anything special to impose the
conditions of entropy in this case, we just need
to plug in the.
Overall internal energy that we computed into this
derivative and. In particular, in serving the.
Average political number that we computed earlier
to get everything in terms of the volume.
So that is the expression that is it's written
here be slightly. We are inserting actually the.
Value of the chemical potential at the zero energy
limit in order to get things in terms of.
The volume, so.
Look back to this equation when no one really knew
was this was the definition of the of the energy
that it's your temperature matches the chemical
potential and obstacles optical three factors to
consider. The particle mass just brings in another
two thirds power of the average particle that
density and divided by five. So that's revealing
how the
average internal energy depends on the volume. And
adding that two thirds power of the protocol
number to the single tower, the part of the number
that we had in relation to the previous page is
three fifths times chemical potential times
average protocol. No end up with this dependence
upon that particular number two five thirds. So
keeping in and fixed.
All that happens when we take liberties with
respect to the volume.
Is that we pick up, so we have here lots of
constants and the functional dependency of the
minus two thirds power so that.
Two thirds negative, two thirds it comes down that
cancels out that negative sign that we had the
definition of the pressure. And then we reduce the
exposure to the volume by another factor, which
corresponds to dividing by the and then everything
else is just a constant that comes along for the
ride. Three fifths times squared over to him and
then this three pi squared with the remaining
factor of the two thirds and the average particle,
number two, the five others. We can rewrite in a
couple of interesting ways, so. Maybe the easiest
way is to recognize that this whole thing is the
energy taking, the derivative of so this is two
thirds times. The average internal energy
nanowires by an extra factor of the volume. So
pressure is directly proportional to the average
internal energy density and. Plugging in the other
relationship we had, the energy was three fifths
times the chemical potential, eight times the
particle number we can read this instead is three
is cancer and the five comes in the chemical
potential average number, number density.
Maybe the most interesting way of expressing this
is. But again. Inserting what we had for that
chemical potential, that the zero temperature for
energy in terms of that same. Particle, no density.
Which is.
From that equation, one to once again.
Just look at it quickly here, that picture of each
person to end times in three pi squared to the two
thirds power, so the two cancel each square mile
over five, and we have three pi squared to two
thirds power. And a two thirds power of it will be
multiplied by this additional power. And it will
be so. Particle, no density now to be five thirds
power, that is. A useful way of.
Getting things precisely because an. Recognize
this average particle, no density as well, just a
density, we can take that to be the relevant
parameter in this expression. So that the pressure
of the gas.
Is just directly proportional to the density of
the five thirds power multiplied by some
complicated calcium factor, depending on the mass
of this particle. And again, like the energy there
is. The new and exciting behavior for the pressure
that we still have a positive pressure, even in
the limit of absolute zero temperature, again, to
be a contrast to. The classical ideal gas photon
gas that we had for prosodic particles. And this
pressure, even though there is a pressure, it's
not related to any force between these fermions.
It's coming from that exclusion principle. If you
owed. Symmetric or anti symmetric functions
describing these fermions. So it's that purely
quantum effect arising from the public exclusion
principle that leaves this temperature independent
contribution to the pressure. Now. Wrap up just by
looking at. This figure here, which is combining
the two limits that we've considered so far,
recognizing that high temperatures, we recover
classical physics, so we should recover precisely
that ideal gas law with no additional pre factors,
PV equals. And team for introducing the same
density in terms of the particle number divided by
volume and pressure that is linearly dependent
upon temperature. So as the temperature is large,
which is. The right hand side of this plant, we
have just a straight line. Olivia Dependent's in
the pressure as you go to the classical machine
and then at low temperatures approaching the zero,
we enter the quantum regime where the quantum
statistics of these fermions.
Comes into play and reveals itself by the
temperature no longer varying at all, with the
pressure no longer growing at all with the
temperature, but rather approaching this constant.
Zero temperature limit for the pressure that you
will see more about tomorrow morning and see how
this plays a role in the physical systems.
So we'll wrap up there for today in the last sort
of rush through this last bit about the two
minutes. The pressure will pick up there again
tomorrow morning. So we have a break overnight to
think about whether the calculations that we have
done and the way to interpret them makes sense.
And from this point tomorrow, we will apply this
behavior of the nation states to some interesting
physical phenomena.
To see all that.
And
with.
Just.