OK, the recording is underway. Welcome back to Tuesday
morning, picking up where we left off after the
overnight break and starting off with the
attendance recording.
First I'll quickly turn on the lights just so that
this side of the board is not in shadow.  So the six digit number is
for today, eight nine, six zero,
eight five.
And that can stay up there and check to see both
local and remote participants, if you have any
questions coming from what we did yesterday
afternoon or what is coming up on the homework due
later this week.
Just to get us back into gear, we continue to
think about ideal gases through the canonical
ensemble, fixing the temperature of the particles
and our being, the focus of our work yesterday was
defining the pressure of these gases that are in
some container of buoyancy. And we introduce the
definition that the pressure was related to the
change in the internal energy of the gas as the
volume of that container changed is a control
parameter in addition to the temperature and
particle number. And importantly, this change in
volume had to proceed without changing the entropy
in this definition. So isotropic change in the
volume that we showed reduces to the usual force
per unit area that pressure.
Is described as in the more introductory classical
mechanics modules on the basis of that.
We introduced the concept of work, which is the
change in this internal energy. That is due to the
application of this external force. In particular
related to the pressure. For that reason, through
this general relationship, the work is the
negative of the pressure times, the change in
volume, which we can write. In a more
infinitesimal looking way as minus P times D.V.,
or if we have some larger scale change, the volume
over which the pressure itself is changing as a
function of being given by the ideal gas law that
follows from the definition we introduced last
time. And this work is just the integral from some
certain volume. What a final volume of that
pressure as a function of volume. Times are
integrated over the change in volume. And this
we've seen is one way to change the internal
energy of our ideal gas and its container. But it
is not the only way. In general, we're going to
have the highest entropy. We have that the change
of energy is just the work. But more generally, we
could have other. Contributions changing the
internal energy that also changed the entry of the
system, and that is where we pick up this morning.
With the concept of heat, so the way to introduce
heat and move beyond changes in energy coming from
constant entropy changes in volume is vital to
keep the volume fixed along with the particle
number. And think about what happens as we change
the temperature of our ideal gas. So we have added
some container. We can heat up that container,
moving over some Bunsen burner, some open flame,
increasing the temperature of the gas inside it,
and therefore increasing its energy from the
relation that we derived in Unit four between the
internal energy of an ideal gas. And as
temperature, we found that the internal energy is
at the back of the screen directly proportional to
the temperature with the proportionality factor of
three times the number of particles. So even
though no work is done due to the fixed volume, we
still have a change in the internal energy coming
from this change in the temperature that we.
It's a tribute to something other than work. And.
As we've seen this additional change, the energy
is only possible if there is also a corresponding
change in the entropy. Here we have varnishing
work, the non varnishing change in internal energy.
And if we consider that change in energy could be,
we can recall that for both distinguishable and
indistinguishable particles. Depends on the
temperature only showed up in. Showed up in the
same way, in the same place. In the expressions
for both of these cases, and in particular, we had
the.
I'm right down on the margin here, just a reminder
that entropy was three heads in the sand would be
over the boy wavelength cubed for the case of
distinguishable particles and a smaller five
halves and. And Lord End times the cube with the
case in the sexual particles. The temperature is
only entering through that thermal wavelength.
Bringing in this factor of the logarithm of the
temperature to the three has power and the three
factors of this wavelength that go along with
cancel out the units in the volume. So it's.
Straightforward piece of calculation to consider
the change in entropy that corresponds to the
change in temperature and change in energy as we
imagine heating up or cooling down the system with
a fixed cooling.
Was used.
Lieutenant, for for all we have to do is look at
the differential factor of this rehab's. And T,
which if we push that differential through the
derivative of the logarithm of T is one of the T.
So we have a three haves and times that change in
temperature divided by the temperature itself and
the three haves and DETI we just saw was precisely
the change in energy that we have in this
situation with a fixed volume. So the change in
entropy is related to the change in internal
energy. With the. Factor relating them just being
the temperature itself or multiplying through by
temperature, we find that that's the change in
internal energy, the temperature times, the change
in entropy, which is what we're going to define to
be keets as opposed to work. So a alternative way
of changing the average internal energy of the
system. Through a change in the entropy, in
contrast to the work which changed the internal
energy while keeping the entropy fixed, in this
case, we have simplified things. We have isolated
the work by simplifying things through keeping the
volume of our ideal gas fixed, ensuring that there
is no work contributing to this change in the
internal energy that is key until a CO two. So
this is the infinitesimal definition of the heat
if we have some infinitesimal change in the
entropy and the internal energy. And the
temperature on all three of those being related by
the expression to be worked out for an ideal guest
last week, we can again. Consider larger scale
changes, integrating over some change in the
entropy from a. Initial state of the system, one
of those thermodynamic macro states characterized
by these large scale properties up to some final
entropy, keeping the volume fixed and identifying
this heat. Coming from this interview over the
whole process as a change in the internal energy.
If you look at some of the references, you may see
the heat and the work. At least when they are
expressing this infinitesimal way, referred to as
the Q and T W, I'm avoiding that fairly widespread
nomenclature just to emphasize that both the heat
and the work, whether infinitesimal or not, are
changes in the energy. And it's tempting to read a
key word as a change in heat or change work, which
in that sentence, in that context, doesn't really
make sense as the heat and word are themselves
changes in this derived quantity that we have in
the canonical example, the internal energy itself.
So questions about the definition of heat to go
along with work is ways to change the internal
energy.
And maybe there's one aspect of this that has been
implicit so far that maybe this won't make
explicit, which is to recall that first law of
thermodynamics, that energy is neither created nor
destroyed. So when we are changing this internal
energy, the canonical ensemble, we know we have
the setup that our system is informal contact with
this large thermal reservoir that fixes its
temperature as the starting point for the
canonical approach. So all of these changes in the
internal energy are in some way reflecting the.
Movement of energy into and out of our system
being exchanged with that thermal reservoir, and
we have defined the work and the heat in such a
way that both are positive when the internal
energy of our gas is increasing. Hopefully that
will come back a bit of the feedback I was hearing.
So when energy is flowing into the system from
that reservoir, from the surroundings in some way,
both the heat and the work will be positive. And
the opposite case, when we have a negative work or
negative heat, that means that energy is being
removed from our gas and placed into its
surroundings in some way, shape or form. And the
remainder of this unit will be looking into the
different ways, shapes and forms that this energy
exchange can be realized and.
So that is hopefully familiar once we start to
think about it, that. Energy is conserved and is
just flowing back and forth between the system and
its surroundings. The definition of heat that
we've introduced actually assumes that the same is
the case for the entropy as well, just like the
energy, the. Should view the interview not as
being created or destroyed, but is flowing back
and forth between the system and its surroundings.
So when this does is positive for responding to
heat flowing into the gas, we have the
corresponding flow of entropy into the system from
its surroundings. And flowing back out again when
that heat becomes negative.
And this is.
Useful in the context of the thermodynamic cycle,
to be sure that if we consider carrying out
various changes to our system, modifying the
central parameters in such a way that it can't be.
Expanding compressed heat and cool, but somehow
gets back to its initial stage, the same
thermodynamic macro state with all of these large
scale thermodynamic properties the same, in order
to do that, we need to ensure that the total
entropy in the system is not increasing so that
the processes are reversible and the system can
get back to its starting stage. That's a dig into
that a bit more in the next section as we look at
actual cycles, but that is. Essentially implicit
in the definition of a cycle, once we go around
some cycle, want to get back to the system, we
started in requiring some reversibility, the
conservation of the amount of entropy in the
system, along with the amount of energy so that we
don't run afoul of the second law of
thermodynamics.
And this actually gives us another Handal or
another perspective on these isotropic processes,
like the change in the volume that we use to
define pressure. We see that with. He's identified.
Has that change in energy times, the temperature
whenever the. Entropy is concerned the change in
entropy is zero or isopropyl process, there must
be no peak flow between. Our system and its
surroundings, which is known as idiomatically
process, so. Formerly, the adiabatic processes,
some change in the control parameters of our
system that we can carry out without transferring
heat between that system and its surroundings, and
thanks to our demand that these processes be
reversible so that they can be part of the dynamic
cycles and aliabadi process that is reversible.
Guarantees that the entered the entropy of the
system is constant during that process and in
practice, if we think about the types of changes
that we can do to the control parameters of a
system in order to realize this.
Going back to that example, the process of pushing
Pakistan to. You work on a gas or moving that gas
over flame to transfer heat into its.
The idea that these processes can proceed without
that formal contact between the system and its
reservoir, that was a starting point for the
canonical ensemble means that adiabatic processes
have to proceed quickly enough, that no heat is he
has time to be exchanged between the system and
its surroundings. In other words, adiabatic
processes are fast enough that they are over and
done with before he has a chance to be transferred
into or out of the system. And similarly, that.
Our assumption of reversibility also means that
entropy has time to be transferred through these
enigmatic processes, and if we think about the
opposite, rather than a very fast change of
parameters that is over and done with before he
has a chance to flow through that thermal contact
between the system and its surroundings if we take
a very slow process. Where?
We change the control parameters gradually enough
that as they're being changed, any and all heat
transfer has the opportunity to complete in full.
What that means is that this heat exchange is
ensuring that the system's temperature will remain
equal to the temperature of its surroundings, that
thermal reservoir, all of the any change in
internal energy is going to be able to balance out
in the temperatures through these two processes,
leaving us with these slow processes, keeping the
temperature constant as they proceed. And just
like the. Define the base word I still entropic to
be isotropic, to refer to a process with. Entropia,
we will call these slow processes with because of
temperature, isothermal and building on that same
record, ISO's for equal. And these are the
idealized, limited cases where real processes are
generally going to be somewhere between these two
extremes, and I would say that usually in practice.
The heat flow required to maintain a constant
temperature is something that is very slow indeed,
and so real processes are typically closer to the
idealise idiomatic limits where the process is
fast and there's not a chance for Keiter entropy
to flow. And we will see some examples of that
coming up, possibly in the story on Friday or
possibly next week's tutorial, and I'll just pause
before we go into something and then expose
themselves. We have. All of the ingredients that.
We will need for this.
Pressure, huge.
Work idiomatic processes and isothermal processes.
The next step will be bringing all of these
ingredients together to construct a full cycle.
Are there any questions before we move on to that
stage?
And hopefully, as we move on to this more applied
point in our work somewhere through with the most
of the definitions for this unit, we can start
actually doing things with the concepts that we
have defined and put in place.
I'll hop back just briefly to this equation. Sixty
two, I lost over one aspect of this going through
it, which is this. Expression, when you're
interviewing over the temperature as a function of
the entropy of the system, which is inverting the
usual.
Functional independence that we expect in the
canonical ensemble, if we, as always, keep the
party going over and fixed that out of some of
these expressions, we have been driving.
Especially in uniform last week, the internal
energy and the Entropia as functions of our
control parameters, the temperature and the volume
that we imagine we have the. Experimental
capability to modify at our will. We need to
assume that these emotional relationships are
inevitable, and in particular, we can think about
the temperature as a function of the other control
parameters, but now also the entropy, something
that is a derived quantity. The canonical example.
And something that will change as a consequence of
our experimental change of the temperature and
volume. But Reverdy, inverting this Malaysian
express the temperature as a function of the
entropy also allows us to express the internal
energy as a function of the entropy just through
the. Simple connection that we have between energy
and temperature, so of the dependence on the
temperature on interview is made explicit, that
carries through directly into the internal energy.
And we can. Consider how this internal energy is a
function of entropy and the volume of our ideal
gas. Responds or depends. On changes both in the
volume and of the internal entropy. So.
Considering this first order, a Taylor expansion
in both of these two variables, which becomes
exactly the limit of infinitesimal changes. If we
expand. The internal energy around the starting
point and entropy with that volume kept fixed. We
have a change in entropy times, the response of
the internal energy to the entropy with a fixed
volume.
And similarly, if we fix the entropy and look at
the response of the internal energy to a change in
the volume. And multiply that through by the
change in the volume compared to its starting
point. Taking the limit where these three changes
are all. Infinitesimal and recalling that. This
isotropic change, the energy with respect to the
volume was what we define to be the negative of
the pressure. And if we go all the way back to the
micro canonical example where the volume had not
yet been introduced, it was implicitly fixed, we
defined the inverse temperature to be the change
in entropy with respect to the conserved energy.
This here is just the inverse of that.
One over tea inverted gives us.
An expression I'll try to get on the same page
here,
moving the starting energy at the initial values,
we're expanding around to the other side. We have
the change in the energy. It's given by the change
in entropy at times the temperature. Plus, the
negative pressure times the change in the volume
or minus PDV, both of which we can recognize as
the keys and the work that we just introduced
yesterday and today.
And what this is, is a generalization,
regionalized form of that first law of
thermodynamics, the. Introduced a few weeks ago,
it is a sharper way of stating the fact that
energy is conserved.
Here, formulated by saying that any change in the
energy has to be due to the different ways that
we've introduced of transferring energy from our
ideal gas system. To or from its surroundings,
both by having those. Surroundings do work on the
gas or vice versa, or by having heat transferred.
Through a change in entropy with fixed point
between the system and its surroundings.
And this equation, sixty three of this generalized
first law of thermodynamics is the final piece in
the puzzle, the final ingredient that we will need
to. Carry out. All the processes necessary to
construct some dynamic cycles. The.
The equations that describe the behavior of an
ideal gas in this container of oil as being
mutilated by adjusting those control parameters,
the temperature. And the volume, and it may well
be useful to have these four equations. Lying
around for easy reference, even once you've moved
on from this point on the page for his record was
on the board for reference, we derived from
distinguishable and indistinguishable particles in
the internal energy, three hands, hands, the
number of times the temperature. And again, for
both of those cases, the entropy depends on this
combination of the volume times. The three has
power of the temperature. So that is nonsense.
We know that the.
Isotropic or adiabatic process with no flow of
entropy, whatever that product to volume and
temperature to the three times power is constant
and we have to the decimal system
that links the.
Macroscopic properties, synapses, the pressure,
body temperature.
Or any thermodynamic states to consider and then
what we just wrote down here, after developing the
concepts of
the two ways that we have to change the internal
energy market by changing the control parameters,
the heat is related to temperature. Times change
entropy. The word is negative pressure times
boiling with the negative side. We can recall by
thinking about the system we went through last
week. Increasing the internal energy by decreasing
the volume of the gas, squeezing things together
and the sorts of that sort of squeezing through a
piston is. One way we can consider to manipulate
the system and we can not distinguish between
changes in volume that are either fast enough to
proceed with no heat and entropy flow between the
gas and its surroundings or those that are
isothermal, proceed slowly, allow all of the
energy flow that's necessary to keep the
temperature of the system constant, the same value
as its the reservoir. So we now have two ways of
the two extremes of changing the volume.
And doing work on the system. Depending on how
quickly that proceeds can be anywhere between
these antibiotic and isothermal limits, it can
also be either that depression decreases the
volume to increase the internal energy or an
expansion point that is about increasing the
volume and consequently decreasing the internal
energy of the gas and potentially doing work on
the surroundings as an engine.
And just in the previous section, introducing the
concept of heat, we talked about fixing the volume
and increasing the internal energy of the system
by heating it up, adding or removing heat from the
gas. In that same context, clamping the system in
place allows that volume to be fixed and adding
heat.
Into or removing heat from the gas is always going
to necessarily change its entropy. On. We can do
that either with the volume or if we keep a
constant force on that piston while adding heat.
We can expect that change in the internal energy
to increase the volume, pushing the piston out and
potentially doing work on the surroundings,
connect that piston to a. You have to get it to
turn the wheel, to move our car forward or
backwards. And if we. Constructs in some sensible
way, a sequence of these sorts of manipulations
increasing or decreasing the volume of the system,
raising, lowering its temperature, the pressure we
can. Bring the system back to the same sort of
dynamic state in which it started defining a full
cycle.
And in particular, once we get back to that
initial thermodynamic status, we can repeat the
set of processes that took us around the cycle,
get back to the same set again, and just keep
repeating that over and over again, potentially
indefinitely. And the applications of these cycles
can be making use of the flow of heat through the
system from its surroundings to do work on the
surroundings, what we call an engine, specifically
a heat engine,
or if we put in some work into the system, we can
use that to remove heat or move heat around.
Allowing. A.
Change in the heat to change the temperature,
producing a refrigerator through just these
manipulations of natural gas in its container. Now.
There is a convenient way of representing these
sorts of cycles and more generally the
thermodynamic state of our ideal gas in this
container, which is to talk about just its
pressure and volume, which, thanks to these four
equations, specify to determine all of the large
scale dynamic properties that we are interested in
from the ideal gas law equation of state, we can
extract the temperature from that pressure and
volume with the number of particles and then from
the temperature particle number, the internal
energy, thanks to that simple relation to those
distinguishable indistinguishable particles in an
ideal gas. So what we can do to represent the
state of the system visually is.
Represented as a point on a diagram, a graph that
has the volume on one axis and the pressure on
another, which doesn't quite all fit on the screen.
This is an example of one of these pressure
building diagrams for PV diagrams that appear on
the vertical axis volume on the horizontal axis
when we.
Construct close cycles. Said that the system has
to get back to a starting point. We will expect to
see the lines on these PV diagrams that are
processes connecting initial states of our system
to final status through some change in the control
parameters. If we.
Placed together at. Cleverly designed sequence of
such processes that bring the system back to
starting point. Those sequences of processes will
be described by closed paths. Along with pressure
building diagrams, the example that's up on the
screen right now is looking at a particular
process.
In particular, the.
The expansion of the gas that we were just talking
about more abstractly, can you back that example
of a piston allowing that piston to be pulled out,
increasing the volume of gas? So. We start from
some initial states specified by the volume
knowledge and the pressure of the system, and we
slowly increase its volume to some larger value, a
final volume piece of F going slowly enough that
any and all heat transfer the system wants to do
with its surroundings has a chance to. To proceed
and keeping the temperature constant and producing
this type of curve on the PVC diagram that you
will just call an isothermal, so the ISO therm is
this process. Represented by this curved line
corresponding to isothermal expression or in this
case, expansion.
That line is that we will call myself Thurm and
keeping the temperature constant from Westlaw
because the temperature, the fixed particle number
requires the product. Of pressure times, volume to
remain constant, so this is the third, both the
temperature and the product of pressure and volume
are constant, which immediately tells us that as
the volume increases with a fixed temperature, the
pressure has to decrease leading to the former. Of
the line I've I've drawn here dropping. Dropping
the pressure as the volume becomes larger and if
we. Again, the. Pressure and volume in both the
initial stage has been at times the pressure and
volume in that final state piece of times BSF.
Requiring that those are equal in order to keep
the temperature equal, that immediately tells us
that the final volume is proportional to the final
pressure is brought to the initial pressure
multiplied by. The ratio of these volumes, so.
With the we can see that the final volume is
larger than the initial volume, this confirms that
the final pressure is smaller than the initial
pressure. And if we.
We cast this in terms of the change of pressure
that built up as we expand the system slowly in
this isothermal way.
With the pullout, this constant factor of not. And
then just end up with the difference of this ratio
minus the initial pressure, not which is then less
than zero. Subtracting one from a quantity that is
less than one.
And I can finally.
Stop introducing new concepts and ask you
something about them just to check that everything
up to this point is is clear. So let me ask you,
if we had in one of these TV diagrams to
isothermal that crossed, that had the same point
of pressure and volume at some point, what would
that mean in terms of the relation between those
two isoforms?
Well, there's only one case in which two of can
cross and what you're thinking of. I know where
you're coming from. If we say those two systems
have different temperatures, then they can never
cross. They have to be parallel to each other. We
can see that by supposing what if the opposite
would happen, then those two systems would be at
the same point in the diagram, at the same
pressure and the same volume and that same number
of particles and therefore the same temperature.
And they would, in fact.
Be the same isothermal. By virtue of having the
same temperature, in both cases, the isothermal is
characterized by a fixed temperature. And that is
in turn related to any position or given by any
position on these PCB diagrams. And your answer is
anticipating the. The next I agree on water. I'm
drawn here to firms with different temperatures.
T and a t f. We're considering now some process
that is no longer isothermal, what is moving our
system from this initial temperature to not to the
final temperature to. And just to switch things up,
how make this a compression rather than an
expansion? So that we start off with some initial
volume that is larger than the final volume we end
up with.
And in just the same way that.
We saw the pressure fall for an expansion that
increased the volume we can expect to see the
pressure rise from its initial to its final value
as we depress the system and decrease its volume.
And now if we consider a fast compression and in
particular the limit of fast enough to be
idiomatic with no heat flowing into or out of the
system. We know that the. The rise in the internal
energy who responded to this compression is going
to be reflected by a rise in the temperature going
from this initial temperature to a final one. And
the way we can get a grip on what's happening in
this adiabatic process for, again, this.
Particular line in the TV diagram goes by the name
of an area that. In contrast to the two oil firms
that. Are drawn in blue.
We know that.
With the. Process proceeding fast enough that no
heat is transferred and. The connection between
heat and the changing energy and heat and the
change in entropy. We can see that in this
adiabatic process described by the media, that
line of the pressure point diagram, this constant
entropy condition, is wanting to be the product of
the volume times, the three power of the
temperature. It's going to remain constant as a
consequence of the definition of an antibiotic
process. Now, two things to figure out from this
relation. With the change in pressure is we
considered for the isothermal case as well as the
change in temperature. And I think there's just
time remaining to churn through some of the.
Calculations from the starting point of the
constant entropy through this process that relates.
Three times do the three ounce power of the
initial and final states, or in other words, that
final temperature is proportional to the initial
temperature, but the concept of proportionality
being, again, this ratio of volumes is zero over
the final volume. Now that the two thirds hour, if
we take the.
Brings both sides of this equation to the two
thirds power to isolate the temperature. The
overall change then pull out that zero. And have.
The difference between this race should be two
thirds power, minus one. And plugging in the ideal
gas law to express that initial temperature in
terms of the initial point, zero times V0. In the
AP diagram.
The diagram of the page so that the population can
stay visible.
You have this expression and the call that the
this is a compression with a final belief, smaller
than the initial volume, the. Confirm what was
drawn on that Peevey diagram. What the final
temperature is larger than the initial temperature
we are increasing. On a lower temperature rises to
a higher temperature, one that corresponds to
larger volumes of pressure for a fixed volume,
we're currently larger volumes for a fixed
pressure.
And.
I'm just running out of time and.
Maybe it would be. All right, to pause in the
middle of this calculation and starting fresh on
Friday, give a chance to review and put in place
the final piece of this Friday morning, seeing
what the corresponding change in pressure is for
this if you get a compression.
And in the meantime, we have the homework to keep
you busy and. If there are no final questions
about what we've seen so far today, we'll pick up
with the. Really, the last piece in this
thermodynamic process, you kind of put them
together into a particular cycle on Friday.
The last call for questions, if not to the
remainder of your day. The rain has stopped. Good
luck with the homework. I'll see you again later
this week.
Well.