All right, that's the recording started. And while
this camera hopefully
turns itself on and gets in focus, I can write down
the six-digit number for today that I have now recovered.
Which is nine six eight five
one zero.
And let's see how the focus is
looking on this camera today.
That is clearly visible despite the bright sun from
outside, so let's pick up more or less where we
left off at the end of yesterday, touching in the
the big picture and the plan for the module. So we
spent a few weeks going through the canonical
ensemble, ideal gases and the use of those ideal gases
cycles to drive heat engines and refrigerators.
And we're going to set that aside and switch focus
to a different ensemble now. So before doing so,
just a quick call for any questions you want to
raise about the canonical example before we set it
aside for the time being and switch over to the
so-called grand canonical case.
Everyone seems content to move on the rank and
file review before diving into the details for
today, the progression of the modules so far that
after. Establishing the the basics was the basis
of the statistical foundation, the probability
space as a statistical ensemble consisting of the
microstates that a collection of particles or
degrees of freedom can adopt as they have all the
time. We first considered the specific probability
of on this micro canonical ensemble or we impose
constraints that number of particles in the system
were fixed as well as the internal energy of the
system. So this had a direct connection to
conservation of energy that required that the
system itself be completely isolated from its
environments and proved. Less than entirely useful
for practical applications, so we quickly moved on
to the canonical ensemble that we've been focusing
on up to and including yesterday, where now we
remove this constraint on the system, be
completely isolated if we allow it to exchange
energy with its environment and in place of that
conservation of energy in the system itself, the
overall requirements of conservation of energy in
the universe allows us to fix the temperature of
this system through that thermal contact with a
large external keypad for thermal reservoir. And
the comic ensemble, we still always count the
number of particles fixed and the generalization
we are diving into today and we'll be applying of
probably for the remainder of the time up until
the term break, is to remove the constraints that
the number of particles within the system remain
fixed, just as we earlier removed the constraint
on the energy within the system. Now imagine that
the system is able to exchange both particles and
energy with its surroundings. And in particular,
those surroundings in this form of the particle
reservoir that was briefly mentioned at the end of
yesterday is going to fix now not only the
temperature, but also a another quantity related
to the particle. No, in a similar way that the
temperature is related to the energy. So that is
what we. Begin with today by introducing and
declaring that the quality that will remain fixed
in the grand ensemble when the particle number and
internal energy or change is both the temperature.
And what is called the chemical potential, that
character you appeared on, the diagram I just had
up.
And we could have introduced this kind of
potential already back in the unit to when you
were talking about the micro economical ensemble,
we define temperature as a derived quantity on the
basis of. Specifying or controlling the internal
energy and number of particles we saw, the inverse
temperature was the response of the entropy to the
change of the energy with a fixed number of
particles the chemical potential is defined in.
The analogous way is interchanging the role of the
energy and particle number, so we consider the
response of the entropy of a system to a change of
particle. No, with the total internal energy of
that system fixed in this definition. We also have
this pre factor that. We will discuss and consider
what exactly it means and a bit of detail.
We have in addition to just that derivative, the
response of the interview to the huge particle
number through the factor of the negative
temperature so that the chemical potential and
temperature have the same dimensionality,
specifically the dimensions of energy in our
that's where those winds constitute a one.
Temperature and energy have the same dimensions.
Now, back in the case, the temperature, while this
definition in terms of a partial derivative was
not terribly intuitive, we have a sense of what
the temperature is, what it means, and how energy
we can expect to flow from hotter systems to
colder systems. The chemical potential, at least
if you're anything like me, you don't have a very
deeply ingrained intuition for what it means or
what it signifies. So let's go through some of its
properties in a bit carefully first during that.
In addition to having the same dimensions as the
temperature, it also has the same intrinsic
intensive properties. So if we take two systems
with the same chemical potential and combine them
into one system, that combined system twice the
size will have the same chemical potential as each
of those two subsystems, just like the temperature.
And in contrast to the particle, no matter what,
your entropy which increase as the size of the
system increases the chemical potential and
temperature. Are those fixed when we look at small
subsystems inside a larger system? And if we think
in a bit of detail about what this definition
really means, but what happens to the entropy when
we change the number of particles, we can conclude
that the chemical potential is generally negative.
Which is. Unlike the temperature. We can see this
by recalling that the entropy is, in a sense, a
measure of the amount of information that's
present in our system. A number of different ways
those particles can be arranged into different
microstates. If we add more particles, even if we
keep that overall energy fixed, they tend to be
more microstates, more ways of arranging those
particles and hence more information or more
entropy. So increasing that. Delta in the bottom
of the story that it leads to an increase in Delta
s implying that the partial derivative as a whole
is positive in general and then specializing to
so-called natural systems with positive
temperatures. We have a product to positive
quantities with a negative sign leading to you,
less than zero. And if we were to. Go back to
second unit, to the entropy we derived for the
spin system in the microeconomic ensembles and
carry out this derivative. We will see we will end
up with negative numbers for the chemical
potential and maybe it's worth saying before
moving on to justify this, that this is a
definition and in principle, we have a choice as
to how we define the chemical potential with or
without this negative side. So we want to justify
the choice that's being made here to keep the
chemical potential negative. We can do that by
thinking about. What happens if we take to some
systems, put them together and allow them to
exchange particles so there will be some net flow
of particles between two systems, just call them A
and B net. We will say have the same natural
positive temperature, but different values for
this partial derivative that is appearing in the
definition of the chemical potential. So say that
system has a larger value for that partial
derivative with the same temperature. That means
that the chemical potential in System A as a
negative value, that this order of magnitude and
the chemical potential of System B or in other
words, the chemical potential for system is less
than that of System B. So let me know if any of
the. Inequality is coming up here are not
immediately clear.
And what we want to do is apply that second law of
thermodynamics to the situation and think about
what happens to the total and total entropy of
these two systems if particles are allowed to flow
between them from one to the other.
So if the number of state bills and particles are
added to the system, A, we can see that that will
lead to an increase in the entropy system made
just by the product of those additional particles
times this partial derivative. And since we
started off by saying that the response of the
entropy particle numbering system was larger than
System B, we see that the change in the entropy is
this debate for A given fixed number of particles
flowing into it is going to be larger than if that
same. A number of articles for editors just to be.
So if we. Talk about a flow of particles, we have
to remove particles from one of these systems in
order to add them to the other system. So the
effect of the effect on the entropy of adding
removing those particles from System A. is going
to be larger than that of adding removing them to
System B,
which means that the only way these particles
could flow from one system to the other,
consistent with the second alternate universe, is
to flow from System B with the smaller partial
derivative to system a bit the larger partial
derivative that ensures that more entropy is
gained from the addition of the particles, a
system that is removed by the removal of those
particles from the big. So the. That entropy in
the universe increases in this process as it must
by perceptible dynamics and connectedness to the
different chemical potentials that we have. We see
that the particles are flowing from System B. With
the larger chemical potential to system A with the
smaller value, the chemical potential, which is
the same sort of behavior as we would expect for
the flow of heat between systems of different
temperatures, keets or energy flows from the
system, the higher temperature to the system at
the lower temperature. With our choice of negative
sign and the definition of chemical potential, we
now see particles flowing from systems with larger
chemical potentials to systems with smaller
chemical potentials.
And the only wrinkle to keep track of is the fact
that we draw this potential on the line here, the
fact that the chemical potentials are negative in
general needs to be on the smaller value in this
case, a as a larger magnitude zero. There would be
the particles are flowing from larger chemical
potentials, smaller chemical potentials. But
because of that, or thanks to the negative sign in
the definition, guarantees that the larger
magnitude for the chemical potential is a smaller
number with the overall negative sign. So while we
could have made the choice to make the chemical
potential positive in our definition, that would
have led to the opposite behavior systems long
from smaller chemical potentials to larger
chemical potentials. And that raises the dilemma
of keeping track of opposite behavior for our
energy and particles flow in terms of temperature
and chemical potential that we avoid by making the
chemical potential negative. So. Now that we have
at least some insight into the chemical potential,
we can more formally define the grand canonical
ensemble. So just as in the case of the Michael
canonical canonical ensembles, it is a statistical
ensemble, a probability space of microstates
sampled by the system as it evolves in time. Now,
the number of particles and the internal energy of
the system is allowed to fluctuate, and the two
things that are kept fixed in your place are the
temperature and the chemical potential. And both
of those are fixed through contact with that large
external reservoir that is now a particle
reservoir. I'll be going beyond the thermal
reservoir that we considered in the canonical case
to questions about chemical potential and the
definition of an ensemble that we have here.
Not hearing any we can, actually. Perhaps he'll
pretty quickly through this next section.
Producing the economic competition function,
because a lot of this is going to be a pretty
close analogy to what we did to put the canonical
ensemble on a solid mathematical foundation. We're
doing qualitatively or spiritually the same thing
in the grand canonical case. Which is by
introducing an Xbox for the form of this particle
reservoir with which our system of interest can
exchange both particles and energy and then
showing that the form of the reservoir is
ultimately irrelevant in the probability space.
That results, we can then work directly with that
probability space, the system we're interested in
without saying or knowing anything about the
details of the reservoir that are that is fixing
its temperature and chemical potential. So we do
the same thing, the same idea as an economical
case, the so-called replica trick, where we
imagine that the overall system that combines our
system of interest, America, with this large
particle reservoir just consists of a large number
of copies of that system of interest. So before we
had an economical case, we had the same idea where.
We imagined they taken the air in this room,
putting it into a closed beaker of the Sports
Illustrated in this cartoon and then allowing for
seeing what would happen to that combined system
of Omega and its reservoir as they were all in
thermodynamic equilibrium and all allowed to
exchange energy with each other. In this case, we
are dispensing with that beaker. We can
essentially declare that our system of interest as
an example is some cubic centimeter of air in this
room and the particle reservoir is the rest of the
room. So particles can flow freely into and out of
that system of interest taking energy along with
them. And we want to analyze that overall system
in the framework of the microeconomic ensemble as
its full energy and tool particle number are
concerned. So these are total energy that comes
from these are copies or replicas of our system of
interest. So it is a visual.
Illustration of the setup.
Similar to the spin system that we had the first
time we did the replica trick, we now have a bunch
of replicas of our system of interest, which we
can declare to be this one in the center. And in
addition to allowing energy to be exchanged
between any and all of these replicas of the
individual particles in them can also be swapped.
Between. The various replicas, but the system
itself and those that form the overall reservoir.
And and for simplicity, let's say that all of
these particles are indistinguishable, so we don't
have to keep track of which particle is in which
replica. We only have to care about the total
number of particles in the total amount of energy
that they have and the microstates of the system
of interest that they happen to be in 40
microstates of the overall. Many replicate system.
Charging through with a few more details about the
setup.
We are going to assume that. The small system
we're interested in, the single replica in this
collection, has some number of possible
microstates and we define the overall microstates
of the system of our replicas in terms of how many
of those replicas are in any particular
microstates of that small system. So this is
exactly the same idea that we went through in Unit
three to define the canonical ensemble. We. Define
the occupation numbers and corresponding
occupation probabilities, we're. For each of these
microstates, Omega III of the single replica small
system, there are in the total number of replicas
in that particular micro state. So the overall
number of replicas is just the sum over all of
these occupation numbers. And normalizing those
occupation numbers by the total number of replicas
gives the occupation ability, the probability that
if we look at the overall system, pick some
replica at random in the collection, it will be in
this particular microstates eye with probability
piece by.
And this analogy to what we did with the thermal
reservoir case is direct enough that we can
already write down some results for derived
quantities of this overall total system of RF,
because we know that the total number of
microstates is just the number of ways of.
Selecting or assigning all of the occupation
probabilities and one up to an end to the are
different replicas. So that's an hour factorial
divided by the product of an vectorial and two
factorial all the way up to and seven factorial.
And the logarithm of that gives us the entropy or
the overall system, which. Looks a lot like the
entropy for. A single system with an overall
factor of multiplying the sum over P4P for all of
the occupation probabilities where we have to get
things in this form, a plan, Serling's formula.
For both our and every one of the occupation
numbers, so there.
The total number of replicas needs to be extremely
large in order to have a large occupation number
for every single microstates of the small system.
The. Really, the only difference in the set up so
far is that these different microstates of our
small system now are allowed to involve different
numbers of particles in addition to different
energies. So is that set up clear before we dive
into the calculation that. We have to do with it.
Let's keep continuing like we did in the canonical
case. What we want to do is, again, to determine
the temperature. Of not only the overall system,
but because the temperature is intensive. The
temperature will be the same for our small system
of interest within this large reservoir. The new
ingredient is that we also want to determine the
chemical potential of the overall system. These
are the two qualities that are going to be kept
fixed by contact with this large part of the
reservoir. And from the definition of temperature
and chemical potential that we started off with
today, we see that we need to first determine the
entropy of the overall total system, take partial
derivatives with respect to energy and particle
number, and that will give us the two quantities
we're after that we want to. Keep fixed and.
As always, when determining the entropy
corresponding to the dynamic equilibrium for this
large system, we have to maximize the entropy,
declare that, identify some dynamic equilibrium as
the condition where the entropy is saturating its
maximum value. The longer has space to increase
further into the second life. And we now have
three different constraints that need to be
satisfied in order to or in the process of
maximizing this entropy to these constraints we've
seen before. Back in the canonical case, the
occupation probabilities, in order to be actual
probabilities, have to sum up to one hundred
percent. And the total energy. Of the overall
micro canonical collection of replicas. So the son
has an extensive quantity over the energy of each
replica. This has to remain fixed at this fixed
value, the total and doing the same trick as we
expressing the total energy, not as the sum over
all our replicas, but is the sum overall in
microstates of the small system we did by the
occupation numbers. We end up with an expression
for that total energy in terms of the occupation
probabilities and the energy of each microstates
of the system we're interested in. So that is
exactly what we had back in the three and we
defined the canonical ensemble and the new
ingredients. Is playing the same game or the total
number of particles amongst all of these are
replicas which just swaps the energy for particle
no in all of these and microstates of the small
system.
So, in fact, this. Constraints on the part of the
number is the new ingredient that will affect the
maximization of the entropy. So adding to the. To
the knowledge multipliers that we had worked with
previously is a constraint on the. Total
probability to be one hundred percent and negative
beta, I should say, that's alpha negative beta.
It's raising the total energy in this combination
of system plus reservoir. We have this third grant
multiplier in the form of GIMA that accounts for
the constraints on the total number of particles
compared to the occupation probabilities for each
of the microstates.
And having set things up in this way, the partial
derivative of this modified entropy in order to.
Maximizers. Is fairly straightforward. Remember,
the derivative of peace of iron with respect to a
piece of cake, is that her delta of like so it
picks out the microscale whose occupation
probability we are taking the derivative with
respect to and in the first term. Of the modified
entropy, picking up a Delta IC and something over
gives us that overall factor of minus our times,
one of the
Delta picking out the key term. In that sum, the
derivative of the log itself is one over.
Which cancels out with the PKK in to leave just
one. Similarly, we have a delta to some number I
multiplied by Alpha, just gives us Alpha Times one.
We have. L.A. Times are a similar delta now
multiply that by the energy, so the energy of the
microstates and then finally. The new ingredient
is gametime are with the Delta and some number I'd
give and take so isolating in this expression that
is equal to zero the.
The only term that depends on the occupation
probability we lose. Everything else, the other
side, the buy through by negative, are so that is
a negative one from the term in parentheses. Plus,
alpha over our military hours in the final two
terms, so we just keep the beta
gamma and in other words, the occupation itself is
the exponential of these four terms.
We can we organize, as we did before, into. Ratio.
Of the two factors that depend on. The internal
energy and political number for corresponding
microstates divided by the.
Negative of the first two terms or one minus Alpha
over. That is makes no explicit reference to the
Microsoft case that we are interested in and we
can define a new
parameter. Is that supposed to be this exponential
factor in the denominator? Keeping the. Other
exponentially as they are.
So we can replace my handwriting with equation
sixty nine, which should match what we just
computed where.
Instead, somebody will be identified as the dragon
on the competition function that gave this section
its title is a direct expression of one of the
original advice multipliers that we started off
with. And that leaves us with a set of free
parameters that we are currently working in. And
again, the same procedure as when we did the
replica trick for the canonical ensemble without
appli each of those three constraints in order to
fix each of these three parameters, declaring that.
All those constraints are satisfied, the
probabilities are well defined, probabilities
getting to one, and similarly, the total amount of
energy and the total number of particles are all
accounted for among.
It was 10 seconds. That was a test. So we are
going through the three constraints to fix the
three parameters coming out of our maximisation of
the entropy to identify thermodynamic equilibrium.
And in that way, define the canonical partition
function. Now, the first of these constraints is
the easy one, summing over all of these
probabilities in the form that we have now derived.
And declaring that the result adds up to one
hundred percent, that is this. One over ZG out
front and then the exponential factor that depends
on the microstates by the speed times, the energy
plus gamma times, the particle number. And we can
stop there because the statement that this some
adds up to one immediately tells us that if we
move this. Partition function to the other side of
the equation is just equal to that sum over the
exponential factors.
They'd be in jail in nine.
The other two constraints are. A bit messy to deal
with. We want to.
Recalling the overall goal of determining the
temperature and chemical potential from personal
evidence of the entropy with respect to the total
energy and number of particles governed by the
micro canonical ensemble in this.
Roughly, Colacello. We want to relate these two
parameters, be that, again, to those toll particle
number and total internal energy, which we can
immediately do by playing in the value that we
derived for. The economical protection function in
terms of being so.
In these expressions, if the overall picture are
we have the total energy given by the sun over the
micro probability is times under the microscope
internal energy or particle? No. Those.
Probabilities now are exponential factor divided
by some of that exponential factor overall,
microstates I'll use different.
Indices for the two songs in the numerator
denominator here, so we just have this complicated
expression, much as we had back in Unit two, that
in principle relates the total energy and particle
number to beta and gamma in. Fairly opaque ways.
Having written this down, that we might as well
simplify things for you.
Have identified some of the denominator as one
over ZG, that's another coopetition function. And
if we note that the. Terms of time, this
exponential factor is equal to the partial
derivative of that exponential with respect to
give up. That would bring down the specter of
supply. And analogously, if you wanted to bring
down a factor of supply, that could take a partial
derivative of each exponential term with respect
to negative data.
We can see them that. Once we sum over all of
those parts of Riverdale's. The partial derivative
is a one year operation, we can take it outside
the sun and end up with another factor of the sum
of all microstates of our extensional the minus
nine, which is the protection function. So overall,
we have an expression relating to the total energy
to the negative derivative with respect to data of
the logarithm of this particular function as a
function of gamma. And similarly, the total number
of particles is related to the derivative of that
same log. That's the key factor with respect to
the other three parameter gamma.
So that is going to be useful in just a bit.
Hopefully something we'll get to today before
Friday.
And the next step in getting to. The end goal of
our calculation is to. Write down this expression
for the entropy now in terms of the total energy
and total particle number. This is the quantity
whose derivatives we're going to take in order to
define the temperature and chemical potential for
both the reservoir and the system that is in
contact with that particle reservoir.
So the quick way of filling in this calculation is
only plugging in the result we've derived for one
of these factors of the occupation probability and
keep the other one.
Hanging around.
And let's see what to do is put a parenthesis
there when want take the word. Out of this
equation, six, nine at the top of the page, the
first turn will be the negative log of ZG. So I
should have left room for. The negative sign.
There, then we break up the exponential sum into
the product of exponential technological both,
which just leaves the argument lightning speed up
the gamma and I.
And.
We can see that the Lord of ZG is independent of
the individual microstates or something over, so
all that is left for this term in that song is
just the sum of the probabilities themselves,
which is one you end up with two negative signs,
three positive. Our Lord ZG. We have a negative
beina times negative are so plus beta, and then
what's left is our times, the sum over all
microstates of the occupation, provability times,
the internal energy for those microstates, which
is.
This factor we have.
Very nearly on the page, but not quite. Which is
to say that some gives us the total energy
multiplying data. And similarly now, with the
negative sign for the game, the total number of
particles from the song of occupation probability
times. The number of particles in each microstates
of the small system of interest,
so.
All you need to do with this is now take the
derivatives with respect to both. The total energy,
as well as the total particle number that defines
the temperature. And the chemical potential, the
temperatures, the familiar one to start off with.
So the derivative of the first term with respect
to the energy has this cost factor of all of the
number of refixed comes out front. And then I want
to recall that this. ZG is a great economic
competition, function is really a function of both
beta and Gamma. That in turn related to the total
energy. So going through the chain rule in this
computation, we can look at the derivative with
respect to energy. And just to save my wrist, I
will leave off the subscripts. This will be the
total energy in this computation. And we can pass
that through to the derivative of. The slogan of
ZG with respect to Baida and similarly the.
Derivative with respect to Yeva.
And to read carefully, to distinguish it from that
partial derivative, some. The second term, we have
the derivative of.
Beta with respect to energy.
Plus, the grid of energy with respect to energy,
which has just been itself, and then finally. The
total number of particles times that derivative of
gamma with respect to the energy
and now these equations, 1771, are proving useful.
We have that the derivative of looks at G with
respect to data. Times are is the negative of the
total energy. It's minus E. Leaving off that
subscription, similarly, the derivative with
respect, given the times are going to give us
positive N. So overall, we have. Derivatives of
data with respect to energy.
Focus has gone funny down there.
That comes with the factor of minus E you have.
Derivative of gamma with respect to energy. Times
a positive and the plus the other three terms from
the previous line. He debated the. Beta and minus
10 gigabit,
which simplifies very nicely the E times positive
and negative, he began with the E times positive
and negative NP and all that is left here. It is
just data.
So we have found, in short, that. This Legrange
parameter around multiplier data is identified
with the inverse temperature through this replica
trick, this process of.
Maximizing the modified entropy and imposing
constraints on the internal the total internal
energy of our our replicator system.
And.
Do we have time to go through the. Similar
arguments. In terms of the chemical potential.
We might, but maybe that would be a good place to
pick up on Friday, this is a way of checking in
and reminding where we are, what we're doing to.
To get going with the remainder of the setup of
the grand canonical ensemble. So give us a chance
to review this calculation of what it means. Are
there any questions that have come up about it up
to this point?
And we have a few days off to think about it.
We'll pick up and possibly get through the
formulation and into some applications of the
canonical ensemble that I see you next on Friday
morning. So. Take care of them.
I'll see you later this week.