All right, we may as well get under way, with the recording
started to pick up the number for this
morning: five four
five six three two.
Let's check to see if there are any questions
about the computer project due in two and a
half days or so, or the photon gas started
working from yesterday, and we'll now wrap up.
As a reminder, we went through a fair amount of
details about precisely what Sauternes are and how
they behave in terms of statistical physics
information, we need to know what are the energy
levels you photons in a finite volume and what are
the
what is the result in Connecticut, potential to be
some over all possible occupation numbers of those
energy levels in a particular setting, the
chemical potential to zero to recognize that it is
very easy to create and destroy these massless
particles of light as we do every day, switching
on the lights and looking first at the derived
quantities coming from the screen canonical
potential. We considered the energy density of the
photon gas as an integral over its frequency.
The frequency of the photon is related to the
energy of each individual photon by a factor of
Planck's constant each part. And the argument of
this is to rule over all possible frequencies of
the photons and the quantity known as the spectral
density of those photons or simply the spectrum
that tells us.
How the overall energy of the gas is related to
different ranges in the. And your frequencies that.
That I can cover and the ultimate result we found
was a quantity known as the spectrum, so we
constant factor with lots of piles of unit
conversion quantities like the speed of light C.
Multiplying this ratio of that frequency could
divide it by exponential factor of each barrel,
make up over temperature, so the exponential
growth of energy relative to the temperature. And
that's a tricky one, as usual, for gas as opposed.
And using the relation between the wavelength of
photons and their frequencies, what is the inverse
of other with the conversion factor of two PI
times the speed of light? That is set by the fact
that the speed of light is fixed to be the speed
of light. You were casting this blank spectrum
into. The form of the function of wavelength
rather than frequency, and that's where will pick
up today with. Some comments about results in the
form of that spectrum that we can identify from
just the simple change of variables that we went
through. The integration of this integral over
wavelengths. As. Factor of 16 PI squared up front
and then dependence on one over the wavelike for
the fifth power. That multiplies the exponential
factor now expressed in terms. Of the wave length
to able to see Overlander then minus one. Laying
out the argument of that integral, which is here
in equation six and perhaps more interestingly.
Plotted in this figure, which does indeed fit on
the screen for three different temperatures, that
corresponds to the. Inverse of that data that
appears in the expression we derived, which is up
on the screen in the debate, is the temperature
and as. The temperature increases, we see
different behavior for three versions of the
spectrum. It's red, green and blue lines. For
temperatures of three thousand Kelvin, four
thousand Kelvin and five thousand. Kelvin, with
just a slight change in normalization, if you were
to plug an equation ninety six yards, you have to
divide out by the solid angle of the circle and
multiply by C to convert from the spectrum density
to what's called a spectrum radians power per unit
area for a solid angle. But what we can. Match up
with this plot compared to the equation that we
have
all, at least temporarily, zoom out enough to put
them both on the screen at once. We can look at
the two different limits first, considering the
limit of short wave length. So that's high energy
use or rapid frequency use that corresponds to the
ultraviolet regime of high energies that are
higher than the violent side of the visible
spectrum. And when we have the short wavelengths,
that one overlap is the fifth factor, the first
part of this spectrum density in the parentheses
becomes a very large factor. Drilling like the
fifth power of the inverse way of life. But at the
same time. The main factor that depends on this
exponential becomes an exponential of a very large
positive number as LAMDA becomes very small. Let's
divide it through here on the inverse relationship
between energy and wavelength so that minus one
becomes negligible. We have a one over exponential
suppression. Of the overall. Power spectrum, which
is what you see down here in these high energy
short wavelength limits where all of the curves
for any value or the temperature down to zero
radians zero energy exponentially quickly despite
the. Power of whatever land to the fire, trying to
push them up.
And the other limit's. We look at the infrared
that has long wavelengths and low energies that
are lower than the red side of the visible
spectrum.
What's going on there is that.
We now. No longer have much. Well. We have a
suppression now coming from this first term in
parentheses, again, that one, there were members
of the five that we can see as a steady decrease
of all of these curves going to longer wavelengths,
SHIRU slotted in units of micrometers. What's
going on in the exponential factor is interesting
because as this one over lambda becomes very small.
As that becomes large, it has the same effect as
making the inverse temperature very small. It is
the same, the temperature large. So the argument
of this exponential factor can become small, both
for large wavelengths or high temperatures. And
it's that high temperature limit that we
identified last week as the classical regime,
where this quantum prediction for gas and metals
Muslims should approximately match. The classical
prediction coming from the Maxwell government
statistics, which is also included on here by
prominently as this black line for that highest
temperature of five thousand Kelvin that matches
the one that is the same temperature, I should say,
as the blue curve for the black spectrum. And we
do indeed see that as we get out to larger
wavelengths, even at the level of three microns.
The classical prediction is approaching quite
rapidly the spectrum for that same temperature to
five thousand Kelvin, and we can even. Recover
that classical theory as an approximation to the
full classical. Result. So we need to do here is
recognize that we have the exponential of a small
number and just expand that exponential power
series. So one plus that small number plus a half
times a small number squared and so on, intricate
that difference in the first term that doesn't
cancel out. Zoom back in to make this. More
visible.
You work. So the factor in the denominator of the
spectrum becomes just the argument of the
exponential TCP IP that HRC Overlander and
plugging that in when power of the lambdas cancels
out with the win over Atlanta of the fifth that we
derived yesterday, and we end up with just the
temperature divided by wavelength to the fourth.
Has the leading order prediction from quantum
statistics in that. Long wavelength infrared
regime. Which matches the. High temperature
classical, this is indeed the classical prediction.
That's. Was found in the eighteen hundreds before
showtimes were conceived of as quantization of
electromagnetic radiation by the third baron
Raleigh. His name was Strutt, but everyone calls
in Raleigh for all the things that were named
after him and James Jeans. So this simple.
Spectrum eight times the temperature divided by
the wavelength to the fourth power was found for
the energy of electromagnetic radiation. Back in
the 90s, hundreds from sending over all possible
energies for each degree of freedom prior to the
development of quantum statistics. I should
mention that this form of the spectral density is
sometimes known as the black spectrum, the
historical origin of that terminology
comes from considering what happens if you have a
hot object at some given temperature t it is
emitting thermal radiation in the form of
microwaves and other leaves on the electromagnetic
spectrum without reflecting any of the
electromagnetic radiation that is in its ambient
environment. So when something reflects all the
light that shines upon it, it shows up as light to
our eyes, like the paper that's being projected up
onto the screen here where it said it absorbs all
of the radiation. It emits only the radiation that
can be attributed to the temperature that shows up
as a black hole or absence of color. So this black
body is a perfectly and meaning and perfectly
absorbing.
Object that's can be isolated from its environment
and the electromagnetic spectrum it emits. And
what we can see here from this classical theory,
maybe even easier to see in the equation than in
the plot, is that as we go to short wavelengths in
the ultraviolet, there is no longer in the
exponential suppression that we had from the
spectrum. Instead, we just have a divergence of
this energy density. And is the power of one over
the wavelength of the fourth. This is.
Something that became known after that Vallentine
spectrum was developed as an ultraviolent
catastrophe has to go to the ultraviolet. We're
the wavelength is short
light at that wavelength is carrying apparently an
infinite amount of energy away from this hot
radiating body. And it was in the year nineteen
hundred that much funk derived the spectrum that
now bears his name be the exponential suppression
in the ultraviolet that he introduced, not with
any idea that
quantum mechanics would result, but just as an act
of desperation, some way to cut off this infinite
amount of energy that was being predicted by the
classical statistics. We call that an act of
desperation and turned out, with historical
hindsight, to be one of the first steps towards
the discovery of quantum physics underlying the
classical physics that breaks down at low
temperatures in the quantum regime.
And one other.
Aspect of this figure that may be worth pointing
out is. How the. Maximum in this spectrum between
its ultraviolet suppression by the exponential
factor and its. Infrared suppression by the
wavelengths for the 4th and the polygons form in
between those two suppressor regimes, there is a
peak where the amount of energy being carried by
photons of a given wavelength is maximized. And as
the temperature increases, this peak becomes more
pronounced and also shifts towards higher energy
use to go along with that higher temperature. And
once we get up to the regime of several thousand
Kelvin. We see that this peak is located in
wavelengths that correspond to the visible light,
you can see from red to yellow school violence,
which. It's not actually a coincidence, these
wavelengths are that three to four hundred to
seven hundred nanometre range. So about half a
micrometer. And. It turns out that the. Solar
radiation is the amount of light that comes from
the sun to the earth. Is also peaked in this
visible region, which is almost methodology,
because having the amount of light maximized in
that region gives somewhat evolutionary motivation
to evolve eyes that are able to make the most use
of. And that particular flight where it is most
abundant coming from the southern.
There are some complications where certain
elements in the atmosphere, especially water and
carbon dioxide, but also even oxygen, can absorb.
Certain wavelengths of the solar radiation that
reaches the top of the atmosphere and doesn't
penetrate all the way down. To sea level or to the
surface of the earth, but even with that effect
that's shown in the yellow histogram here on top
of the red bars that measure the amount of
sunlight that is able to penetrate all the way to
the surface of the earth, that peek of sunlight in
the visible region, four hundred to seven hundred
nanometres is still present.
And what is interesting, comparing the Planck
spectrum, what's here called that black body
spectrum to the amount of sunlight that reaches
the top of the atmosphere, which was initially
measured by folks getting up into higher buildings
and traveling as high as they could on back in the
early 1970s, one hundred years ago, to measure the
effect of that atmospheric absorption. Nowadays,
it's done with satellites, experiments. If we can
see that this yellow histogram approximately
follows the pattern of the simple not interacting.
Black BlackBerry spectrum that we derived based on
the green canonical ensemble for gas and matches
photons.
And in particular, if we adjust to the temperature
that shows up in that spectrum, you get the best
fit to this data from supposing that the
temperature of this photon gas is a little under
six thousand Kelvin. The agreement isn't perfect,
which is reasonable because our derivation assumed
that. There were no interactions of photons with
anything else in the universe. They were just
isolated. Not isolated, but they were confined to
a certain volume that we have now divided out of
this spectrum to get the spectrum density. The
energy is divided by the volume. But even with
that. Those caveats, this fit of measured data to
the functional form of the spectrum. Can predict
the effective surface temperature of the sun to be
a little under six thousand Kelvin, which is no,
you will see on Wikipedia, if you look at how hot
the sun is, at least at the surface where these
photons that we see are being emitted. There is
some significance on dependence of the sun's
temperature on how deep within the sun you probe.
And we can carry out the same sort of procedure,
measuring the energy of the light that we see from
distant stars. As a function of the wavelength of
that light, producing a similar sort of histogram,
fitting it to the flat body form of the spectrum.
To measure the effect of surface temperatures of
the various distant stars, which can range from.
Red giants, where the rinzai we can remember is
the low energy and long wavelength side of the
losable regime that corresponds to temperatures up
to about three or four thousand Kelvin. And then
the other regime, the blue stars, approach the
high energy violet side of the political spectrum.
They correspond to effective surface temperatures.
Up to or even above ten thousand Kelvin.
So that is. A famous application of the blank
spectrum to analyze the light that is sometimes
causing trouble with the visibility of the screens
in these rooms, are there any questions about that
result before we move on to one other use of the
spectrum?
This is going to be. Another comparison of data
and this somewhat idealized modeling based on the
assumption of not interacting massive particles.
What we can do is use this playing spectrum to
determine the temperature of so-called empty space
located in between galaxies or even clusters of
galaxies where there are no stars, no gas clouds,
no matter of any note. What there is in this
intergalactic space, rather than being completely
empty, they are permeated by a low temperature gas
of photons that is left over from the Big Bang
roughly 14 billion years ago and known as a cosmic
microwave background. As the name suggests, these
photons are at low temperatures that correspond to
the more wavelengths of microwave radiation. So
tens of centimeters in wavelength is what you saw
briefly yesterday. And let's pause for a moment to
put up an artist's impression of the scale of the
evolution of the universe, where time goes on from
left to right. And we are here at the end of the
universe's evolution, starting from the Big Bang
and some quick inflationary. Expansion of the
universe after about three hundred seventy
thousand years. The temperature of the universe
cooled sufficiently for electrons and protons to
form neutral atoms that changed the composition of
the universe from the hot plasma of electrically
charged particles to neutral atoms and light that
is able to propagate between them. And it is that
light that after about thirteen point eight
billion years of expansion and stretching of its
wavelengths has cooled down to that microwave
region that we can now see. So when we look back
to the intergalactic space far away, looking back
to the afterglow, if you like, of. The. Transition,
the recombinations, it's called, that left behind
these albums that are now occupying these
microwave frequencies. And, you know.
What? Has been done for several years in a series
of ever more technologically sophisticated
satellite experiments. Has been to look at the sky
in all possible directions and measure the
temperature of these photons in the direction
being looked at and what that produces are figures
like this. Which is a result taken from a
satellite called the Planck Satellites Satellite,
again, another thing named after Max Planck. And
that projects the whole night sky onto the same
sort of oval. You can also see for maps of the
surface of the world. So
this is a sphere being rolled into the Oval, it's
connected along all of the sides. And design, so
that's a different angle, corresponds to roughly
the same area here. Now the measurements of the
temperature that are attained by fitting this
cosmic microwave background energy measurements to
the spectrum turn out to be very uniform in all
directions, a temperature of about two point seven
five Kelvin. So about a thousand times lower than
the energies of the sun or even red giant stars.
And in figures like this, that average temperature
is subtracted away and what's being shown by the
different colors from blue to red are temperature
fluctuations. From these fights to the spectrum in.
Each resolvable direction. And it turns out these
fluctuations are very tiny and very difficult to
resolve. So the. The red colored regions are the
warmer ones that are about 20 Kelvin. I'm sorry,
20 Microtel then point. Out to Miller Kelvin,
hotter than the blue collar regions. So looking at
the average temperature of two Kelvin, that's been
reflected off here. The scale of fluctuations here
is. Suppressed by about four orders of magnitude,
ten thousand times smaller than the average,
having to resolve use for significant figures. In
the midst of the energy of cosmic microwave
background photons to the spectrum and just to
wrap up.
We can take a look at one such fit.
Here as a function of frequency rather than
wavelength, it has the similar sort of suppression,
both in the. Low frequency infrared regime. As
well as the high frequency ultraviolet regime,
this frequency is being measured in units of.
Ten of the 11 seconds multiply by that.
I have noted here that. Around this. Three. And 10
of the 11 seconds frequency corresponds to.
Wavelengths of light that are. Millimeter scale.
And they're going to be the microwave regime about
a thousand times longer wavelengths than visible
light, that's now just below the micrometer scale.
And so this is a figure from nineteen ninety. So
the first experiments known as the Cosmic
Background Explorer, or Kobad that was launched in
the late 80s and produced its results in the early
90s and has since been superseded by a local
Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe experiments
and most recently, the Planck satellite that
produced. This result. This was the example of the
first round of cosmic microwave background
measurements and the solid line that fits the
spectrum to the data points in the boxes produces
a prediction for the overall temperature of the
cosmic microwave background in the direction being
analyzed. We've got two percent uncertainty that
has since been increased by a couple of orders of
magnitude despite those technological improvements
of the past 30 years. The first result did receive
the Nobel Prize in physics about 15 years ago in
two thousand six. Merely by showing that the
precision here pointed to six was just large
enough to resolve the fact that there were
anisotropy in the cosmic microwave background,
temperature at different directions in the sky
headed of the notes and almost forgot to mention
that it is those centrifuges that provide some of
the strongest evidence that we have for the
existence and characteristics of dark matter.
Along with some of the. Maybe more familiar.
Astrophysical observations of how galaxies rotate
around each other and clusters of stars rotate in
those galaxies, that there is ongoing relevance to
the determination of. Of.
The angle dependence of the temperature of the
cosmic microwave background, at least for. The
purposes of this module to the next point to take
away, to wrap up. This comparison with data from
solar radiation as well as cosmic microwave
background radiation is that even though you've
assumed an ideal gas of not interacting, photons
in the collected all sorts of possible effects.
That can interfere with this idealized situation
we still have. We still end up with an excellent
mathematical model for real systems from the
hottest to the coolest objects in the universe
from. Ten thousand Kelvin. Stars to the. Boys in
between galaxies, billions of light years away. So
I'll briefly pause with that statement to see if
there are any questions about. The spectrum as a
whole or in comparison to his experimental data.
And not seeing. And we can charge ahead to wrap up
the full equation of state for the first time. Yes.
So we've been talking a lot about. The integration
of the function that we have to integrate over to
get the energy density of this photon get us now,
we can actually carry out that integration and get
the energy density itself. So when the scale here.
I've written down that integration over the full
spectrum here in terms of the frequency. As the
independent variable Omega Cube divided by an
exponential factor like this one. And all we need
to do to evaluate this integral is. First, change
variables to.
It's been a Farmigo. Each boiling over temperature
so that. The differential factor, Dominga. It's
the ratio of temperature over Plank's constant
times, this to X.
This is a direct change of variables, so there's
no funny business with the limits of integration.
They still go from zero to infinity and we have a
causal factor of T over each bar to three powers
from the Omega Cube and the fourth power from the
Omega.
Integrating the exhumed ducks over E, the X minus
one. Which is it famous in school that we can look
up in? A way we prefer it to be famous, in part
because it's. It's a remarkable combination of the
remote Zyda function and the game, a function that
we saw related to Vectorial powers of Gamma four
is three factorial, which is six, and the revised
Zeta function for a even positive integer is
related to the power of Pi. It is high to the
fourth over ninety times six from beginning to
function. That's three factorial. So we pick up
from that integration. Is they part of the force
that cancels out to powers of high the denominator
and then.
15 in the denominator, a PI squared was canceled
and then four hours of H bar, one of which is
canceled from. The existing factor we still have
three powers is the speed of light and all four
powers of the temperature are unaffected.
So the overall energy density, once we integrate
over this form of the spectrum.
Just depends on the. Temperature to the fourth
power with some three factors that convert that
temperature to energy density and the power of PI
squared and 15 from the data function
and.
Compared to the.
Classical economic result was three halves t this.
T to the fourth, dependent's looks a bit more
complicated. Especially because it is an.
Energy density, and we have to normalize by the
oil in which we have. Can find full time gas. But
we can't simplify things. By considering the
particle number, which, as always, in the great
canonical ensemble is able to fluctuate,
especially with the vanishing chemical potential
that remotivated for gases of photons that are
very easy to create and absorb. And from the same
expression we started off with last week to derive
that energy density a derivative of. The grim
economic potential for the full time gas, the
corresponding derivative with respect to that
chemical potential with the negative sign, gives
us the average number of photons in this gas,
which we can also expect to depend on the
temperature. So this equation here.
Simply plugs in the expression for the great
economic potential, for the photographs that we
previously computed, pulling out the dependence on
the chemical potential. Now it's going to affect
the derivative. And then at the end, once we take
that derivative, we will set the chemical
potential equal to zero for the photon gas.
So.
It's a very similar.
Calculation compared to previous one. We're now
going back in this gap to the initial step of
taking the derivative of the potential.
So once we do that inside this integral over
frequencies,
we can pick up. The. Arguments of this logarithm
is the first step in the chain rule. So when
Lindsay made it to Omega, the positive. Universe
temperature tops chemical potential in the
numerator, we have that factor of Omega squared
coming to law. We have an E to the minus beta
maker coming along with the negative side and then
the derivative, with respect to view of each of
you, brings down a positive beta. And with that
same exponential factor, each debate you increase
temperature cancels out the temperature that your
regular science cancel out. And let me set you to
zero. We get with deal maker there.
The.
Integral from zero to infinity, squared over,
divided through by the exponential arc, each part
of the difficulty. Something that looks quite
similar to the spectrum, this with a different
power of the frequency omega in the numerator of
this integral. Making the same change of variables
as before, setting the beta omega that appears to
be exponential to our variable X.
You pick up a similar factor of the temperature
over each bar now to the third power, two of which
come from Omega squared, which comes from deal.
And then the.
Famous Integral X squared over the X minus one B X,
that's.
Is related to the very similar combination of
Remon Zeta function and gamma function. Now, both
of the arguments, they're just dropped down one
power corresponding to. How x in the numerator in
this grid, so a function of three is two factorial,
which is two and then three months. The function
of Unit three is an irrational number. That's
about one point two.
This overall factor is about three point four,
what is best to leave the rational numbers like
zero three and PI just in their usual form. We end
up with. We have to grant giving us to. Zeta three
times the temperature, naturally. Few power.
Divided by a pie squared. Now we have each part
you see queued for the average time number
densities of the average number of photons per
unit volume.
The fact that this depends on. The third power of
the temperature, while the energy density depends
on the fourth power of temperature. Shows us how
we can simplify.
Our expression for the full time gas equation of
state. Despite recognizing in the overall energy.
Multiplies through by this volume, we can isolate
each of our cube cube times the volume times T
Cube with one power of T left over, we have that
off the screen
and that factor of our cube second with a T cube.
We can relate to PI squared at times, the average
number of photons divided by two times have three.
We squared over two to three, multiplied by a pie
squared over 15, gives us an overall height of the
fourth. Multiplying 30 factors of this irrational
see the function now you see the three. So we have
the same functional format as each of the three
heads and see that we had four classical addresses
in the canonical ensemble. There are just.
Two things that have changed that now we have to
consider not only the average internal energy that
is allowed to fluctuate, but also the average
number of photons that fluctuates in the grand
canonical example. And the overall pre- factor is
no longer three hands.
We were able to compute pretty easily just from
the functional form of the energy related to
momentum for non relativistic classical ideal
gases. But instead, we have this interesting part
of the fourth over 30 times, say the three factor,
which if we look back to the two special integrals
that we invoke, we can actually recognize as a
very fun ratio of camera functions and reminded of
ocean values. Jennifer Zyda, four, divided by a
three to three. Which turns out to be numerically
around two point seven percent, not quite twice as
large as the non relativistic classical factor of
three house.
Now, there's not quite enough time to. Completes
the calculation of the full time gas equation of
states today. I guess that gives us a good.
Good tasks to start off with on Friday, just to
serve as a reminder of what is going on with time
gases. What we can. Wrap up today by recalling
that the equation of state is a relation between
the large scale properties of this gas, which
includes particle, no temperature and internal
energy, but also the pressure of the gas, which we
looked at a lot when we used classical ideal gases.
As the basis for developing from cycles and.
Getting work out of heat engines back in Unit five.
Now. The pressure of a full tank of gas is so
commonly known as the radiation pressure, and it
can sometimes be counterintuitive to think that a
gas of massless particles or gas photons that are
streaming down from the light is exerting pressure
on. The surfaces that we show you, this is just a
consequence of the Amanto that they are carrying
related to their energy and frequency that we've
already seen, and formerly the radiation pressure
is defined in the same way as ordinary pressure
for particles envisioned as a bunch of billiard
balls bouncing off of the services of this
container. We look at how the average internal
energy of the photon gas changes as we change the
volume, which is fine with the negative signs, you
get an increase energy to correspond to a decrease
in volume. And in this change in volume, we have
to make it isotropic or 80 that it keeping the
entropy of the photon gas constant.
And.
Now, looking at the time, I think we have time to
quickly write down the condition of constant
entropy for the full time, us a very simplified
relation that we have. For the example, when the
chemical potential equals zero sum, normally in
the great economic potential, there would be a
third term in this expression related to new times.
The average number of average particle. No. With
zero chemical potential for photons, this boils
down to sort of expression, you add in the
canonical example that the entropy is the
difference between the internal energy and the
free energy. In this case, the land of free energy.
And considering just this ratio of free energy to
temperature. But we can write down and again, make
the same change of variables to X of data for
Omega a pretty. We have yet another fun integral
that depends on the data function, but what
matters here is that this interval is just a
number and is the functional form that we care
about. We can see that the three factors of
temperature over each bar come out of the omega
omega squared, just as for the photon, no density.
Give us three powers of the temperature times the
volume, which is our condition of constant entropy.
And I think the good place to pick up the
remainder of the calculation of the equation of
state on Friday. Final questions before we break
for a few days.
And if not, then if you have the second part of
the computer project due in two and a half days to
keep you busy if you're not already done with it,
and we'll wrap up the summer time gas equation of
stage and turn our attention to fermions on Friday
some of you are able to enjoy. The nice weather
for the next few days, I'll see you back in the
other room Friday morning for radiation pressure.