All right, let's get this in focus just in time to begin.
That's better.
And we'll start off today with the usual six digit
number for you all
It is eight eight two seven
five three
Now we can get another week under way in Statistical
Physics.  Welcome back, to the official start of
spring. And are there any questions lingering
from what we were doing last week with quantum
statistics building up now to the culmination of
this section of the module, which can briefly
recap to get reoriented going into this new week.
So it's the twenty-first of March,
and as has been the case for a little while, we've
been building up to analyses of quantum gases.
Based on the one hand.
Ukraine canonical example, the. Third of the main
sophistical ensembles. Considered by this module,
which allows both energy and particle number to
fluctuate, affixing temperature to the potential.
And along with the approach crime statistics,
which differs from classical statistics by, as we
saw last week, something over screen energy levels.
Considering all the possible occupation numbers
for those emerging models rather than. Consider
individual particles in the something over all the
ways that they could be arranged and trying to
correct for overcounting in the case of
indistinguishable particles, and we wrapped up the
last aspect of quantum statistics last week by
looking at the Bose Einstein.
Statistics of. Those arms particles that can have
those legs.
Statistics of particles that can have any negative
occupation number, the energy level, and compare
that to. The family director. Statistics of
fermions, which can have at most one fairness in
an individual energy level and saw that in both
cases.
In the high temperature limit with a large
negative chemical potential.
Your predictions for both those aren't named
formulas approached. The maximum Boltzmann
statistics
that we derived through the classical approach
that was for attention much larger than the high
temperature that was in turn larger than the
relevant energy levels. It doesn't quite all fit.
On that screen there, but.
Are there any questions about the crime statistics
stuff that we wrapped up last week as the shaking
heads, so I'll just move straight into the quantum
gasses that we took a few minutes to look at on
Friday, reviewing the quantization of energy
levels that occur when we place these gases in a
finite volume. Both sides, though, Kud.
Determines the possible momentum and in terms of
the possible energies for ideal gases in. Such a
finite I'm that to depend inversely on the size.
Of these containers believe that the gases
formulated in the first change that we saw looking
back over this case now relativistic, massive
bosun's in this cubic volume was an adjustment to
our onsides for these types of energy levels.
Based on Heisenberg's uncertainty principle that's
ruled out the possibility of negative or zero
energy states for any particle in this case,
knowing that the particles are confined to a
finite region requires in turn a non-zero momentum
and zero energy in order to satisfy the
constraints on the precision with which the
position and momentum of each particle can
simultaneously be defined and. Restricting the.
Possible injuries appear in the momentum and in
turn the energy use came, like he's said, to be
strictly positive rather than negative. Also, Mr.
Riquelme, Friday, we saw this ultras, the
DeGeneres's, with which different energy levels
are realized, depending on permutations of these
possible, until they rush through a bit just at
the end.
You could just add a little note here that I think
the political responding to this trip generates a
whole set of energy levels with the. Next to a
minimum possible interview for. A single particle
for all possible combinations of. Permutations.
Of the. Where is the. Merger momentum can be
oriented in. The directions, X, Y and Z.
So all of that was, at least in part, a review and
a slight adjustment of what we did with classical
ideal dresses back in Unit four in the framework
of the canonical ensemble. And that would make
things a bit more interesting and brand new for
today
by specializing to a certain type of particles
known as photons, which are particles of light.
And while many of these lecture notes over the
past week, I realized that there is a significant
amount of capital without photons and relativity
and electromagnetism being brought into play in
formulating these ideal gases of photons, not
interacting particles. So I will try to be clear
about. Some justification for some aspects of that
information, as well as setting Selamat. Details
aside, that we don't need for the purpose of
statistical physics.
So maybe the key feature of photons that
distinguishes them from the classical idea of
gases we consider previously are that these
particles of light are exactly massless. And
correspondingly, travel at the speed of light. Now,
what we have to do for the purpose of quantum
statistics is specify the energy levels that are
possible for a system of photons. The volume of
size vehicles cube, and it should be fair to see
that for a system of massless particles equal to
zero, the energies that we were working with in
that non relativistic case back in uniform in the
brief review on Friday are not well-defined. Those
who have energy or momentum squared divided by
twice the mass dividing by zero is nobody's idea
of a good time. So just as a result that we can
take as input and say that the room accepts that
the energy of a photon is. No longer is momentum
squared, divided by twice as mass, but rather just
proportional to the magnitude of its momentum. So
that is the square root of the sum of squares. The
magnitude in each of the three spatial directions,
X, Y and Z defines that. Magnitude and the.
Consider proportionality that relates the photon
energy and its momentum P. Is traditionally.
Cold sea, and it corresponds exactly to the speed
of light and really the speed of light is doing
here is just converting units between matter and
energy. So if we were to work in a sensible set of
units where management energy had the same
dimensions, that speed of light could just be set
to one, the same way that we have done with the
Boltzmann constant violates. Temperature and in
units of energy. And
I'll say just a bit about how this expression for
the the of energy can both be easily remembered
and also connected to the non relativistic
particles that we considered earlier, which.
Are related through your general expression from
special relativity, though, how many of you have
seen that relativity? And if so, what detail does
that you have? Might recall that the energy
squared. For example, is a combination of two
factors first, being squared of the squared and
the second being this momentum times the speed of
light of squared relation that is sometimes called
Einstein's triangle. Just because it has the same
form as the Pythagorean relation, if we have a
triangle with a square on one side, the right
angle and on the other, then the magnitude of its
hypotenuse is squared is equal to the sum of them
squared, squared, plus the square now would be
massive zero as we have here. This just boils down
to an energy equal dependency, which also holds in
the ultra relativistic regime where masses are
very small compared to momentum.
And in the case, the stationary particles from the
momentum is zero. All that's left of this relation
is the famous Masamichi Square. And we can also.
And divide the number of units, kinetic energy
that we had on the previous page, just from
considering the limit where the math is large
compared to the momentum in the units, or if we
take the square root of this relation about the
overall factor of the large. Amnesty Square, then
what's left is the square root of one plus.
Squared, C, squared off over. It was clear to see
that before if we expand that square roots in the
Taylor series. Times Square, times one plus P
squared over two. And squared, C squared plus
order went up to the fourth and the fourth with
the conversion factor. And then spending.
Multiplication there just leaves us with the
massive energy up front and C squared for the
stationary particle in a P squared over two times,
them over M squared is more powerful than the sea
squirts cancel out and there are higher order
corrections or people of the for cubed squared. So
it does. Here is this large mass energy was larger
than the events and the next correction is exactly
the number was a mystic kinetic energy that we
were working with in Unit four and we've been
moving on Friday. Now. That is just a simple way
to remember the connection between these
novelistic regimes.
The trial's not going to focus on the case of
massive where the energy is. Just the momentum
times and to continue specifying the energy levels
for photons of gas, and we need to take note of
the DeGeneres's of all these energy levels, which.
Something that I will just state and set aside for
each momentum that leads to the same. Energy is a
function of the magnitude of the momentum there
are to generate energy levels with what are called
different polarizations. This is coming from the.
Relation between the photos as quantization and
propagated electric fields. Or we don't have to be
that fancy and talk about privatization, but just
call that electromagnetism describes the
propagation of light and in fact the whole
electromagnetic spectrum, which can be polarized
in two different ways. If there is interest in
seeing details about that polarization that can go
into it, say a tutorial. But for the statistical
physics that we're interested in, you can just
take the double degeneracy of all energy levels
for photons as inputs. And this is an additional
degeneracy that multiplies all once we went
through the gate on Friday related to the possible
permutations of the orientation of these momenta.
So with.
The sort of generalities all touched upon, you can
go ahead and specialize to the same volume that we
had before, which leads to the same discrete
momentum for the particles in that plane with a
strictly positive set of integer, X, Y and Z. And
the corresponding energy is now. Are just a factor
of the speed of light see times those
corresponding with same before flying in each bar
and the ratio of high overhead all times the
magnitude of these integer tables, we can write
just as K with no decoration.
So the expression we have for. The energy of a
photon with a given set a moment to specify by
these integers, hey, is this past the time
somebody Shilpi over 11 times that killed in a
volume of size cubed? Which is something we could
certainly work with, but it's more convenient to.
Besides this event and put it in form in the form
of the wavelength of photons and their
corresponding angular frequency, which. Is too
high at times. It's called the cyclic frequency of
essentially the cyclic frequency measures, the
amount of cycles that. The electromagnetic waves
cycles through per second and the factor of two PI
is just a conversion factor, changing that in
seconds, two units of radians per second. And this
Omega here for the frequency. Of this. Foot tidal
wave is. A possible source of confusion with
microstates to try to. Distinguish. And for any
wave that's propagating the. Wavelength and the
frequency of that wave are. Together determine the
speed of that propagation, which in the case of
photons is just the speed of light. So the product
of wavelength times frequency is telling us how.
How many cycles the wave cycles about space, the
second wave length inverse, that number of cycles
to the length of the cycles, getting to the final
form of length per unit of time or speed.
And.
Thanks to. The relation between particles of metal
and wavelengths introduced by the Detroit. Which
we touched on earlier in this course of.
Having. Can find our first home guests to this boy,
you. Size allocute, we require that both the
momentum and the wavelengths are quite as
prevalent as we've already seen several times.
Depending on this ratio of Purell and the wave
subject to the constraints that. And even number,
a integer number of half of what it's made up of
or two must fit in this volume, which is probably
easiest to recall based on this visual
representation down here where the wavelength is
the distance for the wave to cycle both up and
down to the back around to its regular starting
point. So this one here is a complete wavelength
we need in order to have a standing wave that does
not destructively interfere with itself.
There must be an integer number of half
wavelengths so that. Nodes can be fixed to the
boundaries of this volume, so the longest possible
wavelength that can be contained in this volume of
size altitude is precisely the wavelength of twice.
That bill twice the size of the school year,
corresponding to K of one in this relation between.
The size of the container and possibly finds that
it can contain.
Swapping out the white flag over to that appears
the definition of the speed of light with this
quantization condition. We find that the speed of
light. This is the product of the frequency of the
sometimes. Time's all over this, not over this
positive with your career, if I hide it, we can
reorganize. To isolate this factor of higher
timescale, which is suggested because we just had
an equation 90 to exactly the height of the
Alzheimer's. Multiplied by the speed of light, see,
multiplied by each four identified has the energy.
So. This. Quantization of the possible wavelengths.
In turn, quantize as possible frequency's. Baker
is C times PI, 12 times is energetic. So equation
number two boils down to the simple expression
that the energy is each part of Jamaica. So as I
walked to the side, a lot of details about photons
coming into the construction of the end, a very
simple expression for the photon energy. That the
energy is a function of frequency is just about
four times that frequency with the frequencies
quantized by which you are working in. This is the
usual container with a volume of allocute solution.
Pause there to see if there are any questions
about all of the photos and details I went through
fairly quickly and in some cases set aside. Four
separate discussions or just to take his input.
It looks like we're happy to accept this result
for the energy levels of photons. There's just one
quick visualization, beautiful illustration to
highlight one aspect of this which may or may not
be familiar, that's. Is to see.
By plugging in the inverse relation between
wavelength, the frequency by the speed of light,
that the energies of photons are inversely
proportional to their wavelengths. So when we have
George Wavelets. We have.
Small energy is. And low frequencies available,
which is known as. The infrared regime, infrared
being a fancy way of saying less than the red side
of the visual spectrum of electromagnetic
radiation. And similarly, when we have high
frequencies, that corresponds to short wavelengths.
And high energies that are known as ultraviolet or
higher energies than the violent side of the
visual spectrum. This.
Picture here. We'll just flesh out as a bit of
illustration of this relationship and show the
full spectrum of electromagnetic radiation of
photons organized by. That wavelength and
equivalently the corresponding energy, so. You
talked about things in terms of infrared,
ultraviolet, setting them around the visible
spectrum wavelengths of several hundred nanometres
where higher energies or shorter wavelengths are
the violet side of the visible color spectrum, and
the lower energies have longer wavelengths, part
of the red side of the spectrum. At the infrared,
we get to longer wavelengths, 10 micrometers.
And going on for the two larger length scales.
Order. Centimeters in the case of microwaves that
can be used to heat up food and then even tens or
hundreds of thousands of liters of radiowaves,
very low frequency and wavelength, low energy
photons in the other direction takes us to the
ultraviolet wavelengths, shorter than high energy,
violent side of the visible spectrum, eventually
going out to x rays and gamma rays. That probe
site sizes down to the molecular atomic nuclear
scales that correspond to higher energies and
higher temperatures, we'll see.
Through that inverse relation between wavelength
and energy.
So that is what's the background about what
happens your. To plug in what we've taken away
into the grand canonical example, the frame of the
problems is so. As we arrived last week for close
to six, we consider the helpless one energy levels
one at a time in the form of the great medical
potentials. This is. The negative temperature
times, the logarithm of the protection function in
the criminal courts are the fundamental starting
point for analysis. And in the case of those
outside statistics, we derived this form of some
of the lowest energy levels of the logarithm. But
the quantity, one minus and visual exponential
factor, the energy value minus, the chemical
detection by the body temperature with the
constraints.
The. Chemical potential must be blessed in any
given energy level in order for the geometric
series. Defining those statistics to converge and
give us know the final results, so putting in the
fact that the photon energy is dependent only on
the momentum enabled by this trick, you can
believe the sum of our energy levels to a sum over
all the possible vectors of X, Y and Z with the
overall factor of two polarizations states
mentioned.
It's about.
It's the double degeneracy of all energy levels,
in addition to the permutations of the incremental
direction. In what we can do to simplify this
expression in the case of photons is actually
approximate that chemical potential. As zero based
on the.
The fact that we can appreciate that photons are
relatively easy to create and destroy, that is to
say that in a very wide array of physical
circumstances, we can change the number of photons
without changing the energy. Of the corresponding
statistical system to an appreciable extent. So
all the lights in this room, for instance, are
blasting out a huge number of photons every second,
every unit of time for us to be able to dust off
each other and see what's going on. And similarly,
if we heat up food or drink in a microwave oven,
there are a vast number of lower energy photons
with longer wavelengths in the microwave regime of
centimeters and tens of centimeters. That's.
Involve an enormous number of photons without too
much change in the energy, so plugging that
physical argumentation into the expression we
derived. For the chemical potential on the basis
of the generalized identity at the end of Unit six,
you see that even when the change in the number of
photons is very large, change of the energy is
very small. So the overall chemical potential must
itself be very small. It can be ballpark's by zero
to great economic potential. That almost looks
like something you might have seen in the
framework of the war with no reference to the
chemical potential. But we still do have to
remember that the number of photons is going to be
fluctuating in all of these gases. And indeed, the
vanishing chemical Wythenshawe essentially means
there's no restriction on the possible
fluctuations and you can take any conceivable
value without penalty.
And. Just to be safe, we can check that with the
Spanish mechanical potential, we still satisfy the
condition. For. The convergence of both sides
expects to work in a finite volume that requires a
non-zero value of the momentum and therefore
non-zero value of the photon energy
disproportional to that momentum. So the strictly
positive energies remain larger than the vanishing
chemical potential, and those statistics is well
defined for the spokeswoman's.
What we can do to further simplify this sum over
all the possible energy levels labeled by these.
Integer vectors proportional to the momentum is to.
Again, motivated by physical situations, think
about photons in a boy that is very large compared
to the photon wavelength. So that the energies
that depend on one else coming from this volume
are all very closely together and this discrete,
some over it is your chance to win in kids that
can be approximated by. Integration. Over
continuous legal parameters, Jon Karl Capehart and
about to run from this very small number one over
L up to infinity. There is a. Negligible error
introduced by extending those approvals from one
of the way down to zero. Look at these three
spatial directions so we can go ahead and do that
and then convert to Sterkel Point. That's.
Which is. Profitable to do, because we have seen
the full time energy dependence only of the
magnitude of this three reactor. So all of the
angular information coming from the different.
Directions that explain why kids that can be
oriented can just be pulled out into account, the
factor that turns out to be because the factor of
Hiromitsu in the.
Is a visual way of identifying this cost factor of
pilots who used to picture the three dimensional
space of these white kids and think about the
portion of that space that is highlighted by
requiring. Positive values for those three
directions.
No attempts to do that three dimensional drawing
on the board.
Or another other words, real.
Finding ourselves two positive tests, positive and
positive, said, picking out just.
Think of the full year.
Almost
half of. The greater than zero, they'd like to
have less than zero. Similarly.
By values that are greater than zero, neglecting
those that are less than zero and finally
executing their values that are greater than zero.
Rather than.
They're going to listen to your side. Put that
down in the. Lefthanded court system, but it
doesn't matter.
With about one eighth of the total salad angle of
this sphere, we do these angular derivatives from
zero to by halves rather than all the way around.
Zero to pi, those ultra angular directions ending
up with. Just this single integral over the
squared. Legal parameter, perhaps going from zero
to infinity, the time over two multiplied by two
you in the Grand Canal. The potential leaves us
with. Pilots times to prefecture on this integral.
And then the general log of one minus the
exponential with minus energy temperature. Coming
from those same statistics with the initial
chemical potential. We can now just plug in the
photon energy that we. Derived earlier today and.
Change variables from the continuous OK, that is
proportional to this frequency or the absolute
proportionality coming from the speed of light.
To find the finish line before the starting point
for. Statistical analysis. What we have instead of
these three factors, of course, had three factors
of the frequency of Bego that.
Brings in. Three hours of Ellenwood over the speed
of light see times it pulled up in front of the
integral.
And simplify to identify that altitude as the
volume of the container gases and multiply by the
temperature divided by three towers at the speed
of light, two powers of high degree of a frequency
that would be on that frequency squared times, the
logarithm of one minus E. To the energy, the
temperature must be a each Kakamega coming from
the energy of. The football is a function of the
continuous. And frequency, frequency.
So that is. The. Specific form of the grant
potential for default, I guess we have just enough
time to go on and certain predictions out of this.
This expression of new questions about the steps
we went through to drive this or some of the
approximations that we induced along the way.
Let's let's get started with some of the more
interesting aspects of the photos. Yes, the
feeling is that we have remaining.
We're in order to extract a more quantities like
the average energy density of photon gas. We just
need to take appropriate derivatives of that great
potential must be derived at six, which again,
simplifies things to be able to set the chemical
potential equal to zero, removing the constraints
on the number of photons. Our presence in our gas
microstates, so if we. Take the. General
expression for the average internal energy in the
ensemble later to the day, the derivative of the
times, the corresponding canonical potential. We
can express this as itself, and if you go over the
frequencies of the photons.
Divining through by the overall power of the boy
to consider an average energy density.
Where the integral in this expression is crucially
known as a spectrum density or just a spectrum
that relates how much energy in the gas is
connected to photons of a given frequency or by
the. So I'm sorry that this school district uses
the same symbol as the pressure of the context to
keep it clear when we're talking about the
structure density of energy and when we are
talking about the pressure
to. Go ahead and. Push this partial derivative
with respect to beta through the canonical
potential we had on the previous page just to get
a couple moments connected to it. We have a
divided three by the volume factor. Beta cancels
the temperature up front. So we have one over Kubi
Square left over and then we can push the beta
derivative all the way into long ago. I think that
depends.
And the.
Derivative of this dog is going to start with the
arguments in the denominator. Everyone at minus to
the minus beta, each particle bigger than the
chamber brings it through and have a negative the
to the negative beta, each part will make the
numerator. Bring down then another application of
the Chambal derivative of that with respect to
data as an overt factor of minus.
Where the negative signs cancel and we can pull
the constant each bar into this prefecture and
each other secured a square.
Integral from zero to infinity now of. Three
powers of Omega, an additional one brought down
from the derivative and the dividing through by
this exponential factor, as we did before when
considering the. Average occupation numbers for
the present statistics have to be positive. Better
able to make a modest one. Then that derivatives
sorry, the integration over Homebake itself.
Identify this as a control over. Our spectral
density is a function of the lack of.
We can identify exactly what this spectral density
is. The cost of each bar over the speed of light
squared. Tons aspiration of a magnitude. But with
the exponential etchberger, the temperature minus
one, which reassuringly is.
You have written down as a result, one defined in
the equation, 95, your result that is known as the
spectrum that named after the same bucksbaum whose
constant you've been considering. Since all the
way back and forth and just to.
Take care of. Not a bit of manipulation of this
spectrum, including Bill. Analyze it as a function
of wavelength, so rather than the spectrum, as a
function of frequency relating to the energy of
the photon gas to the corresponding frequency to
the photons in that gas, you can relate the energy
to the gas, the wavelengths that are inversely
proportional to the frequency. So. If I out. A bit
of space in this gap just to. Note the change of
variables that Omega is two pi times the speed of
light divided by the wavelength of the Omega is
going to be the derivative of that with respect to
LAMDA. So negative two squared Delenda. We can
also see that. The lower integration limits make
it close to zero, and that corresponds to the wave
length going to infinity. And similarly, the
proper integration limits of infinite frequency
corresponds to banish wavelength. So plugging this
in, we have a minus. Director of. Well, you have
to high C over lambda for each of these three
factors, omega. We have a fourth factor of two
high. See, coming from deal maker with a single
negative sign, a deal maker is now a de lamda,
each part comes along for the ride, as does the
speed of light squared the denominator. The lower
limit of integration is now going from infinity
down to zero over the wave length.
The deal may go to the lame duck. We have three
powers of land from the Omega Cube, another two
hours from the omega of the due to power, five in
the denominator.
And then the exponential factor is almost to say.
It'll be too high. Beater, each bar scene divided
by the state is all the arguments of the
exponential than the final minus one. Unaffected.
And that would simplify this slightly, the power
of two of the four is 16. We can absorb the
negative side by reversing the order of the
integration. I see I'm running out of time, so
just write down the results here we have each bar
for over three hours at sea and then we go zero to
infinity and the fifth. Used to be that each
person will handle this one. We identified this.
As expected from units of wavelength, we find the
same result. We'll just put up here to wrap up
today at 16 per square studio and the fifth time
that whatever exponential minus one Planck
spectrum. As a function of wavelength, so we
reconvene tomorrow morning, starting today, we
will talk a bit about the meaning of this result
will be computed and. Look in particular at how it
matches up to the actual systems of photons in
nature coming from solar radiation, from the sun
back home, from the Big Bang and everything in
between. So it's the final check if there are
questions about the derivation of this average
energy density we just went through to define the
spectrum. And I guess you have all that to think
about it and see it exactly before we pick up
right here tomorrow morning.
I'll see you on that.
So.