All right, that's the recording started and we can get
set up with the six digit code for this morning.
It is seven three zero zero
five nine.
And welcome to a warm, sunny Friday morning. A very---well,
congratulations on getting through that computer
project. So that's most of the in-term assessment
dealt with. Just one final homework assignment
that will be showing up in your inbox during the
break and due the second week we come back, in early
May. Are there any questions about what we've been
going through recently before we pick up wrapping
up the photon gas and moving on to quantum gases of fermions,
which is the plan for today, or at least for
this morning.  In the afternoon, we may well look at
taking a step back to the canonical ensemble and
look at the heat capacity of a
statistical model of solids.  I have a few
hours to figure out if that will be interesting or
there's anything better to do more directly
related to what's been happening this week.
And
it's to get underway with a quick recap, since
it's been a few days last year at the.
From the 5th of March, that's where the cameras
point to.
So we've been looking at the full time gas in the
grand canonical ensemble as a system of massless
photons.
Because the particles are massless, their energies
are given by their angular frequency, is working
with wavelengths rather than P squared over two in
the classical case, and we have to drive the
so-called Planck spectrum. Or it's called black
body radiation. The photons emitted by an object
at a given temperature.
Without any contamination from reflecting evidence
for plants and found in particular, that spectrum
is proportional to. The ratio of that frequency
cubed divided by E to the minus one, whereas in
the classical limit you end up with something
proportional to. How big a square that that would
diverge a little bit of large frequency's a mega
or short wavelengths, so that is known as the
ultraviolet catastrophe. Of.
Classical treatments of the energy of a mass of
photons or radiation. And we checked this against.
With the solar radiation
emitted by the sun, the temperature around. Little
under six thousand.
As well as the cosmic microwave background,
radiation is very low temperature.
Photons left over from the Big Bang about 14
billion years ago, finding, despite our assumption
of not interacting, ideal gases, good descriptions
of that data. From in both of those regimes of the
high-temperature solar radiation and the low
temperature cosmic microwave background, we went
on to find that. The overall energy density coming
from the black spectrum, sharing out the overall
frequencies is proportional to. These see the
power 40, so that's very different from the
relativistic energy disproportionality tea this
gave us. A.
Well, but it's going to give us today is entropy
and the heat capacity, both of which are
proportional to Cube rather than in case the heat
capacity getting constants like the classical
relativistic gas and the interest in the entropy
is connected to the radiation pressure that we
started discussing at the end of Tuesday's lecture
and will pick up to push through the last steps to
the full equation of states for the first time
yesterday. Today, if we are happy with what we've
gotten up to so far, there is the. Dependence on
the internal energy, that photon gas on.
The fourth power, the temperature which we can
relate through the last calculation that we did on
Tuesday to the average number of photons with the
energy chemical potential reflecting the ease of
creating and destroying photons. That, like the
heat capacity, is proportional to three towers of
the temperature with interesting factors of gamma
functions in Zyda functions, showing up from
carrying out these intervals over that spectrum
and by looking at the.
Usual expression we have for the Entropia related
to the internal energy, the free energy normalized
by the temperature in the case of the ensemble
with the energy chemical potential. We can confirm
that this entropy is almost the times here. That's
exactly what we wrapped up on Tuesday.
This is the condition of constant entropy that
needs to go into the determination of the
radiation pressure. We take the derivative of the
photon energy with respect to the. Volume of the
system,
indeed, is even easier to see that the dimensions
of the entropy would get to be the type of CQ
there is a rather complicated integral involving
more of one minus Ticketfly, the sex that having
cast everything into dimensionless quantities like
this X because the photon energy is Omega divided
by the temperature. That's where the factor of
teen Kud gets pulled out of this overall integral.
Which suffices to determine the condition of
constant entropy that we can plug in to free
expression for the injury to the power for. Now
has to satisfy the relation to that tier is some
constant times the inverse cube root of the volume
we call that tends to be then playing in
relation here. So. For the cost of factories of.
Minus PI squared and over 15 each passing year
cubed. Out front of this derivative, which is then
one power of times negative for two thirds power
towers V.. So there is a cost to be to the forward
and left over. The two year. Minus one third kids
looking out.
One of those negative for three hours from the
fourth power of the constant entropy relation to
the derivative of V to the power, minus a third is
just. Minus a third times, one over, obviously,
the negative signs cancel. This expression,
constant factors of high squared over 15 each bar
scene cubed through. As does the of the 4th and
getting. Moved, the new power of water will be up
front, the original V to the minus one third is
still in place, which we can recognize as.
One over three times, because I think the average
internal energy of the folks on gas when we
started off with. So multiplying through by the
volume, we find an equation of state that looks
very nearly like the ideal gas law we had for
classical non relativistic gases all the way back
in for the chemical ensemble. Where the pressure
times volume is just one third of the internal
energy, which we have related to a constant factor.
Times the average particle number. Times the
temperature of the gas in the classical case, the
ideal gas was PV equals a. the fixed and
economical cycle. And the only change in this
equation, 98 compared to that, is this funny
looking pretty factor that depends on the remote
data function. And the fact is a ratio of two
different values of the remote signal function
zero four divided by zero of three, which is
related to actually the dimensionality that the. I
guess occupies three dimensional space, the total
number is proportional to the three, and the
internal energy brings in an additional factor of
Omega in these sorts of integrals over frequency
that we've been doing, pulling out zero for very
few of those. Is that showing up in the equation
of state. So if we were to imagine photon gas is
confined to some surface, you would expect to have
the same sort of ideal gas law type relation with.
Some different ratio of data functions coming up
at the cost of the proportionality test, maybe
getting a little far away from the mainstream of
this module, and this indeed is our destination
for the photon gas, at least for the time being,
having derived.
All of the usual observables, the internal energy
density, every particle, no entropy and equation
of state involving radiation pressure, and we will
now set some time to decide and turn to quantum
gases at fermions unless there are any questions
about the topic of these photon gases or those
other quantum gases more generally.
And to switch things up a bit and keep from. Re
doing the same thing with slightly different
negative signs, let's look for the most part, abs
gas's of. I'm not attractive, but also not
relativistic fermions.
And again, this is being investigated through
quantum statistics as a reminder, this defines the
microstates by considering energy levels in turn,
something over all of the possible occupation
numbers for each of those energy levels, which
would be for on a case, are restricted to being
either empty or filled, unoccupied or occupied
energy levels. The poverty exclusion principle
forbids the identical fermions in this case from
occupying that same energy level and in the
previous units, seven derived. So-called fair
statistics. That governs the statistical behavior
of these gases of one's. The starting point for
the statistics is with all. Sophistical ensembles
is the corresponding production function. As this
form of product over all of the energy levels
which we can label as running from zero to some
accountable but possibly infinite L
and then. Some factor of one plus or minus two
times the difference between the energy value of
the corresponding energy level, minus the chemical
potential.
Where this is clearly connected to the two
possible occupation numbers, which is energy
levels when a energy level is occupied. The
exponential factor reduces to one when it is
occupied, it corresponds to this exponential
factor of ratio of energy, the temperatures. And
unlike the movies, I have seen statistics where
the convergence of the partition function required
that the energy be larger than the chemical
potential, every single energy level, there is no
such restriction in February statistics and. We
really need to see that both negative and positive
values of the chemical potential are. Realized in
nature, that's in contrast to the system of
photons we were just considering, we argued that
the ease with which we can create and absorb
photons corresponded to a chemical potential, that.
Effectively vanishes, so the corresponding
economic potential arising from. This protection
function. It is just now the sun over the lot of
these factors, one plus the exponential
based on which we want to determine the same sort
of energy, the same sort of quantities we were
looking for the first time, gas, internal energy,
average particle, no entropy pressure in the state.
And what we need to do to start off with this is
specify precisely what these energies showing up
in the energy levels are going to these violations,
including any degeneracy where we have distinct
energy levels with the same value of the energy
and the case of the.
Photon, yes, we had massless particles with energy
is given by their frequency. Here are the numbers
in the case. We go back to that limit in science
triangle, the
the mass energy and momentum energy can expand
that for momentum that are very small compared to
masses and find the usual kinetic energy from
classical mechanics squared divided by two, where
quantization filaments in a volume cube, as usual,
gives us. Energy's. Of the same formerly. Reviewed
in section April one earlier this week, it cost
the factor four squared squared times, PI split
over to end Times Square, that system multiplied
by. The square magnitude of non-negative, that's
really positive integers. Why is that label
possible so that these numbers of particles can
have each of the three spatial directions?
So therefore, the generosity is now coming from
permutations of those.
Different possible ways we can have, say, six
units of momentum oriented in different directions,
X, Y or Z, we calibrated those at the start of
this unit and whereas photons had. To generate
energy levels for. Each sets of vector Numenta.
That corresponds to polarizations fermions is
typical for males have a similar degeneracy. So
for any fixed millennial vector, there are two
degenerate energy levels with the same energy, a
different by a quantum property that is called
spin rather than the two hybridization states. And
we have four photons. And spin is. Related to
angular momentum, but it's potentially misleading
terminology because we shouldn't picture these
four year olds as actually. It's an intrinsic
property.
That they possess where? Particles such as
electrons exist in one of the two states either
spin or spin down with the same level as the
corresponding to the same energy in the state
energy levels. This is the same spin that showed
up in the spin statistics theorem we mentioned in
introducing photons and fermions. And I think
he'll say no more about that now what we can
discuss it further, if there is interest, just
like the organization that's going to suffice to
take this as input, that all of the energy levels
with. These novelistic energies come in, spin up,
spin down the parents, and for typical fermions of
those two distinct values for the spin. So all we
need to do. To get under way is insert these
energies into the great economic potential for
seven, which is written down here.
And that overall factor of two from the two spin
states and then the launch of one plus the
exponential of a larger expression that now
depends on. The magnitude of the incident led to a
case squared with the usual factors that are
critical mass and elsewhere, all divided by the
temperature.
James.
Put in that form of temperature, rather than being
beat up to remind you that this is the. Sort of
expressions we came up with in terms of the
different wavelengths that we were considering,
the classical ideal gases, and for the difference
now being that we have. Some or all of the
intricacies of the logarithm of this factor,
rather than having to take a classical approach,
consider back then of analyzing the single
particle production function and then. Trying to
build a gas, many particles based on that.
We are going to proceed in the same way we did
with the time approximate this complicated sum
over three vector memento by. Approximating that
some over integers by integrals over us real
numbers, something that we can justify at least
when the gas is in a large volume compared to.
It's. The other factors that show up in this
energy, in particular, each bar is a very small
number and then that gives us instead of something
over it, why is it? We can integrate over a the
parameters that show up in the continuous energy.
We can convert to spiritual coordinates as the.
Factor being integrated, so the grant here depends
only on the magnitude of these momentum vectors.
So the anger and the just pull out the same solid
angle corresponding to the positive content of the
sphere. So one eighth of the sphere, the solid
angle for PI will use a factor of PI has. So the
overall expression for the economic potential for
this non militaristic firm, Yungas.
Reduce this to a trickle just over the magnitude
of the momentum. Of this expression, the board of
one, plus the exponential of that.
Negative data on this view all divided by the
temperature.
And.
We can simplify this sort of expression by
changing variables much in the way that we did to
convert the full time gas integration to
integration over the total frequencies that showed
up linearly and the energy we now want to.
Integrate over the similar dependence on the phone
you call the administration variable, that now
depends quite radically on the mentality's
particles. So if we invert this relation between.
Momentum and energy and the variables we want to
work with are going to be. The cat, which is.
Factor of the square root of L squared is just 12
square root, divided by high times, Planck's
constant and then. Another square root of two
times the energy. This is what we want to replace.
The factors of Khap Square to show up in the
center for the Dark had itself is then the
derivative of the square root of the energy which
brings down. A factor of two that cancels out half
of that square root to factor in the numerator and
pay for counseling comes along for the ride and
then e to the power one half if we reduce that
down.
By one factor of energy, it again cancels out half
of that square root of the numerator and left with
it one over square root in the denominator with
the differential factor long. So putting all of
this in.
We have negative TV times. Three powers of this
council prefecture them over age. So.
Scrappiness, Altuve. The three have spoken of MICU.
Each party room.
The limits of integration stay the same, the
energy vanishes when much of vanishes, diverges
with averages. We have over all the roots to the
times that need to be squared has squared and in
the logarithmic factor, which is much simpler now
that this combination.
Quantities is is just the ratio of energy and
temperature, so it's back to. So that. Looks
fairly familiar energy minus chemical potential
divided by temperature. Now the energy is the
integration variable we are integrating over. We
can simplify. This result. I did find that a huge
factor is the volume working in. So pulling out. A
square root to factor. The difference between
those two. So a negative route to this square root
cubed. We have the volume, we have a temperature,
the high humidity and huge variety of factors come
along for the ride. Then there is just the water,
the.
One plus the exponential, the sticks and the
Google factor of the square root of the energy
left over from this. Ratio of energy terms in case
squared, divided by the room to the differential
factor.
So the overall proportionality to that building in
times temperature is the same as the photon gas.
And there are obvious differences, both in the
relative sign that shows up in the logarithm as
well as the overall square root energy factor
coming to the normal mystic nature of these
particles. And we can proceed now to take the
usual derivatives of the economic potential and
then evaluate this integral after doing so.
Which is the same approach that we took from the
photographs with different factors. Different
expressions show in the. Objects being integrated
over.
So our target for. This from Yungas, much as it
was for the folks on the West, will be the
equation of the state relating all of the large
scale thermodynamic properties that we want to
drive.
And what big change that we can see in this
expression here compared to the full time gas, is
that we need to retain the chemical potential. We
can argue that it is negligible in the case of non
relativistic fermions that are not necessarily
easy to create. And so in contrast to photons.
But we will be able to simplify our calculations
in a different way if we focus on the low
temperature regime, which in any event is the
interesting regime. Or we can expect different
behavior compared to the classical dresses we've
already analyzed. Is at high temperatures that the
quantum physics reduces to classical actual
statistics. And we can expect is still an to
reduce to classical thermodynamics of non
relativistic particles without having to specify
any quantum behavior or dependence on the nature
of these particles, asteroids.
So.
As a first step towards this equation, the
statement illustrates the simplification that we
can get by working at low temperatures.
Rather than talking about the spectrum of the
system, the look first at the average particle
number given by the negative derivative of the
Grand Canal, the full potential with respect to
chemical potential. That's the relation between
the lived in Unit six.
And even though we're not looking at the spectrum,
we'll still.
Be motivated by some analogy to that to express
the average particle density so the number of
particles on average per unit volume as an
integral over the energies of the individual
fermions in this gas. So we'll be interested in
the integrated. The function that shows up in the
integral that would have. Left hanging around to
carry out some of this work. She goes by the name
of the family function named after the same Enrico
Fermi as Fairmont's themselves. There is some
contrast to that spectrum caps, the overall
factors that you consider to include a place where
each bar cube separates.
Well. The family function, as well as that split
energy, we are here and I noticed that I did have
a typo in this little calculation where. Puyehue
to the denominator cancels partly with the overall
pie coming from the salad angle and we integrate
over in momentum space so there's always pie
squared times each barbecue in the denominator of
the grand finale potential.
So.
If we insert that result for economic potential
that we just. Derived, we can extract the Fairbury
function.
So pulling out. Fear that negative grew to include
both high school graduates, particularly the
negatives, cancel, get that positive. To include.
Overpriced beach bar cubed, the factor of volume
we divide out, so only a tower of T remains and
then we're integrating over the energies of the
derivative with respect to chemical potential. But
this log of one plus. Exponential factor. Times
the additional square root of energy. So taking
the derivative.
Of that board will bring down, first of all, the
argument of going into the denominator so much
less due to the minus beta,
minus the. And then pulling through the chain to
pick up the data. My view, the derivative of
either the plus B, the Times view with respect to
the two, is the initial factor of data. The
inverse temperature cancels out the direct
temperature to be had. Outside of the integral.
Seeking independence at the end. Which we can.
Ben. Clean up slightly by dividing through the
multiplying by the ratio of expenditures
in the plus meter in this new.
Squared each Teichberg cube.
So we end up then with first one. No need to be
the. E minus two plus one times e t e. Which if we
compare that to the equation 99, defining the
family function is the integration of the average
particle density.
With respect to energy, we can read off. The
family function is exactly.
This one over. Exponential factor. Positive. Even
as New Yorkers have the juror plus one,
which. As promised is.
Very similar to the average occupation number for.
The energy level with this energy that we are
intervening over.
If we look back to the calculation we did for
demographics, logistics in general and the
previous units. So what is way of organizing the
calculations doing is. Relating the average number
of particles that we have given the volume to. The
energy levels with a given infinitesimal range of
energies.
That's. Comes in with the average occupation
number as a function of the energy, not so
surprisingly, but then an additional factor of a
square root of energy. And that integration, which
is something that people need to look at a bit
more closely as we go forward. First, I promised
some simplification for considering this average
protocol, no density at low temperatures, which we
are now in a position to realize by. Looking a bit
more closely at the Fairbury function, we just
arrived, and I'm particularly writing it in terms
of dimensionless ratios of this energy to the
chemical potential and the ratio of the
temperature of the chemical potential. So
replacing Beta with one Oberti. The overall
impression that we have one divided by this
exponential of E minus new over T plus one, if we
pull out the ratio of chemical potential over
temperature for both of those terms, is in the
exponential. We can break it up into a product of
two factors. And the exponential of the product is
exponential itself, raised to the power of those
products, so we end up with an exponential of. The
ratio of energy to potential minus one. All that
raised to the power of the ratio of chemical
essential to the temperature. And this is showing
us two main things, one of which depends on the
chemical essential temperature can be either
positive or negative, the other than depends on
the temperature for a fixed value of the chemical
potential. First of all, whenever the energy is
larger than the chemical potential, the argument
of this exponential is going to be positive. So
the explosion itself will be larger than one being
raised to some power that causes it to increase.
So an object to the one used to power, it's larger
still, which is the opposite of what happens if
the energy is less than the chemical potential.
This ratio is less than one. The arguments of the
exponential is negative and the expansion itself
is less than one, and then gets suppressed and
pushed closer to zero by this power that's being
raised to give by the ratio of chemical potential
to temperature and the larger the temperature.
The more suppression or enhancements this
exponential factor has. And depending on. Which
side of this points equals new reform also? Remark.
That's exactly when equals me and the exponential
reduces to unity based in the power of the family
function is exactly what has. One over one plus
one. What is the threshold where? The behavior of
the family function changes.
It's probably easiest to see by putting that
fairly function.
Versus this dimensionless ratio of energy to
chemical potential for. Various ratios of that
temperature to chemical potential. So the four
different lines here are corresponding to four
different values. Appreciate you over team that
showed up as the. Power hitting the exponential
factor in nominator of the function. So you over t
is going to be one to ten or one hundred for the
red and green, Blue and Black Crowes. That
Stoodley approach to behavior that we just
described by looking at the form of this motion
itself.
Now, whatever the energy is less than the chemical
potential, that's exponential factor is suppressed
and all that is left of the denominator is the
plus one. The family functions and approaches one
over one, which is one the maximum occupation
number that we can have for four months, the
opposite happens whenever the enemy is larger than
the chemical potential. The exponential factor
that is more the one who has this power increases
from one to two to ten to one hundred. That's
exponential. More than one gets larger and larger
and larger. So it's exponential suppression of the
function as a whole, driving it to zero. The other
element of an occupational.
So the. He here. Is that not only are we
interpolating between these two limited cases
where. They're all energy levels are filled with
occupation, number one, or empty occupation of
zero, and interpellation happens faster and faster
as the temperature gets lower with respect to the
kind of global financial ratio of new poverty
becomes larger. And in the limits of. Low
temperatures where we're hitting that exponential
factor is much larger than one. We can approximate.
The security function as a whole is simply a step
function that changes. Essentially immediately
from being one for low energies to being zero for
all high energies and.
Before going on to apply that, just to wrap up
today, I should mention something that may already
have seen. And all of these all of the plots here,
the discussions with the treating the chemical
potentially as a positive under. So that we look
at energy is divided by you that are created in
zero and also looking at temperatures that are
greater than zero, and that is a contrast with the
classical limits of large negative chemical
potential we discussed earlier. So next Monday, we
will justify this self treatment of the kind of
global financial as. Be positive, no show why that
is actually required for now, we will just roll
with this and see what happens when we fly again,
this low temperature approximation.
For the family function as a step function in the
result that we've derived for the average, the
density just a few minutes ago, where now?
We have from energies of zero up to new.
This security function is one to pick up the rest
of the integrated team and then for. And the
energy is larger than you at every function at
zero, the integral vanishes and we just have to
integrate from zero to the chemical potential
itself. The integral of Scooter Libby is a simple
one to compute. Council directors on. For the ride
and we end up with E to the power three halves,
raising the power of that argument by one and then
one over three heads, which is the transit's two
thirds evaluated at zero and the.
Which is below zero for the three 1/2 hour is zero.
And you, the three halves gives us a another.
However, three heads that we can combine with that
to an. So we end up with two and hundreds of
chemical potential onto the three house.
Providing that that's too with the factor of two
thirds will be integral and then a three. I swear
to each barbecued.
As the full result for the average particle, no
density, we will make extensive and build on on
Monday.
For now. Unless there are questions about
what we've been doing with the knowledge Mr..
Gaffes or why?
You're going to go wrap up there for the lectures
this week and have office hours now if.
The topics you want to discuss individually, so
hopefully I'll see you this afternoon, I think,
for some consideration of heat capacities, more
comparisons to experimental data.