All right, the bells have finished and I've got the
recording going so we may as well get under way, at
least to put up the six digit number for this afternoon, which is
five, six, one, nine, four, four.
So, welcome back, now to the second half of the term, starting both a new
week, approaching spring, and a new unit, which is
probably a good point to
pause a bit and check in with the plan for at
least the next few weeks leading up to the term break forf this
module. So, we are here on the fourteenth of March, and the
overall plan---
we are where we're headed at the moment---is to
take the grand-canonical ensemble, the third and final
statistical ensemble that we. Went through the
definition and foundation of last week and combine
that with quantum statistics.
To investigate the behavior of quantum ideal gases
that the particles.
Onto my guess is what's on the screen ideal,
meaning that the particles opposing this gas are
not interacting with each other just the way we
solve for classical ideal gases in the framework
of the canonical ensemble. A few weeks back, a
year before. So over the past week, we dealt with
the introduction of the grand canonical example.
So this is the system where the probability space
was microstates, as defined by the possible
configurations of the particles in the system as
it evolves through time. And now, in contrast to
the micro, canonical and grand canonical examples
that we developed, first, the energy. The number
are both allowed to fluctuate and they fluctuate
by being exchanged with a large external particle
reservoir that fixes to complementary qualities in
this approach the temperature.
The chemical potential.
I kept fixed by that large external reservoir
and then we went through the same sort of.
Construction for the grand ensemble, as we did
earlier from the canonical ensemble, looking at
the.
Protection function.
That is the. Fundamental. Object in this approach
from which everything else can be derived. The
resulting potential for land of free energy that
capital find in this negative negativity holds the
log of energy. And then from that particular
derivatives of this potential, we get our usual.
Observables. The internal energy.
The entropy now, the particle, no.
As quantities that.
We can derive on the basis of the partition
function. And relations between all of them
through that general estimate indicate that. And
the second step in the overarching plan for the
next few weeks is to add to this grand council the.
Statistics of quantum physics, without actually
having to bring in or assume knowledge of any
quantum physics, would just take it as nonsense.
How? Approach the definition of these systems,
which will turn out to be the way that we operate
in practice, but before you dive into that, having
an overview of. The large scale plan and some of
the details that we dealt with last week, are
there any questions about where we are or what the
next steps are going to be?
They're eager to see something new in terms of
quantum statistics, which is again being
introduced. In this unit, so this is another
definition of foundation heavy unit that will find
its application to systems by the gases in the
coming unit in combination with the canonical
ensemble. And.
I should start off by saying probably that the.
The concepts and definitions in here are going to
be a bit more subtle than what we went through
pretty quickly last week with the economic
ensemble, we've seen most of the basic ideas
before. Building at the canonical example use the
same sort of a trick to analyze the particle
reservoirs within the thermal reservoir, the
sample, and look pretty quickly through the
corresponding free energy and the generalization
first thought to try to keep from blasting through
all the material in this unit or at least this
first section quite so quickly so that. All of the
essential subtleties and the reasons we have to be
careful about our definitions of quantum and
classical statistics are hopefully clear and easy
to understand.
And the starting point, having said that, we'll
just be. And considering quantum behavior as
nonsense, it turns out to be realized. We got a
glimpse of at least a piece of this kind of
behavior all the way back when we started thinking
about ideal gases that was in it for the framework
of the canonical ensemble. Where we did a bit of
slightly circular argumentation. Noting that the
canonical provision function, so the sum of all
microstates, I love the the factors that depend on
the energy use of that microstates defined by the
set of moments for all the particles normalized by
the temperature in order to leave the sum as a
well-defined sum. We need to be able to label or
count these microstates, the sum over them. So we
said this nonsense that these moments are for the
ideal gas must be quantized in a way that depends
on the volume which they said, which produces a
discrete value implementor that have accountable
number of energy levels that ultimately give us a
comfortable number of microstates for the sum
defining the partition function.
But given that some of these. Matter for each of
the particles in the systems that define the
competition function. We argue that at least in
the regime where this relation holds, which is
that the plank's constant bar introduced as. A
constant relating the volume of the system to the
possible dementor of each particle. If that is
much smaller than this product of the linear size
of the system, so is one side of the ball, you
know, just the gas is contained and is the mass of
the particles that we are considering. And he is
the temperature. Then. Given the energy use that
depended on.
And the big energies we had for each particle were
proportional to.
This product.
Each bar squared.
Over at. And elsewhere. And whatever. The factor,
the numerator here is very small compared to the
rest of it, any of the energy level is small
enough to have of some factors our space very
close to each other, which is to say that the
function being summed over is very smooth and can
be very well approximated by the multidimensional
integral rather than a sum integrated over
continuous parameters rather than the discrete
moments that we have introduced to be the
production function. So. Despite formally
introducing the need to regulate the system by
quantize, it's not until after a few mathematical
manipulations we went straight back to. Dealing
with continuously varying momenta. As an
approximation to that underlying discreetness. And
then we want to define important statistics, there
will be two things we have to change in this story
compared to what we've gone through earlier. The
first is fairly obvious, given the discussion up
to now. So we will retain the discreet energy
levels rather than approximated by a continuous
Ligairi function and. Any calculations that we do
with these discrete energy levels still in place
will remain valid, not only when? The system size,
temperature and gas are collectively large
compared to place, but also in the quantum regime
where these two factors are comparable.
The second change is the more subtle. Which is
related to the fact that in quantum mechanics, we
are dealing with indistinguishable particles,
indistinguishable particles. This is something
that you can get out of the car mechanics module
that is just going to have to be taken as given in
this module. So we will say that we are interested
only in identifying particles that are
fundamentally indistinguishable. And to say that
this is a feature of quantum mechanics. And the.
Issue that arises in this case is how to handle
microstates in which there is more than one of
these indistinguishable particles in a single
energy level of the sort that be considered in the
unit for every. Recall when?
Back around back in this Section four point one
where we went through this argument, there was a
footnote noting exactly where this assumption had
come into play that we assumed every particle in
the system had a different momentum, or to say
that the way it was in a different energy level
with a different value of the energy, and you'll
go through these two steps in more detail, one
after the next, and then we'll see how. The.
See what problem is introduced when that
assumption breaks down and we will also see where
that assumption breaks down, which will correspond
to the quantum regime. There are usual classical,
non-partisan approach is going to run into trouble.
So that's the. Plan for how this the remainder of
today is to go through both of these changes,
Internet first be fairly simple, one of retaining
a discrete energy levels rather than sending over
continuous variables. And the second. Thinking
more carefully about what happens when multiple
indistinguishable particles occupy the same energy
level. So first, we ignore that second issue and.
We will just compute the economical prediction
function for a system with some unspecified but
discrete energy levels. And even though these
energy levels are discrete, they're quantize. By
virtue of ignoring that second issue, we will
still end up with a classical or quantum. System,
not classic, the classical set of statistics known
as Maxwell Boltzmann statistics, we've already
heard Boltzmann's name many times it was marginal
or connected to theoretical developments in
statistical physics. Nineteen hundreds. James
thought Maxwell was a Scottish physicist working
around that same time. He's best known for
Maxwell's equations of electromagnetism, but also
worked out statistical physics as has as his most
famous physicists asked. Two hundred fifty years.
So.
With a brief pause to see to make sure that the
plan is clear.
There are no questions about the broad overview of
the two steps. We'll be going through. Let's start
with that first step and derive great economic
competition function for a system with discrete
energy levels, so. To put some vacation in place,
you will see that these discrete energy levels are.
Label by the variable L lowercase no running from
zero up to some large capital L. which we can take
to infinity while still leaving the number of
energy levels and hence the number of microstates
countable. And during the partition function, well
defined and some over this comfortable microstates,
the energy level itself. We will refer to you with
this calligraphic for a truly e labeled by and.
One minor subtlety in this approach is that the
energy level is characterized both by the actual
value of the energy for a single particle, and so
each energy level refers to the possible
microstates of a single particle. And in addition
to the actual value of the energy with capital E
agreement funds, they will bael, it is also
possible for there to be additional information
distinguishing energy levels so that multiple
distinct energy levels E, Sabeen and Ezabad,
within the different from anything can be
different, indistinguishable even when they have
the same energy. So the upper case energy is our
equal. I apologize already for the proliferation
of different sorts of issues that will have to be
kept track of in this universe as we build things
up.
And the. Technical term of four different energy
levels with the same value of the energy for the
particle is that these energy levels are
degenerate and we will choose to label all of the
energy levels so that whatever this. Index that
increases the energy itself is now decreasing, so
it either stays the same or increases, and without
loss of generality, we can shift all of the energy
levels by any additive constants so that the
smallest energy is Sub-Zero responding to the
crown stage, the lowest energy level, which would
be the calligraphic use of zero,
is non-negative that.
Is justifiable and can be justified if you want to
see that argument. Now, what we have to do with
this notation in place of energy levels and the
cost of energy for these levels is that we have to
define the microstates that we sell over. In
writing down the Grand Canal, the coopetition
function, that depends on the temperature that the
potential new. And you drive last week that
the factor being subdued in the great economical
partition functions, this exponential factor that
depends on both the energy and the chemical
potential times the number of particles in the
corresponding micro space because of all of that
divided by temperature, multiplied by the inverse
temperature below.
Now, there's a.
Nice way to organize the some of the microstates
so that we can keep track of all the microstates,
ensure that we don't lose track of it. You can
also handle them all. In a easy way, based on the
work that we've already done, and this is to break
up the single sum over all possible microstates
into a series of cells, each of which considers a
particular value for the particle. No, so. It's
written here. In his first term to break up the
sum over the microstates, I guess the first is
some over the microstates that have new particles
in them, they're actually always turns out to be a
single micro state of that, which is just empty
back, you know, particles. And then we separate
them off from a second sum over all of the
microstates indexed by chain that involve only a
single particle. So this is. Taking into account
the fact that the number of particles in the blood
sample was not fixed and can fluctuate by particle
exchange with the particle reservoir, and we can
tell you the next song by studying over the
microstates that involve exactly two particles.
And in all of the exponential factors that are
appearing in the song. We can plug in already that
the protocol number multiply that multiplies the
chemical potential is equal to one to two to three
and so on, up to infinity.
What we can do with this, why this is the oldest
trick, is that if we break up these exponential
factors.
Into so where a fixed number of particles, lower
case than times do we can pull this constant
factor of new times in?
Outside of the overall sum and what is next, then,
is just the sum over Bowsman factors, even the
minus beta times energy. For all of the
microstates that have either a fixed number of
articles being one, a fixed number of articles
being two and so on, up to having a fixed number
of particles being infinite and fixing the number
of particles while allowing the energies to
fluctuate with the fixed temperature exactly
defines the canonical partition function for and
particles as a function of the inverse temperature.
So. After we pull out the exponential factor that
depends on the times, the chemical potential.
Times the critical number for all the microstates
with that fixed number of particles.
Chemical factories multiplies the economic
competition function for the corresponding number
of particles, starting with the trivial zero
particle, because is unity and the protection
function for a single particle, you cannot have a
production function for two particles and then
generally some.
Over the number of particles ranging from zero to
infinity of. This exponential factor into The View
is raised to the power of the number of particles
that multiplies the canonical partition function
for that fixed number of particles in each other.
And this is a general result, but we haven't had
to specify any details of the energy levels
themselves.
This holds for any grain economical system with
discrete energy levels, it is known as the free
gas, the expansion a I'll tell you right now,
that's not a term you'll have to remember
something you might see popping up here. There it
is present because this exponential factor that I
put out is called the figure acidy for obscure
historical reasons.
We will benefit from this approach is that now, in
order to compute the great economic competition
function with oil that's calculated down to
dealing with economical partition functions, which
of course, we did for several weeks in the
framework of Abdelbasset cycles, and in particular
we saw that in units three and four that we have
in indistinguishable particles in an ideal system
with these particles don't interact with each
other. That the end particle hold function is.
Just the single particle protection function
raised to the power of end and then normalized by
this factor of one over and factorial that
corrects for the overcounting.
Repeatedly counting different microstates that
would differ only by the labels we give the
different particles. And while I talk, I'll try to
come down with the later on that screen.
So.
Particles get that full factor of the function to
the power. And that counts all the different ways
we can imagine the different particles of
microstates from the particles are
indistinguishable, all of those different
labelling secretly describe the same microstates
in that factory and factorial as to be divided out
to get the correct number of micro microstates. So
that is. The Carex for the overcounting. Of this
invisible particles from the base, the particle
position function off of the powers of the single
particle protection function. But this is. A very
nice expression to insert into the equation and to
keep that guessing factor to our end and then in
the important competition function as whatever in
factorial times, the single part, partition
function to the power, and we can rearrange things
as the cell membrane from zero to infinity of one
over and factorial times, some quantity to the
power end, which is exactly the power series for
the exponential function.
So this whole infinite sum over infinite options
for the number of particles in the Grand Canal
system boils down to just the exponential of the
single particle canonical efficient function times
the sagacity exponential factor of chemical
potential divided by temperature.
We.
The fact that we're considering a system with the
discreet energy levels that we define at the start
of this subsection, so. There are these
microstates labeled by Hill that each have
possibly equal energies separately, so then the
single particle microstates are simply. Counting
how many energy levels there are for this single
particle to occupy. And with each energy level,
the corresponding both the vector. And the
canonical approach is E to the negative by times,
times, that energy, so the overall single particle
petition function simply has to sum over all of
those energy levels of that Boltzmann factor into
the minus beta, the energy. So every so there are
L plus one total microstates, they went from zero
up to L, each of them correspond to a different
energy level, even when the value of the energy
for the energy level may be the same. And if we
plug in this expression for the single particle
protection function into the grand canonical
partition function that we derived through the
capacity expansion, then we have.
The exponential of that figure has to be times the
sum of the factors which we can rearrange before
we get into orbit, if we get ourselves into an
exponential that looks more like what we're used
to for the grand canonical. Ensemble. So the
exponential of the sum overall energy levels of
this exponential factor, it the minus B times the
difference. Between the energy of each energy
level, labor, well, minus the fixed chemical
potential of the system.
So that is. The chemical protection function that
defines this Maxell both statistics, so it's the
grand canonical statistics for.
Classical systems with discrete quantize energy
levels and before going on into the second issue,
that distinguishes true quantum statistics from
this classical result. Was paused to make sure
that.
This. This derivation didn't.
Raising questions in your mind as we went through
his last few minutes.
I guess I've already. Give it away, the next step
in the presentation here, which is on the screen,
which is that. The argument about distinguishable
versus indistinguishable particles that I went
through, I tried to block out the sun and get the
screen a bit more visible is only correct. When?
Each of the particles in the system is in a
different energy level, so when we brought in this
factor of whatever and factorial that we said was
present to correct for overcounting of building
and particle partition function out of a product
of any single particle prediction functions. We
implicitly assume. That's. Each of the different
particles that we want to multiply together can be
labeled in a different way, which is only possible
when they are in a. Different energy level. In the
context of Section four point one, I think it was
this equation fifty one, we were assuming that
every particle in the ideal gas was considered at
that time had a distinct momentum. And we went
through this argument by looking at the different
ways those different Amanto could be labeled,
setting aside until now the question of what
happens when we would have identical particles
with identical momentum.
We set that aside in Unit four because we were
working in a regime, but we argue that the
energies were effectively dirty and continuous.
Thanks to that relation that we had close to being
much smaller than the combination of system
parameters governing the energies. And if we
imagine having a real value of energy energies
that there is a vanishing chance of picking to
real numbers completely at random and having them
exactly matched to infinitely many decimal places
and. This holds more generally if and only if
there are many more accessible energy levels, then
there are particles to occupy. And the regime
where the assumption of every particle in a
different energy level breaks down is precisely
the one we are now interested in. So let's.
Go through a much simpler illustration of exactly
how this can cause problems, I've told you that.
This is a problem of the overcounting factor,
depends on particles being in different energy
levels. Let's think about the simplest possible
system where this problem arises to see that it is
a problem and get an idea for what we can do about
it. So. We will consider a system with a fixed
number of particles and see your end equals two
particles, and we'll say it has five. Energy
levels, so. Calligraphic e Sub-Zero through a
script E for and just to make things as simple as
possible, you'll make all five of those energy
levels to generate and shift the energy so that
every one of these five energy levels as a
vanishing energy. For L from zero to four
inclusive, so the single particle. You know, equal
protection function.
Is simply counting. A factor of one with energy is
zero for every microstates. Independent of
whatever the temperature is, so long as that
temperature is finite and not zero, so that we
don't get into issues of dividing 050 no, take
that as given say that the opposition function. As
a consequence, must be a positive integer, it is
counting how many microstates there are in the
system. So the single single particle case, we
have five energy levels that that particle could
be in over those five energy levels gives us the
five microstates that we know we have.
And this actually turns out to be the same
calculation as a simple combinatorial problem by
counting the number of ways that. This certain
number of particles or bottles. So if we have any
close to particles, we want to place them in the
five different energy levels, we can represent
those energy levels as boxes that can hold these
bottles and represent all the possible microstates
just by drawing five boxes with a total of two
bottles distributed between them, either two
bottles in the same box or one bottle in each of
two different boxes. And hopefully I have
presented the setup clearly enough that you can
tell me the two particle partition function if the
balls are distinguishable in this case.
And so we want to compute the two party
coopetition function, assuming that the particles
are distinguishable when the two of them can
occupy any of five distinct energy levels.
Yes.
Which is in the case of plugging in L and twenty
five total number of microstates corresponding to
the five ways that the first ball can be placed in
any of the five energy levels for each of the five
ways that the second bullet can be placed in them.
So this is the usual relation that we had for
distinguishable particles. In the canonical
example, the end particle partition function is
the power of the single particle partition
function, and that same argument for
indistinguishable particles then corrects for the
overcounting of those two, those two particles. So
taking them from distinguishable to
indistinguishable. We bring in this factor of
whatever and Vectorial, which is one half, and we
find out that the two political parties can
function in this article. This is 12 and a half,
which supposedly is counting the number of
microstates in the system, which is nonsense
because there's no such thing as half a
microstates. So you've got bomb somewhere in this
process. And the reason we cut things down to such
a small example is to be able to look at things in
full detail and see exactly where it went wrong
and then what we can do about it. So. You've
already said that it is the overcounting
correction that goes wrong. And gives us this
nonsensical, not integer number of microstates.
And if we start off in the distinction of the case
that we considered first, we can do that by
supposing that one of these balls is red, that the
other is blue, we can label each micro state by a
five digit code summarizing how many particles in
the distinguishable case. We have to specify which
particular particle is in each of the five energy
levels. So if any of these energy levels has no
particles, we can label it with zero. If it has
the red particle in, it could be labeled with the
power. If it has the blue particle in taking label
with a B. and if those particles are in the
particular energy level, we can label that with a
two and this list here of five times five
different ways of. Putting these two balls in the
five boxes is that full set of twenty five
microstates. That we had the previous page, there
are 20 where the red and blue balls are in
different boxes and five in this last column where
both of them are in every single one of these
individuals.
So that. Is accounting for all twenty five
microstates. And we tried to get to the
microstates indistinguishable particles on the
previous page by. Dividing by two, claiming that
this accounted for the overcounting that we can
actually see in this list every. Microstates in
the first home. Is. Almost the same as every
microstates in the third column, if we just
interchange the blue ball, the red ball. So all 20
of those microstates in the case of
indistinguishably particles are indeed double
counted by exactly the factor of two and factorial
that we are used to. But that is not the case for
the final column where. The red, blue and gold are
both in the same energy level. Each of these micro
states is not being double counted, even when the
particles are distinguishable in the micro state
remains the same. And in particular, is not
corrected for double counting. When we go from the
about particles to the indistinguishable particles
of quantum mechanics, so rather than that total
twenty five divided by Victoria microstates, we
really end up with 15 because it was only the set
of microstates where the particles were a
different energy levels that were double counted
in the classical approach and had to have that
double counting correctly. And having gone through
the sort of exhaustive exercise of seeing what
goes wrong in the classical approach when it's
possible for multiple particles to be in the same
energy level we can. Appreciates the simple way to
fix this, which is instead of something over.
Single particles and then multiply all a single
particle partition functions together to get the
end particle partition function and correcting for
overcounting after the fact, we can turn the
approach on its head and represent the system in
terms of the occupation numbers for each energy
level. Occupation number is something that we saw
before when going through the replica trick to
define both economical and economical ensemble
with an ensemble, their large external reservoirs
here. This occupation number and SIBYLLE. Is
counting the number of particles in the
corresponding energy level labeled by that same
metal. And this gives us the definition of quantum
statistics where. The protection function that we
always start off with remains a symbol over all
the microstates, but we define those microstates.
By considering in turn each energy level and then
something over all of the possible occupation
numbers. That this energy level could have. So
this is.
There are two things to say about this. First of
all, it differs from the classical approach that
we've been doing up till now. But what we did for
Maxwell, both statistics with discrete energy
levels where we summed over all of the what we
consider and in turn, each particle.
And stumbled over the possible energies that it
could have. And in addition to. Giving us a just a
different way of organizing the calculation. It
turns out to be the better way of organizing the
calculation, we have to worry about multiple
occupancy of particular energy levels because.
In the quantum approach, if we take the tactic of
something over the energy levels, something over
the possible occupation, we can see it may be
worth going through that simple exercise in that
way. In doing so, I don't think we have time to do
that in the few minutes remaining today, but it
will indeed turn out that. There is no further
need to correct for any overcounting because we
organize things in terms first of energy levels
and then.
On the screen first in terms of energy levels and
then in terms of occupation numbers, all the
microstates are accounted for one by one with No.
Overcounting, now that we get from the classical
approach and then have to try to correct it, is
exactly that overcounting that becomes.
Problematic, or at least not trivial, whenever
there can be multiple articles in the same energy
level. Now. In principle, we could continue to.
Follow that classical approach and try to keep
track of. How many microstates have this issue of
multiple particles in the same energy level that
would have to be handled specially and not just
divided by one of reinfect real? Normalization
factor. In practice, that turns out to be
equivalent to the quantum approach of something
over energy levels and occupation numbers. So that
is. The.
The definition of quantum statistics and the way
that it varies from vasculitis effects in addition
to maintaining discrete energy levels. We also
have to keep track of the occupation numbers of
those energy levels and approach the population in
such a way that overcounting does not become an
issue even when there can be multiple particles in
the same energy level. And that is a good place to
stop for today. If there are immediate questions,
bring that up now. Otherwise, went back to my
office for office hours and we'll pick up tomorrow
morning by considering. The possible occupation
numbers, that's just part of the occupation
numbers that are possible for energy levels. Two
different cases, but it also sounds like you think
the types of particles that lead to two distinct
types of quantum systems. So that's a great
question. I will see you then tomorrow morning to
pick up with that.
So for.