All right, that's the recording started.  According
to my watch, those bells were ringing just a
little bit early. We might as well get going with
the six-digit number for today, which she is four zero zero zero one nine.
I'll keep that up there and see if there are any
questions about what we went through last week
with the introduction of ideal gases and their
application in thermodynamic cycles.
Today is the seventh
of March and it's feeling a bit more like spring. We'll see if it
sticks around.  Tlace where we are in
this module is today, we're going to wrap up our
discussion of thermodynamic cycles,
which
in turn is built on the behaviour of ideal gases in some
containers, which in turn is built on the
framework of the. Ensemble systems with fixed
temperature and fixed particle number, but
variable internal energy use zoom out.
Refocussed.
So.
Last week, we. Collected the four key equations
board for the Olympic cycles, and in part because
the projector is looking a bit uninspiring,
Brittanys equations down on the board for some
further reference to that solution between the
internal energy and temperature of the gases and
particles, whether the particles distinguishable
or not. We saw that in both cases of
distinguishable, indistinguishable particles, the
entropy is distinguishable part of the time.
Temperature of the three has power so that if that
product were constant, that guaranteed as an
entropy and isotropic or enigmatic process drive
the ideal gas law pressure times. The volume gets
to the number of particles and the temperature,
and finally generalize to the first of all of
thermodynamics to recognize two different ways
that the internal energy of our system can change,
both by exchanging heat with its entitlements or
through the process of work. The application of
force that changes the volume at the ideal gas
gases in this sheet is related to a change in the
entropy multiplied by the temperature. Work is
negative of the pressure changes due to the force
exerted on the system.
We also saw that these equations together allow
the full macroscopic or thermodynamics status of
the system to be specified by any two of these
qualities. So we focused on the pressure and
volume, introducing the so-called PV diagrams as
visual representations of the work scale from the
state of the systems under consideration. As well
as particular, the cycles which formed close loops
on these Peevey diagrams, cycling back, back
around to their starting point as a sequence of
processes are carried out and as an example.
The theme of the cycle we looked at. Cycle that is
called the current cycle. So. The key feature here
is that the thermodynamic system is allowed to
exchange energy with both a hot reservoir and in
the cold reservoir.
And the four is.
That build up this cycle.
Are two stages of isothermal expansion and
contraction, interspersed with two stages of
idiomatic expansion is the practice of drawing c.B
diagrams or DeCaro Cycles. You start from some
point, they do a slow isothermal extensions, which
will be what keeps the temperature constant by
proceeding slowly enough of all possible heat
exchange with the surroundings can occur, then do
a thermal expansion. Sorry about that, that
extension and try to see
exactly high temperature of the reservoir see down
here as the temperature of the Cold War
and then repeat the process with the slow pace of
thermal compression that somebody followed by the
final stage of a famous event of compression. Back
to the starting point. They do it quickly enough
that no heat at all can be exchanged. And the
interviews at either end of. The processes are the
same.
The final topic that we started on on Friday and
we'll wrap up today is looking at the efficiency
of a 30 day cycle. Which is defined as the amount
of work that the cycle can do on its surroundings,
getting useful,
useful work out of the flow of heat through the
cycle. And that has to be normalized by the total
amount of heat flowing into the cycle. And we saw
from the first law of thermodynamics. That while
the efficiency is. Strictly positive, it can be no
larger than one, which is. We can't be phrased. By
saying that the first law of thermodynamics
guarantees that. We can't win with any engine, we
can't get out more work than the amount of heat
that we have to pour into it in order to make it
work. And this is, to put it another way, why the
perpetual motion machines don't exist, theoretical
objects that can produce more work than compared
to the energy that is needed to operate and
operate. So getting back to the place in the notes
where we left off yesterday, we should keep this
on the screen and see if there are any follow up
questions about these topics that you caught up to
where we were.
This is connecting now to. The efficiency. Is
defined in terms of the output work done by the
system on its surroundings, minus the input work
done by the surroundings on the system.
Related to the heat flowing in and out of the
system by that first law enforcement, an annex
giving us the efficiency between zero and one that
we just reviewed. So picking up here, let's go
through the exercise of calculating the efficiency
for the current cycle and make sure all of these
concepts hang together in that calculation. So.
All we need to do is figure out how much work is
being done, both by the system on its surroundings
and by the surroundings of the system and how much
heat is flowing into and out of the system as it
goes around each of these four stages in its
degree, separate from those equations. So it
started off at point A, you want to figure out
what is. Going on in terms of heat and work with
the likes of thermal expansion from point A to
point B.
Now.
I guess through this calculation, you might call
back to some of the results we computed last week
in terms of the temperatures that we saw, was the
specific volume that the system has to deal in
order to close the cycle and get back around and
start reporting, as well as the volumes of the
pressure at each of these four points. And for the
work going back to the original definition that we
started off this year with, we have. But we're
given by the negative integral from point A to
point B of the pressure is a function of volume
that is coming exactly from the ideal gas law is
in times of temperature over Viðga to be that
temperature is fixed at T h
the high temperature of the reservoir. It's a
constant that can come out of. It's integral, and
then you're just left with D.V. divided by V, that
integral is known to its friends as the logarithm.
So.
Plugging in the units from going from point A to
point B, you pick up this ratio.
So there's volumes and these are two of the
qualities that we know we can't control as we sell
the car, so we have a choice of how much we are
expanding. So before taking in the fast economic
expansion from B to C, so the only thing we don't
really have control over in this expression is
that number of particles in. But we can do is use
the idea of gas again to replace that ency with
PVG for. Either A or B, I choose Point A.. That's
our starting point with the input that we had in
September on the. The collection of variables that
we are able to start off with under our control,
and I might as well also get rid of that negative
sign just by inverting the arguments of the
logarithm, looking at the ratio of Vuh over
Overbey, rather than able to figure. We can see
here that since VLA is smaller than ever before
and after this expansion, the argument of the log
is less than one block as a whole is then less
than zero point. The pressure always have to be
positive for. The physical systems of interest, so
what we find is a particular expression for the
work done going from point A to B, that is less
than zero. If we go back to our definitions of the
word means that the internal energy of the gas
provided to the system in the cycle is decreasing.
Energy has been removed from the system to perform
work on the surroundings of the system, turning
the gears, making the wheels go forward.
So in this first stage of expansion, we have work
being done by the system on its surroundings and.
Because it is isothermal also, he is being
exchanged to keep that temperature constant, we
can use the relation between energy and
temperature. To see that the change in the total
internal energy. Is just proportional to the
change in the temperature, which is zero because
the temperature is fixed. So this huge heat plus
the work of the stage has to add up to zero. So
the amount of heat. Flowing into the system. Is
equal to the amount of work being done by the
system, so energy is leaving the system in the
form of work, coming in the form of heat, and
everything is balancing out as we would expect. So
was that first stage of this calculation clear?
I see nods, we can go a bit more quickly through
the remaining three stages, the second stages of
adding expansion rather than isothermal expansion.
So the building is still increasing, but it's
doing so much more quickly so that no heat is
exchanged. So we already have. The result of the
heat flow. The second stage, four feet above sea,
vanishes, and that allows us to. Figure out the
work without going through the formal integration
over the change, the volume of the pressure on the
volume so we can just keep equal to zero. The work
is the total change in energy at Washington.
Energy is 3000 times the total change in
temperature.
So. Catch up with what I was saying that.
We're done in the second stage is three 1/2 times
the final temperature. To lower the temperature,
higher the horrors of war. And if I pull out
overall factor of that. High-temperature.
From the criticism. You can recognize that in
times jihad is the same quality we replace with
times with the ideal gas law. Earlier on this page
and we. Deputed last time around that. This ratio
of the low to high temperatures is related to the
ratios of the bones, VBAC specifically to low
poverty, high is.
Smaller volume to be avoided when you see to be
two thirds power, and that suffices to put
everything in terms of the quantities we can
control. You end up with three haves. Pressure
eight times volume at a times that ratio. The
volume is two thirds minus one, and since this
ratio is less than one versus the smaller volume
compared to BC after the expansion, once we
subtract one. You can get a negative number. So in
this expansion stage as well, the system continues
doing work on its surroundings. So work is being
done by the systems to do useful work. Have a
useful effect on the. The surroundings, the rest
of the universe.
Several. The cycle is mostly symmetric, and after
these processes of isothermal expansion and
antibiotic expansion, we put them in reverse at
that lower, mature acetyl depression at the low
temperatures here, followed by adiabatic
compression. So we can go through the same
calculation just with. The girls and territory
from boy be sexy to the city and the of thermal
compression station.
More.
The ideal gas law relates that pressure now to the
low temperature to times and the same antigrowth
over Dve Overbey. So that is the. To go the
integration of TV over because the water isn't in
Florida. Go ahead and absorb that negative sign by.
Inverting the ratio of volumes that appear in the
logarithm.
And.
There are. Two things we can do here. One has to
again.
Pullout, a factor of the height of the surplus,
multiplying and dividing by the high temperature
to put us back to the intensity and is equal to
the year, then we want to.
The place this dependence on the boy involved with
the input parameters that we work with, I found an
expression for this final volume in terms of the
other three volumes of the system. There was this
one particular value that it had to take in order
for the cycle to close and get back to the
starting point. Michael Origin here.
The ratios of boys, you see over 18 had to be
equal to that ratio of Vuh over BP, so no amount
of compression or temperature has to match up to
the relative amount of expansion at the high
temperature. So putting all that together.
With, again, any relation between your
temperatures and
seem to the two thirds of our times that log of
Vehbi.
At this time now the argument on the border is
greater than one plan because much of the volume
of water within itself is positive. And instead of
having the system do work on its surroundings, we
find that in order to carry out this compression,
the surroundings have to be doing good on the
system.
Increasing the internal energy and essentially
adding to the cost of running the cycle, so we're
no longer getting used to walk out of it. We have
to put more energy into the system. As with the
other isothermal process, the heat and the work
have to balance out. In order to keep the
temperature hostage, you do not consider as well
so that as we could have seen from inspection and
thinking about the physical picture of the cycle,
he has been slow.
Out of the system, into the core reservoir, in
order to keep the temperature constant as the work
is done to compress it. And then finally from.
Last stage about depression from 20 back to the
starting point. We can. Repeat essentially this.
Second calculation of the enigmatic expansion with
the only difference is that the change in
temperature is now T minus T, that is there's an
overall negative sign and we have, again, positive
work being done. Equal and opposite to the work
that the system did in its adiabatic expansion
zone, and yes, of course, because this depression
is adiabatic from due to a. There is no heat
exchanged, as always, for any the process, so that
is sort of eight pieces of information that we
need to compute the the efficiency, heat and
workflow at each of the four stages of this cycle.
So if we collect these results, we identify the
two stages where work was done by the system on
its surroundings. Well, maybe you find this. When
set out to be the positive, absolute magnitude of
the work that the system puts out into the
university to do useful things like training
wheels. This is the negative of the.
Two pieces of work that we completed in the first
two stages, finding them to be less than zero. So
this negative signs are. Accounting for.
The definition of work in terms of changing volume
and keeping the current amount of output work the
absolute magnitude. Similarly, the work is. The
work done to compress the system with the positive
sign, again, keeping this quality positive and we
found the relation for the last stage that the.
Work done for you. That impression was the
negative of the work done for emetic expansion.
And in terms of the heat flow to the cycles have
no heat flows by, you'll be able probably to see
and then needed a. And we saw that he only flows
into the system during the reception to be it was
out of the system during the isothermal oppression
from supervision. That means that since you're
interested only in the keep flowing in to the
system, we only have one piece of data to worry
about. Keep flowing in during the isothermal
expansion from A to B.. So now we can put all of
this together in our definition for the efficiency
of the networks to the put out by the system on
the rest of the universe. So negative the word
from A B minus the four on the stage B, C, and
then subtracting the work that has to be put into
the system by its surroundings in order for this
cycle to operate. So subtracting off B, C, C, D at
NBC, which cancels out the. Initial stage from the.
Similar to the work done by two independent
processes are canceling out and the inflow of heat
is just this negative of the work done by the
system on surroundings during slow expansion,
cancelling that out, we just find that the ratio
is. One plus, the efficiency is much less this
ratio of the work done
in the with depression from CTD divided by the
work done by the isothermal expansion from to.
And what is more, if we actually. Go back up here
and look at these values for that work done in the
the stage. It's this complicated expression. How
does the boy ratio's times that log over the.
Dorothy.
The expansion phase, the rehab that we want to
divide that by has that same factor. It has to log
with the opposite ratio, the smaller going into
the numerator, the larger point that the
denominator. So in this ratio, you pick up a
negative sign from flipping the arguments to the
law. And all that is left is then that ratio. The
third is on the screen.
That ratio of and factors which entered being
related to the ratio of the temperatures, so
plugging in the expressions reputedly find the
efficiency for the heart of cycle of one minus
that ratio of the low temperature to the high
temperature.
And just to check that this result we found
actually makes sense. We have by definition of the
cold reservoir, but the temperature is smaller and
the high temperature of the reservoir, which means
that this ratio is always going to be less than
one in the efficiency, is always going to be
greater than zero. We do indeed have an engine as
required. And you can also see that.
In the limit, where the temperatures of the two
reservoirs approach each other and this ratio of
temperatures goes to one, the efficiency itself
collapses C0, which makes intuitive sense. There's
essentially no flow of heat from the hot reservoir
to the core reservoir through the system. So
there's no work that can be done in the absence of
that heat flow. And even just a visual inspection,
this TV diagram, when we had if we had the high
low temperatures approaching each other, we saw
when we first introduced ISO therms that we would
cross the same isothermal with the same
temperature. The cycle would collapse to that
single process, just going back and forth along
the same isothermal, bringing in. The same amount
of heat from one reservoir was expelled to the
other reservoir and during the same amount of work
that has to be done on it to get back to the
starting point, nothing that can be used to
accomplish anything outside of the system.
So the efficiency vanishes in that limited.
Whereas in the opposite limits.
If the. Called Reservoir and picked up the
temperature much lower than the reservoir, and
this review itself approached zero. Then the
efficiency would approach its theoretical maximum
set by the first port of thermodynamics
approaching 100 percent efficiency.
Either going to one as that ratio of low
temperature, the high temperature goes to zero and
this is. Is generic result that heat engines like
the cardio cycle are more efficient as the.
Difference between the temperatures of their hot
and cold reservoir increases, it is also generic
that as the hot and cold temperatures approach
each other, there is no heating fuel and no work
that can be done as a consequence. What is
noteworthy about the Kano's cycle that we have
considered here? What is the reason we consider
this rather than some of the other cycles that
might be worth talking about in the tutorial, is
that this expression, the widest temperature ratio
that appears in this equation, 66, is actually the
maximum efficiency at any cycle that can possibly
have due to the second law of thermodynamics. So
we already put up or down with the efficiency from
the first law of the conservation of energy. If we
think about the second law.
That tells us that the. Then amount of energy in
the universe about the system and its surroundings
has to be not decreasing as these processes are
carried out and the system goes around its cycle.
So if we go back to our starting point today, that
relation between the nets, heat flow and the work
done coming from the first half of the team, we
can rewrite the numerator of the efficiency in
terms of the difference between the incoming and
outgoing heat. And this very quickly simplifies to
one minus the ratio of the wastage that is
expelled. The call reservoir compared to the.
Energy that is brought in the form of bottles of
water and from the definition of heat, as
temperature times change in entropy, we can relate
both of these factors in the ratio to the
corresponding temperature. Multiplied by the
change in entropy, going along the isothermal
process where this heat is being exchanged. So the
fact that those processes are isothermal is very
useful because of the temperature is a constant.
He flows out during the Depression concededly, the
system is fixed, the low temperature record
reservoir, and it flows in from the isotope
expansion from A to B.. The temperature is fixed
at the edge of the reservoir. And.
Once we have gone halfway around the cycle. The
system has returned to its original makeover
status. The amount of entropy in the system is the
same at the end as it was at the beginning. And
the only thing that can possibly be changed is
that the amount of entropy in the surroundings
might have might be different now that the system
has gone around the cycle. So as heat comes in to
the system in its expansion, that brings more
entropy from the reservoir into the system and
that entropy that has to flow out of the system
into the cold reservoir as he goes out. So in the
end, the amount of heat that is left of these
reservoirs is a decrease by that Delta s coming in
from the people coming into the expansion, which
must be smaller than the increase produced by
expelling waste heat to the whole reservoir. So.
Maybe just to connect with the balance, the
efficiency, we said earlier from the first law we
saw that this efficiency of ADA equals more, that
equality occurred only is on the screen. Equality
in this inequality occurs only when you have to
waste being expelled by the system. Varnishes
Second law says that the amount of waste can never
vanish because if it did that, entropy would be
vanishing as well in violation of of the Second
World. So plugging in this inequality that the
amount of entropy flowing out of the system has to
be greater than the total amount. The universe is
not decreasing.
They use this ratio is greater than or equal to
one, because we are subtracting the ratio, it
turns into a less than or equal sign in the
overall efficiency of any engine we could possibly
construct. Consistent with the second X is less
than or equal to this one minus the ratio of the
low temperature to the high temperature, and that
is independent of any engineering tricks we could
hope to play. That is a fundamental constraint
from the second law of thermodynamics and also
happens to be this equation. Sixty six that we
computed for the current cycle. So the participant
realizes the maximum possible efficiency that. If
that they possibly can.
During the final stages of the cycles of. So I
will wrap up by mentioning the possibility that we
could well take this kind of cycle and put it in
reverse, so instead of expanding the system at the
height of the horrors of war, that could be
absolutely sure that the contraction show that
create on chalkboards particularly visible. But
this is very simple exercise converts all these
Theros extension at the low temperature, the
causes of war to form a cycle that goes around the
same for processes in the opposite direction. So
what this is doing now, instead of having a net
amount of work being done by the system on its
surroundings, thanks to the flow of heat from the
hot reservoir to the cold reservoir, we've
reversed the science in all of our calculations on
the previous page. So what we're doing is moving
work. From the cold reservoir to the heat is
coming in from the cold reservoir. And are doing
work to bring in that heat and expel the heat out
the hot reservoir
at the price of having to do work on the system
rather than having the system do work for us. So
what's going on is that this process of removing
heat from a cold reservoir is ensuring that the
temperature of that cold reservoir remains low and
in fact, even lower. What this is doing is setting
up a refrigerator where the cold reservoir is
where we would keep our lunch. And we do work to
keep the temperature that cold reservoir cold by
shifting heat from us and expelling it into. The
reservoir formed by the external environment. So
that gives us a refrigerator rather than an engine,
instead of taking advantage of heat, so to do work,
we do work on the system in order to create a flow
of heat and the analog of the efficiency. Or a
refrigerator is known as the coefficient of
performance and is defined in the same spirit as
the efficiency of what we care about is the amount
of heat that we are able to remove from the cold
reservoir. And the price for that heat is the
amount of work that has to be done on the system.
And as before taking it out, the balance of the
efficiency from the Second World through Anex
began. The place this difference in work with the
difference in heat and simplifies to find a
professional performance is one over the ratio of
the heat out of the system into the hot reservoir
divided by the heat flowing into the system from
the core reservoir minus one. And when we replace
that. With the inefficient inequality we derived
about. We actually find so we have the opposite
connection between the inflow and outflow of gates
and the hot or cold reservoirs. So this ratio.
Rather than being the ratio of the low temperature
to the high temperature for a refrigerator is the
ratio, the high temperature, low temperature and
the simplified gives a performance related to the
low temperature that we want to achieve, divided
by the difference between those two temperatures.
So this unlikely efficiency can be greater than
one, in fact, and that limit where the two
reservoirs have the same temperature. We see that
a divergence which makes sense if the. The looks
have returned the body, but we want to refrigerate
is already as cold as the high temperatures and
the rest of its surroundings, then there's no work
that has to be done in order to keep that low
temperature level.
And I will say that we're practical refrigerators
you might have in the kitchen, the typical value
of this coefficient of performance is around five
to six. So clearly greater than one and. The final
remark for this year, the ultimate inevitable
cycles, is. I related to the efficiency and
cooperation of performance of real devices.
What we might talk about the tutorial on Friday is
that real devices are. Not the kind of a cycle, so
even though the cycle realizes the maximum
possible efficiency for you from the tank engine,
it is not a practical way to use heat to do work.
And that is because it is too slow, especially
because it has to have those two isothermal
stations for expansion and contraction, isothermal
means that process is slow enough for all possible
heat exchange occurs.
And if we want an actual engine like an internal
combustion engine. Were these sort of engines that
we have powered refrigerators, they have to
sacrifice the theoretical efficiency of the cargo
cycle for the practicalities of operating on
timescales of. Seconds or less rather than hours
or days, so. I pushed through it to complete this
before, but we have had today let's pause now to
see if there are any questions about the
efficiency of the kind of cycle. Or refrigerators.
Not hearing any just. You've won last. Saying
about the efficiency of Olympic cycles, I
mentioned at the start that the first off to the
next ensures that we can't win within the next
cycle. We can't make a actual motion machine that
puts out more work than it takes in the four feet.
Second level increase in energy is telling us that
not only can we not win. It's also possible to
break even the work that we get out of the engine
always has to be less than the amount of energy
flowing through it. And fortunately for the. So
just a few minutes left today, not hearing any
questions about whether they had a fight with law
at least motivates the next topic in the module.
Which is getting back to the more formal
developments of statistical ensembles. In
particular, developing the grand, fanatical
ensemble, so since there are just a few minutes
remaining, I'll speak loosely, qualitatively for
the time being. We're thinking back to what we've
done so far before, digging into some details of
the gases and their use in thermodynamic cycles.
We started off with the first statistical example
we considered was the microeconomic ensemble,
which directly connected to the conservation of
energy. The first law from the banks by requiring
that the energy of any system described when it
has to be fixed as that system evolves, a time
adopting its various microstates that turned out
to be impractical for.
Use it for use in interesting situations like the
Matrix cycles, so we quickly replaced it with the
canonical ensemble where instead of keeping the
internal energy of the system fixed, we allowed
the energy to fluctuate by exchanging energy
through verbal contact with a large external
thermal reservoir that in turn fixed the
temperature of. While still keeping that political
no fixed and the economic ensemble essentially
fills in the other piece of that development. So
we now allow the. Article number, as well as the
energy to fluctuate. By being exchanged with a
large external reservoir of a different sort. This
is the this will be one of the developments,
formerly a particle reservoir. With which the
system of interest can exchange both energy as
well as its particles to the number of particles
in the system will no longer be fixed. In the same
way that the system's energy will no longer be
fixed. But there will be two other qualities that
are fixed through this contact with the particle
of one of those is the temperature, as we saw, for
the canonical ensemble. The other one will be a
quantity known as the chemical potential, which is
a little certainly much less familiar than the
temperature. So we'll get into that tomorrow
morning. I guess the.
The details of what exactly is fixed by allowing
particles to be exchanged between the system and
its surroundings is.
A bit more of a calculation than. We have time to
go into right now. We'll pick it up tomorrow
morning and.
You flesh out this basic idea of having started
with fixed energy and particle, no, not without
both of those two very fixed to other quantities
instead through contact with the large external
reservoir. I'll wrap it up there and invite any
more questions. I'll be setting up the office
hours and. Ten minutes or so and. If there are. No
further questions. See you all again. Tomorrow,
we're in the other room.
Well.
Once again, the.