All right, despite the small crowd, I'll start
getting things underway.
It's a more pleasant day outside than the last few
and at least some folks were up late last night
getting that homework assignment in on time. So you
feel relieved about being halfway through all the
homeworks with this module already.
And the usual starting businesses is the six-digit number
for the attendance monitoring system this morning, which is nine three two nine
seven seven.
And I'll put a bit more on the board under it as we
recap where we have been this past week or
the past few weeks.  Are there any questions to
bring up before I dive in?
Actually, I can mention that an interesting
question came in asynchronously over this past
week, which I will try to write up a bit about on
the Canvas discussion board over the weekend that
maybe once I catch up with all the debarking is
now a bit late on my part. This question was, how
do we actually tell if the system is in
equilibrium? Some of you have been assuming it is
in the canonical ensemble that all of our systems
are in equilibrium. All of the microsleep
probabilities are equal and there are, I guess,
both theoretical and practical answers to how we
can verify that this is actually the case in
theory, if we. Imagine we can measure what
microstates system is in, we just have to repeat
all of those measurements a sufficient number of
times to see that these microstates are popping up
with equal probability that results from similar
equilibrium in the case of the micro ensemble. But
in practice, there are a couple of obvious
problems with that pozole, one being that
determining the micro state requires mapping out
the behavior of all of the microscopic degrees of
freedom in that state, usually not something we
can do in practice. Imagine figuring out the
locations are meant to have all the air molecules
in this room. And in the micro canonical case
specifically, there's the requirement that energy
be conserved in that system. And if we were to
dive in and try to measure all of its degrees of
freedom, we wouldn't necessarily be interacting
with it, exchanging energy with violating that
assumption for the microeconomic example. So the
practical answer is that's not something you
really do with the micro canonical ensemble. You
want to look at the large scale macroscopic
thermodynamic properties of the system, which is
why we have turned to the canonical ensemble and
actually gives me a. Segway into the recap of what
we've been doing over the past few weeks, that is
on the screen for the morning at.
Before the march.
So today, we are still in the process of bringing
everything together from the past few weeks,
starting with the canonical ensemble where our
system is in full contact with some large external
reservoir that fixes its temperature and allows it
to issue energy. And in the ensemble, we've looked
at specific systems of Baddiel gases
that are placed into some container of a volume
beam. And we have. This week, they're considering
ways that we can manipulate the systems of ideal
gases in their container to.
Have them do stuff for us.
And in particular.
Designing a sequence of changes to these systems
that can be brought together into a closed cycle
that we will repeat and that's what we will
continue with today, possibly wrap up, maybe not
finish. It's on Monday, but the.
We have seen that two generic ways of manipulating
these ideal systems to change their energy, so.
Using our control.
Over the control parameters, the temperature of
volubly systems, and remembering that when we are
changing the energy of the system, you're really
exchanging that energy with its surroundings, fix
its temperature. And those two ways are.
Quantities we we've defined as heat and work where
work. Results from some change. The volume. Due to
the application of Air Force. The connection to
the classical mechanics concept of working for
some physicians, that work is infinitesimally the
negative of PDV energy increases when the going
gets smaller, depressed, which we can integrate to.
It's not if it doesn't work in the heat. Have
connected to changes in the entropy.
She is the temperature times that does change in
entropy. And then.
Putting together lots of these changes, we have to
really make cycles that we can analyze with the
four equations that have been set aside about this
board for reference. The first thing, the internal
energy for the House and the of the past, it's
been indistinguishable from the connection between
the temperature and total energy of an ideal. Gas
is a fixed number of particles of economical
ensemble. We then have the condition of constant
entropy at the volume of the gas times, the three
power.
Constance.
To
adiabatic cycles, so much better processes in
which he does not exchange dive into that after
this recounts that have the equation of state the
of small.
What? Well, you
said the number of steps, the temperature and then
the generalized, first of all, from dynamics,
which is broke down there, the change in the
internal energy of the system. He calls were.
Smiles
and.
That's the easy way to keep track of these
processes. We have introduced pressure building
diagrams where the macro state of the system is
specified entirely by the pressure and the volume
that determines the temperature through the
internal energy.
And two particular processes.
That we have.
Looked at all these preferably diagrams
rewriting prison walls or isothermal processes
that are slow enough that all possible heat
exchanges completed and the temperature remains
constant as the pressure and volume are changed.
So every point on this line is this is a different
canonical ensemble. The big difference volume for
the ideal gas and correspondingly different
pressure subject to the condition of a fixed
temperature. And where we wrapped up on Tuesday
was a similar consideration of. Maybe that's the
line on the PV diagram for processes that are fast
enough that no heat is exchanged and therefore no
energy tubes is the heat, the entropy is not
changing on the so-called eightieths that connect
to different levels that are parallel curves on
these pressure volume diagrams with two different
temperatures. And that's where we have left off
with this idea that was figuring out the change of
the temperature as we compress the volume from
something.
See, what I can get down here is we compress the
volume from some larger going to a smaller final
volume we can see. If we believe what we doing
here, that the pressure is going up and the
temperature then is also going up. Which we can
tell from the audio, that's all the product of the
time to be is proportional to the temperature. And
if we go straight up increasing the pressure to
fix volume, we see that we the final temperatures
to be larger, the initial temperature. We verify
that last time since this initial volume over the
final volume will be raised, about two thirds is
greater than what the change in temperature is to
zero. And now we want to figure out the.
Change in the pressure that is coming from this
idiomatic expression, decreasing the volume. Of
our system, and
we have all the ingredients from what we've
already done and been talking equations up here,
and I'm actually going to. Do is rewrite our
starting point, the condition of constant entropy
that defines the Aliabadi process of no heat
exchange. And if I take. That expressions of the
condition of constant entropy from the start of
the process to the end, if I hit, that would be
ideal gas law, right? I guess I should say, I
think the two thirds power of all of the.
Quantities in this expression that the ideal gas
law is relating to the initial temperature to
pressure times volume. Over the number of
particles at that initial stage. And this is
similarly equal to the two thirds hour of the
final volume times the final. Pressure, volume,
and will the ends cancel and just rearrange this?
We get the final pressure in terms of the initial
pressure. That is.
And say zero factor up front and then two thirds
times another three thirds power of the initial
volume is the initial volume, five thirds power at
a similar volume to the firefighters factor and
states that we divide out.
On both sides and. You can then. Write down
similar looking change in the pressure just in
terms of the initial pressure and this compression
factor, the ratio of initial and final volumes. So
it looks a lot like the change in temperature. The
difference is we have pressures rather than
temperatures over again. And the. Howard, that
this. Boy ratio is raised to is up to five thirds
rather than two thirds, as well as fraction of
what it is, it is still positive, as we drew in
the initial diagram. So that diagram, at least, is
taking together. That's an accurate description of
what is going on. So. That gets us through the
section we're working on to back up to where we
left off on Tuesday, the final section in this
unit and in our main application. Of the canonical
ensemble, 28 Gas's. I'm guessing hard questions
about all that, regardless of which you've seen
before, but this is an opportunity to shut one out
before we move on to an actual bona fide for the
next Michael. As advertised, a connection or a
collection of processes that. Form a closed loop,
circling back around to your starting point, and
it may well be. Worthwhile for you to try to draw
this particular cycle on the border. So you have a
sense that there's two weeks
later ages and and and diagram the starting is
that we have a expansion. And in the pressure from
some initial point to some B and then a different
type of expansion details into off to see you
compress the system. So D then the final.
Progression to get back to that starting point
and before diving into the details of each of
those processes, let's see. Let's. It was sort of
the key idea that was introduced by the fellow,
the cycle is named after her go back in the 18, 20
years before the laws of thermodynamics, before
you came up with the idea of having our ideal gas
system, the working substance of this process. In
a container that can exchange energy. With not one
external thermal reservoir to fix its temperature,
but rather with two reservoirs, one of which is
hotter than the other. So we have a hot reservoir
with a high temperature and a cool reservoir with
a low temperature tell. The idea is that by.
Allowing the system to exchange heat with both of
these hot and cold reservoirs, that is a practical
way to realize this thermodynamic cycle and as we
will see, you use it to do useful work on its
surroundings. So.
We produced the highlights that the high low
temperatures are going to be identified with the.
State of the system with microstates at these.
A man to see in this pressure building a diagram
of the size that we have just above the high
temperature,
the low temperature and our main control parameter
is going to be the whole system. We can expand
from point A to point B, C, then compress boys and
back up to volume A. We imagine that we to survive
the initial pressure that comes along that from
the ideal gas law from going forward and the
temperature. And that's the important thing to get
a.
Physical idea of what's going on in this process
that can be represented more abstractly and that
diagram. This is a good illustration from a
Schroder's textbook introduction of thermal
physics showing these four stages of the current
cycle and the specified two for one more piece of
important data that each of those, which is what
exactly is. Happening and what is kept fixed in
each of those cycles, so starting from that
smallest volume A, we expand the volume to be. We
have our usual picture here of some ideal gas in a
container with a movable piston that here we are
pulling up to increase the volume. Of the of the
gas, and we imagine that we do so. Isothermal is
the slow expansion that allows heat to flow in
from that hot reservoir that here is big picture.
On the right hand side of the system, so this is a
slow expansion from point A to B. Whether that kid
is allowed to flow into the system to keep the
temperature fixed at his age and then going from
point B to C will speed up the expansion so it
becomes much more rapid. And in particular, is
that enough to be idiomatic and see how much of
this page I can fit on the screen or keeping it
legible and InFocus? That should suffice. So in
this stage. We have a fascinating expansion with
the more heat flow that takes the system to that
lower temperature to isoforms, that drew more in
the initial water at an 80 event in a pressure
building diagram. So temperature
in that initial stage I that expansion, trying to
draw things here to make it seem reasonable that
the next stage of. Compression going from sea to
team is also isothermal, so we reverse the
direction that this piston is moving, we start
decreasing the volume and we do so slowly enough
that heat has a chance to slow out now into that
separates that different core reservoir with a
lower temperature, keeping the volume of the gas,
keeping the temperature of the gas fixed at the
low temperature of that cold reservoir, even as
its volume decreases in this compression. That
also is this slow process, expelling kids to that
reservoir into the final process is.
Just analogous to what we were doing before we
speed up the changeability, you still keeping in a
depression, ideally to get back to that point A
and now making it fast enough. And it is idiomatic
and no further heat is exchanged. And the.
Question to address
what conditions have to be set aside in order to
make this cycle a natural cycle that does
successfully get back to its starting point, is a
after going through these four processes
isothermal expansion, adiabatic expansion,
acceptable compression, elevated compression. And
I said on this drawing this diagram, we have
control over this quarter. The volume you can
choose. How much we expanded the system?
Slow and isothermal eighty four point eight will
be how much we expanded quickly to see and then
how much we. Depressives both slowly and quickly
to get back to the starting point so we can freely
choose the three volumes Einsteinian. Subject to
the constraint that we get from the high
temperature of the horrors of war, what is your
Congress at this point? It has to be chosen
precisely so that these two processes of
depression lie not in exactly the right way to get
us back to our starting point. So if this diagram
if we take these three volumes, that initial
pressure. We're only at the initial temperature as
given, we should be able to use our four equations
for thermodynamic cycles and the condition that
the cycle closes to predict all of the other
aspects of the system as it traverses this time of
the cycle. So those are the four variables I was
describing that we have control over and zoom back
in. Now, that's not trying to keep the
illustration of the page.
It is, as we've seen, these points of the diagram
are specifying the temperatures have a free choice
of these three buildings at the initial pressure.
And you want to figure out.
The.
Single correct value of the fourth volume at that
point. Video that has to be. Chosen precisely in
order for the cycle to actually be a cycle and
return to its starting point as we go around it
and. No apriori, there was no guarantee that this
question could even have a solution for the
current cycle and expect from inspection from the
drawing board and that this will indeed be
possible. For other more complicated systems,
there's not necessarily a guarantee that a
collection of thermodynamic processes will be able
to form a closed loop in this sort of way. So that
leaves us these. Five unknown quantities that need
to be predicted in terms of the four given
quantities as well as the fixed particle number,
so in. And we can do this in a systematic way,
just like around the three point thirty three.
Additional points in the cycle, apart from the
starting point that is completely specified and
making sure that. All of these pressures,
temperatures in that final volume are expressible
in terms of the parameters that we have control
over. So are there any questions about the overall
set up before we dive into checking that that
computation?
New questions. Locally, only locally and. And the
starting point then that is actually given here in
the text as it heads in the first stage from HIV,
we know that the temperature remains the same.
This is a thermal expansion. So we find that
pressure PCB we just need to set. Or require that
the. Expression for the temperature from the ideal
gas law remains the same at point B as it was.
That's why have been cancel out having and fix
economic ensembles. This is the ideal gas law
giving us this equation for the fixed temperature
related.
The pressure at point B is this. Yes, it is. Sorry
about that.
Hopefully that is fixed that much of a waste of
time, space at points A, B, so the pressure at
points B is proportional to the pressure point
with this factor of personality being the ratios
of the civilians died down correctly this time.
And the so I don't see we have. If similar
computations to do for the pressure, but we also
have to.
Figure out of the self-consistent, the way that
the low temperature of the cold reservoir that
would be consistent with the volume C and the
pressure P, C that we've come up with. And at this
point, I will. Advertise that the spirit of the
competition is similar to the isothermal stage
from the beat, but going from B to C. We have an
automatic process that fixes the entropy. So
instead of using the equal temperatures to derive
our relation between these two points, we can
apply our condition of constant entropy at the
Times T to the three power. Is fixed and that.
Points be that.
Expression is the volume of the times, the hot
temperature, the high temperature, the hot
reservoir, and that has to be equal to boiling
point sea times, the three horsepower of the low
temperature of the cold reservoir. Now, this
immediately gives us that temperature tell in
terms of the parameters we have under our control.
This is, again, proportional to the high
temperature, taking the two thirds of power of
both sides of this equation. We now have the
personality factor being. This ratio be over VSC
to the two thirds power. And using the ideal gas
law. You can bring in this same expression for
that High-temperature, we get things in terms of
the set of variables that we. Said the quantities
we started off with. And high temperatures today
over N. What times this two thirds power of the
ratio of the two volumes that we can control?
Is there any nomination for. How to go after the
pressure points from. What we have in the spirit
of what's been done so far.
I think in the interest of getting through the
cycle of charging ahead in. I'll tell you one way
to do this, as usual, there are many ways to solve
these equations for these unknowns, but one useful
trick for all of you, so that excitement is going
to be that the number of particles is fixed and
the ideal gas law relates to that number of
particles to be. Three variables that we. And
available to us. The pressure, volume and the
temperature at that hole, four points in this
cycle. So we were interested in the pressure and
volume and see now when the temperature is to low.
This is the same number of particles as the system
we saw off with with this full control times over
that high temperature.
Which then gives us an expression for the pressure
point, see as to ratio's. The ratio of the volume
here with respect to the A rather than. B b that
we have the temperature in terms of, but we also
have been rated above the low and high
temperatures multiplying on both sides of this
equation by travel and.
The pressure had the starting point A comes along
for the ride in that reorganisations. And we can
then. Plug in this ratio to low or pretty high, is
this ratio of volume speedy over v.c to the two
thirds power?
Give me everything in terms of the quantities that
we have control over, just the two factors of the
sea separate their. So, again, a pressure
proportional to the pressure of the system now
with two factors of the small hole in the V.P. and
intermediate volume started like this, you see in
the intermediate players B over v.C. So these two
factors are both less than one. We can check that
the pressure has decreased as we've gone halfway
around the cycle consistent with what was shown in
that TV diagram. And similarly.
This ratio here is also less than one confirming
that the low temperature is less than the high
temperature, which is always.
Pleasant to to confirm.
OK, so getting back to point B from Point City, we
are now reversing the process of change in volume
that allows all possible transfer to proceed. So
not too surprisingly, we can. On.
Use that.
Well. There are many ways to do this and maybe the
more interesting way to. To ensure that the system
can get back to our target, the starting point of
A is to begin with the same. Condition of constant
entropy now connecting those two points deep in a.
To that final debate stage, so we can approach be
from both sides, but thinking about the constant
low temperature that we have from the oppression
as well as the constant entropy that we have to
demand in order to get back to the day after the
final stage of adiabatic expansion. So starting
with that condition, of course, naturally
connecting the volume with the high temperature.
Then we have there to the unknown volume and
indeed and the low temperature that it has after
it's isothermal compression.
You find.
The expression for that unknown voting
proportional to the starting point would be a.
With this ratio of high poverty low. To the three
house power. And.
Up as we went to see. Not too much on the screen,
we found this ratio of T high in T low, that's the
ratio of the volume is TVB over vasi to the two
thirds power. If we take a two thirds power to the
three has already get the ratio back to power one.
And we see that rather than lower high with T
higher, pretty low, we just end up with this V a
times the inverse of this ratio we see over VEB.
Which we can then again check it is larger than
the VA as drawing a diagram and we can extract
from this a simple relation between all four of
these volumes that specifies uniquely the single
special boiardi that you have to choose in order
to obtain a. Well, define some of the next cycle,
two products of the volume, eight times I can see
at the top left and right corners of that diagram
need to be equal. To the product. Of Beeby and
Viji at the top left and bottom right corner of
the diagram.
And then wrapping things up by the last unknown
quantity. Pressure would be. And again, news. The.
The number of particles in this canonical ideal
gas.
To get that pressure in terms of quantities, we
have already computed some proportional to, I
guess, computed or taken as inputs and then to
ratios coming in the ratio of the volumes and the
ratio of the temperatures now to low divided by T
rather than T high divided by T lowest of. Which
if we. But in some of the manipulations down here
from this relation between the four volumes, we
know that the ratio of volumes to here is the same
as the ratio of VEB. Over ABC. And some believe
from it's just the top of the screen now, the
ratio of low to high temperatures is that same BB
able would be seen to be two thirds power. Which
altogether is the initial pressure times the.
Volume ratio from the antibiotic expansion phase
be over the U.S. to the five thirds power. Which.
And as expected, is less than the external
pressures of the final stage of the impression
that you have to start. So these results are
useful not only to confirm that the cycle is valid.
We expect more from our ability to draw the line
again, but it is also a starting point to. See
what's in practice we can do with this kind of
cycle. In terms of how much work, if any, it can
do on its surroundings compared to the amount of
work that has to be done by the surrounding system
and the amount of heat that has to be transferred
between the two. Different thermal reservoirs that
the system is in contact with that onto the screen
here. So
it's been a bit slower than I anticipated. What?
Finish answering this question today about the.
Amount of work done by the cycle to be the people
can certainly do the set up of the calculation on
Monday and then move on to the next topic, leaving
the ensemble behind. And going on to the grand
canonical example as a forecast or preparation. We
can say that this question of how much work the
thermodynamic cycle can do on its surroundings
compared to the amount of heat that it needs to
run is.
Defined by this concept, known as the efficiency.
Of the third cycle, what specifically if we want
our cycle to be an engine that does work by
bringing in heat so the efficiency of an engine of
this sort is just the ratio of those to quantity,
as we were talking about the network that it can
do. So the difference between the work it does on
its surroundings. With the work that has to be
done on it, subtract it off, divide it by the
amount of heat, and it has to bring in from its
surroundings and operate in the second equation
here. I have defined a few.
Well, few quantities for convenience just to keep
track of negative signs, this in work, in the work
that has to be done on the system by its
surroundings compared to the work that is done by
the system of strategies that can be used to turn
a wheel and make the bus go forward. So we've seen
that when the surroundings do work on the system,
they reduce the internal energy of that system.
Through the general first law of thermodynamics,
that's the situation when the overall work, the.
The negative TV, the computer is positive. So, for
example, a decrease in the volume. Requires that
the system requires that the surroundings to work
on the system to a positive overall work that will
call this work in. And keep everything positive.
So all four of these parties are going to be
defined to be positive when the system does work
on its surroundings, its. Using energy that it has
to do something useful outside itself, so it's
lowering its own internal energy, corresponding to
a negative value for the overall work Miles, to do.
Output work, which we will. Defined to be positive,
is that just the negative of that overall quality
of work that we've defined, minus so many changes,
is positive. You can expect work to be done by the
system of the surroundings. And this is the if you
want the absolute value of that work by carefully
choosing the negative signs to keep everything
positive. And there's a similar story with a cheap
flowing into and out of the system. When he was in
Mishu, equal to temperature type situation,
entropy is positive to raise the control of the
system. It flows out that times change and entropy
is negative. And we define the kids with the waste
heat that is expelled to be the negative then of
the overall heat exchange. Now, we defined earlier
this week, so that gives us the second quality in
this equation. Sixty four at the efficiency is the
network done by the system. So how much would you
put out into its surroundings, minus how much work
had to be done to it as input? All normalized by
the amount of Keat. That has to flow into the
system, so the total amount of heat that flows in
making no reference to any heat that might flow
out. In the case of the engine, we are going to be
interested in the situations where that network is
positive, where work is done by the system that
has to be done to it in order for it to operate
with both cue in. The inflow keeps and this work
done, being positive, the quantities, the ratio is
also positive. So the efficiency that we've
defined here is. Always a positive, never strictly
positive.
And from the first of the millennium, we can
actually place an upper bound on how efficient a
heat engine can possibly be. So that's the.
Overstate this to to wrap up. And the calculation
is fairly simple, one showed here an equation
sixty five where we know that because the system
is returning to its initial from an erratic state,
by the definition of a cycle that gets back to the
starting point, we know that all of the energy
flow into the system has to balance out around
each of these cycles. So the net amount of heat
that flows into the system compared to that which
flows out, plus the amount of work done on the
system compared to the amount of work it does, has
to all cancel out to zero. So that the work done,
this difference between the output work, minus the
input work,
can be no larger than the input amount of heat
that is equal to the difference between the heat
flowing in and the heat going out. And that is
itself a not negative quantity, I suppose all of
these equations here I should have had. Less than
an hour greater than or equal to science, because
it's possible to have varnishing work. Or
banishing heat flow, as we've seen in the current
cycle. In other words, the. Efficiency, the ratio
of this network divided by the heat can be no
larger than one. And this occurs when Kuis out is
equal to zero and there is no way to get expelled,
so. This is sometimes phrased as the statement
that the first of all of the attacks means you
can't win in a heat cycle, you can get no more
work out of the cycle then the amount of heat that
has to be put into it in order for it to operate.
So I'll wrap up there. You have time for any final
questions about this setup, work and efficiency.
And otherwise, obviously, some of you and possibly
more back this afternoon will look a bit more
detail at mixing, mixing entropy and the question
of thermodynamics.
According to.