That's the recording started, and this is
the code for this morning:
Nine four, zero zero, one five.
Are there any immediate questions before we resume
working up to quantum gases in the grand
canonical ensemble?
It's been a few days since we were last in this
place in the notes.  So let's just quickly catch up with
the plan for Friday the 18th of March.
It's now one week before the final part of the
computer project is due. We may get into that in the
tutorial this afternoon, rather than this morning.
We are building up to quantum gases
in the grand canonical ensemble.
And so far this week, and for at least the first
part of today, this has led us to.
Focus on the details of. Monthly statistics, as
opposed to classical statistics we dealt with
earlier in the term.
And the distinguishing factor here is that rather
than going over the household energy is that each
single particle can have in a more physical system
with many particles. We want to define microstates.
From the.
Occupation numbers of energy levels. I'm just
trying to see how much I can fit on the screen
here.
So.
Rather than. Coming up with a single particle.
Protection function and then combining all of
those for overcounting in the case of the missing
particles, we consider the energy levels of our
system and some over all of the possible
occupation numbers that those energy levels can
have. And we have gone through now two different
cases. Particles known as Bozo's compared to.
Those known as Hermione's, different possible
occupation numbers.
And the book is on a case number of particles and
energy level l can be any negative integer zero
one, two, three off to infinity in the thermionic
case.
There is only.
Possibility of having a single particle in any
given energy level, identical formulas have to
simultaneously compute and a. compute and we are
now in the process of. Checking that the resulting
quantum statistics.
Reduces to the classical result be drives the
start of the week in the classical women's.
I had the screen just to start the claim that this
classical element corresponded to high
temperatures, so many questions come up going
through that quick recap to get back to left off.
Three days ago from.
15TH to the 18th, this claim was a fairly
qualitative argument that the classical limit is
the high temperature regime. Rather than the low
temperature regime where we should expect quantum
of classical statistics to disagree. I did just
give a heuristic argument for this, and what we
can do to satisfy ourselves with this argument is
in fact correct, is actually analyze the. Three
sets of statistics that we've derived in the great
canonical ensemble at these high temperatures,
some of the back syllables of the classical
statistics, the Einstein and quantum statistics of
bosons and the family, Dirac quantum statistics
and fermions and aim to see whether our
expectation or claim that all three of these
become consistent in the high-temperature
classical limit is in fact, correct. The subtlety
here is. What can happen with the political No.
At high temperatures. It is possible to.
End up with an uncontrolled number of particles in
the grand economic ensemble. We have to be careful
to consider the appropriate high-temperature limit
so that we are really comparing physical systems
that don't have a divergence number of particles.
And to illustrate this problem, which may not be
obvious with the state, you will see what what
happens going through the calculation for these
three sets of statistics that are reproduced here
just for convenience in the form of. They cranking
out competition functions from which everything
else is derived and starting from each of these
cases, we want to go through the calculation that
we introduced. In Unit six, in the great ensemble
to compute the average particle numbers as a
function of the fixed temperature and chemical
potential of each of these systems and putting all
three of these canonical production functions
together. Can highlight both their similarities
and differences. Hopefully that improves the focus
slightly. All three of them depend on this
exponential factor, a generalization of the
Boltwood factor that now includes the ratio of
chemical potential to temperature one over data,
as well as the energy for each energy level level
by. And in all three cases, we see that. The man
attracting the ideal computation factories is just
a simple product of a factory for each energy
level, that depends only on the energy of that
energy level. The difference comes from exactly
how these exponential factors are being multiplied
together in the classical maximalism case. We
actually have the exponential of the exponential.
Which changes to this geometric series, one over
one minus the exponential for those I statistics
and just a simple factor of one, plus the
exponential and the very direct chaos due to the
restrictions of the occupation numbers for
fermions. And in all three of these cases, it is.
Very easy to break down the great economic
potential, so we call it this is the negative
temperature times, the logarithm of deportation
function. So all we have to do is take the
logarithm of these three expressions is converting
the law into the product of factors, too. If some
of the log of each factor and recognize that the
void is exponential is just its arguments. So we
have put an actual goals in case the overall
factor of minus two times the arguments. Of that,
more be exponential now summed over all of these
energy levels level from zero to al. In the case,
the war involved one over a factor is the negative
marks, the negative signs cancel out a positive
temperature. Times the sun over these laws with a
relative negative sign in front of the exponential
factor in the case. There is no additional
negative sign to cancel out the negativity from
the definition of the potential. So there's an
overall negative sign, but a relative plus sign in
front of the exponential.
So. These are.
The intermediate stage to the actual calculation
of the average particle over which we derived the
Section six point three to be just a negative
partial derivative of these great potentials with
respect to the chemical potential. And we can go
through this calculation in this gap here
for convenience. The key to the great logical
potential from the previous page. In order to just
take this derivative. Inside of the sun over
energy levels. So that brings down a positive
factor of beta keeping them the same exponential
term in the latest data entry level, 9:00 a.m.
beta is in room temperature. So those two factors
cancel out.
And for. Convenience. I'm going to write this as a
some of E to the minus X, so defining this X of L
to be a factor beta minus use of particular,
rewriting that all the time.
In this competition at the next. The next
computations do become. Bit more. Nontrivial,
though. Also for later convenience.
OK, go ahead and write the exponential with the
negative argument that's going over exponential
with the positive arguments. So sum over overall,
the energy levels of one divided by the
exponential factor of the speed of times energy
minus chemical potential. And something similar
looking will pop up when we go through the
exercise of taking these derivatives of the log in
the bull's eye, something that can be tracked
cases.
And the on this case. We have another negative
sign coming in from the definition of a particle
over here, so that overall factor of minus T up
front the silver and the derivative of the wallaga
will give us. One of the arguments of that log is
either the negative Exell moved through the
chamber or. Putting the derivatives through into
that negative exponential term of each of the plus
data times you. Is going to bring down the overall
negative side, the positive data, then exponential.
Of negative axonal and again, temperature and the
temperature cancel out, we can divide through by.
E to the power supply to get the sun over energy
levels of one over the positive minus one. So just
differing by. Subtracting one compared to the
results in the Maximalism case.
And it's pretty similar for this final tribute to
Rick statistics looking at the average particle,
No. In the case of fermions, we now have a
different negative sign out front and as well as a
different negative sign coming from the. Factor in
front of this exponential. So it's a positive beta
e to the minus Excel over one plus minus X now
canceling things out and dividing through by the
exponential factor as above Eataly, plus X plus
one. So differing from the business case only by
the relative sine. In the denominator. And. One,
that. Notable or useful feature of all three of
these results is that they are coming out as the
sum over energy levels of something that depends
on just the energy corresponding to the sea level.
So we can find this to be. The average occupation
number for each particular energy level is that
with the lower case and rather than the upper case
and. So this is the average number of particles
that is in each energy level, something from the
ground state level zero up to the maximum level,
which not surprisingly, gives the overall average
number of particles in the system as a whole.
And. You should put a label on here somewhere on
the inside, the expectation that I call that next
wolfmen. This is similarly the. Average occupation
number is a function of energy level, the Einstein
case and the. Similar average occupation, no very
direct statistics.
So finding that. The overall occupation number
factorization is somewhere over the average
occupation, one year for each energy level to
extract the average occupation numbers in the
three cases restored by the Times is available on
this chemical potential. I was just calling on the
calculation to save something. And see that.
There is a.
Compelling degree of similarity between all three
of these results, the classical case just has this
one over exponential factor compared to the pros
on the very different quantum cases that add or
subtract one from the exponential of the
denominator of the average occupation number.
A few things we can do about this is that in this
case, all that varies from energy level to energy
level is the value of the energy. This is of how
and when the EFL is. Say, combined with the
potential to make a very large positive number
multiplied by the positive temperature, we get a
very large exponential factor and the overall
occupation number vanishes, goes down to zero as
one of a very large number, but the opposite
limits. The argument to the exponential is a
negative number that as long as the magnitude that
exponential is negligible, it goes to zero
compared to this one. And we find a maximum value
for the Iraq occupation of Iraq of one in case
where that exponential factor approaches. Zero or
so. No.
And that connects to it's not set here, but that
connects to the convergence of the geometric
series that we saw on Tuesday when coming up with
the expression for the bull's eye protection
function where. Let's have that reproduced here.
We can pull that up. The other piece in those
notes.
Well, we found that.
At the top of this page, ninety seven thousand
eighty five, the Bose Einstein statistics only
converges when this exponential factor is less
than one. Or equivalently, the energy has to be
larger than the chemical essential for every
energy left. And if we plug in that results to the
occupation number that we have now,
give us
the requirement that the energy always be larger
than the chemical potential. Guarantees that the
argument of the exponential is. Greater than zero,
so the explanation itself is greater than one, and
there's no divergence coming in from. The
denominator can be both Einstein occupation number.
Which you will also see.
In graphical form. So from the definition of a
potential protection function for those on
assistance, we guarantee that.
This divergence that would happen if the
exponential factor were to equal one is avoided.
So that is an excellent question connecting to
what we saw a few days ago.
For the purposes of today, though, we're
interested in the classical events where we want
all three of these different types of statistics
to introduce the same predictions, at least
approximately to show that the quantum physics
that we expect to be on underlying fundamental
level is reproducing the large scale classical
statistics. That was developed many years before
quantum physics was even. Imagine, and it's really
easy to see from putting things together like this
that. It is possible to get all three of these
average occupation numbers to be approximately
equal when the exponential factor is much larger
than one, so that's exponential plus one or minus
one or exponential zero, approximately the same.
And the corresponding average occupation numbers
are also. Approximately the same, and this does
connect to. How we started off this unit by saying
that quantum statistics arises where it becomes
important when. The probability for two particles
to occupy multiple particles to occupy the same
energy level is not trivial, which screws up the
overcounting corrections in the case of individual
particles that we could do classically with these
large exponential factors in the denominators. All
of these average occupation numbers are very small.
So the probability of having a large number of
particles in any energy level in any microstates
is also very small. So we are in the classical
regime where we can expect to your energy level to
have at least one party going into those cases
zero. But there is something weird going on
connected to the subject. What about the service
today, which is that what we have identified as
the classical limit? Is where this argument to the
exponential Betis heightens the difference between
the energy level and chemical potential is much
larger than one.
Which if we recall that the is the signature.
Seems to look like a very small temperature to get
this ratio much larger than what? At least if we
imagine that the numerator is some fixed quantity
for a the energy level, it can make this ratio
very small by making sort of make the ratio very
large and the temperature on denominator a small.
And if we were to instead of the. Take the knife,
high temperature limits Sebadoh point zero again
with this fixed difference between the energy and
chemical potential than the average population,
numbers we have up here would be one. In the case
of natural willfulness is this silly argument that
the exponential is going to zero, the exponential
one. So that is one of the one is one case, one
over one plus one is a half, as you were
discussing earlier, in case we actually start
approaching infinity that we can't reach. Exactly,
to avoid the diversions, extra constraints on the
difference between energy, well, the energy value
and chemical potential.
So it looks as though the classic element that we
have found by computing the average particle
number in each of these three cases really seems
to look like a low temperature rather than this
naive high temperature level where we. Ignore the
other. Parameter that defines the great canonical
ensemble. Not only the this year, but also the
temperature and chemical potential that. Care can
be adjusted to balance the effect of higher
temperatures, so we can see here that as we take.
Temperature, larger water, the average occupation
numbers of the average number of particles is
increasing of the decreasing denominators, the
results that we computed. Which is to say that. As
the temperature gets higher, we start to see a
larger and larger numbers of particles. Which are
increasing the probability that those larger
numbers of particles may end up in the same energy
level.
And in order to balance that effect, we have the
chemical potential to adjust in tandem with the
temperature to get the true high temperature
classical weapons. Where not only does the
temperature go to zero, but the chemical potential,
which we can recall is generally negative from our
work in Unit six, needs to be sent to a very large
man if you make it a valid. And whether this has
the effect in this equation. Eighty nine. That as
the denominator in this ratio becomes large in the
high-temperature towards the numerator with a
subtraction of this and the potential that is
going to negative infinity becomes even larger,
even faster, satisfying this inequality even at
high temperatures. And what this is doing is.
Reducing the probability for seeing large numbers
of particles in the system more negative and gets
the greater the energy cost is increasing the
number of particles in the system, going back to
the definition of the chemical potential as the.
Responsive to systems, energy or entropy, to a
change the protocol number, and then
at the same time that we are reducing the
probability for large numbers of particles by
making the chemical potential negative, by making
the temperature more positive, we increase the
number of energy levels that have a measurable
bolson factor.
The exponential of minus energy poverty becomes
the larger probability of single occupancy
as that city going forward here in the heart of
the exponential, that becomes less suppressed. So
together, these two effects are giving us the true
temperature that. Which has a pair of inequalities
that not only does the temperature have to be
large with respect to the energy levels of
interest, but the negative chemical potential has
to be even larger than that temperature, which to
satisfy the liquid derived above, looking to see
where these average occupation numbers become
approximately equal for both classical and quantum
statistics. And
we. Got the three results for that average
occupation of anger that we found for classical
national statistics in the red dotted line, the
blue Quantico's systems and the solid blue van in
the green directions that sticks on the dotted
green line, we see that they do indeed come
together of the edge of this plot in this regime
where what's being plotted only, for example, axis
here is exactly that combination of energy by this
kind of a potential divided by senator. That we
are giving must be greater than one in the
classical regime. So this is the true
High-temperature what? On the right side of this,
what we can see even that looking at values around
four, which is not strictly much greater than one,
there's already no visible difference between.
These three types of statistics. But you do start
to break away from each other as we go to. A lower
temperature regimes over on the left side of the.
Flot.
Let's put it the limitation there, so we see
looking first at the case of very direct
assistance, a visual confirmation of the
mathematics we did earlier. That the limits of the
occupation number for any given energy level
vary only between zero and one consistent with the
exclusion principle that forbids multiple
occupancy. A very, very unusual.
We also see if it goes on this case, the
diversions that was
discussed before the premiere this week and in
response to that question and in between them,
that classical maximalists is this it doesn't
really know anything about the quantum physics
that becomes important about energy, just keeps
increasing exponentially quickly as this ratio
that appears in the exponential factor increases.
So that's the maximum value and. The divergence
for.
Those are some statistics, but isn't this the
problem, but no. Actually legalized the major.
So that is.
Confirmation of our earlier claim and heuristic
argument that classical important statistics
should become equivalent in a classical. Regime or
classical with it, we've identified as the
appropriate high temperature limit where the
chemical potential is adjusted to control
particles, we're economical and sample. No pause
here at the end of this unit before going go to.
Actual applications to quantum systems of gas is
to see if there are any questions about. What we
have seen so far.
Yeah, the always.
Or.
If.
I don't know why that is, that these.
Yeah, this is something that we defined by seeing
the structure of the average particle number that
we used in these cases, we went through this
computation based on our derivation from Unit six.
This is a good question.
You know, with. The factorization that simplifies
life for these nondrinking particles that we're
dealing with so far. And we found that each of the
average particle numbers, so the total number of
particles in the microstates breaks down or
factorization into the sum over all of the energy
levels of some expression that depends only on
energy for the energy level and the.
Essentially define the.
Object being slammed over as the average
occupation number for that energy level, which we
can motivate as well by seeing the relation in
this case, that when we have an expression for the
total number of particles on average in the entire
system. And that breaks up into some over the
energy levels. The thing being sold over is the
average number of particles in the corresponding
energy level and we defined earlier back at the
start of this week, the number of particles in the
energy level is defined as the occupation number.
So here you're sort of generalizing that initial
definition to become that average over the
probability space, identifying.
As average as an occupation number, because it is
precisely the number of particles occupying that
energy level. So if you want, this can be a
definition that is inconsistent with both the pure
occupation number without averaging over
microstates, as well as consistent with the full
particle number in the grand approach.
So is that clear enough?
How these. The Republicans are going to tell the
party of their occupation of the. Averages of both
of those are pretty economical. So.
And one possible question that someone has about
might have come up would have been. This more
heuristic argument that the quantum regime
corresponds to when the weather is a large percent
probability of having multiple occupancy of energy
levels. We've seen in the family directive case
that, of course, multiple can is forbidden and
there is a story to tell about how we still obtain
assistance in the direct case was zero probability
of having multiple occupancy and. Onto this
forecast that this is something we will be getting
into over the next week or two, looking at quantum
assets, both of those on the fermions, and we get
to the thermionic case, we will see how quantum
effects are still important. Even when the
occupation number is restricted to be either zero
or one and multiple occupancy is forbidden by the
nature of particles in quantum physics.
That will not be what we do for the remainder of
the day or Monday. We've got about 10 minutes left
to do a.
Bit of a recap connecting what we have now done
with quantum statistics and the grand finale, the
ensemble to earlier considerations of. The
classical non relativistic ideal gas, which was
the topic of Unit four, that's where we introduced
the idea of having an ideal gas confined to some
volume of a cubic volume of size that were Kud.
And just to get started, looking at gases of
photons, which are particles of light and the
particular topic, particles of light that I
remember mentioning on Tuesday as an example of
famous bosun's that we have all around us all the
time. Let's just do a quick recap of how these.
Massive goes on, so not relativistic particles
behave in an ideal gas in the context of the great
chemical insult. So I have. Improve the rotation
slightly to change the number of energy levels
script out, so let's not confuse with the size of
the container that these particles are confined to.
And we want to. Recall not only the. Economical
patriation function and potential for the
statistics, which I'll skip over, because we just
looked at that at the start of today. We now want
to. Compute not only the average particle number,
but also things like the pressure, internal energy
and entropy. Usual large scale macroscopic or
thermodynamic quantities that. We saw during this
war looking at ecological disaster cycles. And all
that we have to do, starting from this general
expression with a.
Placeholder for the energy value corresponding to
each energy level is actually specified, the
energy levels for our system would interest. Which
this is where we will see more concretely the
issue of degeneracy, where different energy levels
or in the end will have the same energy, which is
something we have already seen in the novelistic
ideal gas where each particle.
With such a mess mass in this volume, allocute has.
Quantize energies that depend on the. Some of
integers, so this is coming from general, not
relativistic expression that the energy is
momentum squared, divided by twice the mass in
these moments of. Our quantized that depend on
these integer labels, X, Y, Z, with an overall
factor of each bar times higher overall
convoluting. Inverse links to units of movements
there by two units of energy.
And for convenience, we can supply something we
did in the Gap for and define this, Beaupre factor
is per square. PI squared over two times the mass
of the particles L squared to be a constant unit
of energy that is coming in then with. This
combination of factors, the one change that we
have to make for quantum particles, is that the
jurors now are no longer merely about negative.
They must be strictly positive and.
The reason for this is, again, something coming
from on physics at. You don't need to know in
advance, and I'll just motivated by here to wrap
up today.
It's a feature of quantum physics known as an
uncertainty principle, which was first discovered
by Gregor Heisenberg. He was about twenty five and
it relates the precision in quantum mechanics with
which the position and momentum of any particle
can instantaneously be defined in principle. So.
It's not an issue of observation or measurements,
it's how will define both the position, say, in
the X direction and the corresponding momentum,
this piece of X.
Are actually in existence in Major so. What
through the forward calculation that involves the
standard deviation includes the precise factors of
two high level visit here. And just. The relation
between the. The. Uncertainty or precision with
which the position of any particle can be defined,
multiplied by the precision with which its
corresponding momentum can be defined, it must be.
Larger than. This plank's constant for.
Which is relevant when we have placed an ideal gas
in a container before, you know, on a side,
because I guarantee you that the position of the
particle is known at least as accurately as well
as a whole, just because you know what's inside
the box. So the position is determined up to the
size of that box, which requires that this moment
cannot be zero, which would be determined. Exactly.
It has to be at least that ratio of over Delta X
or department over help, which not coincidentally,
is exactly the P factor of two vectors of Pi that
we were working with already for motivation from
the underlying quantum physics taken as an onsides.
So.
With this in all of that, we can.
The consideration of these different energy levels
and the number of this case and just categorized
not only the energy level, but in this case, what
is the what are the generous use of these energy
levels and how the energy levels to behave with
the same energy and the interest of time? I'll
just sketch out a few of these. Where? You can
start. From the ground state energy level, where
the energy use of zero is three times that
elementary unit, we just define each four square
square over to him elsewhere. That corresponds to.
This integer vector being one one, one, the
minimum possible value of three components. So the
degeneracy here, the number of energy levels with
this energy is just this one. If we go up to the
next value of energy, so the first excited state.
You would have we need to make one of these
components of the two rather than one, and then we
square that to get the energy. We get four plus
one plus one or six times that fundamental unit.
And the degeneracy of the energy levels with this
value of the energy is three, depending on which
of these components of K we choose to be the
larger one equal to two. Similarly, moving on to
making any two of those three on the next smallest
number. So. Spectroscope two, two, one, two, one,
two, one, two, two. We end up with nine units of
energy and again, I just listed three ways of
getting that.
And even after this and figure out for yourself,
maybe you have just read it down in the interest
of time that we have three energy levels with 11
units of energy.
Coming from. Making any one component. Of that,
after a three square to nine, then add one plus
one, we make things all to.
That's what we get up to 12, Absolon, in the
single case, two to two, so that is. Maybe a quick
recap will need to recap on Monday afternoon when
we go on to the case of massive snowstorms.
We'll pick things up with that novel case of
massless particles in an ideal gas Monday
afternoon and talk more about thermodynamic cycles
in the tutorial and see if there are any questions
about the computer project that is due less than a
week from now. And are there any final questions
to wrap up this morning's discussion at.
If not, I will. Shut things down. Hope to see you
again for that this afternoon.