All right, we'll start getting under way.  Welcome back to the
second half of the first part of this week and I'll
remember to put up the six-digit number first this time. It is eight seven two
six five seven.
That can sit there for the rest of the hour and we can pick
up pretty much where we left off yesterday, which
was essentially the end of the non-relativistic
fermion gas at low temperatures, where we came up
with, essentially, the equation of states.  And I
can check if there are questions lingering from
last time about what we got to,
or anything different.
But now this result here in this gap is indeed
the equation of state for this non relativistic
fermion gas at low temperature. So it's the usual
target we've been going after with all these
quantum gases into the classical ideal gas before
that written in a few different ways, relieving
the pressure either to the energy density, the
density times, the chemical potential new or.
Fighting in the relation between that number of
density and chemical potential for the low
temperature for gas, just in terms of the
intensity of the number of particles per unit
volume raised to the five thirds power, and what
is unusual about this result compared to the
equation of states that we derive from the
classical ideal gas PV equals A.. Which also
persisted with just a minor change in numerical
constants for photon gas is that there is no
dependence on the temperature at all in any of
these relations. The energy and density are
independent of temperature, at least for a
sufficiently low temperatures, leaving this
constant temperature, independent pressure or
equation state that we can plot here as the low
temperature limit on the more general expression
in some python code will produce notes and
interpolate between this low temperature, constant
equation of state and the classical ideal gas law
at high temperatures where the pressure becomes
linear and the temperature with that.
Proportionality just be the number that's
available, so. Having. Reached the equation of
state for the non relativistic, at least at low
temperatures, we can see this at work. In physics
of a certain type of supernova explosion of stars
and maybe before going on to that, I should also
reiterate the overall physical picture that led to
the equations that we found where we had the idea
of all the particles in this gas filling up energy
levels one after the next until they reach the
maximum energy level at which all the particles
are accounted for that corresponds to that Fermi
energy. So that is a very useful picture of what's
going on behind the mathematics to explain both
why the energy and pressure are independent of
temperature and low temperatures, as well as why
that chemical potential has to be positive in that
regime with only a single microstates
corresponding to that organization, of all the
particles filling all of the energy levels with a
low energy up to that maximum very energy.
And that sort of physical picture is essentially
what's realized in certain types of stars and
particular.
Very dense stars known as Whitehorse that are
related to these type of a supernova explosions of
stars and as a prelude to seeing how that operates,
just mentioned that the.
The question here is, how low does a temperature
have to be at practice in order for this low
temperature equation states to be valid? So that
constant pressure that we derived yesterday is
known as the university pressure and. The
terminology here is not exactly perfect, it's
something you inherited from the past, so the
degeneracy is unrelated to the multiple energy
levels that we all have the same value of the
energy. The idea is that at these low temperatures,
all the particles in this gas want to be at the
lowest possible energy, which is to say that the
very direct distribution exponentially suppresses
the occupation probability for energy levels with
higher values of the energy. And as close to equal
energies as these fermions can get is the system
where all the energy levels are are filled up. So
they're trying to be degenerate, but can't quite
make it due to the point exclusion principle. And
in order to.
Have this non-zero degeneracy pressure in order to
realize this physical picture where all of the
particles are trying to fill the low energy energy
levels due to the low temperature that.
Temperature has to be low relative to that Fermoy
energy. The highest energy level that is filled in
the limit of zero temperature and the place where
any additional Hermione's being added to the gas
would have to enter the first energy levels
available for them to fill up so long as the
temperature is small compared to the energy we can.
Rely on having a. Nonzero generosity, pressure and
the zero temperature limit. And just from the
definition of the energy that we had. We looked at
yesterday, which may as well write down, so we
have here.
That up at the top of the page from the energy was
squared. Over to the three PI squared and then the
average particle density arrays to the two thirds
power. So we can see that this dependence on that
density of two thirds is increasing the energy as
the density increases, which becomes particularly
relevant for stars, where the gravitational
attraction of an enormous amount of matter is
introducing very high densities and
correspondingly high ferme energies. So that's
even ordinary temperatures that we would consider
every day. Levels not particularly low turn out to
be very small compared to the energy. So just to
give some illustrations matter, like this table
tends to have roughly an Avogadro's number worth
of particles in a cubic centimeter of changing.
Units to adults per cubic meter, we have something
like 10 to be twenty three times two to convert
from centimeter commuter times, a cube to get from
all three dimensions of space takes us up to ten
to twenty nine atoms per cubic meter. And this
I'll just tell you, if you plug in the conversion
factor between the topic units, energies and
temperatures corresponds to a fairly energy of
about ten thousand Kelvin. So that even the
temperature is two orders of magnitude lower that
we are working in right now, our low temperatures
compared to the very of everyday metals, for
instance, electrons moving around in the metal.
If we consider those white dwarf stars I mentioned
earlier, we have. Energies that are about a
hundred thousand times larger, which correspond to
densities that are then. One hundred thousand
times to the power, three halves larger, so things
like ten of the thirty six atoms per cubic meter,
which you can plug in the relation between
temperature and atomic mass units, is usually
talked about in terms of about one ton of mass per
cubic centimeter.
And this is. About a million times more dense than
our sun. So back to 10 of the six, that would be
what we got if we tried to cram all of the matter
in our son into a volume. About the size of the
earth, one hundred times smaller radius or one
hundred cubed is a million times smaller in volume.
So that is the context for the sorts of energy,
the temperatures, where we want to apply our low
temperature equation of state from yesterday. I'll
just say that the reason these wildfires are so
dense is because the nuclear fusion processes that
typically inject heat and energy into stars has
turned off and they have exhausted all of the
elements. So hydrogen, helium is what are fused
together at very high temperatures and pressures
to produce energy from nuclear fusion. But as you
know, hydrogen fuel, hydrogen and helium nuclei
fuse together to produce larger nuclei higher up
on the periodic table. Lithium really up to carbon
and oxygen. And once that. Nuclear fusion has
ceased all of that heat and the radiation pressure
coming from this nuclear fusion, which formerly
formerly counteracted the gravitational traction
in these stars, has entrances. And the only thing
that is left to balance the. The gravitational
attraction that's pulling all of this matter into
smaller and smaller volumes, making the denser,
denser. Is exactly that degeneracy pressure coming
from the Pauli exclusion principle rather than any
actual forces? And this is. The only source of
pressure left to counteract the gravitational
attraction and keep these white dwarfs from
collapsing into either denser objects and
eventually to black holes, once the. Maternity
services shoved into such a small region that. And
that's right, and forms in the framework of
general relativity.
So maybe the one. Remarkable aspect of this
physics. Worth commenting on is that. This is the
pressure we derived, this coming from a non
attractive ideal gas of quantum fermions and the
fact that we can accurately describe even these
extreme, very dense and very high energy
conditions as not interacting particles. Yusoff.
Part of the reason why it is so useful in an
application that the large numbers of particles
and the negative energy scales comparing the
temperature to the Fermi energy conspire to. Allow
even a good description of.
Matter in extreme environments from a fairly
simple physical principles, and here we are helped
by that very large ferme energy from the very high
pressure. So apparently energy around. A billion
kelvin.
It's crucial to keep the temperatures of these
blackhorse low because once that so I should say,
as the as time goes on, the white floors are no
longer burning any fuel in nuclear fusion. But of
course, when they formed, they formed at the end
of that nuclear fusion process. So at the time
when the hydrogen fuel run out, temperatures in
the interior of these Wetmore stars tend to be
about 10 degrees coming from that high temperature
nuclear fusion. And they only gradually cool by
admitting that thermal radiation over the course
of 12, they really have to be cool for trillions
of years until they reach some equilibrium with
the very low temperature, cosmic microwave
background
that has an order of about two Kelvin rather than
10 million Kelvin. So we're saved by the very
large Verm energy that allows even temperatures
that if they were in this room, we would consider
to be very high and still be considered very low
and effectively zero temperature to a very good
approximation.
And yes, I have said that. Left on their own,
white dwarfs will happily cool for trillions of
years is what it would take for those temperatures,
10 million Kelvin to eventually reach equilibrium.
With the low temperature cosmic microwave
background radiation, which is itself cooling off
as time goes by, it's currently about two point
seven Kelvin and dropping. By the by the day, very
slowly.
The way that this connects to supernovas is if we
consider a white dwarf star in what's called a
binary system where there are two stars orbiting
around each other, at least one of which is the
white door. So this is an artist's impression of
the sort of binary system where we have. On the
left. Some companion star to that white dwarf,
which is still burning its nuclear fuel, producing
energy radiation and emitting a steady stream of
particles, and by having this very dense. White
dwarf star nearby. The gravitational attraction of
that, that object pulls in all of the matter being
emitted by the companion star, that's gradually
over the course of millions of years and trillions
of years, piles up in the white dwarf, increasing
its particle number, increasing its density and
increasing its temperature by virtue of.
The larger amount, the larger densify, that's. Is
being brought into play. And a somewhat more
complicated calculation, bringing in relativistic
nuclear physics in addition to the statistical
physics that we are considering.
Identifies the critical density for the star at
which new and different types of fusion reactions
can start to occur, and in particular, the carbon
and oxygen that I mentioned earlier, that the
fence consists of become able to fuse themselves,
which requires larger density compared to hydrogen
and helium. And this happens when the overall mass
of the white dwarf. Is about 40 percent larger
than the massive or so one point four for about a
few percent uncertainty. This is a value of the
math known as the chandrasekar.
Something drives by to remind you chandrasekar in
the nineteen hundreds and.
As soon as the carbon and oxygen in the white talk
are able to start fusing and producing lots of. A
new source of thermal radiation and a new source
of energy and an increase in the temperature, this
fusion procedes quickly enough that it actually
undergoes what's called a runaway reaction. So as
the fusion recedes, the temperature of the white
dwarf is increased faster than its density can
adjust, as we would expect from equations, to seem
like the ideal gas law that we end up with a very
dense object and a very high pressure. That, in
turn, encourages more and more fusion, giving more
and more energy until.
A significant fraction of the total mass in the
star million times that of the Earth. It's all
fused into heavier elements, increasing the
temperature. To billions of Kelvyn, rather than
just hundreds or tens of millions and producing
belatedly and increasing the pressure that blasts
the white door for cart. Releasing about five
million times the energy that the sun that would
release through its hydrogen fusion in a
comparable amount of time.
So this is a supernova, a very rapid a very
violent explosion of a star, and it's not the only
type of supernova that's possible.
It is an obscure historical reasons known as type
one, a supernova. The other types of supernovas
tend to come from larger and heavier stars that
collapse very rapidly as they run out of nuclear
fuel, and that collapse immediately produces a
supernova. The key aspect of these Type 1A
supernovas that. Are based on a way to start
acquiring additional matter, additional density
from a companion. Is that thanks to relying on the
degeneracy pressure of a low temperature Fairbury
gas to. Stabilize the system as it accumulates
that matter, the people in a supernova is always
triggered at a very regular, predictable point,
just as the amount of matter the light accumulates
passes this chandrasekar limit at 40 percent
larger than the mass of our sun. And because this
very specific amount of mass is the trigger for
the supernova. All of the Type 1A supernovas are
very similar and independent of. Whatever the mass
or the temperature of the star was at the point
when nuclear fusion ran out of hydrogen and helium
fuel. So what this provides is a very regular
process that astronomers can look at what they
call a standard candle where by observing how much.
Energy and radiation reach the Earth from a
distance Type 1A supernova, making calibrate
precisely how far away it had to be in order for
that amount of energy to reach the earth. Not
knowing exactly, exactly the same amount of energy
in the same matter was put out at the source of
that supernova. And there was about 20 years ago,
a very large scale worldwide project to map out.
Lots of Type 1A supernovas, various distances away
from the earth, which correspond to the supernova
having occurred many years ago and the like,
taking thousands or millions of years to reach the
earth.
Traveling at the speed of light, so by looking at
supernovas of different distances to get a glimpse
back at the. Behaviour of the universe at
different points of time as a supernovas were
occurring and the light from them was traveling
towards us. And the surprising observation of that
mapping process was that. The longer go the
supernova occurred, the faster it seemed to be
moving away from us or to see things, in other
words, the expansion of the universe. Is actually
accelerating, so the universe is expanding more
and more rapidly. As time goes on over the course
of these millions or billions of years. And this
is a phenomenon that we observe without yet
understanding what drives that, we give it a fancy
name called dark energy, which is somewhat
nonsensical. And.
And in the context of general relativity, I'll
just say that this dark energy is terminology that
refers to exactly the accelerating expansion of
the universe that was initially revealed by
observing these type of supernovas, relying on the
regularity thanks to the slow build up of mass
counterbalanced by their degeneracy pressure and
that. Receive the Nobel Prize in physics lab 10
years ago, getting ever closer to the present day
and upcoming Nobel Prizes. So any questions about
that application of our equation of states for non
relativistic and gases?
We can move on to
someone we consider the different regime going
from the non relativistic, from the obvious to the
relatively large mass compared to particle, its
particles, momentum to the relativistic regime.
Which gets us back in somewhat of a full circle to
the photon gas that we dealt with last week.
These so the difference now being that we will
consider Marsalis, who effectively Marsalis
fermions rather than Krotons where?
We can motivate, considering the relativistic
regime by. Noting that it is.
Relevance in nature, even in this context of the
supernova explosions, if we convert to the the
energy of a billion Kelvin we just mentioned for
the light dwarf star into units of. Millions of
electron volts. So looking at energies as opposed
to temperatures, just a conversion of units, we
see that the electrons in these Whitehorse that
are providing and pressure that stabilizes them. I
have this kinetic energy of about three hundred
thousand electron volts that is comparable to the
mass energy of electrons, five hundred eleven
thousand electron volts. Which is the regime in
which we can't necessarily neglect militaristic
corrections to the behavior of these particles and
indeed in, say, Carter's calculation, this
relativistic effects were crucial to show that
anything interesting happens around that
Chandrasekhar limit.
Unfortunately, the. Intermediate regime between
relativistic ultra relativistic energies is
typically the most complicated, at least
enlightening to analyze. We have to. Account for
the effects of relativity. We can't make any
simplifications the way we could for photon gasses,
so for purposes we will. Just. Consider the ultra
relativistic regime looking at gases of massless
Hermione's that are not completely unpredictable.
These are an excellent approximation to thermionic
particles known as neutrinos. Which.
Are also a topic of very active experimental
investigation. At prisons in particular, related
to the. The masses of neutrinos and the puzzle of
explaining why you treat the masses are so small
compared to all the other fermions that we know,
like electrons on neutrino masses, are many orders
of magnitude smaller than electron masses or any
others. We don't actually know how small they are.
We only have upper bounds. As well as lower bounds,
what the masses of the was can be, but for many
years they were thought to be exactly massless.
It's because their voices are so too small to
resolve experimentally, and it was. Just six years
ago now, the twenty fifteen Nobel Prize that was
able to prove that neutrinos have to masses at all
places that lower about. On their possible
Maskell's.
Even though those masses are not zero, they are so
small compared to. Any energy's any conceivable
momenta wavelengths that these neutrinos have that
we can treat them as masses, the programs to a
very good approximation and use the same. Approach
the same mathematics as we had for photons, the
masses, mohsen's where. The energy and the ultra
relativistic regime is the speed of light times
when these particles, which we can in the same way
recast to place in times the angular frequency. Of
these fermions. With the angular frequency
themselves are quantized by being defined in some
volume cubed that brings in the power of L..
Leading the. Allowable frequency Omega to integer
vectors. All of which are positive. And. We again
have for each of these values of the individual
romantic. To each other, energy levels, we are
here to. Degeneracy is coming from spin rather
than polarization, so the same factor, too, but a
different physical origin, the same spin as we had
for non relativistic fermions previously.
So we can begin.
Consider a large volume, a large volume else of
the integer case are well approximated by
continuous real numbers that is replacing the cube
in this momentum space with the sphere. The family
surface that we looked at yesterday, people lined
up as a quick reminder.
This picture. Correspondence going from the into
Zurich approximated those as a continuous real
parameter that we can integrate over rather than
dealing with sums,
and we can also.
Easily create and destroy neutrinos for the same
reason that we can easily create and destroy the
photons like those coming from the light. These
energies that depend only on the frequency of the
neutrinos are. Very small. So a large. A large
number of neutrinos are passing through all of us
every second, and something like a trillion
neutrinos per square inch per second is the flexin
between us passing through Boston through the
Earth.
So a huge number that is easy to change is that
change the energy, which is. What corresponds to a
small or approximately vanishing chemical
potential with that? Change in the number of
particles does not significantly change the
overall energy of the system. So the grand
economic potential that we end up with compared to
the full time economic potential that we saw last
week, are two different two changes, the negative
side both coming from the starting point of very
direct statistics as opposed to sticks. And if you
are to look back through your notes to that
equation before you'll see it does not have an
overall negative sign out front, but it does have
a relative negative sign, which is the argument of
this likability factor. One liners, an exponential
rather than one, plus the exponential. So we have
plenty of time to do through the calculation of
the internal energy and average particle number
based on.
This economic potential for massive photomontages,
just label with that Greek letter, new for
Neutrino, where we recall the setup of great
potential from now a few weeks ago, the internal
energy is just given by the derivative with
respect to the infrastructure data of that
infrastructure times, economic potential. And for
the average particle, no, we have the negative
derivative with respect to potential of the
economic potential. And then at the end of taking
that derivative, we need to set the capital
attention to zero. Which has already been done in
equation one of the six. We just have that
exponential of each Farmigo negativity rather than
the additional factor of either the new Oberti.
That we're coming for you, so you might as well
just go ahead and do those computations where the.
Derivative.
Of the the function, the detail with respect to
data is going to first with the argument of that
law into the denominator. And then go through with
the chain rule, derivative of that exponential
factor with respect to data is indicative of each
farmiga the exponential factor itself and then we
have. The overall factor of Omega squared coming
along. And we can just combine the third of mega.
From.
Combined with the additional power from the
derivative of the exponential factor and change
variables as we have for. Tax equal to our mega.
For each part of routine, so that this moment
dealmaker wielded by the ratio T over H bar to X
or X, so.
Collecting these constants, the negative signs
cancel out each bar over, see huge piles squared,
and then. People in factories of T divided by far
from. I'll make a cube and from the deal by so in
total, four of those factors, the limits of
integration remain the same through this direct
relation between variable X and if we. Multiply
through by the plus data HRO, they could divide it
by. Plus each Farmigo multiplied by one, we end up
with one over one, but rather X cubed over the
positive X.
Plus one. Which is one of those fun, no integrals
that depends on the remains of function and the
gamma function and the particular now that we have
a relative positive time in the denominator of
these integrals. All that does is bring in a
numerical factor. It depends on the power to which
this integration variable X is raised numerator a
factor of one minus one over to raise of that
power. So in this case of executed, we have one
minus one over to Cube, which is one minus an
eight, which is seven eighths. Again, before it is
three factorial, which is six. So six times seven
eighths is.
Seven times three over four, and then we remind
theater function.
For.
Argument for
is it the fourth over 90, so 90 multiplied by four
thirds gives us 120 overall factor of seven fourth
that we can then plug into the computation
underway. To find.
That overall seven, we have two factors of pie
after canceling out with the two in the
denominator, we have T to the power four and then
that one hundred twenty each cubed, C cubed. So
again,
finding the same sort of functional dependence of
the energy density that we had for the photon gas
where. The. Energy of these this gas of masses
neutrinos depends on the volume times temperature
to the power for.
And if we proceed. The similar substitution in the.
Average particle, no density. We're now taking the
same sort of derivative, restoring this factor of.
E to the. New over tea and then setting up
potential value equal to zero at the end, so.
Churning through this change of variables more
quickly, we will pick up.
Only two powers of tea over power from the two
factors of Omega squared, plus a third factor from
the Omega, the derivative itself is bringing down
a factor of beta, which is the inverse temperature,
and will eventually cancel out with that out front.
So we can cancel that out and be left with just T
over H cubed times. But it's almost that same
integral. Just now, X squared the X plus one T X.
Which follows the same pattern as we had for
the integral executed over the X plus one, we now
have one minus one or two squared is one minus a
quarter, three quarters times Gamma three, which
is two factorial or two. So three quarters times
two is three 1/2 times this irrational factor, say
three of the Roman Zeta function. So. Collecting
all that gives us.
Rehabs. There it is, so free. Zeta three T cubed
over two pi squared each four cubed C cube stone
also. As for the case of the photon, yes, the
particle number is one powered down in temperature
compared to the energy. In other words, that
energy of the neutrino gas is proportional to
the particle number times temperature, both of
which are then personal to buoyant times.
Temperature to the fourth.
And you can even. Plug in a note here, what that
constant of proportionality is where.
I have enough room up at the top of the page, all
fit on the screen at the same time. Right.
This
energy as the between a number of times we need to
end up with. Seven PI squared times over 120.
The factors of heart and see are the same and both
of the energy density and particle numbers, so
they are accounted for. We just need to cancel out
the remaining factors in the particle numbers. So
to. PI squared over three, Zyda three. So the
overall factor to consider proportionality in this
expression is going to be
seven pi to the four. Divided by one 20 over to 60
times, three is one.
Times have Monday, the function of three and then
the number times temperature.
The last step to the equation of fate for this gas
of Marcellus fermions, which looks like a good
place to. Lined up for today is to impose the
condition of chaos and entropy so that we can take
the. Derivative of the energy with respect to the
negative volume.
And just as for. The photon us.
Recalling that the energy is. One over temperature
times, the difference between the internal energy
and the. Free energy, Europe, the great economic
potential.
We again have an integral over X. Of each Farmigo.
A change of variables that brings in three powers
of T divided by far from the three factors of X
outside of the logarithm. That integral over the
logarithm is yet another. Factor that depends on
the remote Zeta function turns out to be something
like. Seven to the fourth, over three sixty, which
is seven quarters times.
Zeta for.
But we don't actually care about what that value
is, only the functional dependence proportional to
volume times T cubed is relevant. Because when we
plug that in to. This derivative. We have from the
for the energy, there is seven pipes squared to
the four. Over 120. Each part you see, Kud.
And imposing this constant neutrino entropy.
Tells us to fix T equal to some constant times the
inverse cube root of the volume. So for powers of
B to the minus, a third gives us V to the minus
four thirds multiplied by T to the plus one leaves.
Overall.
B to the minus one third.
So derivative with respect to be of some comfort,
to be for to minus the 30 counts, for the constant
entropy condition, so that derivative just brings
down a factor of minus the third cancels the
negative sign. You bring down an extra factor of B
that we can pull out front and just have all of
the house factors coming along. For the ride here
to be to the fourth from the city to the fourth to
the remaining B to the minus third, which is then
just one third of the energy of the neutrino gas
divided by volume or rearranging we have.
Equation states for Marcellus. Fermions that
follows the now familiar. Functional form of the
ideal gas law pressure times volume is one
thousand times the average internal energy related
that average internal energy to the neutrino
particle number at the top of the page. So three
times when he is five hundred forty five, the
factor of seven out of the four over Zyda, three
coming along. To give us, again, a different
numerical factor compared to both the classical.
Ideal gas law equals energy, as well as the
equation of state for the photon gas, where we had
the factor of PI for over 90 days in the three.
That was the ratio of Zyda of four over the three,
we have that same ratio of Zeta functions just
with an additional seven eighths over three
quarters, which boils down to seven six four
overstated. Three said yesterday that this ratio
was about four point nine. So multiply that by
seven. Six gives us another factor, very close to
one. So just a few percent deviation from the
classical ideal gas law for this gas is Marcellus
fermions. And that is that at least was the end of
the day, which is why I pushed to get through the
end with our immediate questions, we can take them
quickly before next class tries to get in here. I
see that we are just at the end of time and. And
not seeing any real pick up on Friday was just a
bit of additional detail about how to accommodate
a low but nonzero temperature in that non
relativistic from Yungas going beyond the
approximation of the FERME function is a step
function. So see you back for that. To wrap up the
part of first part of this term. Take. The rest of
you there.