All right, might as well get underway. Welcome
back to the last quarter of the term for
statistical physics.  We will cover here the final
major topic of the course, going into interacting
systems and the new phenomena that can enable. But
first, let's put up the usual six digit code for
today before I forget about that. It is six two, three two,
six zero.
Before diving into the new stuff, since it's been a
while since we have last gone through
statistical physics, let's do a bit of recap of
what we've seen up to now and what remains as well
as some of the. Majestical notices that. Piled up
during the spring break. So today is.
The 25th of April.
We both in there and.
Terms of some just legal matters, the.
First homework assignment was. Returnability in
the last week or two, you mentioned that there was,
again, like the first part of the computer project,
a fairly broad distribution of marks. The average
was around sixty eight percent, with the standard
deviation around 16 percent. And that's roughly
what I was aiming for by making that number more
challenging than, say, the exam would be. So don't
be discouraged if you. I ended up with a
percentage that seems low on the face value, since
there is that average and standard deviation to
take into account the. Next step, though, is the
final homework that also appeared last week and is
due next week, so Thursday, the 5th of May go 10
days is going out to that. And normally it might
take a look at that in the tutorial on Friday,
since there was no tutorial last Friday. We can
just skim through the questions quickly here, make
sure they all clear and see if there are any
immediate questions about them. And just to get
underway with that, the first question we have is
actually picking up from one of the tutorials
before the spring break in at the last one. But a
couple of weeks before looking when we looked at.
Idealized sort of Namik cycles, describing
internal combustion engines, in particular
comparing the auto cycle for a petrol engine to
this diesel cycle, the diesel engine in question
is one that came up in that tutorial but was not
answered. Your chance to answer yourself. What is
the efficiency of this diesel cycle and how does
that compare to the efficiency of the auto cycle
for a internal combustion engine?
Second question also is not too dissimilar to the.
The mixing entropy that we looked at in another of
the tutorials here, instead of looking at what
happens upon mixing two distinct gases. And what
you just consider the mixture from the outset with
the new ingredient, that the gases now have
different properties beyond their cover that can
be distinguished by their wavelength. Which leads
to some interesting relations that could arise
among the standard observables that we impute for
an ideal gas's of the sort compared to. The two
separate gases of each of those particles
individually, if the other species were absent.
Quickly running through the third of four problems
here, dealing with the economic ensemble,
particularly the sagacity and expansion that. Came
up in the lectures relating that grant model
competition functioned to an infinite series of
economic competition functions. And deriving some
relations between observables or the Grand Canal,
it's not over, the number fluctuate and
derivatives of the Grand Canal, the potential of
the Landauer free energy with respect to that from
gas, it just may be a good opportunity to
highlight the point of this final relation that we
will be able to derive in this way, where if we
look at the relative fluctuations in that average
particle number compared to the total number of
particles, much like we saw in the case of
diffusion in the first year, we're back in
February, those relative fluctuations vanish as
the number of particles increases. In this case,
the average particle number going to infinity,
something called the thermodynamic limit. That has
come up briefly in the lecture notes and will come
up again this week. So what this means is that
when an average particle is large, the relative
fluctuations about it are vanishingly small and it
can be approximated as simply the constant
particle number, which is the distinction between
the grand, canonical and canonical examples. In
other words, the pragmatical ensemble system
described by the Great American ensemble
effectively reduces to economical system with a
fixed number of particles, one that picks up the
particles. It's large. So that is a worthwhile
relation to drive this case for maximum the and
then the final question focuses on the
magnetization, which we will introduce possibly
today. More likely tomorrow will get for the.
Later in the week here, we're still looking at not
interacting system of spitters.
So not reading him the bulk of the new information
that's coming up this week with interactive
systems, but with the wrinkle that each of these
degrees of freedom as a value continuously in the
range of minus one to one, rather than just taking
those two extreme values, that's a difference
compared to the knowledge and expense systems that
we consider all the way back in units two and
three. And the focus of this question is, Danto,
given the set, compute the economic competition,
function magnetization and look at the limits of
how that behaves at high and low temperatures for
a fixed externalising field strength gauge.
So that's just a quick look through that final
assignment due next week at the immediate points
of confusion or concern about it.
And that here know there is time for those to come
up if they occur to you later on and move on to
the next. Logistical matters still, which is that
final exam, the schedule for those was released
and for this module, it is a one hour personal
exam scheduled for Wednesday afternoon at two
thirty p.m. on the 1st of June. So toward the end
of the assessment period and being held in the
sports center, which came as a surprise to me
because there were. Rooms for exams in that sports
center. I'll try to track down the specific
location so I can be sure to find it about leave
you. Even on your own on that first of June? And
to provide some more resources for that exam
preparation on the Canada site for the module,
I've uploaded a couple of sample exams and also
linked to the past exams repository, which is
fairly modest for this module on 20 20 was the
very first time this module ran. And this that
makes this year the very first time it was not
disrupted by at least so far, so that 20 20 exam
is in the repository. Twenty twenty one was an
unusual year in terms of exams and assessments. As
you know, that is the final exam for twenty twenty
one is going to be two samples that are uploaded
to the bottom of this page on campus where right
now it's just the sets of problems for you to look
at and consider and get a feeling for the scale
and style of the exam. And at some point today,
I'll upload modules, moral solutions to accompany
these postings. Which we can probably discuss
before the end of. The teaching at. Weeks going
forward.
So.
That those are the main logistic issues for today,
though maybe I can start to.
Look ahead to what is coming up and mentioned that
compared to twenty twenty the first year, we had a
ordinary run of this module, we are now two hours
ahead in terms of covering this year, which gives
opportunities for. A few more supplements to be
added, possibly on things like booze. It's a
conversation little Gaspé transitions or spin
classes that receive to be recognized by the Nobel
Prize last year. So as we go forward over the next
few weeks, there will be less of a gap between the
release of the lecture notes and lectures
themselves as I try to figure out what topics will
fit nicely in terms of time and theme. With what
we are going over and the time that remains, which
I guess brings us to. The recap of where we have
been and the foundation that will now be building
on. And it's worth probably. Briefly going back
all the way to. Beginning.
Laila. The foundation of probability theory in
terms of probability spaces that consider
measurements performed on experiments that are
then defining outcomes, sets of those all possible
outcomes of these experiments that are then assign
probabilities and the particular realization of
statistical samples as the probability spaces that
correspond to a collection of particles that are
evolving in time and probabilistically adopting
different possible microstates as they as time
goes on and these particles are left free to do
their thing.
And we have looked at. Three distinct statistical
examples, so.
Rather than writing anything here, might as well
zoom out to. The big picture contrasting these
three statistical samples of the memorable way to
keep track of how they differ, both in terms of
the constraints that are imposed in each of these
samples and what those constraints mean in
practice.
So in the microeconomic ensemble, we directly
apply the conservation of energy, as well as the
conservation of the number of degrees of freedom,
particleboard, which means that we are considering
a system that is completely isolated from the rest
of the universe. There's no way for any particles
to be exchanged within the system or no way for
energy to flow into or out of the system. Whereas
with the Canaletto ensemble, that's more
realistically matches out of the sorts of
experiments that you've done.
In. Physics and. Science, more broadly, we still
preserve the number of particles and allow those
to freely come and go, but we do allow energy to
be exchanged between the system and its
surroundings so that we can do things like look at
it and measure it and manipulate it. And we set up
in place of that constraint on the energy. The
temperature is now in quantity fixed and the
economical framework by.
Demanding that the system we're interested in is
in thermal contact with the large external keypad
for thermal reservoir with which energy can freely
be exchanged. And that is large enough to fix the
overall temperature of the system, went through a
couple to the heat and the canonical ensemble
takes this to the logical conclusion, along with
particle number and energy, to fluctuate with the
large external reservoir. Now, being a particle
reservoir with which the system can exchange both
particles and energy. Now, keep it fixed, in
addition to the temperature, the chemical
potential that. Effectively describes the flow of
these particles from the high density to really
secluded city.
So.
Over the weeks, we have not only. Defiant,
introduced. Those micro, canonical, canonical
examples, but in all three cases. We have imposed
thermodynamic equilibrium.
By maximizing the entropy of the system, they see
that back in writing is at least plausibly legible.
Maximizing the entropy of these systems, being
consistent with the second law of thermodynamics,
that the entropy is not decreasing, pollution
increasing
led us to be economical. The graphic novel, the
case, the precision function.
And the corresponding free energy or potential as
the fundamental starting points for analysis of
systems governed by the use of probability spaces,
and we've seen particular examples of applications
of the canonical ensemble to the classical ideal
gaseous.
Of the swords appearing in question two of the
biggest homework assignments as well as.
Thermodynamic cycles.
So the question, what addresses and the canonical
case?
The corresponding quantum ideal gas is.
Where you have two types of quantum particles goes
up to four each with their own distinct behavior.
So we have gone through quite a bit so far, but
all of it has been considering systems of
particles or degrees of freedom that don't
interact with each other. As always, precise
mathematical way we get into today and tomorrow
defining what it means for particles to be
interacting or not attracting. And as we introduce
interactions. And you will find that systems
become more complicated, but also allow a broader
range of more realistic behaviors to be modeled,
and we will do so building on all of these.
Concepts, tools and techniques that we derived
prior to the spring break, and as I understand,
this is a extended introduction to getting back
into the course of stuff like one less thing that
as we went through. All of the topics so far, if
any of those sounded unfamiliar and you had a hard
time recalling what the point was, what the
details were, I set up a way for you to flag those
you can do anonymously, just filling in a response
to these polls everywhere, activities that I'll
leave potentially and definitely see if there are
asynchronous concerns. Outside of class meetings
that can then be addressed as we go forward, for
instance, in tutorials, so I will continue to say,
are there? Any questions in the media, questions
about the roadmap that is taking us to the point
that we are now?
Typically, there are not, and that poll everywhere
provides a way for any questions that do come up
at any time to be symptoms, to be quickly and
easily, rather than putting you on the spot here
in that.
So the.
Zoo is adequate to move on to those long term
message systems. Where?
There's even a bit more here about the recap in.
Looking at some of the specific physical systems
that we found were very well modeled by not
interacting systems in the last tutorial before
the spring break, we put that. The heat capacity
is accelerating, so fantastic agreement between
our calculations coming from the well, coming from
the Dubai theory of Soldz, but also totals to
those capacities, as well as the blank spectrum
for solar radiation and the cosmic microwave
background. There are. So those are examples,
we're not interacting systems. And tell us a great
deal about what is going on in physics, but there
is, of course, much more that can go on and cannot
be captured by these monitoring systems. And just
as a bit of general motivation, you talk a bit
about phase transitions. As. Phenomena that
typically are not captured by not the tracking
systems, the biggest transitions, as you probably
appreciate, occur in a very wide range of
circumstances, but every day and extreme and are
exactly the type of physical phenomenon that we
want to mathematically analyze and describe using
statistical physics.
What they amount to is when we take the same
system, the same set of stuff, and depending on
the control parameters, the conditions in which
the system exists, it's temperature pressure, the
overall large scale system exhibits vastly
different behaviors. So in an everyday situation,
we can think about boiling the kettle to force
liquid water, to transition to steam. Both
collections of EU molecules behaving in a
qualitatively different ways, as well as actually
freezing liquid water through solid ice is another
phase transition of this sort. Maybe more exotic
example that. Maybe less familiar, but some of you
might have heard of the courtroom on plasma,
that's. Is the phase in which the matter in the
universe existed for the first few microseconds
following the Big Bang until the universe crumbled
enough for these quarks gluons to transition into
the protons and neutrons, particles that we had
and everything else are made out of today.
Maybe to split the difference between that every
day and extreme. A flag. An interesting. He's a
particularly interesting phase transition that
occurs in type of materials, not the type of stuff
that we work with every day, are things that can
easily be produced and played with in a physics
lab. That are based on graphic and get something.
Exotic, but in the news, so it's a remarkable
material that consists of. A single atom thick
sheet of carbon atoms that are made in the form of
a hexagonal or honeycomb structure. You get an
idea of what that is. This picture out here shows
two large hexagons or honeycomb cells. Overlap on
top of each other in such a way that the smaller
unit hexagons that they're built out of overlap
into.
Certain numbers of cells zoom in a bit here, you
can see there are that's maximum zoom or hexagons
within hexagons in the system of two layers of the
single atom, thick graphene placed on top of each
other and motion very slightly by the small angle
theta that is around. One degree, but one degree,
I think, is the. Next degree with the next
significant figure in that theater, what was
discovered just a few years ago was that in this
situation where two layers of graphene are stacked
in twisted by just that small amount. The overall,
while their system transitions from the normal
electrical insulator phase, the Graffin exists
where it's sort of like wood, it doesn't really
allow electrical parents to flow naturally turns
into an electrical superconductor where electrical
currents are able to flow without encountering any
resistance, which is to say without producing any
heat from the air flow and as a consequence,
without using any energy to the production of
wasted. So superconductivity is. A remarkable
phase of conducting materials discovered a little
over a century ago. That's. For reasons I.
Although we're talking about generally only occurs
at very low temperatures in this case of twisted
by their grapheme, the temperature below two
Heldon, so about minus three hundred degrees
Celsius. Now, numbers. And for decades now,
there's been a worldwide push to. Find these sorts
of novel materials that exhibit superconductivity
at higher temperatures, ideally room temperatures
that don't require a great degree of cooling,
which would allow if such materials could be
discovered or design and we were able to build
electronics or power networks out of it. You can
no longer lose large amounts of energy to the
production of waste, to the energy efficiency of
all technology would increase dramatically.
Superconductivity that can also mentioned is a key
feature of a lot of quantum devices that are
employed in quantum computing precisely because
none of this waste is produced, that leads to the
delicate quantum superposition. Being destroyed in
those quantum computers, so the irrelevant phase
transition in this situation. Is that from an
electrical insulator to a superconductor allowing
electrical current either not to flow or to flow
without resistance? And this example of the phase
transition along with those others, like water and
plasma discussed, have to do with the interactions
between the degrees of freedom in the system.
It is, in fact, the. The way in which the two
sheets of hexagonal lettuces align to form larger
hexagons that allow more powerful interactions to
be introduced into these systems between that
stupid phase transition. That's a bit of a
digression into physics that isn't really relevant
for what we're going to be doing here now. And of
course, I just couldn't resist chatting up some of
that fun stuff. This is all motivation for
investigating phase transitions. And as usual, we
will introduce this sort of thing by going back to
our simplest physical system, one of these systems
that we have already considered. Back when they
were not interacting to introduce things like
entropy and temperature, the canonical example. So
as a more detailed recap and reminder of that
particular system in the not interacting case. The
internal energy for a given microstates labor
supply that is determined by the orientation of
some fixed number of spins. Is just the product of
each of those orientations with an external
magnetic field.
Strength parametrized with this constant variable
pitch that we always take to be positive. And the.
The end here represents the orientation of the
spin of the little and spin, how to be big and
total that takes only one of two possible balance
of the spin is a line parallel to that magnetic
field. Then this estimate equals one and the
energy gets a contribution of negative each
lowering it. If the spin is a. parallel to the
field, then it is to give you the minus one and
the energy gets a positive contribution plus age.
So we saw back in June three that the ground state
of the system, the macro state with minimal energy,
is the one in which all of the spins are aligned
parallel to the field. So there the sun is just
the sun over and factors of one. And the total
energy of that ground state is the negative of the
total number of spins times the external magnetic
field.
So we use this, the tracking system as a
playground to explore the physics of information
in the way that the entropy and internal energy
differ with the temperature, depending on whether
or not the spins were distinguishable or
indistinguishable. At least for this unit, the
focus only on the distinguishable case where all
of these spins are embedded in a fixed lattice. In
particular, we'll consider just simple cubic
lattices, at least from. Said the lectures, there
are other lattice structures that will be
interesting to discuss in the tutorial, and we
also go beyond the earlier work by allowing these
lattices to be multi-dimensional. So back in two
and three, the latter be considered in this
external field of speech, just some number of
spins of the line, either up or down the line or
into alignment with the magnetic field where the
position of each spin in this one dimensional
lattice.
System of spin is arranged line.
Just allows us to leave Alaska and say, guess what
we did off there in this particular microstates
that I've drawn here, it's been Escalon has you
plus one mile spense estate has value minus one.
And it's not too hard to repeat this same sort of.
Visualization for. A two dimensional scan system
gets progressively harder as we consider higher
and higher dimensions. There again, with that same.
Fix external Magnetic Fields Beach, we have a two
dimensional array of spins, a line either parallel
to the magnetic field. So the first state and the
fourth row, this micro state has the value of plus
one. The fourth spin in the first row has a value
minus one aligned against that magnetic field and.
While we will focus on. That is one or two or
three dimensions spins arranged in a line, on a
sheet or in a volume, mathematically, the
construction of used spin systems works just as
well for any integer, no dimensions, one or above.
And it will be. We will see you useful context in
which thinking of abstract mathematical.
Systems in higher numbers, interventions of the
three that we operate in will be useful to gain
insight into the calculations and determining.
And so, Tim.
Define that more vigorously, more mathematically,
what we mean when we say that these systems are
not interacting, we can. No, first, that the
overall internal energy or the systems we consider
so far factories into a simple sum of
contributions, so individual energies for each
individual degree of freedom in the system. And
this is at least an aspect of the overall
factorization that we have seen in our previous
treatment, where we saw, for instance, that
considering these storm systems, we could analyze
them by computing the single particle partition
function, in this case, a single spin that points
either up or down and then obtaining the overall
importance for protection function, for instance,
in this equation, for one, just by taking that
product of identical independent single particle
partition functions to the incredible production
function that I could be able to see. And that's
just the power of that single particle partition
function in this case, two times the hyperbolic
cosine of that magnetic field divided by
temperature.
Now, this is an aspect of factorization,
factorization is a bit more subtle. That just
being able to write the overall internal energy as
a sum of contributions from different degrees of
freedom. There is a stronger condition that needs
to be satisfied in order to guarantee
factorization or guarantee prevalently that the
system is not interacting. Which considers what
happens to that internal energy when just one of
the degrees of freedom is changed. So call that
the degree your freedom in serving the subsequent
I, as you refer to, different microstates. And
suppose we make some change to this particular
degree of freedom. That's produces some change in
the overall energy of the system. Delta, a subject.
The system is not interacting if and only if. The
change in internal energy for any arbitrary degree
of freedom turns out to be independent of all the
other degrees of freedom. Labeled by nightfall
Tuesday. So part of the reason for reviewing the
track and speed system in so much detail here is
to demonstrate that this definition makes sense
and that we do indeed recover, confirm that under
this definition, the indistinguishable speeds that
we've been considering are, in fact.
Not attracted, so the only possible change that we
can make to any of these degrees of freedom is to
negate its value, which corresponds to slipping
its orientation with respect to that external
magnetic field. If we pick a degree of freedom
that happens to be split up along with the
magnetic field, we flip it to spin down negative
for Angelyne and vice versa so we can consider
what happens to the internal energy. Upon.
Performing that sort of spiritual navigation of
the degree of freedom for an arbitrary still in
the system. So what we can do starting from that
internal energy.
We wrote down on the previous page is pick out
from that song over all and spins the spin that we
will be flipping. And then what remains in the
song is all those other degrees of freedom, Candy,
that are not equal to Jay.
So when we put that spin, that's picks up a
negative sign and nothing else happens to the
other spins. We then take the difference between
the new internal energy after that speech and the
starting points that we wrote down here, can you
see that Delta is associated with Arbitraging? So
those sums canceling the difference in the left
with just two times, eight times the original
value of that spin. As subject, which has to be
the. Independent of all. The.
Other degrees of freedom that been with Kate J.
Which
checks out with.
Our claim that this is a not a tracking system by
the more formal definition that we now have.
So any questions about that were the build up to.
To this definition of what it means for the system
to be interacting or not.
Because the next step is to.
Make things a bit more interesting by changing how
the internal energy of our system depends on the
degrees of freedom. So really, this is a different
spin system where the internal energy has, in
addition to the interaction or the contributions
of the energy from each of these spins coupled to
that external with added fuel, we have a second
term, the internal energy A. Contribution to the
internal energy that depends on the product of two
spins, SMG Times, that's OK. We're the sum here.
Is being taken over.
AU pairs of nearest neighbor spins in the lattice,
so the Haitian being defined here is that Jaquet
in parentheses are picking out all sight, all J
and K that are next to each other in any one of
the. The dimensions that we are operating at, just
as a quick illustration of this, we look at a 2D
lattice representing the Spinosaurus points rather
than upward of Delaporte arrows. The nearest
neighbors of this size, circled in blue,
correspond to those four sites circled in red,
either left or right of it in one dimension or
above or below it in that second dimension.
Similarly, for all the higher dimensions that we
might consider.
So now in this case, we can. Do the same exercise,
computing the change in the internal energy of
flipping a student with this new expression for
the internal energy. The approach is the same with.
We write the internal energy, pulling out the
arbitrary spin we're going to flip so from the
first term. We can pull out of jail and there will
be some number of terms in this, some. For all the
spins that are in. The nearest neighbor cares,
Jake, for this fixed J this SJT gets multiplied by
České, and then there are all of the other two
spin combinations that don't involve our spin of
interest. OK, so this is a sum over nearest
neighbor pairs this little M and K that do not
contain J. That same product of spin time spin
came.
And then the same sort of. External magnetic field
terms that we had before, minus stage times
yesterday, plus some of all that are not.
So I'm flipping the spin, S.J making the change
that I was her degree of freedom, the sign of this
first term. Flips to become positive. Back in. N
never pairs of jeans. Nothing happens to the
second term. Something over here, it appears, that
do not include spenger.
In the thick of a negative sign. On spenger
multiplied by the magnetic field. But not. The.
Other degrees of freedom. So taking the difference
here.
Those two terms that don't involve Jay Hawkins and
Delta, a subject that comes out, is to get a
factor of two times the spenger now multiply not
only by age, but by. There's some barricade the
nearest neighbor appears to have escaped. So.
Hopefully, there are no objections to that
calculation. We can see that. In contrast to the
not tracking system, this new internal energy.
Produces a. Changing energy upon changing what the
degrees of freedom that depend on other degrees of
freedom. So this Delta, Ajay.
Now depends. These this.
With Kay. Going to change. So this is. Now
contracting. System, in contrast to the simpler
one that we've been setting up to battle.
Rather than. Going on to introduce some more
terminology about the underlying structure of
these systems,
best to stop here by.
Just reiterating that we have now confirmed that
this new spin system with an internal energy that
depends on products of substance, in addition to
the product of a speed with that external magnetic
field, does provide us with an interacting system.
And after a overnight break tomorrow morning, we
can look forward to starting to do more
interesting things. With this simple interacting
system, so. Unless there are questions before we
break for the evening, I will forward to seeing
you back in the other room tomorrow morning at.
When?