All right, welcome back to Friday afternoon.  As
a reminder before I forget, the University will be closed for
the bank holiday on Monday. So after this, I'll see
you again in the other room Tuesday morning.
Another thing I don't want to forget is the six-digit code for
this afternoon: one three, five five, zero zero.
And then I have three things planned that we could
have some fun with this afternoon.  But of course,
this is also your opportunity to bring up any
issues or questions or concerns about what's been
going on in the course that you may want to discuss
more detail, so before I dive into what I have
planned, let's see if there's any
issues you want to raise or questions to ask.
And it may well be that some of the questions on
your mind are concerned with the first topic at
about 4:00 today, which was just a few quick
comments on generic feedback on the solutions,
that homework that came back to you over the edge
of the break. Where we got mentioned on Monday
that the markets were generally reasonable average.
Sixty nine, plus or minus 16 is a standard
deviation. And no one question that really stood
out as particularly challenging or not. The. On
the whole, the. Most marks came from this first
question about the.
Drift and diffusion of oil droplets model, as they
would do in a random walk. And. Here to the. The
key step was just this change of variables.
To something that depends all the time that the
war in Iraq is progressing and this is the key
because it makes the. Could you grab the
probability distribution symmetric in you so
fucking you divide us, you.
Is asymmetry of the probability distribution,
which is not the case for the distribution and the
function of X, precisely Duse that on. So most
folks were able to realize that they wanted to
account for the whole integral over all possible
positions of this random walk, give the one
hundred percent probability for locating the oil
in question and then break that up into the error
function region around symmetric around zero.
Along with the remainder we are actually
interested in.
And that cemetery is only possible to identify
after making that kind of pendant change of
variables after which the solution. Boils down to
solving a quadratic equation there, Ali, or by
hand.
Question two was the. One, that.
People seem to find it easy to sell the whole
latest America works, even though there was a bit
of a funny business with the.
The final bit about what happens when the systems
with positive and negative temperature are brought
into verbal contact and be able to exchange energy,
which reminds me that I actually set up a little
illustration of this beyond what went into the
solutions. I can actually recover a few seconds.
On here.
So the.
This is interesting because I have definitely
opened this up recently that are showing up here.
Did you hear this negative temperature?
Open and.
Looking at the expressions in in the first two
parts of this problem where the entropy is the.
Just difference between the full and and minus
whatever fraction are in the positive energy US
state. Which of these degrees of freedom have that
not zero energy absolom so that. That number is
known as X. We can put in any arbitrary large
numbers for the total number of degrees of freedom.
And as we've seen before, this entropy has
maximized.
Right in the middle, when half of the degrees of
freedom are in one of the two possible. Energy
levels and the other half are the other one, but
of course, this. Maximum is interesting because it
means that the slope is zero and that slope is the
inverse temperature. So here's the derivative. So
Epsilon over t dimensionless units that crosses
zero rates at the point where the entropy is
maximized. Which corresponds to. As most people
found the temperature that diverges at that same
point, the inverse of this derivative.
Now, the connection that this has to the final
part of the question. Has to do with the.
Connection between the energy and temperature. So
the question was phrased a little baby is what
happens when systems of positive and negative
temperature are brought into trouble contact. So
looking at this part, that's one system on the
left, half of the frame. No contact with the
system on the right half. And if you. Look back at
the calculation done in unit to see that the
energy would kind of flow from the system with
more energy on the right half of this grid system,
with less energy on the left half. Which has.
Somewhat counter intuitive impact on the
temperature itself, so as the system that has
negative temperature and the right half gives up
energy to the other system, it moves closer toward
those that midpoints and therefore picks up a more
negative temperature. Whereas the other system
that is giving energy, the positive temperature is
moving to a higher temperature at the same time to
be temperature. So the two systems are actually
moving further apart as they're brought into
contact is becoming increasingly positive
temperature, the other increasingly negative,
which did a few folks up who based this on sort of.
Usual intuition that if you have two systems with
different temperatures and the thermal contact
that will try to approach the same temperature
rather than wandering off to temperatures further
and further apart. So that is another way that
these negative temperatures coming from the
canonical ensemble are counterintuitive and in
fact, more generally to the convention here. You
can prove that. Temperatures only 10 to
equilibrated between two such systems if the heat
capacity is always positive. That heat capacity
being the derivative of the energy with respect to
temperature.
So that is a even though this question what is? So
hard for most folks. There are interesting
connections that are more broadly.
And question three is mostly calculational, the
only place where. Folks are sometimes in danger of
getting tripped up was in the small second part of
it, asking essentially what the result means in
terms. So when we find the heat capacity is
proportional to the square of these fluctuations,
what does that mean for the microwave energy use,
which requires some care to distinguish between
was microwave energy supply rather than the energy
expectation value that sums over all possible
microstates with the probability distribution. And
some folks try to comment on. In this part of the
question, so rather than. Pulling out the
microwave energy and seeing what could be said
about it
was tempting to just say that if. Derivative of
the expectation value. And if it was, then.
You are tempted to say that this means that the
energy expectation value must be independent of
temperature, which.
Is not always true because we are considering just
a single point with a capacity advantage, rather
than requiring requiring that it be zero for all
temperatures and is also focusing on the wrong.
Variable, there's a big difference between that
expectation value and the individual state energy
use that we are able to. Determined must be. All
the same for every microstates in the system, but
not necessarily the same for different
temperatures.
That's.
Quickly, Mark, in there,
similarly with regard on the final question, which
was a lot of fairly straightforward. Computations
and approximations, the trickiest aspect of this
is the high temperature expansion. There are.
Nontrivial series expansions to keep track of
where. In particular, in this actually in the
expansion of this ratio, one over one minus the
expense of minus X. It's sometimes tempting to.
Expand the denominator there just to be order in X
that you think you want to end up with the apple,
so to get.
The leading coefficient here, I expect to be the
leading coefficient that doesn't cancel the
dominator, but as we can see from Converse's, the
expression of the exponential expansion of this
geometric series actually have to keep terms to
execute power and the denominator in order to end
up with something that is accurate only to order X.
And similarly, what's the other an exponential
factor in that ratio is brought in, it has to be
expanded to.
Order. Peter Square, which is the square variable
in order to end up with something in the end, that
is order Batel just due to the cancellations that
are coming out from enumerator and laminator, so.
Those are the sort of highlights of each of the
four questions, the. The main issues are the
better connections to interesting aspects of
physical physics there. Any further questions that
we want to follow up on about
that first homework assignment?
Since I'm not seeing any, I will move on to your
second. Third piece is the more fun, somewhat more
fun, the two year olds have been out of the core
content for the module.
Interesting and fun to think about and do some
calculations with, in particular in. This tutorial
problem here, which I just put on the Web site. A
few minutes before we started this afternoon, I've.
Got a bit of background material about different
forms of nanostructures and why they matter go
through that, it's a brief presentation of both
some conceptual questions that we'll get through
this afternoon and then a more challenging
calculational question, which was actually what I
was thinking about putting on the second homework
assignment, but decided it would be a bit to mean
someone just talk about it this week and we
actually expect to leave it for you to be able to
think about over the holiday in the coming week.
So.
In the work that we've done so far this week of
the easy model and will continue doing, we've
focused just on. That model to find out what same
dimensions that were shown in the left side of
this figure here, but of course, there is a large
number of different possibilities for the lack of
structure that we have where we can define these
sorts of interactive systems, a lot of which bring
in.
Important information coming not from the form of
the interaction itself or from the degrees of
freedom, but how they are organized both in
physical experiments as well as more abstract
mathematical considerations. So the little ladies
here, for instance, is the political class that
was mentioned in passing on Monday that. Tom is
the latest, the graphene is far better than
essentially the reason graphene has some
remarkable
properties, both electronic and structural, is
that it consists of this very regular lattice of
storage, which we can distinguish from the the
square lattice in a few ways. The simplest is by
looking at how many various neighbors in a given
site house for the square lattice. We've seen that
a given site has. For years, neighbors to
symbolized to two times the nearest neighbors
delimiters. Can easily see here for this two
dimensional optical lattice at any given site as
not four, but three nearest neighbors, which. Also
turns out to be related to the dimensionality of
the system, the coordination number that I'm
describing here, which is just a fancy term for
the nearest neighbor sites that any given site has,
as always, with periodic battery conditions for
this honeycomb structure that.
Coordination number is the plus one in these
dimensions. Where higher dimensional
generalizations of. How do you come last if you
can wrap your head around how to visualize those,
which I have a difficulty with our doing this
hyperthyroid analysis and show up in mostly
theoretical work, but we're. And then.
In that area, so this nikolaidis is relevant for
Graffy, the reason it has such tensile strength,
conductivity and so on. In investigations of. High
temperature superconductivity, so trying to
manufacture materials that superconductor at a
higher temperature that lead to Kelvin, where the
twisted by the graphene system has its
superconducting phase transition.
Decades of work in physics labs all over the world
have tried to design and manufacture materials
that undergo that sort of superconducting phase
transition at the highest possible temperature,
trying to get close to room temperature of 300
degrees so that we can burn electronics and
electrical systems without losing any energy to
waste heat. I had. All sorts of language, lattices,
and these three dimensional materials played key
roles, and in that process, just as a quick
illustration of the will force me to zoom out a
bit.
This is.
It was from that. Wikipedia is showing a class of
superconducting materials.
To times where there are different options of
exactly which atoms get inserted into these
complicated layered structures.
Which depending on how exactly. The.
At the time the species are chosen and what
percentage of them are selected. So the process
that is probably shouldn't get distracted by
talking about the critical temperature for
superconductivity and materials of this sort can
be pushed all the way up to around 50 Kelvin, one
sixth of the way from two Kelvin superconductivity,
trusted by the graphene.
On the way to three hundred Kelvin room
temperature, this is sort of the state of the art
and ordinary pressures where you can see that in
addition to the complicated connections between
these different species that allow the electrons
to flow without any resistance at low temperatures,
there's also a larger scale superstructure between
the. Alternating layers of the system, the
protective layer to the Clintonian layer down at
the bottom. So that's just a bit of practical
application to motivate considering some of these
different structures. The third one here just
finished going through that list.
Is probably trying to get us motivated by the
trials that you can see out there where any given
site now has a coordination number of six.
Which is twice the coordination of the political
homeless and essentially can be obtained from the
hurricane. Lettuce by filling in the sensors of
each cell.
Like still, as an illustration filling in, that
hexagon produces triangles and doubles the
coordination number and. And as always, there are
higher dimensional generalizations, all this is a
star lattices where the body centered Cubitt was
drawn. Here is the simplest example, moving up
from two to three dimensions. Using some different
colors to. Highlight the simple Kubic lattice that
is embedded. Within the body center that Cuban is,
where if you go through and count the number of
links connecting any of these sites to all of
their dearest neighbors, you will reproduce that
same. Two times B plus one, where three quarters
of the age she's at that level for that central
purple sides can give all the sites that it is
connected to. That is the purple site is sitting
in the center of the body of a simple tube defined
by those eight, which is that terminology used by
synergy devices come from. And before diving into
work for you to do, I'll just mentioned that this
coordination number is a characteristic of all of
these different matter structures, but it's not a
unique characteristic. You can have different
lattices with the same coordination number, which
is I had included this. Type of a structure here,
which also has information number for the same as
the square lattice, obviously a. Different
distribution of. Use for your state was given
different interactions and. You get a different
visual appearance, so. With that little bit of
time spent, time, day.
Best trendspotting, that excursion, we're going to
think about what happens to the easing model if we
define it on these lattices, which is to say that
the nearest neighbor is Shakila, that we some over
is now given by some by the structural design
beyond the simple human case that we've been
considering in the lectures.
What makes this especially interesting is that we
generalize it is immoral to have a tunable
parameter controlling the shrimp of distracting
term, so. The energy is given by the somewhat of a
task of our nearest neighbor take scale by this
confidence factor, which whenever GAO is positive,
it's pretty trivial just to scale things through a
redefinition of what we mean by spin and get
exactly the same physics as the GAO equals one
case that we've been considering.
But some different things happen if Jay becomes
Negatus and three pairs of alliance teams
contribute to a positive energy rather than
negative energy that we've been considering. So
just a few minutes. And possibly, possibly for
five minutes to consider a couple of conceptual
questions just about this set up with reference to
the very simple lattice structures, square
honeycomb triangular that don't quite fit on the
screen at the same time.
The. First question is all six of these cases, the
three letter structures and the two choices for.
The interactions from the side of the interaction
strength.
What is the Granite State, the state of energy,
possibly multiple different states in each of
those cases and building recall, that means you
have a sense of what the state is, what is or is
there or a parameter that could distinguish the
ground states from the disorder, microstates that
we generally expect to dominate the system at high
temperatures. So this is the answers to these
questions are. The starting point to consider if
there is a. If there exists two different places
and if so, whether there is a true face transition
between them, so
a few minutes to think about that and feel free to
shout out if. Any of the. Set up or the point of
this question is not clear.
But as well as the recording of that. Yes, will
help if I presume that require a limit and.
I'm guessing there will be no objections if I
claim that. In the case of a positive job, grouses
that you have found, at least conceptually, are
the same as the ones that we looked at, a class of
30 square Latisse with a positive J equals one is
exactly what we considered a class immigrant
status, where all the spins aligned in the same
direction.
Particularly in the case where we consider the
zero field limits, there's no distinction between
all the spin to the top or plus one and all of
them pointed down minus minus one. That's also the
same case for any of these three lattice
structures to generate round stakes in all three
cases.
With all spins aligned in the same direction.
What about the case of the negative interaction
strengths, which are less than zero? I. Claimed
was qualitatively different than that.
Any ideas what the ground states could look like,
say, of the square, like this one that we're most
familiar with so far from the easy model work
lecture's?
Perhaps we could start answering that question by
speaking about what happen to the. Ground states,
in the case of positive that we just discussed, so
this is visible. Florida was big. So you now have
the energy. We say that is minus one to the value.
It is
almost ubiquitous. All the students on both sides
of the border, states that we saw in class for all
the spin's are alive. All these products, SJS, are
just plus minus one squared.
So that the energy is more than being. Negative.
Two times as good times, the number of sites is
the number of links to elections, which is
possible to win. So a very large. Value for the
energy and in fact, the maximum possible energy
that we can have out of the sign of the
interaction term and the energy has been reversed.
So are there any states that. Could produce a
lower energy that us closer toward the ground
states. And it's not that. So if we. Will be here
once big problems come down. So rather than being
worried, whether it's the one that just pushed
aside there and brings energy down by two units,
it removes one unit from the positive amount and
the unit to the negative column.
Starting from this basis, we can essentially
generalize and say that we get a reduction of the
energy from having these two storms opposite to
each other, that a further reduction by having
spent considerable time there, comes along next to
it and similarly in the end. So there is a pattern
developing up and down since. That we can continue
in the other direction, so if that comes up, then
maybe that's then used as a negative contribution
to the energy from that link between them. So this
guy wants to be part of a negative contribution to
that one, as well as a negative contribution from
the vertical and so on last.
So that is. The overall structure of the ground
states for this case of a negative interaction
strikes on the simple tube ubiquitous. And in
terms of terminology, this is described as an anti
thermogenic.
Siskin.
Performs.
So the ferromagnetic is something we saw briefly
in the lecture. What's the motivation for let's
use them to consider developing this easy model?
Well. The material has a large and lasting
magnetic dipole, so the sphere of magnets become
magnets at low temperature when all of their
magnetic dipoles from the constituent molecules
align in the same direction so that aligned ground
states resolve for. Positive coupling both in
lecture and just now is called the fellow in the
States. This one where is a regular pattern of
Pantelion and particles corresponding to
interactions with the opposite side is a fancy
like system. So we can appreciate that overall
position, but there is. Regular array of
oppositely oriented particles is just going to be
exactly zero in this great state, which is the
same magnetization that we get at the high
temperature phase. But on the other hand, there is.
A certain amount of order in here that we at least
intuitively, would think that we could capture
with some order parameter.
With an eye on the time, I won't go into too many
details, but it is possible for this guy to define
quality as a stable.
Which is,
of course,
minus one to the end. I should sleep over here
over all these scandals, and so just sit down, as
we did for the organization summit that's been
going on with a factor of minus one to the end. So
that. The positive spin at site.
Zero plus one negative spin aside, one contributor
minus one plus minus one, plus one, and it all
adds up to the large non-zero value here. And it's
possible to relate this to the derivative of the
of the log of the free energy derivative, the
derivative of the free energy, which is the longer
the partition function. By adding an additional
standard extra field contribution to the success
that couples and this is an.
So that is, in fact, a bona fide order parameter
for an anti Semitic phase that distinguishes it
from both the high-temperature disordered phase as
well as the ferromagnetic phase for all the
students are aligned as the usual using model
we're looking at in lectures.
And the. I will just mention that essentially this
constitutes the opinion on this hexagonal, this
type of glass alternatives.
Up and down the street on all of these various
neighbors.
I don't know. Well, here this guy is, that would
be consistent alternating pattern that also has
that non-zero of magnetization. The Funchess is
the triangle, the
OR.
Put it here, we just look at a single cell of that,
trying to relax and we say one of those kids is
going up. We've seen that to get a negative
contribution to the energy of the ground states.
We want. All of its neighbors to be walking down
the opposite direction so that the energy with
less than zero is itself turned out, so it was
more expensive to do that. Now, this pair of
nearest neighbors is kicking a positive
contribution to the energy rather than the
negative contribution that we want from all of
these things in order to minimize the energy.
In this case, we're just this simple cell of three
students trying to integration, you can prove this
is the best you can do. There are six possible
orientations of two students in one direction and
one the other that are the lowest that. You can go
to the antigrowth and the case, things that can
help you start to feel that this. System from the
one you have to sell out to
for less with some large number of students. We
start seeing all sorts of flashes. Want this to be
obvious that there's a clash with that? It's to
have this up, so that's contributions for those
two links now we
know it's going to have one of the other two.
It's a mirror image of the.
So this situation is very strange in
that it easy model is trying to the latest is
known as a frustrated anti-hero. And that's where
the connect briefly with a bit of theoretical
computer science question of finding the ground
state for a given number of sites is not possible.
To compute in a polynomial amount of time with a
polynomial is in the number of sites that you have.
If you add another site to the system, finding the
microstates, minimum energy takes exponentially
more time than the smaller system. So if you're
given the ground state, you can check. That is
energy is small pretty quickly. So the question of
finding the ground states is known as has been the
key calculation here that stands for non
polynomial and abstract computer science
determinations, that means that it takes
exponentially longer to find the solution. But
once you have a solution, check it quickly. And
this question here, the. Frustrated easing into
heroin is
a huge problem without going into details, you can
think of that, say the other, exponentially higher
computational problems can be mapped into this
sort of system. That's a riverside.
The conceptual the qualitative aspects of the
housing bubble on different land structures
obviously running out of time much more quickly
than I anticipated. Going to just wrap up by
posing what? Narrowly avoided being one of the.
Questions on the homework assignment, which is
motivated by physics. There were spin classes,
which I don't really have time to talk about today,
but we might get back to you later on over the
next week or two. If time permits, then there's a
further generalization. The is immoral to
couplings that can vary on different levels. How
does indeed have practical application in a lot of
experiments, which is how you receive a Nobel
Prize that 10 months ago have to really work on
this in the case of let's call a fully connected
lattice
rather than. Now, the.
Some say it's been years and years of others and
some slightly further away from the connected case,
sometimes called the complete graph, every side of
the. This is a neighbor of every other side. So
that's illustrated here, going from there, trying
to sell. Up to systems with four, eight or 12
sites and a number of links that increases, like
the binomial coefficients of engines to. So as a.
Phone conversation that you can do on this fully
connected Latisse email. Her off to at least part
of the. Until next week can simplify things by
going back to a constant interaction strength. And
trying to compute the procreation function. For
the energy given by the same sort of using
Hamiltonian where now? Somebody go to the nearest
neighbors need something over all pairs of sides
of the lattice, so just in case with the
interaction strength that decreases as the number
of size increases so that the energy parasite's.
Our interview per spin remains five times as it
increases, so sorry you didn't get a chance to
start playing with that this afternoon, but it's
something that you think about the weekly column
and siblings below there that I'll skip over about.
The productive way to approach this by
reorganizing the problem in terms of possible
values of magnetization, so. That is all the time
we have this afternoon off until Tuesday morning.
Don, as always, feel free to get in touch if any
questions come up about this or indeed anything
else.
What
was that?