It is just about time to get underway, so here is
the six-digit code for today:
two six two, four seven four.
So far this week we have introduced
interactions and phase transitions in general,
looked at the Ising model on a d-dimensional simple cubic lattice
as the simple playground to make those discussions
more quantitative, and we've seen on Tuesday the two
distinct phases that pop up or emerge from the
Ising model at high and low temperatures. So any questions
about those general issues before we pick up and
start to look at the more interesting regime of
what happens in between those two limiting
behaviors?
Let's see...
To quickly recap what we have
gone over, the Ising model
itself is defined by this energy that sums over
pairs of nearest neighbor spins, multiply by each
other in addition to the usual.
Coupling between the STEM degrees of freedom and.
The external magnetic field spins have values plus
or minus one, and the nearest neighbors are. You
find. By the underlying lattice structure of.
Which we may take a look at some of the
possibilities this afternoon is the detail, no
particular person boundary conditions. To.
Out of the space on the page and simplify the
overall structure of the lattice and be considered
the zero field is the model. And the of high and
low temperature. So as the temperature becomes
high, we end up with.
Equal opportunities for all of the microstates,
just one over. The total mobilization factor to
end and with all microstates equally probable, the
phase is determined by. The degeneracy is the
number.
District microstates with a given energy
for a different distribution of operating expense.
And. If we characterize this by the magnetization.
So, William, verbalised difference, looking at the
absolute value of the case of zero external fuel.
And the total magnetization womanize by the number
of spins, which is the difference between upward
and downward when he divided by the total.
When the. Things is determined just by counting
the degeneracy of the numbers of possible
microstates with different distributions of
operating expense. We have roughly equal numbers.
That is where binomial coefficient is separately,
which was a topic of one of the first tutorials
that we did for the start of the term. The
magnetization then becomes. Approximately zero
approaching exactly zero in that thermodynamic
limit. But the number of degrees of freedom
becoming large.
The opposite limit, how low temperatures, the
probabilities are exponentially sensitive to.
Their energies in particular, all excited energy
levels are exponentially suppressed compared to
the ground states, just to say that the. The
Granite State wins.
Evy. I have seen from this energy that. The.
Ground state with the minimum energy occurs, the
absence of electrical field for all of the spin's
are aligned in the same direction.
Whether that is plus or minus, we can't tell but
that.
Produces what we call the order phase. But there
is a tendency for all of these things to align in
one direction or another with the absolute value
of the magnetization approaching its maximum value
of one. As the temperature gets smaller and this
order phase. Is in contrast to the disorder things
up here and maybe give some intuition beyond. Just
writing down words of equations, we can look at
some examples of microstates of the easy model. At
high and low temperatures, these are some figures
from. Schroeder's book on thermal physics, where
he's considering a 20 by 20 lattice in Colorado
squares in that light as either black or white,
depending on whether the skin is a plus or minus
one. And even for systems that would certainly not
add another page to use 20 by 20 degrees of
freedom do correspond to two to the four hundred
power possible microstates. So that's about 10 to
the power of one hundred twenty. So
few samples are coming from. A computer program
that samples those microstates proportional to the
probability distribution and at high temperatures,
we can get a visual sense that.
Given the roughly equal probabilities for all the
different microstates we are. Almost guaranteed to
end up, for example, from that flat distribution
with a. What the even number of operating expenses
when black squares in this case, so. Even
comparing Iran and missile states, but those four
hundred spins are said to be black or white here
with equal probability. If you have a temperature
of 10. In their.
In the. Units of.
Of magnetic fields, so. Get into those units a bit
later on, this is a relatively high temperature
where you can see the. If we didn't have to leave
this out here, we wouldn't necessarily be able to
tell the difference between that random mental
state and the. Because they draw from the top of
the distribution at a relatively high temperature,
while the situation changes as we go to the low
temperatures, we end up with big blocks of spins
all around in one direction or another,
corresponding to almost all sides of this lattice
being either white or covered in black. And then
the interesting question is what happens in
between those high, high and low temperature
regimes, which is what we'll focus on today and
probably on Tuesday as well. We can see and it is
more intermediate temperatures, there is a more
intermediate behavior there. Still a mixture of
black and white spin's that there are regions
where the spins are all stay here, the mostly
black, and here they're mostly white. So if we
were to zoom in on smaller sections of this twenty
one lattice, you might see something that looked
like the lower temperature case. But if we were to
zoom out and look at the latest as a whole, we
still have roughly equal numbers of operating
expense as we did in the high temperature phase
just to sort of this home. This is a larger system.
Computed in the same way.
Numerically sampled from the probability
distribution, now with four hundred by four
hundred sites so that there are something like ten
to the forty eight thousand possible microstates.
And.
Temperature here is set to be two point two seven,
which is an interesting number that we'll get back
to if we can see islands of alliances, of all
different scales, easier to look at the marksman's
visually and with this little island of mostly
black spins there, the larger island over there.
So this one water just filed over here. If we had
selected any of those kind of 20 by 20, Latisse
being looked at the previous set of figures. You
might have thought the system was butterface. But
looking at the larger scale system, we could see
equal numbers of upward and downward pointing
spins. So an overall visualization that's more
consistent with this phase. So, two. Briefly
policy, if there are any further questions about
those visas before we dive into. Putting this sort
of visual.
Consideration, home work, mathematical footing.
We zoom back in here, the key concept that. Makes
the.
Discussion of these high temperature cases, very
mathematically well-defined, is the concept of the
order parameter, which in the case of the easy
model is the magnetization we've been discussing.
This is a quantity that is small in one phase,
what we've identified as the disordered phase with
reference to the sorts of visualizations of the
user model, and it becomes it goes to zero and
that sort of limits. But there's a number of
degrees of freedom. But the other ordered phase or
the parameter is not zero and in particular large
enough to be easily distinguished from zero.
The lawsuit over some of the forward construction
of the theory of these transitions, which could be
a model in itself, but there is a distinction
between the true order parameter and just any
given quantity. We want to define that by behave
differently in these two phases. And that
distinction is that the order parameter formally
is related to some derivative of the free energy.
So in addition to finishing in one phase and the
other, it's got to be a different order parameter,
it has to be related to a derivative of the of the
free energy use of water, of the partition
function and. Just to give a so we've always
assumed this to be the case for now. It is
possible to have what are called topological phase
transitions that have a actual transition between
two different phases but do not have an altered
parameter characterizing them. And these are. Not
only interesting, but important as well, so I
mentioned in passing here that the most famous
example of a technological transition without
water is known as the transition. Discovery
independently by Brzezinski is to be impossible to
tell us the K.A., which was a recently recognized
Nobel Prize in physics five years ago. Now, we can
also generalize this concept of water parameters
you think of. Specific systems that have multiple
distinct transitions, each with multiple distinct
order parameters related to different derivatives
of that free energy. But for the time being, just.
Keep working with the. Using ball with the
magnetization is that over the perimeter, you will
see its relationship to free energy in just a few
minutes. And with the border parameter in hand,
distinguished. The disordered phase there is zero.
And the order phase would is not necessarily its
maximum value, but anything distinct from zero. We
can formally define the phase transition and
distinguish it from a smooth and gradual crossover
between two distinct phases, which is the.
The question of the drive to what is a phase
transition mathematically, so mathematically we
only have a phase transition when the order
parameter itself is discontinuous or diversions or
one of its derivatives with respect to the control
parameters of the system, exhibit such a
discontinuity or divergence, which typically will
only appear in that thermodynamic limit of an
infinite number of degrees of freedom. So we say
that the we express the order parameter as a
function of the control parameters. And see if it
or any of its derivatives with respect to those
parameters have. Discontinuous behavior included
divergences, and if they do the value of the
control parameter. Corresponding to that
divergence, which is commendably is known as the
critical point of that phase transition. So that
is the general definition that we can quickly
specialize to the easy model itself, where having
turned off the external fuel to the suction, the
temperature is the only remaining program that we
have to to very well fix the structure with a
fixed number of degrees of freedom. So that
critical point. Becomes a critical temperature,
T.S.. Where?
If we do have a phase transition, there are these
two possibilities to consider the border itself is
discontinuous in this case or the border parameter
is continuous, but one of its derivatives with
respect to the temperature, is discontinuous with
versions. So these two cases or. Coming out of
some obscure process of historical understanding
are known as the first and second order phase
transitions, respectively, so the first order
phase transition. There is a. The street jump in
the water perimeter itself, so the magnetization
in the case of the easy go.
There is a second order phase transition, that
order parameter is continuous at the critical time,
really continuous for all temperatures. But it's
derivative as a discontinuity, which we can see
from this schematic picture here, if we were to
approach that critical temperature from. Lower
temperatures, the left hand side, and we see that
the derivative of this line has a very large
negative slope becoming larger and larger as we
approach to see. That corresponds to probably try
to draw that to the side.
Derivative with respect to temperature of that
order parameter.
That.
I said it was negative slope, so I just.
And those actions down to negative values. We're
coming from the left, the eventually subversions
option A. Infinitely negative value is coming from
the right with the. Value of the A parameter is
always zero. The slope itself is. Derivative of
zero, which is zero, and that gives us, in this
case, the discontinuity. In the first derivative
of the order or so, it is still able to transition,
but with that. Discontinuity in the derivative
rather than the order itself becomes known as the
second order phase transition. So historically,
there were also discussions of third or fourth
order phase transitions where depending on how
many derivatives you had to take to see this
discontinuity, that would be the order of the
phase transition. That's an antiquated terminology
these days and.
Modern parlance, anything that features a
continuous order parameter, but a discontinuity at
some finite number of derivatives is just that
second order phase transition. So whenever the
order perimeter is continuous, is the second row
the case?
And as the. One final comment on the. General
aspects of his transition before looking in more
detail at this model mentioned above in this
definition, the role of that through the equipment
which is typically required in order to see actual
discontinuities. So what happens? In general, we
have a system with a finite number of computers,
that freedom that's. Instead of the actual
discontinuity showing up in court versus control
parameter as in increases, is the sort of smooth
behavior that.
More and more rapidly, Gary.
So this is.
It's more the smaller the end is, the smaller this
is its.
It becomes a more rapid transition. And it's only
in the limits of infinite and that there is
additional discontinuity emerging, so.
Our formal definition is sometimes some of the
textbooks, you'll see that they will say true
phase transitions only occur when there are an
infinite number of degrees of freedom. But really,
we can tell based on how the independence of the
entrepreneur on the temperature varies as the
system size increases, whether that discontinuity
is developing or equivalently, that divergence in
its first derivative. So these techniques are.
They will find out how the system varies as its
numbers of degrees of freedom, change and.
I think we will get into that and this morning,
you have enough other topics to. To go over in the
time remaining is the way to distinguish whether
or not a change between faces is a true transition,
even when these systems are finite, as of course,
everything physical is. So that is.
Abstract or generic? Definition of phase
transitions of first and second order. And
assuming there are questions about that, we can
make things a bit more solid by
looking in more detail at the U.S. model. As it.
Transitions between its high temperature
disordered phase and that low temperature order
things, so this might allow some of those abstract
discussions to be made more concrete. But, of
course, mentioned earlier that the easy model is
only soluble analytically in one or two dimensions.
The end still a net zero for your case, and in
particular, if you want to restore an external
magnetic field, the solution is only known in the
one dimensional case. So. If you want to say
anything
mathematical about this. There are sort of only
two options available to us. One is numerical
simulation of the sort you did on that computer
project, which is relegated to Unit 10 or have
some general discussion of that. What we're
focused on here is a way to get an approximation
to the using model. That will allow us to look at
the transition region. Hopefully in a reliable way.
Even in the presence of a non-zero external field
where the resolution no longer needs an average
value. So to start the process towards. This
result, we can. Look at a bit more detail about
the deposition. With a non-zero external fuel. And
in particular, we can see that from its definition
is the difference between the number of operating
expenses and the brutality and expense, it is
probably related to the sum over the spin's
themselves. We look at this sum that whenever we
have a positive spin, it contributes a plus one.
Whenever we have a negative spin to contribute to
minus one, which
overall estimates just gives us the total number
of operating expenses, minus the total number of
dollars on expense, kind of one minus one for each
of the corresponding degrees of freedom.
And of course, this is useful because we've seen
exactly the similar spins before, it showed up in
the using model energy in the first place, which
means that we can rewrite. The internal energy for
getting microstates I in terms of this
magnetization, so. And is the average value of all
these things in the given microstates? So multiply
three by and relates that sum itself to end times
magnetization for a total magnetization. The
Capital M. That varies with the number of spins of
the system, so plugging this internal energy in to
the economic competition function. Some of you to
the minus made the Times internal energy, the
negative sides cancel out, we can overall factor
hold the temperature better on both terms. And we
have an expression for the partition function that
explicitly depends on the translation of each
microstates defined by the spin configuration.
So this is the promised connection between that
magnetization and free energy see organization
appearing in the partition function.
And the free energy itself is just the logarithm
of that production function with a factor of minus
two fronts that we can. Plug into a derivative
with respect to the external feel. With an eye
towards getting something that depends on the
magnetization, so.
Proceeding with the definition of that free energy.
The derivative of the log. This one over Z, that's
the derivative of Z with respect to H and moving
that derivative through the sun over microstates.
The derivative of the exponential is simple enough
to do in our heads. We end up with some overall.
Microstates of from Chambal Bita. Times,
mobilization and times that same exponential
factor was derivative we have just taken.
So the inverse temperature data and the
temperature cancel and. Looking at the inverse
protection function multiplied by the sum of
Raulston configurations of the mechanization of
the corresponding spined configuration.
We can identify that as just the expectation value
of the total magnetization with a negative side
for a criminal, 18 times the expectation value of
the normalized micronization that ranges from
minus one to one. So rearranging some of these
intermediate steps, that gives us an expression
for that expectation, value of the magnetization
or order parameter it is. Minus to you, sorry,
plus to your friend. So the minus signs cancel out
those equality's. And define convert that. Tea to
one of the.
And normalization factor or whatever in the times,
the.
Derivative with respect to external fuel of the
logarithm of the protection function. So this is
the promised connection between magnetization and
the free energy that confirms it is a formal order
parameter.
Is that quantity is rigorously defined?
Now, if we go back to this relationship between
the position for a given spin configuration and
the average value of the some number that
configuration. You can push the.
Would apply the expectation value to both sides of
that relation. And then relate the order itself to
the expectation value of the average spin, or to
say the other way, the average of the expectations,
values of all the spins as we sum over all of the.
Spin configurations, so the expectation value is
given by that sum of all possible spin
configurations, meaning that this quantity is
independent of any particular configuration. It is
simply a function of our two control parameters.
So. But on the next page, that's Paul.
The average spin is a function of the inverse
temperature data, and that means that appeals to
an age independent of. The spin configuration
itself. And there's a trick that we can play
around with looking at the spin spin interaction
in the internal energy of the user model. We can't
exactly rewrite this by adding and subtracting
that average magnetization from both of these
factors, so SCBA minus M plus M is just as
subjective. And if we organize this as the
fluctuations sometimes called Beltagy, how the
speed S.J fluctuates around the average value of
the spin.
Then we can expand this product into.
Four terms, so the fluctuations square S.J in this
case correspond to nearest neighbor sites defined
by the structure and the cross terms, the
individual spins multiplied by this constant
magnetization in duration and on the temperature
of magnetic field, minus that overall constants
and the squared.
So what we've done in this equation, 114, is
actually take a simple product of two things, make
it a lot more complicated by. We'll leave it up to
fluctuations around the absolute.
By subtracting that absolute squared, the. Purpose
for the benefit that we gain from doing this. Is.
By conjecturing. That these fluctuations on
average are small, we can make an approximation
that this term of two small factors multiplied by
each other can be reflected.
Leaving only the.
Remaining terms in this expansion. I should note
that this is somewhat non-trivial approximation
because
obviously these are the two values of that you can
take plus or minus one cannot be cannot both be
close to the average magnetization. So before you
put the flip one of these spins. We see a big
shift in that individual fluctuation, but if we
suppose on average, that's. All of those big
individual fluctuations around the mechanisation
cancel out, which. We know that the climate they
have to give us that position as the average, we
can justify this approximation, which then
replaces that. Spin, spin, interaction term in the
easing, the internal energy to what is called what
is known as the field approximation. They're only.
Terms linear in the individual spins remain in the
song over here to stay with us.
And this summer, Brewer's neighbors that simplify
that second term is just a constant for every one
of the nearest neighbors that we have computed
earlier this week that there are these times and
possible terms. In the sun for a p dimensional
symbol for ubiquitous, so that constant factor
just comes out front end times and Times Square
with the overall negative side pences, with the
relative negative side. And then in the other term,
we have the two spins on either side of the link
defining or the link connecting these nearest
neighbors.
Which means that if we sum over the overall
population, the largest, the entire large volume,
every single spin is going to appear twice, once
from one, says S.J onces effectively.
There are then.
Yeah, to the. Copies of each individual has been
submitted in some of her legs,
recall maybe be a bit more detail in this written
down here, thinking of how many times it's been a
little counted as we go over some of the links in
however many dimensions that we have, we've
counted that there are two deep links connected to
each of these spans. All of which are included in
this song, so.
We can rewrite. This some of your neighbors
assisted some over the themselves with that cost a
factor of two and the cost factor coming along
from our expansion in terms of fluctuations. So
combining that some over. Dispense with the some,
you already have connectivity, make them feel this
equation one 15 results where we just have a sum
over the spin's times that two times zation plus
the external magnetic field, which we can write in
a. More evocative way by defining effective
magnetic field that depends both on the control
parameter itself to be. Magnetic field we started
off with, as well as the mean value of the spin
multiplied by the number of links connected to
each site in the sun. So this is sort of the
historical origin of the name of this
approximation, we have introduced an effective
feel that you spin that sees that depends on the
value of the spin given by the magnetization. So
this result is. Goes by the name of the main field
approximation, which otherwise is a bit mysterious
while neglecting these fluctuations. Gives us this
effective feel, depending on the spin and in
essence, we are supposing that we can average over
all of the nearest neighbors that you seize to
produce. And approximately Konsta factor that we
can account for just as a modification of that
magnetic field, which is sort of the conceptual
aspect of this, that cycle, back to on Tuesday,
when we wrap up the discussion of the windfield
approximation itself will get a bit further today,
stirred by. Considering what happens from the.
Take this new expression for the energy in the
mutual approximation and put it through our
criterion for identifying an interactive system.
I remind you is.
Looking at what happens to energy when. An
arbitrary degree of freedom is changed. In this
case, it is. A single spin where the only thing we
can do to get to. Change it is the game, its value.
So when we flip that single spin, this first term
is a constant until the independence of the
Confederation and the dependence on the external
on the effective magnetic field, that we just pick
up a negative sign for the spin of the other state,
the same and not too surprisingly, the
corresponding change in the energy. Is just twice
that effective magnetic field times has been
installed as this is.
Independence of all of the other degrees of
freedom.
We have taken our using model, the paradigm of an
interacting system and
reduced it to, you know, interacting approximation,
but still accounts for some of these nearest
neighbor interactions through this definition of
the effective magnetic field arising from
expanding precisely those nearest neighbor
interactions.
So let's see. When the time goes.
We have enough time to. Push forward the analysis
of this new fuel approximation to. And we set up
the identification of a phase transition in
Mischaracterisation, which. Is now much simpler
than in the case, the the is involved because as a
not interacting system through our formal
definition, we can expect the petition function
and other observables to factories to boil down
into just a product of that single particle
partition function. Just as happened for the full
on the case back in three. So. Plugging in that
mean fuel energy. Into the corresponding
protection function.
Try to put both views on the projector at the same
time. We have this overall concept turn up front,
that's as it does not depend on any of the spin
configurations. We can just pull out. The
multiplicative factor of the exponential of minus
the times this constant in these times, in times,
standardization squared and the dimensions, and
then all the same configurations are defined by.
The plus minus one values for each of those things
where the remaining split independent piece. Of
this exponential factor. It was just given by the
some overspenders with some prefecture just
justified to be this X minus B the times, the
effective magnetic field, which was put back many
weeks ago to another track, expenses to the
equation. Forty one we had exactly this for. Of
the protection function. Aware that some of our
spins inside the exponential can be broken up into
the product of the exponential of the spin with
the spin taking two values plus or minus one, we
have the exponential of X plus the exponential or
minus X known to his friends as a hyperbolic
cosine for each of those and spins independently
the factories calculation that just raises. That's
hyperbolic, cosine. To the nth power that we can
insert the defective magnetic field to get the
full equation one 16 or the beam partition
function, a constant exponential factor times a.
And powers are being hyperbolic, cosine that
depend on the mechanization. So this is far
simpler than the easy model where in a general
number of dimensions, there is no known analytic
solution. But it is interesting that. The
partition function depends explicitly on the order
parameter, the expectation value of this
magnetization, which we have recently seen, is
itself. Related to the derivative of that petition
function. So if we look at the derivative we
derived in general terms earlier. The
mechanization is one over 10 times better times
the derivative of the larger the production
function with respect to the magnetic field.
All of this factor depends on age and only one way
that's inside the hyperbolic cosine. So the longer
the power brings the power in, down, out front, we
have the logarithm of the hyperbolic cosine of the
defective magnetic field, plus a bunch of other
terms that are independent of each drop out of
that derivative. So taking the derivative of that
long term, what's the hyperbolic cosine of the
denominator and then the chain rule it through to
get a hyperbolic sign in the numerator with a
again, another application of the chain rule,
taking a base out front, cancel out the one over
data that we started off with. So since you
because if they a and we have an expression that
has the. Order parameter the. Expectation, value
of the organization on both the left and right
hand sides. We found that that magnetization is
equal to the township itself with some dependence
on the increased temperature they're going to feel
and dimensionality of the system. So. The
Minnifield approximation is only self-consistent
when this equation 117 is satisfied, look,
considering that order parameter as the.
The variable, the degree of freedom to to analyze,
so that is where we will pick up next Tuesday,
university will be closed on Monday for the bank
holiday. We will look at the solutions of the
self-consistent supervision equivalent to finding
the roots of the hyperbolic geometric equation,
leading the charge of X to X itself. And we will
see what those self-consistent solutions have to
say about the phases of the mutual approximation,
depending on the temperature dimensionality. So
are there any questions before we break for the
morning? So we'll pick up with that on Tuesday,
this afternoon with that, some of homework
solutions and
some the things that we can do with. Let us know
what, General.