All right, we might as well get under way this morning.
We'll see how this microphone holds up after not being
plugged in overnight.  And we'll start as always with six
code for today: nine one one, two oh seven.
With that we can pretty much pick up and keep going from where we got up
to yesterday afternoon, after the extended check-in
with logistics and the recap of the first three
quarters of the module.  We got motivation from phase
transitions to look at interacting systems and
then defined what exactly interactions amount
to in terms of how the internal energy of the
system changes, upon making a change to any one of its
degrees of freedom. It's non-interacting if that
change is independent of all the other degrees of
freedom, except for that one, it is interacting
otherwise. And we introduced this simple internal
energy for a system of spins on a lattice. That
includes now the contribution to the energy coming
from a product of two spin's. That.
We can give you mentioned before going into the
details that given the negative signs that are
coming with each term here. There is a energy
preference to get to the lowest or most negative
energy, but from aligning the spins with that
external magnetic field H in the second term, that
corresponds to a value spin that is plus one. And
assuming that this is greater than zero and that
gives a negative energy, and the way to get the
negative energy of the first term is to have these
two spins on their nearest neighbor sites have the
same value that is point to the same direction. We
would end up without a plus one squared, minus one
squared there. The overall negative side then
gives another negative contribution, lowering the
energy.
As is preferred by the bolson factors and
canonical sample that we derived back back in
March. So if there are any immediate questions
about.
Those. Aspects of what we went through yesterday,
this is a chance to shout them out, otherwise you
can keep moving forward with the observation that.
There is one more ingredient just beyond the. Form
of how these spin degrees of freedom are being
multiplied together, and that is the sum over the
parenthesis JDK something over all of the pairs of
nearest neighbor spoons in our lettuce, it depends
on the latest that we have that we work with,
which can either be something that is fixed by
nature or if we're dealing with different crystals,
they can come up with different structures or
we're interested just in the mathematical aspects
of the systems. We can imagine all sorts of
different lattices with different ways or nearest
neighbors to be distributed. So at least for the
first pass through, we will focus on what are
called simple cubic gladys's. We drew a couple of
examples in one and two dimensions yesterday, and
one of the gaps in these figures are illustrating
some of these features of these simple cubic
gladys's in two dimensions on the left and. A
three dimensional, three dimensional, simple cubic
lattice of the right, where we can see in the case
of two dimensions, for instance, that if we pick
out any given site or spin that we're now
representing as a solid circle every point rather
than an up or down arrow just for simplicity as we
look at these higher dimensions. It has. The four
nearest neighbors, which not coincidentally, is
twice the number of connections, so each of the
two dimensions, we can go forward or back, left or
right from our base site as well as up or down.
And in between each of these pairs of nearest
neighbors, we can draw a solid line known as a
link. So what is back on the previous page between
nearest neighbor sites? We have a regular grid
that we can draw links and look at. In this simple,
ubiquitous case, the sets of nearest neighbor
pairs of sites that we have to sum over in our new
expression for the internal energy correspond
exactly to each of these links. So in this case,
the four nearest neighbors correspond to the four
links. And I've marked in a little red hatch there.
And here in three dimensions, we have
illustrations of links going forward to be right
up or off into that third dimension. We've sort of
projected onto the plane here, the human eye piece
of paper and as we go.
To higher dimensions with these little structures,
there are additional higher dimensional elementary
objects that we can start to consider.
So the. Two dimensional elementary units of
surface area. Yes. I laid it over here and can
also be seen interventions is known as a catch.
And once we get up to that three dimensional
elementary unit of volume, that's just a cube and
we have a simple cubic lattice and one attempt to
draw any cubes out here, we can generalize all of
this to higher and higher numbers of dimensions.
We have so called hypercube classes and we're the
elementary units of the. To the of the dimensional
universe is known as the hypercube, just the
product of a single link in all of the available
dimensions to. The D in which we are operating
will stop. So because we have to sum over all of
these nearest neighbor pairs that correspond to
the links in order to compute the internal energy,
that's the basis of our interacting system on
these simple cubic gladys's. We may need to worry
about what exactly happens if we tip the edge of a
planet like this and this is relevant since.
Everything in nature is finite, so what happens
with this link, for example, that is dangling off
the bottom of our two dimensional wires here? The
simplest way to approach this, the one that we
will do, I think without exception in this module
and is done in most research, is to suppose that
this link down at the bottom here is the same link
that comes off at the top. There they are
identified. This is something known as periodic
boundary conditions, which is saying that once. We
encounter in any side or. The site of the latest
in a number of dimensions. Links that go off to
the edge of what we choose to draw and simply wrap
back around to the other side of the lattice, it's
similar to a classic arcade game, Pacman, where if
you go off the video screen and any one of the
dimensions, the
character immediately appears to be bottom of the
opposite side. So there are a couple of ways the
periodic boundary conditions can. People will be
confusing if you think about the. In. In a
different way than we have in mind, so the first
thing to note is that all of these links are
essentially the same length. All the nearest
neighbors are the same distance away from each
other. Even when we have to wrap around from the
left of the lands that we've drawn back around to
the right. And it's still the same distance away
as any of the other links in the system. So.
We can emphasize this. By drawing a line of
structure with periodic boundary conditions in
this sort of way, as this is a one dimensional
lattice, so there are just one direction we can
move from one dimension which we can move forward
or back from any given site. So there are two
nearest neighbors for each of these sites and we
have sort of come around. Periodic boundary
conditions to connect the links that were
identified at the left and right edges of this one
dimensional lattice, ending up with something
represented as a circle on this two dimensional
sheet of paper. So this emphasizes that there is
still constant separation between all of the sites
in the lattice. But it can introduce a different
misconception, which is that periodic boundary
conditions might induce some curvature in the way
that we have turned this one dimensional lattice
that used to be a straight line into something
that looks like a circle. What what's really going
on is that this impression of curvature is a
consequence of how we are visualizing the system
being drawn on a two dimensional sheet of paper.
And really, this is still a straight line we are
just representing it in. This visual way for
convenience, and this, of course, generalizes to
all of the higher dimensional structures. So if
you have two dimensions, as in this example up
here and you identify both the left and right
edges and the top and bottom edges. You may well
have seen the previous modules end up with a
tortoise, a doughnut that looks curved, if we
imagine it being embedded into three dimensional
space atop a logically, it is a flat structure,
just the same absence of curvature as the sheet of
paper that we have written it on up here. So the
periodic boundary conditions.
Don't change any distances between the sites,
they're all separated by the same distance and
they don't introduce any curvature, we'll end up
with flat Tauri. Introduced to this circle in one
dimension, the usual toreson for a two dimensional
system of higher dimensional hypersaline as we go
up in the higher number of dimensions. So just
check to see that there are no objections to.
Those details about the letter structures that are
underlying this system we're considering now.
And if it did come up, feel free to shout them out
with this. Underlying basis, all established, we
can start to. Specify some of the details of the
system in general, in particular counting the
number of links that we have, depending on the
number of dimensions that we are considering. So
in this one dimensional case, it's easy to see
that there are the total number of links. So each
site has two nearest neighbours corresponding to
two links attached to it, but each link is
attached to two of these sites. So if we were to
count to ten links, all of the ones that connect
to all of the sites here, we would have to divide
that by two to account for the double counting of
each link. Being attached to two of those sites,
so that is to say that the total number of links
for this whole system is to an over to August and
she gets we can also see by going around and
counting. The number of sites up to end and then
the number of links in between them also up to nd
in this very simple one dimensional case, and if
we look back to the two dimensional lattice, we
can tell that same sort of story that we saw. Each
site has Fournier's neighbors forward or backward
in each of the two dimensions. We still have two
sites connected to each link. So the total number
of links, which I'm just calling the number times
now, is then those. Fournier's neighbors divided
by two links for two sites per link for each of
the sites. Let us and we can generalize this to.
The dimensional case, again, with periodic
boundary conditions to keep all of the sites the
same the same number of links. So. Indeed, it
mentions. You will have these to the
links that attach to every site moving forward or
backward in almost every one of these dimensions,
as always, there are two sites. Shearing.
Each of these. Linc's.
And if we put those two facts together, then we
end up with the total number of links is two times
in.
For two days, links from each of the sites in the
system and then divided by two to correct four
double counting, so just ending up with the times
and try to leave a dot in between and look like a
differential factor. And that's the total number
of links or the total number of nearest neighbor
terms in the energy we are considering that
defines this interacting spin system to a number
of terms. That person knows both with the number
of sites and the system, as well as the number of
dimensions of the states are distributed across.
So. Now that we have both the.
Equation for the internal energy that and as well
as the underlying. Hypercube, a structure that
defines where the nearest neighbor terms, where
the two students get multiplied together to
contribute to the energy. What we end up with is a
system known as the easy model on accumulates in
these dimensions, that is.
The title of this section is not surprised that we
are encountering this terminology, it's called the
easy model because it was invented by us, you'll
have Lence. And what happened historically is sort
of fascinating story that you'll have. I was
trying to come up with a model for Ferromagnetic,
the way that certain types of materials can pick
up a overall collective magnetization depending on
their temperature. And had the idea that. Coming
in tonight in 1920 with the new consensus that
these materials are made up of of molecules and
suppose that each of those molecules has a
magnetic dipole structure of its own, which can
either add up or cancel out to provide this large
scale deterministic response or not. The idea was
that depending on the temperature, the least
magnetic poles represented as the been working
with would. Alive or not, if you find a Ph.D.
students and it's easy to actually solve
mathematically the. This qualitative conjecture
that the simple speed system we have presented
would. Describe magnetism, so using did this a few
years later, working just in the one dimensional
case, if you could solve. Exactly. And finding
that the results did not agree with experiments,
even for these one dimensional materials of.
Essentially a straight line system of magnets, and
it was only about 20 years later that anyone with
the mathematical capabilities to solve the two
dimensional case came along. Fellow by the name of
Flores on Zagor. Who was eventually to receive the
Nobel Prize for different work, but in in the
nineteen forties, exactly solved the two
dimensional system, at least in the case of zero
feel this age going to zero and was able to show
that indeed it behave differently from the one
dimensional case and in much better agreements
with a wide variety of phase transitions, as we
will see going forward.
And.
Things really took off again a couple decades
after that, so starting in the 1960s with some
further work on especially these two dimensional,
higher dimensional cases, it was realised that
these simple open systems could be applied not
only to magnetism, but to essentially any system
where there are two possibilities that you can
distinguish between. So things like neural
networks where neurons are firing or not, things
like segregation in cities where people are
similar to their neighbors or not. And there have
been thousands of scientific studies summarized by
this little magazine article that I have uploaded
to the canvass site, not a cartoon picture of
magnet's that is being used for all sorts of
applications. In addition, just to the fair
magnetism it started from. But we will have a
chance to see some of those later on. For now,
I'll mention that if we go up from two dimensions
to three dimensions, there is no known exact
solution and such a solution may not even exist.
We have to take a different approach to analyze
using model once we get above two dimensions and
we can appreciate the difficulties just by.
Looking at the economical production function for
this theory, that, of course, is based on the
energy we have written down, it depends on the
configuration of all of these and spins as well as.
On the set of nearest neighbor pairs that are
interacting with each other under our formal
definition of interactions. So due to the overall
production function, of course, is the sum overall
microstates, each micro state is defined by a
different configuration of the skin. So there are
two to the power and total microstates, as we've
seen for the not the tracking systems. So.
Solving the easy model would amount to coming up
with a. Nice analytica, close form expression for
what here is a sum of exponentially better
exponential factors, each of which has
three times, and then plus in terms within the
exponential and importantly due to the interactive
nature of that first term where changes changes in
energy with a positive change in the spin, SJP
also depend on all the nearest neighbor Spoon's
ask.
That means that you're no longer able to factories
this partition function the way that we could for
the down the track in case that only had the
magnetic field turn to eight times the sum of all
the things that gave us the equation. Forty one,
which was just the powers of identical, hyperbolic,
cosine terms. Without that, we're just stuck with
this exponentially large sum exponential with no
known exact solution, once we get up to three
dimensions where there are six nearest neighbor
terms.
For each of the spins that are double counted in
that first term, so even if we try to do a brute
force evaluation of this partition function.
That also runs into the same issue of a rapidly
exploding number of terms. So if we drop down from
our usual 10 to the power, twenty three to just
ten, twenty three spends a little over a thousand.
So simplifying the system by 20 orders of
magnitude and size and to give a number of
dimensions and we can see that. There are going to
be two to the N terms, to the thousand power is
roughly three hundred in terms. Which if we were
to try to evaluate on any existing or foreseeable
supercomputer, would take well beyond the reach of
the universe to not to complete. So we have to be
a bit more clever about how we analyze the
interacting easing model. We can't exactly solve
the partition function in. Any more than two
dimensions of a two dimensional case, it's
really a tour de force of. Mathematical analysis,
so famously complicated calculation.
So we also can't numerically evaluate this, but we
will have to do is simplify things and we will
dive into that in the time remaining unless there
are questions about. The U.S. model models we have
now to finance and the aspects of it that we have
highlighted.
And not seeing anything, we can move on to the
simplification strategy, which not too
surprisingly is.
The same one that we employed in the not
interesting case where we consider the extreme
limits of the system and in particular, we'll do a
couple of things. We will look at the limit where
this external magnetic field vanishes. So we'll
set each equal to zero and get the energy down to
a single start, a single term expression that just
has the. Yes, there were some times escape, so
with that magnetic field turned off, we have at
least a shorter expression to right for the
protection function, but still one with
exponentially exponential. And we will, in the
zero field case, consider what happens at
asymptotically high and low temperatures. Where we
can expect some aspects of the system to simplify,
some microstates to be relevant, some others to to
dominate and just to give a forecast of what will
be driving for in this next stage of our analysis
of using model, we will see. Not too surprisingly,
that have high temperatures. The behavior of the
system is qualitatively different than the system
at low temperatures. This is also what we saw in
the economy, tracking cases, and we can identify
each of these high and low temperature limits as
distinct phases of the system, similar to the
phases that we talked about more qualitatively
yesterday, like the actual steam at high
temperatures compared to liquid water at lower
temperatures. This allows for there to be a phase
transition between these two phases. But that is
not a priority guaranteed because there is a
specific meaning to a mathematical meaning and
definition to what we mean. We talk about a true
phased transition, which is what we will wrap up
this section by
spelling out in the context of the easy model. So
if we just have two different phases to different
types of behavior at high and low temperatures,
then either be a true rapid transition between
them or just a gradual evolution from one of those
limits to the next. As that control parameter, the
temperature is very low. That gets called a
crossover in contrast to a phase transition. And
we will see as we see, the first step is to
delineate these two different phases and then we
will define the difference between that phase
transition and the crossover between them and then
move on to try to establish which of those two
possibilities, phase transition or crossover is
realized by the easy model, both within and
without a external magnetic field. So that's the
plan for probably the rest of today. So we'll get
underway with the high temperature regime. So in
the asymptotic minute where the temperature goes
to zero, it's been a while since we've seen data.
So we recall that that is the inverse temperature.
Well, as promised, there is a significant
simplification of the partition function in this
case.
We have from this equation one child that is still
at the top of the screen, that petition function
is the sum over all configurations of our spins
and the exponential factor of that percentage of
the times, the sum of all, in your standard terms,
sending it to zero except some just zero. So that
picks up just counting that one for every single
spin configuration of which there are two to the
power and available. So this is looking a lot like
the not attracting. Case that we had earlier, in
the absence of an external feel, every.
Configuration, independent of its actual internal
energy, is adopted with the same probability. As
always, working in the dynamic equilibrium, so in
effect, we can physically what's going on here is
that the. Temperature is so large that the energy
coming from the village of Orientation's all of
these new receiver spins is irrelevant.
Whether the spins are aligned with each other,
reducing the energy or one opposite with each
other, increasing the energy makes no effect to
the overall behavior of the system, all of which
is dominated by the huge amount of thermal energy
that is sloshing around.
So. What we can do to characterize this system
where the internal energy is irrelevant is
consider a slightly different observable. And in
fact, a simpler one. That came up yesterday in the
context of the final homework assignment. This is
the magnetization of the system, a bit of
terminology coming from the historical roots of
this model as a model of romanticism. But what
this is, is just counting the. Total number of
upper pointing spins minus the downward spins. So
initially we define up and down with reference to
external magnetic field, the skins with the value
of plus one that were considered to be aligned
with the field minus one or against it. Now that
we don't have the field, we can still keep that
same definition of spin having plus or minus one
to state oriented up or down. There's just no
energetic preference for a spin to be pointed out
as opposed to being put down. I guess they decide
I have time to fit in here, is that this reveals
that symmetry of the zero field case. So once you
remove that external feel and don't have it to.
Prefer one direction or the other. We can flip
every single spin in the of system without
changing internal energy or anything other than
the overall sign of this magnetization. So.
There's nothing in the absence of external field
to distinguish a system up from one with all the
spins pointed down, or similarly, if we have a
complicated microstates with lots of upward and
downward sprinkled around, if we flip all of them
at the same time, we end up with. Effectively, the
same physical system from the.
Corresponding opposite microstates, so of the
microstates are carrying up these pairs related by
symmetry, transformation, flipping all of the
spins at the same time.
So getting back to station. We will typically
normalize it by the total number of spins. And
what this does is just make it easier to compare
systems of different sizes so the decision has a
value that is always between minus one, plus one.
Speaking of the this is lower case than. So it's
now the difference between the plus one minus the
minus hospitals divided by the total number of
plus and minus spins, and in order to account for
that symmetry, I mentioned the absence of external
fuel. It also makes sense to focus on the absolute
value of the U.S. so that we don't pick up
duplicate copies of just different biocide, how to
find that symmetry, transformation, something all
of these systems at once. So have some value that
ranges from zero to more than the limit zero sum.
There are people numbers of positive and negative
skills.
And the limit of one is by all of the skins are
either a plus or minus, and there's no difference
between those two microstates.
So what we want to do is. Figure out the
expectation value of romanticisation in our
high-temperature limit.
We do that in the usual way that the expectation
value of any observable is a value that observable.
We're getting the microstates, some deverall, the
microstates, so. And by.
The probability for the system to adopt that
microstates we have seen that all of the
microstates have an equal probability of one over
to. So the expectation value is just going to
depend on. How many of these equally probable
microstates have particular values of the
magnetization so we can pull out that constant?
Probably have military control over to them and
see that the expectation value is just related to
the sum of all of the major decisions for all the
microstates that will be dominated by.
The most probable value for this magnetization. So.
This is.
Again, because the energy is not playing any role
in the coming days, this is producing effectively
what we already considered it for, the non
distracted case. Where as an example, we looked at
the ground state of the system and we saw that
there were just two microstates with that maximum
mobilization of one where all of the end spins are
either plus one or on spins or minus one. And this
is, of course, a special case of the binomial
coefficient factorial that we are used to seeing
in this context, where the number of states with a
given number of upward pointing spins. Out of the
total is just the binomial coefficient, the ratio
of these factorial factors which are now
sufficiently familiar with to recall that the
spinal cord deficient has a narrow peak around the.
Limit where half of these things are pointing up
and the other half are pointing down.
So not only is that.
So the microphone has died from not being plugged
in, get him to stop beeping at us. So not only are
there more microstates with a roughly even number
of distribution, even number or equal number of
upward pointing it down expense.
There are enormously larger numbers of microstates
in that regime where the magnetization, the
difference between the number of upper pointing
and Dalrymple's expense is small or varnishing,
which is to say that the main position is. Towards
its lower limits of zero. So what we have overall
is the expectation value that's just counting the
numbers of states is going to approach zero as the
number of degrees of freedom in the system. Is
increasing the peak that we have in the spine that
we'll factor distribution becomes narrower and
narrower as it increases and this limit of and
going to an infinite number of degrees of freedom
is. Just that through the limits that we mentioned
yesterday, it shows up in the final homework
assignment as the. Limit in which the canonical
canonical examples are effectively equivalent. On.
So in that limit, we have.
Absolute value of the mechanization effect of
vanishing for any final, and we will have at high
temperatures a small value of the mechanization,
close to zero, it can be closer to zero as it
increases and. This we'd describe or we call a
disordered phase of the system where there are
roughly equal numbers of upward and downward spins
and no overall pattern to how those upper
Delaporte expense are distributed.
Across the US, it's all all disordered and.
I think we have plenty of time to get through the
opposite lower temperature limit where we. Can
expect, as advertised, something different to
happen, so this is the case in which the
temperature is becoming very large, going to
infinity, and we want to determine the
magnetization here. And.
In the same sort of way as we saw, we're not
interactive systems, we now have this both form
factor, the exponential of the speed of times, the
energy.
That appears in the canonical petition function,
equation 112 as Peter. Becomes large as opposed to
small disposable factors, exponentially enhancing
the preference for enhancing the probability where
the system will. Adopt, for example, sampling
microstates where there is a lower or more
negative value of the energy. So as the sum of all
your neighbors becomes more negative. And gets
multiplied by the large indoor temperature and the
low temperature regime. We have it exponential,
the very large negative number which approaches
one.
Whereas the.
The opposite regime we have, the very large
positive number has that exponential suppression
that we saw before and we'll see you again. If I
move more quickly through the rest of this, this
on Friday, but what we can expect is just as we
saw the opportunity for the tracking system, the
ground states should dominate the expectation
value for any of your including that magnetization.
And the impact on the expectation value from
higher energy microstates will be exponentially
suppressed. And we've seen already that there are
to be generally ground states. When the. External
field of the easy model, Danishes.
In which case all of the spins are. Aligned in
either the two directions. And it becomes easy to
confuse the. Energy of. Both of these ground
states, energy is just the beginning. Some of the
product spends on sites.
Since these spins are always aligned in the same
direction, both as I and as as came in the ground
state will be both plus one or both minus once
there are two factors, plus or minus one, the
negative signs, will that cancel in that square
again? Just something over the number of newspaper
pairs with the sign. That was these times and in
these dimensions, so the overall energy is picking
up a minus one contribution. From everyone. Of the
new types and links in the latest.
And.
Because all of these things are alive, we've
already seen that mobilization in the ground
states is. Exactly one. And we can check what
effect that first excited the set of first excited
states will have on the overall expectation value.
So to get from a ground state to a first exciting
stage. The only thing we can do is flip a single
spin, so starting from either of these two states,
from the center line up or down, we negate one of
the spins we get, one that is pointing down while
the rest point out we have one that is pointing up
all the rest point down.
And the total number of microstates that have this.
This particular set of operating expenses
responding magnetization is just, again, the.
Binomial coefficient now with a single speed
pointing out or equivalently and minus one spins
pointing up at a single point. Now each of these
factors is just equal to in. Their son gives us to
an. Degenerate microstates. Where the position
normalized by the number of degrees of freedom is.
Almost one, but not quite an exact approaches, one
as the number of students increases. So. The
deviation from the maximum position in this first
excited state is just a one over and correction
that vanishes in that moment.
So. In order to.
Figure out what effect this first excited state is
having on the system, we need to compute the
probability now and it will be adopted. That, in
turn, depends on the first excited state energy
where. We have. Rather than minus one from every
link, we have a. Plus one coming from all the
nearest neighbors.
Of the one spin that has been flipped with respect
to all the rest St..
From that spin, this our. To the.
Links that have a positive contribution to the
energy and dimensions and then all of the other
links in the latest. It's the same minus one
factor. That's what we had before and the ground
states there are now the times and minus those to
the.
Linc's. With this negative one contribution to the
energy is that plus two to minus the Times and.
Minus two D lengths for a total of.
We
seems.
That was a testament to the scrap of this gap here.
The total is minus and minus 14.
So I'll just go a couple of minutes over today to
bring everything together quickly. So looking at
the relative probability for this model to be in
the state with the maximum magnetization versus
the first excited state with the one over and
change. To that maximum is just a product of this
ability, depending on the energy and times, the
number of microstates with that probability. So
the probability of being in the ground state. Is
the two distinct microstates multiplied by that
large exponential factor and the probability of
being in that first excited state is the two and
microstates times the slightly different factor by
the speed of times, the energy of that versus the
states, which is these times in minus 40. So
canceling out the speed of times, an exponential
factor and moving the negative exponential up to
the top. We can confirm. That the crown stage is
exponentially more profitable for the system to be
in as the temperature data becomes a large number.
There is an exponential factor in the temperature
of the first degree on stage compared to the
linear factor and on the multiplicity of the first
excited stage. So as we go to sufficiently low
temperature, a sufficiently large beat up, we have
exponential domination of the ground states. And
as we saw before, the non interacting case only
exponentially suppressed contributions from the
higher energy levels. So that is to say that in
low temperatures we have. All of these bands
aligning for ordering, so this gives us the order
to phase where the magnetization approaches. Its
maximum value of one as the temperature decreases,
so.
20. Twelve minutes over today just to wrap up,
that's. Scan of the possible faces of the U.S.
model at zero field and high and low temperatures.
And we have contrasted these two phases by looking
at the accusation, seeing that in one phase, the
organization is small disorder phase and the order
patronization is large. We'll pick up on Friday by
looking at. The possible ways that we can connect
between these two phases as the temperature varies
from one minute to the next. So I will forward to
see you then back in the other room, down the hall.