So we are ready to go with the last meeting of
statistical physics before the break.
Starting with
the six digit code for this afternoon.
It's three two,
three nine, two nine.
And
we can wrap up quickly with the one last piece in this
supplement on the Sommerfeld expansion that we
didn't get to this morning.  Though I'll first check in if there
are any immediate questions about what went
through this morning.  This last piece is
not so much to do with the Sommerfeld expansion
itself as an alternative that we now have access
to, which is a real difference in the nineteen
hundreds. So the Somerfield expansion is a way to
recast, intractable, integral to a series of.
Management rules, we can compute word about order
finding this severe dependence on the temperature
and the heat capacity of the low temperature,
family gas and living order in what is a fact, an
expansion over here, an expansion in terms of this
ratio, the temperature divided by a fairly energy.
And we can expect this expansion to break down
when the temperature is an order that fury energy.
Not only are we neglecting the key to the fourth
effects, for instance, this equation, one of nine
of the consistency condition that we got from the
particle number that relates to the energy and the
chemical potential, depending on the temperature
of high square is about 10. So when T squared is
about one point two times per square, those two
terms will cancel out. The dominant contribution
will come from precisely the next correction that
we're due to the fourth over the energy to the
fourth that we have collected.
But.
We have that summer film doesn't is Python or more
specifically, computers that are capable of doing
easily numerical integration through Python or any
other programming model of. Of your choice, which
we can bring to bear on this problem by recasting
it first in terms of dimensionless, ratio's,
dimensionless degrees of freedom, which are the
ones that match up to what we have to
dimensionless numbers we have access to on a
computer as opposed to the temperature of energy.
The chemical potential has units of energy. So if
we go back to the full integral that we hit with
these our expansion to get a low temperature
approximation and we plug in the expression that
we have from earlier in the week for this pre
factor, the constant terms that are collected in
the states.
What we can do here is replace the square root of
energy and the differential to you by three has
powers of this X Times team. So we get a square
root X times X and then T to the power three
halves, which combine with whatever the Fairbury
energy to the three has. Power gives us the three
horsepower. They dimensionless ratio of the
temperature relative to the energy. And similarly.
Stick in this X for the. One of the exponential
factors is the data of the better times, it is
just the X that becomes an infinitely large number,
has X goes to infinity, which is by far the jokes
which rearrange that have very small factors of
the lightest X everywhere else in this ratio. And
then finally, we're left with an exponential of
minus B to be able to smooth over T. And if we
also introduce a dimensionless constancy as this
ratio of chemical potential to Fairbury energy,
then that exponential factor just matches into a C
divided by the dimensionless lowercase T.. We can
see if we look at that ratio of security factors
of Fairbury energy cancel out. And this is equal
to you over the dimension for capital here.
And just as we saw this morning in the summer
field expansion, we have factors of the average
particle number on each side of this equation that
drop out. And we are left with just the
consistency condition relating this. Complicated,
integral to Wilsonville, simple number one. What
we can do that is. Choose a value for the
temperature and choose a value for the sea, the
chemical potential telefon to evaluate, to go,
which only takes a few lines of code. Excellent
libraries available for iPhone and see if this
relationship works out, if we get one as demanded
by this consistency condition.
And what we can do at that point is keep rerunning
that conversation with a fixed temperature and
different values, the chemical potential, until we
find the correct value relative to the very energy
that satisfies that condition. We just arrived. So
why change?
Those. Projector here and look at a python code
that I will upload a canvas this afternoon. This
does essentially what we just went through. We
define a value for that dimensionless T so twice
the free energy in this case. And then adjust the
chemical potential in terms of the Fairbury energy
and numerically integrate dysfunction, the square
root of X times to the minus X divided by the
exponential of minus C over T minus 40, plus
another factor that into the minus X and check to
see how close we are to what we should have won.
So this is roughly where I ended up. So it should
be pretty close to one if I look at. This chemical
potential of about minus two and a half times the
very energy where a temperature of twice the
Fairbury energy, it's just about. Less than one
part per thousand of. And you fire and collect.
This result for the appropriate chemical potential
as a function of the temperature to the minus two
point four six corresponds to two point oh, then
that produces the very last red point on this plot,
which you see in a slightly larger size down here.
I just went through a handful of values of this
dimensionless ratio for the temperature, then the.
Correct, chemical potential, not as a fund or in
units of the free energy up to a couple of decimal
places, that just took a few minutes. And then I
can compare this to that, the order quadratic
result. We got this morning that showed. The
chemical potential approaching the family energy,
the limit of zero temperature with quadratic
corrections, at least in the regime of. Tea over
the energy that we can rely on the expansion to
converge. So you see there's good agreement for
small volumes of temperature, that quadratics
dependence. And I just thought of this dependence
beyond where we may expect to see problems. Indeed,
we do see some noticeable discrepancies setting in
right around. The. Value, there was first two
terms cancels out the expected issues. But maybe
the more interesting result here is following up
on something we came across earlier this week or
possibly the last week, which is that as the
temperature increases, we do indeed see the
chemical potential changing from negative, from
positive to negative, getting back into the
classical regime where we introduce the chemical
potential, where we want to take the classical
limit that corresponds to this high temperature
quantum gas with a large negative value of the
chemical potential. So that is going beyond the
limitations of the Sommerfeld expansion with some
assistance to modern technology and confirming
some of the claims earlier, and that's all there
is to say about all that I have to say for that
supplement.
And that lets us get back to the actual tutorial
problem that we just looked at fairly briefly
toward the end of last week, this Einstein model
will be solid where
someone just being pictured as some regular array
of atoms that are held in place by oscillators
between those.
Where each of these oscillators is treated as a
non interacting degree of freedom and. The.
Resulting heat capacity can be predicted compared
with these experimental data through the usual
sort of calculation we've been doing and we got to
the point last week checking on what would happen
if we followed these solids just as a bunch of
spins pointed up or down. Of course, with each
atom in this array finding that the capacity is
always negative as it should be and is
proportional to the inverse temperature squared
divided by the hyperbolic cosine of that inverse
temperature times the external magnetic field.
So this appropriately banished in the limit of
zero temperature in agreement with the data we
were looking at, this actually turns out to be. A
universal result sometimes called the third law of
thermodynamics. And related to the Entropia and
the connection between entropy and heat. But there
were problems if we try to match this bottle for a
solid, not attractive experience to the
experimental data that motivated this
consideration in the first place, as the
temperature gets large and small, the other side
goes to one and. The capacity as a whole vanishes
roughly proportionately to whatever temperature
square is shown here for. Temperatures larger than
that, I feel, in contrast to the experimental data
that roughly approach a constant battle that high
temperatures of a few hundred Kelvin.
So that's where the ISIS is aiming to make a
difference and provide a better description. And
we at least put up. Last week, this forced.
Procedure to derive the heat capacity from just
the definition of the bottle itself into the
oscillators has some amount of energy that comes
in quantize units motivated by Einstein's work on
the electric effect. And the statistics of
counting how those units of energy can be
distributed among the oscillators connecting the
atoms in this model of a solid. They'll give us
eventually the total number of microstates, the
entropy temperature, energy from its peak capacity.
So perhaps at this point I'll just pause the
recording for five minutes or so and you can. Let
me know how far you got along this path already
and how far you get at the end of that, unless
there are questions about the. The basic set of
definitions of this model where. I'm not going
over some of the things we introduced last week
with this case to a number of units of energy for
each Baalbeck as basic unit energy in an
oscillator itself. If that isn't clear, we can.
Revisit it and get up to speed. Otherwise. No hit,
pause and start timer.
So that was five minutes, just check and see how
it's come on, if you are having a slow time
getting started or or the job and board.
I will say that this first step is figuring out
the total number of microstates is the real needs
of the of the problem. And once we have the total
number of states that everything else sort of
follows through the work we've done. It sounds
like
customize. Yeah, that sounds right. To have a
spoiler factor.
That was last.
This one,
which is equal to.
Chris. That is indeed what I have. And if everyone
is happy with that, we can look at a.
My favorite way of driving that, which there are
many ways of getting at this result,
but it's one nice one is recognizing that the
competition works here is divided, dividing two
units of energy into an indistinguishable
oscillators distinguishable due to their fixed
location in the solid. So this is the same county
as putting bolts into boxes. And we did when
introducing quantum statistics with the change
that the boxes are since you are now
distinguishable. It can be. Defined by putting in
and minus four walls, dividing these boxes in a
sequence of symbols corresponding either to the
units of energy or the dividing lines between the
oscillators that are going into it. So this sort
of sequence of symbols. We describe what is that,
11 minutes of energy divided among six boxes
through 16 symbols, so.
And minus one of those plastic balls and. All that
we have to do is choose. All of the possible ways
for a case of these case, plus embarrassment,
symbols to be units of energy that are
distinguishable and we then have all of the
remaining symbols are fixed to be those dividing
lines, the walls. Fully specifies microstates. And
you can check out. As I have this printed out, I
do it through here quickly.
You seem to be in good shape with this.
Check the results against that minimal system of
three oscillators,
if there are no use of energy to the state to
distribute among those three oscillators, there's
only a single microstates. Each oscillator has
units of energy that is equal to.
So.
Three oscillators to
choose to choose zero is only one possible way of
managing that. We thought it was one minute of
energy, it could be either of those three
oscillators. That's three microstates, which is
the three choose one. And something interesting
happens when we have two units of energy, we
finally get something that is not possible with
that spin system. The spin, we could just have a
spin pointing up or down, we could call that no
energy or what you have to do in this model. We
now have the possibility of having an oscillator
with two units of energy, something going beyond
the system. So we have this three microstates
where. The two units of energy are either the
three oscillators or the three different ways of
having one unit of energy to mobilize voters. And
the third one having no energy. So six microstates
in total. Which we want to match for choose to,
which is four factorial over two squared, which is
the. Six. For them, sometimes to two square,
finally. The three units of energy, we can have,
all three in one of these oscillators, you can
have one unit in each of them. Or six possible
ways of dividing two units of energy in one
oscillator and one unit in another. And that three
plus one four six is 10, which is that five choose
three is five times four. Overtrading is a B10.
So that is a check that the explicit computation
we can do with a small number of oscillators
matches this combinatorial result in terms of.
Satriale's and binomial coefficients go back to
the usual regime for a solid working with blink of
an eye is no worth of oscillators, ten of the
twenty three and a comparable number of units of
energy to distribute among them. I can simplify
things just slightly by dropping those miners arms
even within the factory. We could say that this
ratio of factory owners is approximately given by
just Caples and factorial factory and factory. And
the logarithm of that ratio gives us the entropy
that we can hit with the leading order of
Serling's approximation and again, minus in the
linear terms, K plus and minus K minus N cancel
out. So we're left with just combinations of logs,
Caples and types, along with cables and by key
like minus and walk and.
So that is already the second bullet point to the
step to capacity and the third is taking the
derivative of the entropy with respect to the
energy that defines the inverse temperature. Of
the solid. And this is usually what we. Just plug
in the relation between the energy and the units
of energy that gets. The derivative in terms of
this cave, which already expressed things in the
pick up of what it was in derivatives of the K
through 12 of the law, takes the cake. Listen to
the denominator of two plus one. And similarly,
you get along OK, the negative side. Now, that
minus K over today, which is one cancels out that
we can combine things. Into the temperature given
by the unit of energy that we work with in the
solid. Times, this logarithm of cupolas and
overcatch, which is one plus and over record with
both and K Motors positive numbers could be invert
to bring down the temperature is made up, divided
by this log. We can easily see that the
temperature is indeed positive. We have a lot of
something that is greater than one.
So this. Corresponds to what we call the natural
systems of the MicroCon global context. With the
positive temperature already a contrast with the
spin system, which is where we introduce the idea
of temperatures in the first place. And as we
discussed back in. That needed to come out, so the
natural positive temperature reflects the fact
that more and more microstates are opened up when
we have larger amounts of energy in the system to
unlike the spin system, where it's going to be
filled with so much the maximum amount of energy
that they're able to carry. Here we can just keep
adding more and more use of energy to each of
these oscillators and have more ways of
distributing those using energy among the. Total
number of isolators. Well, as. As he increases.
And I have here flooded the relation between that
cave and the energy itself, because the energy
itself is what we want to isolate in order to get
to the heat capacity. So rearranging this
expression, taking the one off into left hand side
and dividing through body temperature multiplied
by below the exponential rates both sides and
subtract that one can get an elevator for a mega
minus one related to. This and Farmigo divided by
energy, that reorienting again gives us the energy.
Is in today's world divided by this exponential
factor? That is not so dissimilar to the
expansions we were seeing for a full time gas, and
that is. And observation will come back to to wrap
things up, but at this point, we now have the
capacity, the derivative of that energy with
respect to.
The temperature that we can relate to, minus the
spirit times, the derivative with respect to the
inverse temperature, and that is a straightforward
derivative to do the denominator. Brings in a
negative sign that cancels out literally the sign
denominator squared and the chain rule through HBO
may get you to the better part, may go and change
variables to the one that suggested the problem is
X equal, better age. But we can see towers of
better in each of the numerator. So X squared
added to the X to the numerator divided by X minus
one squared. And the denominator.
So this is the result equation one in this in
these comments on the real problem, that is the
that is the capacity for nine states. And the
question now is how does it compare to the
experimental measurements that we started off with
and so on, did not work with the studio system
before getting into that many questions about the
steps coming up to here. Sort of once once the
total number of microstates was expressed in
functional form, it was basically targeting
through the sequence of definitions of reason
before to turn the crank to the capacity. So just
as we did for that school system, we can start by
considering the high, low temperature limits of
the sea capacity and see whether and if so, how
well they respond to what we want to describe
experimentally. And the low temperature limit.
This X is inversely proportional to the T and goes
to infinity is always exponential is a very large
numbers. We can ignore the minus one in the
denominator and end up with something that. As a
factor of the age of the X in the denominator of
vanishes exponentially quickly as the temperature
goes to zero. This is. This vanishing, of course,
is required by that third law of thermodynamics. I
mentioned at the start of this, we know that the
heat capacity has to be limited to the absolute
zero temperature. And the fact that it does so
exponentially quickly is similar to the spin
system and also. A quantitative poll comparing to
experimental data. We'll get into that in just a
bit. We got to check the height of where the
system broke down completely it here and the
exponential E to the X can be expanded into a
power series in the usual way at the leading order.
We can just approximate the X is one of the
numerator and one plus X. The denominator, which
would be minus one, is cancel out leaves and X
squared to cancel the X squared the numerator and
tells us that the heat capacity approach is a
constant value that is non-zero. So rather than.
Dropping back down quadratics, the disorder in the
expansion of the exponential in terms of the
temperature, we see something much more promising
with that cause the dotted line that. Is. That is
possibly consistent with the experimental data.
Overall.
Now, we can also go beyond that, just that leading
asymptotic limit could be equal to the number of
oscillators that actually compute the
leading temperature dependent's to this result.
This is similar to some of the stuff that we do on
the homework. Seem to be graded where the king is,
I'm sure you've seen, is. In the expansion's
keeping enough terms to work with a given how the
mix in the full expression rather than the
numerator or denominator by itself. So expanding
the exponential is to a few orders it out again,
but leaving one of the denominator, we can pull
out of X squared to cancel with the X squared of
the numerator. And then square the remaining terms
later and start with that one squared that have
two times I have X from the crossroads and then we
have again to tie this to one sixth from the
crossroads of X squared, one in the square, and
then another quarter from this over to quantity
squared. That. Three twelfths plus four fouls as
of the Seven Dwarfs, and we can change the
denominator into the geometric series up to now.
Kubic Order in this small X. So we have to retain
up to quadraphonic order, enumerator. And up to
quarter to quarter, both in the term being treated
as small to expand, that is serious as well as the
number of terms in that series the quadratic will
get.
This now just becomes a question of expanding out
this product. One time want to give the living
constitution and then two terms that come in a
linear order. Next, we have. X times one plus one.
Times X and then this minus six times one is a
minus one, so those two terms cancel out at the X
squared level. We can start with product of those
two terms coming in with a plus a half. And then
minus X times X comes in with a minus one minus
seven, 12 X squared times one minus seven plus,
and finally the one times X squared from here
brings in the one to cancel out that we were left
with six twelfths minus seven 12 leaves us with
quadratic dependence on the inverse temperature
and alcohol factor with each bar squared squared
of the twelve. So as shown in this figure, this is
the plot of the exercise on high capacity
approaching that constant factor at high
temperatures vanishing exponentially at low
temperatures. And we just arrived at the rate at
which high temperature limit was approached,
vanishing quite radically in the temperature. So
this plot, at least, is consistent with our
experimental data and the fact that I am flipping
between two sheets of paper, one with the
theoretical prediction of some experimental data
reminds me of.
A saying by the gunman many years ago that in
physics it's customary to put theory and
experiments on the same piece of paper, and that's
something that you can play with during the break
by inserting units for these temperatures. Each
participant to try to match up to the scale with
which the heat capacity is being measured from
these data. Speaking of that scale. It becomes
interesting and actually reveals a flaw in the
design of solid if we zoom in so much lower
temperatures. So rather than the hundreds of
kaledin that we have here, we started looking at
zoomed into Tev about four Kelvin and below 40,
squared up to 18 and plotted on the vertical axis
here, not the heat capacity itself, but rather the
ratio of heat capacity and temperature. We can see
the limit of absolute zero goes to a non-zero
value slightly below one, these units of
individuals per square. It is then. Very well
described by a straight line in T-square, which is
to say that the capacity itself has some linear
peace process that intercept Alpha and a cubit
piece proportional to that that slope gave up in
this plot. And this is, as we mentioned, not what
the unsign solid gibs that predicted next
eventually vanishing chip capacity and zero
temperatures. So we did not have straight lines on
a plot like this. This is a polynomial approach,
in particular, this polynomial. And actually, from
the work we did this morning, we know we recognize
this linear contribution to the heat capacity as
the prediction that we got for a low temperature
for gas through the leading order of the overfill
expansion. We have that result.
Now, the last thing we did this morning, which was
a bit rushed at the end, was fine for the heat
capacity. They said, look, temperature through the
summer. The question is, is PI squared over two
times the number of particles over the feel the
energy policy mix that identifies both the
functional form and the value of this alpha
parameter in PI squared over two times the energy.
Which can be compared to this experimental data to
actually measure the energy of. The electron gas
that we can attribute this this turn its
contribution to heat capacity to.
And we can also actually, just in the last five
minutes, motivate without going through the full
derivation where the tube is coming from and why
the Einstein song gets it wrong.
The key picture is that these oscillators that are
being treated as completely independent body
interact and feel
that they are connected to the very atoms. And in
an actual solid whenever one of these atoms starts
to wiggle around and try to move, it's going to
affect the atoms around it. And you can expect the
movements of atoms in a solid to form a pattern
and in particular this sort of pattern. And I know
sort of skipping through these comments pretty
quickly will get uploaded for you if you. But let
me see the dots. And here is. Representative Adam
along one dimension of itself, and the idea is
that these can be modeled as propagating waves.
The displacements and the atoms from their
composition is correlated with that, the adults
around them. In patterns with wavelength and
frequency, it's just like those we considered for
photons,
the difference with photons, though, is that when
we get to very high frequency, these are very
short wavelengths. There's actually a cutoff on.
How should we like to be? We can't have atoms that
are. Having a collective motion on a shorter
distance scale than actually separates those atoms,
there's nothing collective left behind with this
cut off and the frequency is the maximum frequency
is proportional to the cube root of the number of
atoms, which is different by a factor of three
compared to the number of oscillators. So these
waves in sorrow's collected motion of atoms are
called photons.
And they behaved in some ways quite similarly to
photons. There are other. Important differences,
chief among them being this cut off on the back,
some frequency. So if just to wrap up the first
nine weeks of the module, go back to page 111 and
look at the energy density for a full time gas.
And instead of integrating the frequencies up to
infinity, we cut them off at some maximum
frequency. Let me go through the usual change in
variables that we did I.
Last week, or possibly even two weeks ago now for
the first time, gas, then this X integrity over is
inversely proportional to the temperature and the
integrity is cut off at some function of
temperature. And we can now look at the high, low
temperature behaviors of this at high temperatures
relative to this so-called DIBBY temperature t
study. That is some complicated combination of
constants coming into this way of looking at
things, the so-called bi theory of solids. Well,
that X is very small, we can just expand the
exponential, get to one plus X, minus one X, the
denominator that is a integral to do the role of X
squared is executed. So we end up with three
powers of the temperature from the limit of
integration to cancel out three of the four powers
in temperature. You started off with short on gas.
So we end up with. Energy that is linear in the
temperature, which means a heat capacity that is
constant, and it turns out to be that you actually
go through the calculation the same constant as
the guys solo. Just found one in the units
reported earlier, but of course, the interesting
stuff happens at low temperatures. That's where
the cell breaks down. And the divide approach. Has
this cut off on the education, becomes very large,
approximately, gets back to the full integral from
zero to infinity? We considered in Section eight
with three. Which was that delightful combination
of game of four and three zero four. But the key
is that that is just a constant no high school
over 15. So this for. To the fourth, dependent's
remains in the energy density at low temperatures,
taking a derivative means the heat capacity. Is
vanishing without proportionately to T cubed,
exactly as we saw in this more detailed look at
lower temperatures. So that is. All I have to say
about that really enjoyable to see. Some actual
comparisons with experimental data and the
considerations you have to go through in order to
get realistic physical predictions out of
knowledge, ranking systems could be three weeks.
I'll be in touch in the meantime and start to look
at the complications that show up when we go
beyond the non interactive theories like these and
actually introduce interactions to very
sophisticated physics. So you were able to have an
enjoyable and productive break. I'll see you a few
minutes from.