So we may as well get underway.
Let's deal with the six-digit number before I forget.  For this morning, it is three six
nine nine three zero.
So, we've reached the last day before the spring break,
though it feels less like spring out there than at this
time last week. And we have gotten
through Unit 8 on quantum gases of bosons
and fermions with enough speed that we
have this hour to get a bit more into some of
the fun details justifying some of the claims and
approximations that we went through earlier.
Before digging into that, we can just recall the
brief recap without running things down, since we
are changing gears just a little bit. That's so
far this week we focused on Fortum gases, the
fermions looking both at the non relativistic low
temperatures where we approximated this very
function as a step function. Michael responds to
all energy levels filled up, to be fair, energy
equals to the chemical potential view at zero
temperature and then all higher energy levels
unoccupied or empty. And this had interesting
effects, both in producing a value for the average
particle number, an average natural energy that
we're independent of the temperature, as well as a
non-zero degeneracy pressure that was also
independent of the temperature remaining zero even
at the limit of absolute zero, and is responsible
for processes known as type one supernovas that
have been of great utility to astrophysics and
cosmology. And we then looked a bit more briefly
at the opposite. The ultra relativistic Fergana
gases motivated by neutrinos, which are very
nearly massless particles coming up with a
equation of states that limit that looked a bit
more like what we are used to, almost exactly the
same as the photon gas, just different by a factor
of seven six. So about 20 percent different
numerical factor in the usual relation, TV
proportional to a..
And today.
The plan is to. Build on the novelistic side of
things a bit by asking what happens if we have a
small but not zero temperature to the extent that
we cannot approximate this very function as a
simple step function to a reasonable level of
approximation? We can start to try to start by
asking if there are any questions about what we
have seen this week and the main topic of this
that. We want to go beyond what was. Initially in
the syllabus on the topic of quantum gases of
fermions, just to illustrate one application where
it is indeed necessary to go beyond that low
temperature approximation of the Fermi energy as a
step function, which is if we consider the heat
capacity as the derivative with respect to the
internal energy, the derivative of the internal
energy with respect to the temperature. From the
approximation. Of this family function as a social
function, reminding you here what that full family
function is essentially the. Fairly direct
occupation, number four, an energy level with this
energy e
approximating this as a step function, which is
exactly correct, only the limit of the temperature
going to zero corresponding to the rest of it be
to go into infinity. Then the temperature
independence result for the energy gives us
ignition key capacity, the capacity going to zero.
So we have essentially no information about how
the heat capacity behaves at zero temperature,
what it is related to and with what numerical
factors. And as we saw in last week's tutorial, is
heat capacity is one of the most convenient things
for experimentalists to measure. So it's
worthwhile. Give me a solid prediction for how it
behaves at low temperatures as opposed to in the
limit of absolute zero temperature.
The starting point for this analysis is to go back
to the sort of expression that we had for
political number and think about. What to do with
it when we cannot approximate the very function as
a step function, which is our earlier calculations,
just killed off the whole range of this integral
about equal to you and brought in the factor of
use of the three has. Just the cost of
proportionality in front of it and for convenience,
both in this calculation and if we circle back to
look at those Einstein conversations in the
tutorial after the break, it's convenient to
package. Everything apart from that family
function as some other function, what is known as
the density of estates. So this. Combination of
volume times, the square root of two times the
part of the mass cubed times, the energy all over
the square root and the normal factor pi squared
plus constitute.
Is essentially here just a shorthand that we could
do without that becomes convenient, as you will
see, we're going through the calculations and all
those constants. We can just package into a single.
The variable juice not. That we can plug back in
once we've gone through all of the manipulations.
And the density of states is essentially what it
says on the tin. It is the number of single
particle energy levels for some physical energy
states now expressed as a density, not per unit
volume, but per unit energy. So density of states
is a function of the energy. And we can read this
equation one hundred seven for the average
particle number to be the integral over the number
of energy levels given energy range multiplied by
the very function that gives us the probability
for each of those energy levels to be filled as a
function of that energy. So these two plots here
grab from one of the textbooks in the recommended
supplemental material in the lecture. This is.
Showing how the states, the states and the
integral more generally work out, but in the case
of zero temperature on the left where the family
functioned as a step function, it guarantees that
all states up to the energy are filled, all of
those with the higher energy or empty that shaded.
Which corresponds to field versus MPU states and
the total number of particles manages to go over
that shaded area and the density of states times
their step function. And once we. Go to a.
Strictly positive, but still small temperature, we
pick up some non-zero probability for energy
levels with values of the energy larger than the
energy use of F to be filled. And this did not
come out so well that the overall. No particles
now. Is the area under the solid curve that
multiplies together the density of states,
essentially the square root e times, the constant
and the primary function, that's exponentially
suppresses the probability of energy level with
higher energies being occupied? And one other
thing we can note. About. This way of visualizing
things is that for every one of these. Higher
energy levels that is occupied, the particle
occupying it
at caesura temperature would fit within the range
given by the Fermi Energy. So there is a one to
one correspondence between these occupied higher
energy levels in the unoccupied.
Lower energy levels to the left of that Fairbury
energy at lower energies and the feminine energy,
we can also see that that's due again to the very
energy being set by. The average number of
particles, so that that vertical line, the energy.
Is just counting the number of particles in the
occupied states and the rate of it must match up
one to one with an occupied state to the left. One
other feature of this plot at non-zero temperature
is that the chemical potential now no longer
exactly corresponds to the fear of the energy. If
we go back to the purity function just briefly, we
can see that when the energy equals the chemical
potential, the argument of an exponential function
vanishes. So zero is one and the energy reduces to
one over one plus one half. And this happens at a
value of energy that approaches the Fairbury
energy and the zero temperature limit and is
smaller than the thermal energy for non-zero
temperatures, which is a claim that we can confirm
by actually going through the evaluation of these
bills, both for average particle number and
average internal energy. That's. As we saw in our
earlier work, differ only by the presence of an
extra factor of the energy being carried by
particles that are being counted.
So before diving into the mathematics of how to
evaluate this as you go through this check to see
that no questions about the basic motivation or
setup we're going to here.
And not seeing any. You will go through what is
called the Somerfield expansion, something that
was mentioned last week, I think with the
temperature independence limit being just the
first term in this expansion. And what we will see
is that the Somerfield expansion is really just a
glorified timber expansion where the real work is
done in setting up the problem in a form where it
faler expansion that can be justified looking at.
The stuff is complicated integrals that involve
square roots of energy divided by exponential
functions in the energy. So the first step in
Zurfluh expansion is to integrate by parts. And
because it's been a while since you've done
integration bypass, I'll just remind you of the
schematic setup that we have something to go and
we can express as a function. You times the
differential factor of the different function.
D.V. and this is equal to, again, schematically,
the product of those two functions. You would be
evaluated the integration minus the integral of
the function v the differential to you. So to
apply this integration by parts to integrated. Of
the average particle, no. What we do is identify
that function, you as the family function itself,
which we're no longer approximating as a step
function, and then DV is everything else. So that
square root, the times, which means that the
corresponding function V. Is each of the three
halves power with a two thirds in front to cancel
off the power and get back to that differential
for so.
Putting in this identification into the integral
that we have, we have you times V is. Two thirds
energy, the three times that fermenters year
function you evaluated at energy equals zero and
infinity, and then we subtract off two thirds of
the integral zero to infinity. Of the three times
the differential over you, which is the derivative
of the family function. Times the differential to
now.
The first term was called the boundary term, we
have particularly simple results, we've seen that
that Fermoy function is always some number between
zero and one. So with some finite number is
multiplied by zero zero. And the limit where the
energy goes to infinity is to pull up every
function again and look at that for any non-zero
temperatures will find a better. As he goes to
infinity, the exponential factor is large, the
fear, the energy goes to zero zero again. So all
of these battery terms. They both the initial go
to zero. And we can repackage the remainder of the
integral as two thirds. I was the integral of
minus derivative of the function and the energy to
be free Avesta
and.
Looking at the. Negative, integral with respect to
energy of the family function, she can achieve the
end of energy, minus the potential plus one to the
minus one power. Taking the derivative of that
brings that exponential factor. Down into
numerator with that extra power squared, and then
the chain will move with minus one factor for the
power cases up front, the chain rule then gives us
a factor of theta times due to. So that's why this
new.
And we can change variables to make this a bit
more compactly, especially to the X, X plus one.
Involving the X plus one squared where X is this
combination. Of the difference in energy minus
chemical potential.
So plugging that in to the
grid that we have, we end up with. Same two thirds
integral from zero to infinity will now be able to
go over this. One of the X.
And you can just rate. The integrated. Is the X?
Over the years, plus one squared.
Times either the power of three has taken that
data from the. Derivative you and bringing it into
a differential factor which could be recognized as
the differential factor of.
X with the ID, that one equals zero at the lower
level of integration, X is minus the Times MU. So
we out of.
Terms of. X with just this residual. Factor of
energy to the three house power left over.
But this expression here that if you drive.
If we plug in the overall collection of constants
zero that appears in the density of states, it was
Eurocracy factor relating the average particle
number to this particular integral. And it might
be the question, why go through the trouble of his
credit cards just to end up with something that
looks like such a mess with ratios of exponential
and a term that has already that is now related to
X and someone that obviously the advantage of
doing this, which. Sommerfeld, that was smart
enough or skilled enough to see and we can
appreciate by looking at the figure at the bottom
of this page, is to recognize that by casting the
integral in this for. We have something that is.
Exponentially suppressed both in the region of
large X, where that the denominator is
approximately E to the X squared, in the case of
the other people, the X with the numerator, we end
up with one over an exponentially worse number,
but it's also exponentially suppressed. The
opposite of it when X is a very negative number,
margin lending to small zero, where the
exponential of a large negative number is much
less than one. And the.
Overall, integrated is then or can be expressed as
one over another, exponentially large number
exponentially with minus X, which is a much larger
one, and the remaining factor of X of the three
halves coming from that energy. Can't really do
anything about an exponential factor. Suppressing
things, and I've left that. That could be the
three halves of the plot here, what we could see.
Is it sharply function around? The region where
the energy is equal to the chemical potential,
this combination is being the time square minus
new, centered around zero. And this rapidly dies
off as this combination of quantities becomes even
just
a factor of a few. And certainly by the time we
are five, there's almost nothing left in the tail
on either side of this function. The important
thing is the appearance of BITA and that
accommodation, which means that. If we fix the
temperature at a low value that corresponds to a
large volume of beta, then we don't have to shift
very far away in absolute terms of the energy from
away from that chemical potential in order for the
Interbrand to be completely negligible. So this
factor of five that I pointed out here corresponds
to the absolute value of embarrassment greater
than about five times the temperature. So the
lower the temperature, the quicker this
exponential suppression sets in.
And that is the. The Senate version of the bill
came up with, which allows two approximations
valid at low temperatures, the first of which is
to simplify the structure of this integral change
of the lower limit of integration that was minus
daytime's view. If we consider the. The limit of a
large data set to something greater than you might
be under 10 or more, you can see that.
Emerging, this region of integration is bringing
in all the major contributions that don't show up
in this plot from a region of very small X, so we
are free to include those in with the integration
domain that. Is it more convenient to work with?
When we actually try to evaluate these integrals
in order to put that back on the screen there, in
order to actually evaluate these integrals, we
need to handle this factor of each of the three
hands, which is a second approximation we can do
through a Taylor expansion. I mentioned expanding
the energy around MUE. Precisely because this is
the region where the integration is not negligible
and this becomes a very narrow region as the
temperature decreases, so the first few terms in
this Taylor expansion, we start off with just that
central value, usually the three halves, and then
take the derivative of each of the three as set
equal to view and multiply that by the linear
factor so that derivatives just brings down the
power. Three halves we set to view the remaining
square root factor and the next term does the same
thing with the second derivative. So we bring down
first. A factor of three has been another factor,
one half gets three quarters tops. Another factor
of one half gets three eighths. The square
displacement is minus two. And now the result of
two derivatives into the three halves is key to
the minus half. That is set to the chemical
potential, which we can now rewrite in terms of
integer powers of X.
This.
We recall, oops. Is.
This actor, by the time, has the energy Midas
chemical potential. So each of these is new terms,
is a power of X over data. And by virtue of having
X raised to an integer power in the resulting
integrals, it becomes something much more
tractable than trying to integrate the square root
of execute.
So. If we just rewrite those babies as we're in
terms of the temperature we have. A few leading
terms for the average particle, no, in terms of
particles that we can consider one by one. So the
first term in this expansion is just the constant
attention to the three halves that gets pulled out
of this integral over. Frightened to go of the X
over the X plus one square, so we need to evaluate
that. We need to evaluate the next term that has
one factor of X showing up alongside the
exponential factors and of the extremities, the
powers of X, so X squared times the X over the X
plus one.
In the interest of time, I'll just charge through
these integrals. Show you how they're done that
rather than leaving them for you to work on. The
trick to the first interview was to go back to.
The integration by parts we did a few minutes ago
and recognize that this. It's the X or the X plus
one squared is closely related to the derivative
of the family function, in particular, if you keep
track of all the factors, the data can see that up
to a negative sign. This integration is just. The
derivative of that very function as a function of
energy integrated over that energy rather than
over X, as we have defined it, like the integral
of a derivative, just gives us the value of that
function. That's why it is the. Antiderivative,
and this is evaluated, but the energy is minus
infinity to infinity,
recalling that very function that we have here is
just integrated between zero and one. This limit
where the energy is plus or minus infinity is
exactly where this function becomes zero or one.
So when the energy is infinite, this is a very
large exponential factor for a non-zero up finite
or any finite data, which is the right temperature
and whatever. A very large number, then infinitely
large number. Those to zero to the other limit of
E going to negative infinity again for a finite.
We have a very small number and B for every
function goes to one. So that's what that integral
is, just one.
The second integral. We can do a similarly simple
calculation just by. Expanding out the square in
the denominator's, this is two powers of the X
plus one. And then if we divide through by X in
the numerator, we end up with. Is the integral of
X over one of those factors, B, B, B, X, plus one,
the dividing through gives us one plus E to the
minus X over X. And we can see that this
denominator now is symmetric if we exchange the
gate X, so replacing X goes to Windows X, we just
swap these two terms in parentheses. So that is an
even function in the denominator. It's obviously a
function of the numerator. I heard the results
coming from from you already, the integration of
an overall odd function. Across a domain, that
symmetrical ground zero is indeed zero, and this
would actually hold for.
All of the higher terms in this Taylor expansion
that you have. The powers of X in these tentacles,
so we can already know that the T cubed term here
is going to vanish and the fourth is going to be
the first power that we have collected. I guess
the interesting thing happens now. When we have
the T squared, a term that is proportional to this
final integral X squared plus one squared. So this
is even if the goal is not varnishing, it's not
just a antiderivative. And what we can do here is,
again, go through integration by parts. Really, we
said that function. You want to be the X squared
and then give. Is everything else you'd be next or
even next? Plus one squared the X. Which, as we
have seen, is that VSL is the negative ferry
function. I just want everything to be X plus one
and. Just.
As before, we will get. The.
Very out. It is actually convenient here to note
that because this is an even function, I forgot to
drive that argument to its conclusion. We can
change the meaning of integration to be zero to
infinity with just a factor of two. For each side.
Of. That symmetric debate of integration and now
putting in. You times V, you get minus two X
squared. X plus one evaluated at zero and infinity,
and then the subtraction cancels out the negative
sign you have twice the integral of. View, which
is to ex again over either the ex plus one.
Now, just as you saw in our first integration by
parts, just when it's convenient to change the
standard of integration, we have the fabric
function times SULABH something proportional to
the energy and that energy is zero zero, sort of
the numerator of the energy goes to infinity. We
get zero from the infinitely large factor in the
denominator. We are again left with no so-called
boundry term and just the integration over. X
divided by X plus one, which is an integral we
have seen before. Let me see if I can track it
down in a reasonably short amount of time.
When we were looking at the ultra relativistic gas
of neutrinos, you had a couple of particles of
this form, axis of power divided by the X plus one,
the X. And we saw a general expression for. Those
integrals in terms of numerical factors, gamma
functions and Zeta functions going power lower. So
rather than dwelling on the
experience of the ex, we have to go over to X
times, even the X, so there's no overall factor of
four that we have already. There is that one minus
one over to the one power. Now the pre factor and
then you a function of two and Z the function of
two.
Get a function of two is one factorial, which is
one four times a half is two and three one zero
function with only the two to pick it up or I'll
just tell you, it is over six. So the result of
this integral is high speed over three and. One,
the is in to her expression.
The average price number, the first thing to go
was just one second. Zero zero third integral is
high school level three, which we collect gives us
this expression. Is that cost factor that depends
on you to the three halves. And then PI squared
over three times, four times the temperature
squared divided by the square root of the chemical
potential. So in restoring this constant vector.
In the density of states. We have. To. Times
Square two is the three of two or three times
higher than the previous path, potentially again
divided by three per square each barbequed, which
is exactly what we found in the limit of zero
temperature with the step function approximation
for the very function. And we now have the leading
correction to that, which depends quite
dramatically on the temperature and has a one over
square root chemical potential term similar to
that with similar factors of the mass of the three
power plants constant, chilled by squares, cancel
out with that rebound, say the function of two.
This actually becomes even more interesting if we
express it in terms of the family energy, a way to
wrap up the average part of the of convenience for
what we saw already with the density of states. So
kicking the three has power of both sides of this
equation gives us a huge. Over
two into the three handles China threatens to lead
to. Q And then the terms in parentheses are
reasonably linear power, there's a three PI
squared.
An average particle, no, in the factor of the
volume. Which we can. Recognize, I've written this
here, that volume times routes to include is the
numerator of zero. That's pi squared cubed shows
up with nominator. So if I replace. Everything but
the three have end with. This G zero relation
between. The cost factor and the density of states
and the energy. To the three power.
Which plugging things in to this equation here. V0.
Equals three and the two, if you're one of the
three, Halsy. Three halves and two thirds cancel
out.
And we end up with just and three times this ratio
of view over here to the three haves. And if
something similar happens in the second term. G
zero is three, pi squared, T three has divided by
12 is three eighths
or sorry, one of the three Kansas 12 the four
which is double to eight. So there is again that
be a factor of average particle number PI squared
T squared over eight. Times that energy, the three
haves just as the previous term, and then the
square root of chemical potential. And what is?
Fun about writing things in this way is that we
now have. With the average particle number wrapped
up in the Fairbury function. The explicit
dependence on the average particle, no cancels out
and we can rearrange to isolate this ratio of
chemical potential in terms of units of the Fermi
energy.
Which of the left hand side we have, the one that
we can subtract from that square to square over.
It's very interesting to the three house, to the
square root, and then raise everything to the two
thirds power to pick out just that ratio. So that
is what is written below. We have successfully
reproduced. Target. And again, considering low
temperatures and neglecting the order key to the
fourth terms. We can just expand this Powerball.
As one minus two thirds times, this factors that
two or three to six that date back up to 12, and
because the second term is already small, we will
introduce a small error from setting the ferry
energy to be the chemical potential, which is
which is at zero temperatures. The error in this
identification is coming in at order of
temperature squared and is part of a term that is
under the order temperature squared. So overall,
that is accurate up to terms for neglecting the
fourth power in the temperature relative to the
family function. And that that combines those
three has one power into an overall function
squared. And we end up with this equation is known
as a consistency condition. That comes from the
average particle, but doesn't explicitly depend on
that, apart from, as it appears, within the fairly
energy. I see that the free energy approaches the
chemical potential as the temperature goes to zero,
and then we've derived a living correction, which
is indeed negative, decreasing the chemical
potential, which is exactly what we claimed at the
start of the supplement. So this is one of those
claims justified and. And check to see if there
are questions about the Sommerfeld expansion that
we have now gone through to meeting order to get
this result.
So looking at the time, we have to. Final pieces
in this little supplemental. We can get through
one of those documents, remember this morning,
circle back to the other one in the afternoon. We
need a tutorial. This is a supplement anyway, so
no harm then shifting just the last couple of
paragraphs to the tutorial. You can go much more
quickly through the computation of the average
internal energy. Which, as we have seen is. Set up
almost the same as the average particle, no, just
brings an additional factor of energy. So overall
power of energy to the three haves. Rather than
energy to the one has to be integrated, so the
only difference in integrated parts is that we end
up with that function is now two fifths of the
five halves, two thirds of the three halves. So
change in the numerical factor and the function of
energy that we are going to be putting through our
expansion, having reformulated things. In the
sharp explosion around. Equal to you, the Taylor
expansion itself is almost the same. You just pick
up different numeric factors for taking the
derivative into the five halves. We also have
different powers of view that appear in these
first three terms. So five has three 1/2 and
positive one half rather than the three halves and
plus or minus half that came from the previous
magic number. And plugging all of this in, we find
that we have to deal with the same integrals which
we found to be one zero and PI squared over three.
So at the end we have the average internal energy
give it in terms of the chemical potential as we
use the five halves, plus a correction that is
again, quadratic in the temperature and now
depends on the square root of new.
And just as we did at the top of this page, we
want to get things in terms
of the very energy which we will see provide some
elegant results. So this due to the five have
power coming from
our results for the approval number. We have to
move the very energy to the right hand side, and
this is approximately be energy to the five gas
power times the factor, one minus 30 squared over
12 if. Also raised to the five house power.
And similarly expanding.
This. Small deviation from one is one minus that
five has power of that function, we have the the
five halves times one. And then minus five hands,
so that gives us five twenty four times PI squared,
T squared and then A.
Lingering factor of.
So this thing is here that is squared. So even the
five haves divided by each of the four has
lipshitz that square root of the Fermi Energy. And
plugging this in for that view, the five helps
power in the average internal energy to free
energy leaves us. With that first term. Three
fifths.
No times.
If to the five heads of the three hats is a single
factor of energy sucking in the second term here
into the first term. And the expression for the
control energy, we have three fifths times five
twenty fourth leaves us with one eight times
cancel and twenty four with three states. We have
another factor of average particle number PI
squared and then T squared. And then.
E two, the one half divided by E to the three
hands is a factor of one over the ferry energy.
And then finally the second term here we can, as
we did before, to collect the order T-square
correction in the order to use the term dropping
that order, the fourth correction. So this is a
plus three Ade's. Average particle, no. PI squared,
T squared and now E to the one half over each of
the three has again. Very interesting in the
denominator.
In other words, we have the.
The factor that we derived earlier this week was
internal energy had zero temperature is I consider
proportional to the particle number with that
factor of three fifths that we saw. And then three,
it's minus one is two aides or a quarter of PI
squared. Oftentimes, that is part of the number
and a factor that is quadratic in the temperature,
which gives us if we take the derivative with
respect to temperature, we have the linear term in
temperature left over. And that's. Quarter becomes
a half, and I have this sign there, which is
positive, three eighths minus one. It was positive
the quarter and we have a non-trivial, huge
capacity for the gas at low temperature that is
linear in temperature with a no MPRI factor factor
that we have now derived. You can't compare with
experimental data, which is some people say for
this afternoon. So. Sorry to run a couple of
minutes over to reach this result, the low
temperature heat capacity for a non relativistic
of yes. Which we will see at play this afternoon,
looking at the same experiment they started
discussing in terms of STEM last week. So
immediate questions shouted out otherwise. We'll
see you back here in a few hours.