Okay, good morning, we'll get underway. Welcome to
May, after the long bank
holiday weekend.   Let's see, I should have a six-digit code for this
morning somewhere in this plan.  And it is four eight,
two seven, nine eight.
Let's see what we have for this week: the final
homework assignment due Thursday. If there are any
questions about that, this is an opportunity to
bring those up.
Alternately, let's do a quick review of what we've been
up to since coming back from the spring break last
week concerning interacting systems. So the
third of.
And.
Our focus on. These interactive systems. Obviously
is centered on the easy model, looking at this in
some detail and from several perspectives,
different numbers of dimensions in the story, we
look at different structures and over this week,
we're looking at different ways of approximating,
solving and otherwise analyzing the system. And
maybe I should emphasize more than I have, that
this is not only because the easy model is very
widely useful and broadly applicable, but a lot of
these techniques and concepts are more generally
applicable to all sorts of its existence. In
particular, the question of. These transitions
that we used as motivation and looking at the easy
model. Where we eventually built up to a rigorous
definition of what it is, as opposed to just a
change in the system as it's controlled, that is
very. And we're leading these phase transitions to
the behavior of. So-called border branders.
Where?
The order parameter is some derivative of the free
energy, the log of the protection function at
ADFIS transition is either discontinuous or
exhibits a discontinuity in some derivative of
that order parameter with respect to some of the
control parameters of the system. So of the easy
case, we mapped out the general setting of.
Ordered phase that a period of low temperatures
with this water parameter, the easy model, this
magnetization is rigorously non-zero while at high
temperatures the.
System is in a disordered phase where the sort of
parameter is exactly zero at least.
In the thermodynamic limit, where there are
infinitely many degrees of freedom and to make the
decision here as. Advertize.
To be in order parameter, it should be a
derivative of the free energy or proportional to
that derivative and the explicit. Expression for
this is the derivative with respect to the
external magnetic field, each of the using bottle
of that modular partition function that gives us
the. The free energy, so we call it the free
energy, is minus T Z. This is just the negative
one and the derivative of that free energy. So.
With that all set up, the question for the easy
model becomes, is the magnetization or its
derivatives with respect to the temperature
discontinuous at any point between is ordered and
disordered phases at low at high temperature?
Respectively. So.
To look into that's getting away from the liberty
cases and looking at what happens between them,
our first strategy is to come up with an
approximate description of the using model.
This main field approximation. Is based on an
effective field. So it's effective, which is.
Related to the input external magnetic field, but
also brings in dependence on that order parameter
of Americanization with the factor of two
depending on the dimensions. And qualitatively.
This is replacing the interactive term in using
model with this external field that depends on
qualitatively the meaning of the average of. The
nearest neighbor spends for each. Degree of
freedom that gets incorporated into an effective
field, and that's the sort of way to remember that
minefield terminology.
Even back to where we wrapped up on a Friday.
Based on.
The resulting energy and petition function that
removes those interactions by replacing them with
this effective female, you will see that not only
is the order parameter still related to the
resulting free energy, the log of this new fuel
production function, the production function
itself. Depends on that order parameter, the
magnetization. So this relationship then gives us
a self consistency condition for the organization
directly considered as the. Three parameters are
essential in. This expression, which we can solve
to. Find out. What possible values of your
parameter are consistent with this Medfield
approximation? So that gets us back up to where we
were to see if there are questions about that or
related issues before going on to. Look at some
solutions to the self-consistent condition
equation 117.
And not hearing any locally or remotely.
Let's motivate a fairly straightforward if you
build up so mathematically elegant way of looking
for solutions to self-consistent the conditions of
this sort. One way of phrasing them is that we're
trying to. Find the roots of the complicated
hyperbolic trigonometric equation, believing the
chance of X and X itself, but at least if we are
only interested in the solutions, we can
investigate this just by putting these two
functions and seeing where they are the same. So
this figure at the bottom of the page here, we do
this for essentially the simplest possible case
where you fix these two dimensions. The
temperature, your data is one over four, so the
temperature itself is four, and then all of the
terms in the tank are multiply up to one. We set
that extreme in the field age to zero. And now
we're just looking for the solution when the
hyperbolic tangents of the magnetization equals
the magnetization itself, we can see from
inspecting this diagram that there must be at
least one crossing between these two continuous
functions, that large positive values of that
magnetization along the horizontal axis. It's
clear that the candidate approaches one as a
limiting value. And itself can greatly exceed one.
The opposite happens at negative values. The
magnetization. So on one side, X is larger than on
the other side, it's smaller and right in the
middle. Exactly. At. X equals zero is where we
have the one possible solution to the minefield
self-consistent condition in this zero field case
for temperature for. And we can recall that the
vanishing order parameter is associated with the
disorder phase, which hopefully will prove to be
consistent with the interpretation we want to get
out of this whole approximation, making the easy
model, not a tracking system.
So what we can now do, starting from the simplest
possible case, is turn that magnetic field back on
and the self-consistent since self-consistent the
condition and also check what happens for
different temperatures, which were the temperature,
the control parameter that we focused on last week
identified the two phases of the using model. And
just by inspecting the argument of this Tange, we
can see that if we have a positive value for the
external magnetic field, then all we would need to
do is shift the value of the magnetization to get
the same argument to the tank that we had down
here. So we should expect if we fix that
temperature of the quarter, that a non-zero
memorisation, particularly positive magnetization
will shift this Tange curve to the left smaller
values and to cancel out the positive age and vice
versa when it's negative. And that is exactly what
happens. And that is shown in this
next. So keeping of one over four and turning on
either each of two, which is this green curve or
each of negative two, which is the blue curve. And
I simply read those off by seeing the positive age
shifted to negative values. And vice versa for the
negative. Now, what happens to the intersections
in this case is that they are shifted away from
zero disordered magnetization, pick up a non-zero
value in each case, particularly for the positive
magnetic field. We come up with a positive value
for the order parameter, approximately four point
nine. And it's mirror image for the negative
magnetic field, which is pleasingly exactly what
we would expect when turning on an external
magnetic field or the using model. The non-zero
value of the magnetization that corresponds, it
has the same sign, the magnetic field, so it
corresponds to the spins in the system showing the
preference to align with the magnetic field so as
to lower the overall energy of the system. That is
also we identified as we ordered phase with a
non-zero value for the parameter.
So now we have one more control parameter to
adjust, the one we're really interested in. What
happens when the temperature varies in a
particular?
What happens is the temperature decreases that we
expect to. Enhance this ordering based on the
limited cases we consider last week,
going back to the right hand side of our self
consistency condition, a lower temperature is a
larger beta overall factor on everything else. And
the argument to the Tange. So that means that any
small change in the magnetization is going to be
enhanced by that larger beta temperature. So the
argument of the Tange is changing more quickly
with the magnetization. So we should expect to
change to approach its limiting values plus or
minus one more rapidly. The magnetization varies.
Obviously, I'm not putting units on horizontal
axis of maybe I should, they are kept all the same.
So by comparing. These two. Sets of solutions to
self consistency, condition for a.
Relatively high temperature to. T equals four and
now a lower temperature, half that T of two with
the same non-zero values for the magnetization.
You can see the steeper slope in the and more
rapidly as advertised, that corresponds to a
greater degree of alignment at the. Solution, the
single solution in the is a condition for each of
these fields, which is to several significant
figures. Plus or minus one for the organization
corresponding to the positive and negative
external fields, if a lower temperature enhances
the system's inclination to align with that
external field and of course, the limiting values
of the Tange, which is always between minus one
and one place, limits on all possible solutions of
that self-consistent C condition. So the
magnetization that is predicted can only ever be
between minus one and one, which is also
consistent with how we have defined that
magnetization back to something over all of the
spins in the system rather than looking at the
algebraic properties of. The derivatives of the
free energy. With respect to the control parameter.
So.
Those three sets of plots essentially illustrate a
straightforward strategy to identify solutions to
these sorts of self-consistent conditions and
questions about those before we really drive
through. Now to the search for a possible phase
transition and to check to see whether there
really is a divergence in romanticisation or not.
So now that we've seen the.
Basic behavior, we can go back to the.
Main situation that we are interested in setting
that external field to zero and varying the
temperature when we did this is where we saw the
two different phases high temperature disorder,
phase of the temperature audit phase in the easy
model in the previous section. So we'll turn off
that magnetic field, getting back to that
intersection at. And equals zero as a solution to
sell the self-consistent consistency condition and
then prepare three different values of the
temperature, two of which we've seen before, the
green line, that two equals four was the very
first case we started off with, with that single
self-consistent solution at identifying value of
the memorisation to be associated with the
disorder phase. And the lower temperature T equals
two and the blue line is what we were considering
at the presence of the magnetic field previously.
So now turning off that magnetic field shifts the
steeper blue curve back to be centered around
varnishing magnetization and just for symmetry
around the starting point of temperature for a
double double, let's look at the red curve for
each year of age, which even more clearly than the
green. True, we started off with has only the
single solution. At varnishing zation, so as the
temperature increases, you stay in the disordered
phase of. That is our interpretation of that
self-consistent solution, what we want to focus on.
Is the lower temperature case, so it is hard to
beat, it is a half. Well, now that we've shifted
the Tange back to be centered around zero, there
turn out to be three possible solutions to
self-consistent the condition. Three intersections
of the. Two curves on the spot, the dotted line,
that is just the magnetization itself, M equals M
and then the blue curve, that is the cash, the
derivative of the free energy.
So. For convenience, we'll say that these non-zero
solutions are at some. Plus and minus and knots,
which, as the temperature gets lowered further and
further in this curve, becomes deeper and deeper
and intersection gets closer and closer to the
limiting values. I'm not going to one that
correspond to the ground states of this zero fuel
system.
The question now is what to make of there being
three different solutions to the self-consistent
condition and what we need to do is. Take a brief
excursion outside of static equilibrium. And think
about what happens if we were if the system
happens to fluctuate away from one of these
self-consistent conditions, is it pushed back
toward the value of the mechanization that it is
very close to or is it pushed away from that value?
And if you just to elaborate on this handwaving,
discussion of pushing. We're thinking of the
system itself as some sort of blind process that
is simply attempting to satisfy its self as the
condition, it's trying to find values of the
motivations that.
Corresponds to intersections on these plots, but
all I can tell is whether or not the magnetization
is too small or too large compared to the
derivative of the three energy. Essentially, all
it knows is. The difference between the two sides
of that equation. And then if the magnetization is
too small, the system will try to raise it. If the
magnetization is too low, the system will try to
lower it and try to raise it. Trying to get back
to the. A situation where self consistency is
satisfied.
So
focusing on. The blue curve, the low temperature,
where we have these three solutions, if we look at
what happens right around. That's self-consistent
point with the magnetization varnishes, if we go
to some infinitesimally small positive values,
though, won't all fit on the screen. So go down.
Go back and forth between the port and the
discussion, so if we look at.
Just on the positive side of the zero
marketisation axis, you can see that the
magnetization, the dotted line. Is too low
compared to the hyperbolic catch the game that it
wants to be for self consistency. So as we just
described, the magnetization is too low. The
system will try to raise it to get back to its
consistency. So it will be pushed to larger values
of the organization, to the right of the spot
where, of course, once we get out there, we can
see that the self consistency condition turns out
to be even more badly violated. The magnetization
is still too low and it gets pushed further out of
the way until it reaches. The next intersection,
next, self-consistent points with a non-zero value
for the order parameter corresponding to the order
phase, and exactly the opposite happens for
infinitesimally small negative values of
evangelisation. And see, the position itself is
now too large compared to the. Hyperbolic tangent,
this is not enough. So the system then tries to
lower it, pushing it out to more negative values
all the way until it hits that negative solution
of the self-consistent condition. So any deviation
away from that perfect balance of vanishing
mechanization will lead the system to settle and
reach equilibrium or recover equilibrium.
The. And in order to face with the large non-zero
value of the marketization.
Maybe an alternative way of looking at this is to
recast this.
Graphical way of searching for self-consistent
locations to instead of plotting the hyperbolic
tangent and mechanization separately looking for
intersections Clotaire difference and look for
routes, look for points for that difference
vanishes. So as before, there are there's always a
routine self-consistent point advantage in
legislation and at lower temperatures, we can have
three points at zero plus or minus. No, not.
And now we can essentially rephrase or reiterate
that discussion of the system as a process that is
supposed to satisfy, we feel of consistency when
this difference is greater than zero, that means
that the legislation is too small to completely
cancel out the Tange. So the system will try to go
to larger values and naturalisation. Pushing off
to the right on the spot, so any positive value
for these curves corresponds to a push to drive to
larger volumes of liberalisation and similarly,
negative values of magnetization is too large to
be self-consistent,
overwhelms the tension, produces a negative, a
difference. So the system will push it to smaller
values. Off to the left. Looking at how these
three curves that we've had for three different
temperatures behave around that. Self-consistent
point they all have when the temperature is high,
these dynamics
restore that equilibrium. Any deviation from the
vanishing position will be pushed back towards the
vanishing magnetization from the left and right.
And the opposite happens when. The temperature
becomes lower around that point, advancing their
position is small deviation, pushed away and
enhanced until it settles down at the non-zero
value responded to the ordered phase. So any
questions about that whole argument based on self
consistency and the search for solutions to our
self consistency, condition for the order
parameter of the Beeville approximation?
The conclusion that. We're able to take away from
this way of looking at the system is that we are
at least capturing the expected high temperature
phases of the easy model through this, not
attracting the fuel approximation. And high
temperatures, we see some consistency, demands,
varnishing magnetization. Which corresponds to the
disordered phase and then lower temperatures. Lead
to a system that gets pushed to a non-zero value,
just as we would expect in the order to face.
And now now that we have a non interacting system
that still retains some information about to be
interactions in the using model that have been
wrapped up in this effective field based on the
values of this nearest neighbor, spin's we can.
Do a bit more than it's possible for the U.S.
model itself in general and. Search for the value
of the temperature at which this 090 is
magnetization solution becomes unstable, and these
values with the solutions to the self-consistent a
condition with a non zero ordered base or the
parameter appear. So. You saw about looking back
to our initial discussion here, that in order for
there to be three intersections, you would need to
have the hyperbolic tangent be larger than.
At some positive, positive value of the
organization, so asymptotically of our values of
smaller.
And at zero, if we want to have an additional
crossing of these two curves, in addition to the
zero points, we would then necessarily have to
have all the cash that has a fund that is larger
than that. This is a way of describing in words
what we can easily see from this plot, what
happens at that intersection, the derivative of
the free energy goes from being. Smaller than in
itself to be larger. So. A way of putting that now
from pictures through words and into mathematics
is that we need the slope of that tangent right at
the.
Solution to the is the condition at varnishing
magnetization to be greater than one so that the
cancer becomes larger than M for the positive
value of M.
So because we're looking right around this point
where the argument of the cash is small, right
around zero, we can go ahead and expand that Tange
as a. Serious. So the argument is.
This with magnetic field set to zero, is two times
the inverse of the times, the dimensionality times
order parameter. So.
This is just Exit's arguments to beat up the end,
that's approximately zero, and then. Plus, the
something an order. Of that magnetization, Kud. So
we won't be derivative of this with respect to the
magnetization on the horizontal axis here. And you
want, after taking the derivative to set the
position to zero, even if we had included
arbitrarily many higher order terms in that
particular expansion, they all would have had
leftover values of the magnetization that would
kill them off when we set them to zero. The only.
Term that remains is in this derivative is to be
the derivative of a linear term, reduces the
constant and we want that, we want to know when
that equals. One, which is the boundary between
there being only a single solution to the disorder,
vanishing bastardisation or all three solutions
that allow the order of things to appear so two
times the inverse temperature times the equals one.
That means simply that the temperature itself is
the inverse of that two times the just one over a
critical to. So we have a very simple prediction
from the field approximation for the critical
temperature of the using model in any number of
dimensions at critical temperature should just be
the main field. Tells us two times the
dimensionality.
Which actually is a fact to be
considering earlier these three lines here with
the dimensionality to. Are just T equals to D. So
the green line, both in the intersection and we
look at the difference actually corresponds to the
two dimensional critical temperature. Which is, in
fact, why the slope of this difference is
vanishing for that reason, why they're so. The
three values of the temperature were chosen with
some and here to be for two dimensions, the
critical value that half of that and double that.
And. The next question, I should say, I've been
calling this a critical temperature to you, Steve,
but I haven't actually shown that there is
critical behavior at this temperature critical to
your being, that situation we discussed with some
discontinuity or divergence in the order parameter
itself or the derivative of that order parameter
with respect to the temperature of.
So in order to search for. Discontinuities in that
or we need to express myself as a function of.
Which is going to. The possible by.
Getting back to the self-consistent mission that
we've been considering all along.
Setting. The order parameter equal to the
derivative of the free energy, that, in turn
depends on the order parameter. And then. We can.
Anticipate that.
Well, we are interested in looking at the critical
temperature to see if it is a critical temperature.
Any discontinuity or divergence of the order
parameter is going to appear at this, see? But
this is precisely the value where the.
A stable solution of the self-consistent condition
for any changes from a zero to a non-zero value,
and I mentioned this to motivate the conclusion
that for temperatures around to see. We can
conclude that the order perimeter itself is much
smaller than one, it's just when it starts to
become non-zero, depending on the temperature is
infinitesimally larger or smaller. So we can
expand a hyperbolic tangent again with our
expansion.
For small values. Of the magnetization and hear
here to. Keepa.
The. Two leading terms in order to have something
that doesn't cancel out on either side of this
equation. So it's up to be magnetization, Kud.
Neglecting, at least for the moment, the higher
order, fifth power of the magnetization from the
expansion of the Tange,
cancel out magnetization from each side of that
equation, further plug in that to itself. Is. He
said, well, data is the inverse temperature, one
over 80, so can't those things out and rearranging
things we have. The negative one third to the left
hand side of the equation. It becomes a positive
one third and then to do is to see Peter is one of
the team that is killed and there is a
magnetization squared coming along with it. Then
on the other side of the equation, we have to deal
over two times, Peter, just to see over Oberti.
Minus the one position that we can't cancel out.
So this is simple enough to solve for that
magnetization. Then if we take the square root, we
get plus or minus solutions with. A three year
value of.
T of the T C now cubed.
The square root of three haves.
And then.
One half power of T, C over T minus one.
If we pull out a there's a one 1/2 there.
We can simplify this slightly by pulling out. A.
Take over tea from this factor and. Making the
argument that a large power of tea over to sea,
around the critical temperature that we're working
with to get a small value of the mechanization
means that this overall factor is approximately
one, you can't be neglected. So. Approximately
dropping that factor and keeping only the square
three. We have an.
Instead of the T minus one, one minus T, T, C to
the one half hour. And obviously, we want the
argument to the square root to be a positive
number to keep the organization.
Real and not imaginary, and that actually matches
up with something that I glossed over when
motivating small.
Which is that we were considering temperatures
that are lower than.
The political temperature not higher than critical
temperature, but still very close to it to justify
this approximation of the small magnetization. So.
With a little shortness of space in that gap, we
did. We cover the. Stated resolve here we can.
Distribute. Replace the one by taxi over taxi and
rate the non-zero value of the mechanization as.
This square root factor, T minus T over T to the
one half power. Which goes smoothly to zero as t
approaches to see.
So coming from.
Below, from the audit phase, the non-zero value of
the magnetization goes straight to zero at this to
see where it matches that the stable value from
the self-consistent condition for the disorder
phase. So for all value to the temperature at the
parameter in itself is continuous.
It approaches zero from the left and right, but in
different ways, it's always zero in the disordered
phase at high temperatures and vanishes like a
square root power of the difference in the control
parameter for lower temperatures and the order
phase. So that means that we don't have a
discontinuity in the order of self. So there's no
first order transition. But if we look at the
first derivative of this magnetization with
respect to the control parameter, that positive
one half power comes down to become a negative one
half power. So this. So-called susceptibility, the
dependence of the order parameter on the control
parameter in this case, the derivative of the
magnetization with respect to temperature does
indeed have a divergence. That's what we can now
identify as a true critical temperature equals two
D.
Where the political temperature is location of a
second order of transition, where the order
parameter is continuous but its derivative
diverges.
And getting back to it, we started talking about
right at the start of today. The. Palillo,
dependent's of this diversion, so leaving aside
the constant factors
as he approaches to see the derivative of the
mechanization versus like one over the square root
of a small number. And the. Dependence on the
difference between the critical temperature and
the control for energy itself.
Raise to some nonentities, your power is a fairly
generic feature of all sorts of order phase
transitions. I should mention that B needs to be.
Now, an integer for four is typically not integer
for the order parameter itself, since if it were
an integer power and the derivatives would
eventually get it down to just.
That's maybe telling us that it's approaching
10:00 and should start wrapping up. But. The. This
power be. Turns out to be a powerful way to
categorize and classify it. Various sorts of
second order, various transitions, something will
come back to probably next week, not Friday, it is
known as the critical experience and characterizes.
The second order phase transition at the critical
temperature, the critical value of the control
parameter.
And.
There are just a few remaining comments about the
minefield fuel approximation that we'll make
before going into some exact solutions on Friday,
and in anticipation of that, we can compare. This
may be an approximation to some of those exact
solutions as a preview and see how well it works.
So to summarize for any number of dimensions, the.
The Medfield approximation to the easy model is
simple cubic lattice predicts a second order for
transition at a critical temperature that is two
times the twice the dimensionality. And the
critical element in every case is half the one
over square root dependent's there in the
derivative. In one dimension, we will solve the
using model exactly and find that there is that
new phase transition at all. That's what is
derived in his PhD thesis in the nineteen twenties,
why he thought that this model was a failed
attempt to describe real magnetism. But we will.
Well, the thing to note now is that in one
dimension, that Medfield approximation is not good.
It fails to predict the absence of a transition
that we can exactly solve for.
However, if things become better in higher
dimensions, so moving up from one to two, there is
an exact solution for the two dimensional model of
the square lattice. It sounds like fortius we want.
Be able to go through that, but we can. Just. Tell
you that it does feature the second order phase
transition. And it's critical temperature is a
little bit above two, so the critical temperature
a little bit below point five. This is something
not exactly a funny function of warmth and square
roots. We will be able to drive that through the
provision of the stability. From the exact
solution, we can also compute the critical
exponent. Of the magnetization, the two
dimensional case, which is one eighth so
qualitatively a meaningful approximation, is
giving the correct prediction that there is a
second order phase transition. But the. Critical
times, your critics is about twice the actual
critical temperature for compared to two point two
seven. And the critical exponent, which predicts
the wind field approximation is off by a factor of
four to one over eight.
However, this trend of the usual approximation,
getting more reliable in a larger number of
dimensions continues. We have to compare things
with numerical results for the created. They're
equal to three. But as we will in the interest of
time, put off, let's recap on Friday, there is
greater and greater agreement as the number of
dimensions increases. And there's also a way to
understand this qualitatively, that when we have a
greater number of dimensions, each of the degrees
of freedom in the U.S. model has a greater number
of nearest neighbors to interact with. So it feels.
A better approximation to the overall deal, that
would mean fewer approximations based on. And in
the abstract, look at the infinite number of
dimensions. We can even show that meaningful
approximation is, in fact, the exact solution to
the using model on every. Degree of freedom has an
infinite number of nearest neighbors, and so it
feels exactly the mean value of the overall
mechanization as a whole. So I've got a couple of
minutes over giving. That preview will come back
to this. On Friday and then dive into some exact
results for the easy model to wrap up this unit,
any final questions from you before we close down
for today?
Any good luck wrapping up that homework for
Thursday and I will then see you the following
morning at noon to 10:00, so.
And so
they had the ball commission is so much for this
test and she wants to look at it as the cards
close to zero will
tell you, it's.
So here the expansion is that is a good question.
So the key is that the magnetization, if they'd
have to see and this is time to move to and to
have expansion, there is a expansion for Tenge X
at large. I'm looking for some point so we can
actually go back to these guys, the chance to
purchase one at infinity. So if you try to expand
one minus the change, I believe it is possible to
come up with an expansion in the. Some small
gravitron have to look up. The truth is, I believe
there is a large expansion. I believe there's also
another there may well be a class coming in here.
The.