Okay, sorry for delay getting underway. In addition
to Zoom
not behaving itself on here, there were also issues with the
printer again, which means that we don't have things printed out to go through
some of the derivations we'll be talking
about today.  Though I did manage to make a note of the code
for this afternoon's class,
which if I copied it down correctly should be
five eight, two seven, six eight.
And, let's get
started, as usual, by checking in to see if you have any
questions about what we've gone through in the module
so far, what remains or
to that?
And if not, then we ran out of time last week,
going through the third. How they plan for for the
tutorial, which was just to give a little
reorientation on the security problem, looking at
different structures versus thinking more
qualitatively about the possible grievances,
responding to order to disorder two phases
depending on the level of structure. And
countering the concept of frustrated anti-terror
magnetism where. There are trying to the Latisse
that is not bipartite, so I'm trying to remember
now how much of this we actually discussed last
week and how much was just in the pit of the
solutions that went online a few days ago. But
bipartite Gladys's like those.
Which include those like the square and Honeycomb
badasses, allowed all of the latest sites to be
broken up into two distinct sets its theby and the
parts dividing all the sites into two different
parts, like square minus the serial, red, black,
checkerboard and. Which also holds the shifted way
for the.
Lettuce. But not for the utilities, so that if we
have to sell one bit of spin there, one down there,
if an entity, a couple that prefers this
orientation to reduce the energy, then there is no
way of making all three interactions between these
three.
Also, the order one or the other of them has to be
giving a positive contribution to the energy or
frustrated one that is expanded to the full set of
lattice with many sites. Then there are many
possible ground states. Most are all degenerate
and trying to keep track of all of these
configurations with that grossetête energy is one
of these exponentially hard, not polynomial. Not
deterministic all your problems in. Some
situations. So. Maybe the best thing for me to do,
which is why I'm back on canvas.
Wants to.
Grab the file that was uploaded next, I think
should be in the discussion, so make sure that you
are able to get it even before it's uploaded to
that module. Paige.
OK, so I'll fix that this afternoon and go through
the back door that is available to me at.
And windows were just not built at the moment.
We'll have here once it loads a better
illustration of. The frustrated MP for magnetism
that we went through last week, should it ever
choose to load a small PDF?
What's going on?
Should not be.
Such a challenge, so here it is, finally,
technology going slow, but it gets there and so
this little drawing here on the on the right
actually took from a paper all the way back in
nineteen fifty showing a one of the many. States
of this A.M. is a model of the triangle, the
latest that has the minimum ground energy, there
are all sorts of ways that the. Upward pointing at
the point expense, the pluses and minuses in the
system can be shifted in order to keep that same
energy. So even in the limit of absolute zero
temperature, all of those battleground states
produce a non-zero entropy for the system. And
trying to you can prove that in the latest system.
So not just the simple Tudeh frustrated energy for
a but going into three dimensions or looking at
the random spin class couplings.
It's possible to prove that. Solving those systems
is ENPI complete problem in the language of
theoretical computer science, that any
non-deterministic polynomial task can be mapped to
solving such a system where this non-deterministic
polynomial means that if you have an answer given
to you, it's quick and easy to check. But actually
finding that answer in a systematic way is hard
for Sheck. Part of the sense that the amount of
work required for any algorithm increases
exponentially with, in this case, the number of
lattice sites. So
that was.
Stuff that we discussed, if not in so much detail
last week, went through the bare bones of it and.
Focus on. So.
Using model with. A couple in jail could be thrown
into granted for a positive or negative, but the.
Novel feature here that we consider. That's one of
the simple tilings of two dimensional space and
fully connected lattice, or a complete graph,
which is the. Diagram that I had on here, and I
don't think we had a chance to discuss this last
week, so. What the complete graph is sort of I
tend to call the fully connected lattice just to
emphasize the connection to the other lattices
with the. Thinking about is every single site is a
nearest neighbor of every other site, which we can.
Interpret in a couple of different ways, the more
physical lay and the more mathematical. The more
abstract mathematical way we have, the idea that
all of the sites in the system are equally far
away from each other, which is not possible to bad
ratio in a two dimensional surface.
Essentially, we are treating these mathematically
as of all of the lines in each of these, lattices
is the same length. Whether they're connecting
those two points, they're those two points or
they're just the same distance in some abstract
space, in a more physical approach. You can say
that maybe the distance doesn't matter as a
physical length, but the strength of the
interaction is the same independent of that
distance, so that if you have arrangements of
particles like this in some crystal, there's a
long range interaction between them. They all
behave essentially as though they were right next
to each other
in terms of how that interaction.
Manifest itself, the effects of that interaction
on all the different particles so you can go
through the accounting here, but it's also an easy
question to see that. There are one 1/2 times
entertained by this one leaks in this total fully
connected Latisse over every one of the insights
there are in minus one links to the miners from
other sites. And then each of those links has two
sites out there. And so there's a double counting
for that argument and also recognize that.
Factor of in times of minus one or two as the
binomial coefficient of choosing two sites out of
the total. Fought to define each one, so the total
number of links is scaling like the square of the
number of sites in every state, hands and legs
connected to it, and the total number of sites.
And the task was to consider using model on this
fully connected lattice. And.
Try to see if we can solve it, similar to the way
we solved the using model on the one dimensional
chain of spins this morning. This is one of the
situations where an interacting system of this
sort has an exact analytic solution. The partition
function can be expressed. As a closed formality
expression rather than a sum over all
configurations and fight back to these comments
that the printer refused to give me a few minutes
ago, the.
Starting point for this was the hit we lost over
last week and something that. I showed off earlier
in the week as.
With a bit of a connection to going from. The
sweet songs to continuous intervals in this case.
The answers to rather than trying to sum over each
individual, link some over the different possible
values of the magnetization when each of these
sites can be pointing upward. So.
We know that.
For insights, there are countless one possible
values of discussion and all the of I not one, so
that half of them get zero or give them all the
lie down. There is an plus one. Going from the
overall accusation of negative one plus one, those
limits. And then for a large enough and
enforcement values, all evenly spaced in that
interval plus minus one, we can replace that sum
over the discrete values with the integral over
the continuous value similar to what we did before
with ideal gases and what showed up and generated
some questions about the homework that was due
yesterday. So that's why I didn't save this
discussion to have right now, but at least the
first little bit of the solution. On the Qantas
side earlier in the week, where the key what
distinguishes this fully connected Latisse from
the easy model we've been considering all square
and trying to lattices and so on, is that. Now,
with all of the sites connected to all of the
other sites and straightforward to break up this
sum over all of those links into a product of some
over individual sites, would you give us that
magnetization that we're going to be integrating
over just the. Average value of the spin's, some
for all the sites. So.
We started off with the song over J. Less than K
to avoid double counting, but we can't just as
well double counted, added a factor of two. So
that's a fairly trivial identity, getting all the
changes that are not equal to KS. And if we
replace the sum over S.J time, this came with a
product of the two songs. One over S.J. and S.K.,
this product will have all of the terms we want
and also all of those we don't want J equals K, so
there are any of those for each value of J equals
K, they give a factor of S squared, which is
always one for E in the plus minus one, and we
subtract that off and have everything in terms of
the magnetization. So sum over and values of one
and. And there are the two factors of in times
stabilization there, so the energy then as the
simple form of writing everything in terms of
acquisition, and then that gives us the partition
function as the sum of all possible values of the
mechanisation times, the exponential minus theta
times, the energy. I can't scribble over the
screen that's up here, but I can sort of point to
different features of this map. You may already
have looked at this and go through it fairly
quickly.
Split things up into terms one that depends on
that couple, on the defense, on the external field
age, and then each value of the magnetization is
defined by the number of upper expense or the
number of Delaporte expense with our usual
binomial coefficients, the total number of spins
choosing, that's a pretty pointed number. So
converting this into an integral to the
magnetization, the next step is to express this
binomial coefficient in terms of the magnetization.
And I may give you five minutes or so to to play
with that and get a expression for the partition
function entirely in terms of the magnetization,
and then you can start to think about how that
might be evaluated to get a closed form expression
or, in other words, to exactly solve this
particular system. So let me know if this is
something that you have already done during the
week. I suspect not given the homework to
yesterday, but
so long as you keep yourselves entertained, say,
for the next five minutes, pause the recording and
check in that door before pausing to say if there
are any questions about what the next step or
steps would be in the quest to solve this
expression.
I'll give you a chance to work on it rather than
just listening to me ramble on. So I've got the
recording back the way again and. Now that you've
had a little bit of time to wrestle with this and
see it's moving pieces, I'll reveal a nice trick
that can help to simplify things, though I should
mention that there are. Several distinct ways of
solving articles of this sort, so what we're doing
today is one focused on combinatorics and
approximations, and it's also possible to
introduce auxillary variables, what's called a
cover story, part of its transformation. And in
these comments, there's a link to a whole textbook
whose second chapter is solving this system, but
is sometimes noted security advice model rather
than using model on the fully connected lattice.
The trick that can help us simplify the approach
commented on in these comments is to take this
fundamental fact
and this fact factorial.
Only I left enough space in front of that to cast
an exponential. Will, this new law helps in a few
ways. First of all, that exponential factor added
to the exponential speed multiplier against the
overall degree and just becomes the single
exponential of this logarithm, plus that being
able to anticipate a this one possibly better H
and M, and you can also.
Expand the logarithm of this ratio of factories in
the usual way, so the living couple of terms and
service expansion of that toilet is more and more
in line, minus an. We'll have the minus and plus,
plus, plus, minus the kids that only your
children's names and.
And subscripts, and then it's being in the
relation between him and mechanisation. We get the
first step, complete the partition function
expressed.
So I mentioned that in the course of plugging in
this expression, there are some nice cancellations
and simplifications. So.
What we can see is that. There are anywhere to
look in terms two of those that cancel off the
meeting, then log in. And then there are two
factors of an over to a half with the negative
sign, which is plus over to the law, to this two
factors that give an analog to an area to look for
properties that the logarithm and then for the
arguments of the log would be minus and over two
times log one plus one minus seven. We have a
minus or two types of log of quantity. One minus
ten squared can absorb that negative side to put
it into the. And finally, the midterms come in
with opposite sides, minus in the first term and
plus in the second. So we have over two times the
log of that second argument, one minus M over that
log of one plus N. And then we insert that back
into the partition function we had about to pull
out the Halstead's magnetization and the piece
there is missing DNA there where, as advertised,
we have just the overall exponential of some
series of terms that we get out of the vaccination
for the final factor. And then on. And then Jagan
Square an inch that we had before, is it possible
to get both of these on the same screen? Not so
easily you can recognize. That after pulling out
that overall factor of nd you're left with those
final two terms that appear here and what I've
done at the end of this first line is pull out the
overall factor and and represent that as the
exponential of this function of the position, race
and power.
And.
I guess the.
The next step that.
We could go through that I may already flash on
the screen, is how to evaluate this integral now
that it is all expressed as a somewhat awkward
function of that magnetization.
And what we can do is take an approach similar to
what we did and looking at the Sommerfeld
expansion just before the spring break, we argued
that. These exponential functions that we're
integrated over have some steep peak in. So they
this.
The.
Peake is going to be further amplified in this
case by the exponential function being raised to
the power of a very large integer, no greater than
one. So a solution, a way to solve this equation,
sometimes called the closest method, a step is to
sense method is to find the maximum of this
function that is being exponentially added and
then having that exponential rate to the power and.
Prove. Are your to assume that? It is. Harrex to
approximatively function. Around that maximum,
this is the effect of losing the public safety
that we did in the context of quantum gases, and
then that simplifies the structure of the integral
enough to to solve it in a fairly straight order.
So.
I think at this point, you may as well just keep
talking through the solution rather than going
back and forth and leaving it for you to play with
things, the first step of following that procedure
is to find the maximum of this function itself.
Which we need to take the derivative of all of
this with respect to M., the final two terms are
easy ones that long for his independent so we can
get rid of that. And.
As we go through this review of.
May as well work through some aspects of it in the
first term, we have that one of the finest and
square which is moving into the denominator, the
beginning of two times and the numerator that
cancels out to be the denominator.
And in front of the factory of.
The fact the. And then when taking the derivative
of M times the log, we can recall ratio of two
separate
times, the derivative of. One minus one minus
seven is now with the Chambal. Negative sign in
the numerator and then the denominator will be
negative four plus M signs
for other factors of negative one coming from the
chain will last two terms. Just give us bitted J
and B, the beach.
The noise cancellation of the.
We arrange.
Two factors here, that factor, the denominator is
one more than.
So out about the denominator, we have one minus in
Times
Square. So their willingness to the to their end
of the numerator and one minus in the denominator.
So this term here, which is that entirely in the
left with just the log and the
two simple terms that depend on that coupling
electric field. And the log itself is actually a
bit simpler than it might seem at first glance,
thanks to a new identity, that once they don't
have to look up from hyperbolic trigonometry, that
the inverse hyperbolic tangent of some function is
one 1/2 times the log of there's a typo here. The
actual relation is one plus in the numerator and
one minus in the denominator, and we can reverse
with an overall negative sign on the log. So this
term here
is negative.
And we found this to be the times and for each
of the interesting sets distributed to zero to
identify extremely simply that the. Magnetization
itself at the extreme end of this argument is the
chance of better times JAAM plus stage, which is
essentially the self consistency condition that we
derived.
Through the midfield approximation earlier this
week. And we study the solutions in some detail.
The only difference here compared to the lecture
earlier this week is the presence of the coupling,
Jay, coming from the definition of the model.
There is better than the two times that we had in
the midfield approximation, counting the simple
Kubic nearest neighbor pairs for each spin in that
context, and I guess based on comments at the end
of our treatment of the midfield approach, it's
not surprising to see. A way to recover the
Medfield result from this fully connected lattice,
precisely because we saw the wheels of
approximation perhaps better the more neighbors
each side has, and it is fully connected that as
each side has that maximum number of neighbors. So
it's another derivative to distinguish Minimbah
from Máximo after we've set the first derivative
to zero. We want that second derivative to be less
than zero to get a maximum. And this is an even
simpler derivative that we can now pretty much do
in our heads what we did before today, one by one,
over one minus M squared, and that's remaining
factor of beta. So if we consider that this sort
of solution to the self-consistent condition, we
see that this is only a maximum of the arguments
appearing in the partition function when beta is
sufficiently small so that the second derivative
is less than zero. And this is an alternative way
of identifying that critical temperature rather
than looking at the what I call the flow lines of
trying to resolve that, self-consistent the
condition of the graphical method we went through
in the lecture. This tells us the points, the
what's called the curious temperature, where this
disorder selection becomes unstable and the
ordered solutions remain stable. And if we focus
on those. Stable ordered solutions at. Arbitrarily
small temperatures, they remain máxima as that.
Stable value, the solution of itself, and this is
a condition approaches one and this. Ratio
diverges. And we can then plug in as they all fit
on the same screen, not quite. Keep an eye on this
and plug it into the usual Taylor expansion around
one of those two non-zero solutions, the ordered
phase, knowing that in order to account for the
second solution, we will just have to double what
we get out of considering this one side of the
diagram of the expansion of the entire ground
around this maximum. But this line here is just
plugging in what we had earlier. In terms of the
full function F, it appears in the grand. Jeff
organized in such a way to call back to that
self-consistent deconditioned in terms of this
representation of the. Our tenge, which cancels
out almost everything in these brackets, except
for a minus MJM zero over two and in particular
all explicit dependence on that external magnetic
field drops out. At these self-consistent points,
though, there remains implicit dependence in
determining what this M0 actually is, the solution
to that self-consistent condition.
But at this point, we are just about done, we can
take this expansion of. That function F and plug
it back in to where it first showed up in the
partition function we had. The exponential of end
times, this function f of the magnetization so we
can pull out now from that, if you go over to the
first two terms that do not depend on them. So
that gives us. Another factor of either the minus
and the timestep zero over two from the second
term and the exponential of that log is just its
arguments for over one minus seven squared raised
to the power of another two. And all that remains
in the integral is a nice Gaussian integration. So
long as we can expand the domain of integration
from minus one to one all the way out to minus
infinity to infinity, that is also something that
we justified with doing Sommerfeld expansion,
showing that the errors that are introduced by.
Including those nonphysical values of the
magnetization are exponentially small and indeed
vanish in that thermodynamic limit of going to
infinity, where there are rigorous balance, you
can prove and that. Are proven, if you want to see
them in in this book from published a few years
ago, some folks in Switzerland,
but proceeding to carry out that Gaussian
integration just gives us that square root of pi
divided by the multiplicative factor on the minus
seven squared, which is. Just one minus beta Jim
undisputedly and not squared, divided by what,
minus amnot squared? So in the end, we have a
closed form expression for the protection function,
we did do some expansions and approximations to
obtain this, and it is possible to show that this
is actually an exact solution with a bit more work
and a bit more care that I figured I would spare
you and.
Much as we saw this morning, we're looking at the
exact solution for the one, the easy model, just
having a partitioned function is not necessarily
so useful for us. Just looking at that, it's
unclear what it really means in a intuitive
physical sense. The use of having this is as a
starting point for. Doing analysis of observables
coming from those derivatives of the free minus
two times blog, the petition function, and we've
actually seen what we will get for the
memorisation already when we isolated the.
Argument of the exponential and looked at its
extreme until we recovered the exactly the bean
field relation that we got from the field
approximation, which is the exact solution, the
transcendental equation coming from this partition
function, which resulted in class earlier in the
week to find this result for the magnetization and
in particular predictions for that critical
temperature and the critical exponents of the
corresponding second order phase transition. So.
In retrospect, I'm glad I gave a somewhat easier
problem on the homework rather than than this one,
but hopefully this was entertaining to see how the
analysis goes through to get exact results in
statistical physics. And it also calls back to
some of the techniques that we've seen before, the
summer of expansion that apply this method of
steepest descent. And we're used to. Manipulate
certain documentation to binomial coefficient to
get things in a more tractable state, so I'll stop
talking there. If there are any questions about.
This security device model for the other aspects
of the model I to shut them up now, otherwise, you
know, get one step closer to enjoying the weekend
with the warmer weather.