All right, let's get going just a couple minutes
late while I tried to set up some stuff for later
today. We'll get back to that when the time comes.
We can also see how the projector does with the bright
sunlight coming in as we zoom in to better fill the
screen.  And, before I forget, let's deal with six-digit code,
which for this morning is one zero, nine nine, zero two.
And unless there are immediate questions we can
pick up pretty much exactly where we left off at
the end of yesterday.  Having gone through the second
analytical calculation for a simple case of the
Ising model in a small number of dimensions.  So
comparing the two-dimensional case that we worked
on yesterday to the one-dimensional case that we
were able to solve exactly last Friday. We could
see that key, key difference between them and the
three key steps that we had to go through were
leading the. Independent Degrees of freedom, these
films that live on the site with the interactions
that they have that are associated with the links,
and this reveals why things are so sensitive to
the dimensionality of the system, because as the
number of dimensions increases each side, each
degree of freedom is connected to a greater number
of links. So it interacts with more and more of
its neighbors. Eventually, that whole infinite
dimension of limited approaches, the fully
connected lattice, the complete graph and play
with a bit in last Friday's tutorial. So. In one
dimension, there's an equal number of sites in
Lagos, and we were able to recast the sum of all
of those interaction terms as a sum over. The
states themselves taking into account the
constraints that were brought in to make sure that.
But the one each particular spin was interacting
with its two nearest neighbors, it was adopting a
self-consistent value that was imposed just by
recasting things in terms of matrix multiplication.
And that is insufficient itself in two dimensions,
where instead we took a more roundabout route. We
did not get an exact analytics emotional that
exists. We proceeded by swapping out. The
configuration, some over those degrees of freedom,
the skins for a different sum over all possible
interactions between them. Those links being
either on or off and then work backwards by
identifying the strengths that the links that
result, there had to be even number of links
turned on at each site that we could relate them
to interactions between dual spins located on the
two Allardice. In the case of the simple square
lattice in two dimensions, its dual lattice, it's
just another square that has shifted so that its
sites in the center of focus and the end result of
all those manipulations was essentially this
expression which reproduced our. Target for a
certain goal and that we have the original
petition function. That depends on the temperature
data. Being identified with a new production
function for that same two dimensional using
system.
Depending on the dual and temperature to tell them
that we. To. Define, see or identify with a
particular value of the original data, along with
a bit dependent factor that is independent of the
other, the spins or the dual spins. And the
relation between these dual inversed temperatures
that had been held up can be cast in a few
different ways and the debate is held, is that
negative? Half more attention paid off? Or as we
turn through some type of trigonometric identities,
we saw that there is this inverse relation that
the hyperbolic sign of twice the do obeida is the
inverse of the sign of itself. So if we were to
plot the corresponding values to say how this
General David Shelbie depends on like given a
percentage or better, whenever data is large and
that synch becomes exponentially large, the
denominator towards the fraction itself. So we end
up with much more value for Telma and vice versa.
Small data, one over a small number gives us this
large number of inverse relationship like so
swapping out. The high and low temperatures in the
original system and its dual.
So. Before commenting further on that weekend. Do
some similar manipulations to this constant
prefectly that we have out here. A factor of a
half coming from the dual spins, double counting
all possible configurations of links turned on or
off, and then these trigonometric factors and
powers of twice cost me the simulator, which we
worked out. Yesterday, the double identity, that
is just the synch of two data, and we've now
derived that the essential to data is the inverse
of the sense of the dual two data. Tilde, or we
can. Pull out a factor of one over hyperbolic
cosine from this product and identify. It is
hyperbolic, cosine squared times it Hansch, which
is useful because we earlier saw that the
intention of Beáta is an exponential factor in
terms of the dual inverse temperature and plugging
in this ratio and rearranging gets us back to the
way that we framed this duality.
To start off this section yesterday. That's able
to isolate all the dependence on the inverse
temperature or its dual on either side of this
equation. So this has reproduced what we initially
stated as our goal, and now we can just wrap up
this whole unit on interactive systems with some
comments on what this really means, having gone
through the exercise, for one thing, we don't
really have to care too much about these people in
the field, independent counsel factors that come
along for the. Now, multiply the petition
functions, so it's not too hard to show that if we
multiply a petition function by a factor that does
not depend on its microscopic degrees of freedom,
it does not depend on the individual microstates,
but legal control parameters such as the
temperature that drops out of all of the
expectation values that we can actually observe
when analyzing these systems. That is an exercise
I will leave for you to play with rather than
going through here myself. So what we have for
money do we can ignore those three factors and
just say that the systems themselves, this is set
up better instead of being tell up are equivalent
four pairs of. Temperatures in their Dools satisfy
this relation. High temperatures are meant to cool
ones or lower ones and lower temperatures, not to
high temperatures. Now, this can be subtle because
it does not mean that the two dimensional using
model we've been considering is the same at high
temperatures. What's really going on is that two
different using models in terms of two different
sets of degrees of freedom are being identified by
this duality.
And we've seen that the. And each one of these
using models is going to be distinct, different
phases at high temperatures. That's where we
started off with our analysis of this is a
charismatic interacting system. A couple of weeks
ago where. The high and low temperature phases of
each of these easy models are qualitatively
distinct and in the high temperature.
If we consider the low temperature forward, phase
four, seven years experience, we know that at
least more than what dimension are largely aligned,
producing a non-zero value of the order parameter,
the magnetization. And this order phase is mapped
by Kramers Wanita duality onto. A disordered phase
of the dual spins rather than the disordered phase
of the space itself. So we can formulate this one
phase in terms of a different parameter, sometimes
called the disorder parameter and.
More guys are in the low temperature phase of the
original system with the high temperature phase of
the dual system, which can. Or vice versa, which
can simplify calculations in situations where one
or the other of those phrases might be easier to
work with. That's the general power of duality.
That's in some situations the dual system may be
easier to work with than the original system. Now,
the two dimensional using model linear new
developments special in a few ways, one of which
being that the dual system is just another version
or another iteration of the system that we started
off with using model is mapped by this duality to
another using model.
With a different set of double spins and this is
in general not the case.
But because it occurs further to the easy model,
we can learn one very interesting thing from
Kramer's Monia duality, which is what? Happens
when those two phases, the high temperature
behaviors that are ordered or disorder can come
inside if we set the inverse temperature equal to
its dual. So that the systems are being mapped
directly onto each other rather than from one
phase to the other phase. This is the only
possible inverse temperature at which a phase
transition could possibly appear. The interface
between those high and low temperature phases.
And it turns out that this relationship equals
Matilda has a solution, we recall that.
Derived.
The inverse relation between the hyperbolic signs
of being invaded, Hilda, so setting data equal to
be to tell that just means that the square of the
sense of the twice this critical inverse
temperature has to be equal to one or the critical
data itself is just one 1/2 times the inverse
synch for the arc of one. Which is related to a
logarithm of one four through, two through. A
fairly standard identity for that inverses. Which
is similar to the. Our identity that we
encountered and working with the fully connected
virus in the tutorial on Friday. And this then is
just a number, a prediction for the exact value
that is approximately four point four for.
Corresponding to the critical temperature itself
won over the sea of about two point two seven also
known. Exactly. So this result historically was
derived in nineteen forty one. I was involved in
it and it was in nineteen forty four, three years
later when Einziger managed to produce an exact
solution for the two dimensional using model
beyond the scope of what we are able to cover here
and in the exact solution that if found, the
correct reproduction of this exact critical
temperature was. And strong early piece of
evidence that the solution, very difficult
calculation, was, in fact correct.
And since the nineteen forties duality to have
played a greater, greater role in theoretical
physics. And in general, the duality is that are
a centerpiece of modern ongoing research on a lot
more complicated than of individuality. This is
one of the simple early cases that started off
with field is not the final word. And I've already
mentioned that Creamer's one of the duality is
special in that the original system, the two
dimensional using model, is mapped by this duality
onto another two dimensional using models of dual
degrees of freedom. Are the same type of variable
these two state spends, plus or minus one Atabay,
the same interactions with those nearest neighbor
couplings that define the U.S. model. And this is
very special and unusual in terms of duality. So
if we were to. Repeat the attempt to repeat the
work that we did yesterday and the three
dimensional case where there are six. Links
attached to each site. Things would want go
through until we got back to depression, some over
the powers of those sites where. Switching or
converting that into in terms of the dual spins
would not actually suffice to resolve all of the
constraints and. But we would find is that the
dual system for the three dimensional is involved,
even though it's associated with the simple Kubic
lattice in three dimensions, which is the jewel of
the Cuban class, it's four degrees of freedom
would interact differently than the original using
model. Particular, they would have what's called a
cage interaction that is in some sense a discrete
analog of how photons behave. So from a three
dimensional using spin system to a theory that
looks more like quantum electrodynamics. So the
silk duality of the two dimensional using model is
a special feature and the one that allows us to
predict the transition temperature. Exactly.
And maybe the way in which modern dualities are
especially complicated is that they usually can't
be proven the way that we did yesterday, the
calculation that we went through was. A little
complicated, but fit into just a single class
meeting, whereas.
The two entities that are used in twenty first
century theoretical physics research are typically
not something that can be derived so completely,
but generally proceed by making a conjecture that
one system is dual to another argument how the
degrees of freedom and interactions are mapped out
to the other, and then checking that conjecture by
trying to compute as many different observables in
both the original system and the dual system as
possible. Also complicated because usually neither
of those systems are solvable themselves. So just
to give a. Shout out to one of the more famous or
widely discussed sets of dualities. There is a.
A whole class of duality relations that are known
as holographic duality is also sometimes called
idiocy of t devalues or gravities realities that
setting the terminology aside relate to certain
theories of quantum gravity, two theories that do
not involve gravitational interactions but are
still quantum theories of interaction, fields that
are. Can be built up to his generalizations of
interactive systems like those we've been looking
at the past couple of weeks, and just to give one
bit of.
Advertisement. Part of the motivation for fully
connected Latisse that we looked at last week is
that this appears in one of the more famous
holographic dualities that has attracted a lot of
research attention over about the past five years.
This is known as the swankier model named after
Sibiya Sachdev and Electronegative, who Sustiva
developed a model of interacting fermions on that
fully connected class back in the early 1990s. And
then over the summer of twenty fifteen, Aleksi
could have made the argument for the conjecture
that the behavior of these interacting fermions on
a fully connected lattice. Is secretly describing
the same dynamics as quantum black holes in the
theory of quantum gravity. Which has in the. Past
five years or so led to about a thousand
scientific studies being published exploring
different aspects of the behavior of both of the.
Lattice side of the system, like a model itself of
fermions interacting, is fully connected lattice,
as well as the gravitational side of the duality,
the dynamics of black holes in quantum gravity. So
that is just a brief aside to highlight a
connection between some of the things that we've
been doing in this course and some of the really
hot topics of research. That it's going on as we
speak and also the final end of the extended
section that we had on these interactive systems
before moving on to. A final much before synthesis
and look at some broader applications of
sophistical physics, so
before setting aside completely checking to see if
there are any further questions or topics of
interest about about that topic, we will. The
building on it a bit more as we go into. Unit 10
at the.
And we have a few. Hours left for a quick look at
quick survey of some of these broader applications
of. Statistical physics and interacting
statistical systems especially.
So.
Starting with this, what I call a synthesis, we
will be bringing together some of the.
Work on interacting statistical systems built on
the statistical samples that we defined earlier in
the molecule and synthesizing that with the
numerical computing exercises that were the
project that you did earlier in this term. And the
motivation for this is that for these interacting
statistical systems, there is in general no way to
solve them. Exactly. The one dimensional using
model and two dimensions are very special in that
sense. And even if we were to turn on that
external magnetic field and the two dimensional
case. There will be no known exact solution and
possibly a. The issue is not whether or not, you
know, it is an exact solution may not even exist
for the non-zero feelings in two dimensions or the
three dimensional using model, any higher number
of dimensions that remain finite field theory is
just the approximation to the actual dynamics.
So if we want to explore more broadly the kinds of
interactions that are possible in statistical
systems, we need to. Do one of two approaches
either come up with some more systematic
approximation scheme, either bringing in
corrections to mean field theory or different
sorts of expansions in some small parameter or
some small coupling? This is the domain of
perturbation theory, that is. I'm not going to be
talked about here, it is usually featured in
modules on field theory and quantum mechanics the
other way that we can maybe more directly pursue.
Interactive statistical systems is by analyzing
them numerically using computers, which is an
approach that has become increasingly important as
computers have developed over the past 50 to 70
years. And in part, the development of that
computing technology has been driven by the need
for numerical computations to solve interacting
statistical systems in all of their guises, both
within mathematical sciences and beyond.
So. Considering the economic ensemble, just to be
definite, what we want to get from in America,
cooptation our predictions for any observable
expectation, values of interest, which. I try to
fix the focus there. We can recall artist
expressed as the sum of all microstates of that
quantity evaluated for the corresponding Bykov
state, aided by its credibility in the canonical
example, that probability. Is proportional to the
Boltzmann factor, the proportionality constant is
the partition function itself, something over all
these Balsom factors for all of the microcircuits
in the system?
And we mentioned when introducing InterAction's. A
couple of weeks ago that.
Exactly, evaluating all of the terms of the
microstates contributing to these songs that
defined expectation values is a fairly complex
task. So if we consider just a simple, easy model
to a spin system with freedom has only two states
and say we have roughly a thousand spins. Then
there are something like 10 to the power three
hundred terms in that artificial function and even
the largest existing supercomputer or even one
that we can imagine, would have to burn far longer
than the age of the universe to churn through all
of those different microstates in a naive brute
force approach. So if we have lattice sizes that
are 10 cubed in the three dimensions using Model
Six in the Fourth Dimension Olesen model. It
already seems to me that these tiny systems are
out of reach of numerical computing. Never mind
the thermal limits where. Dynamics of interest
like these transitions are formally defined. But
at the same time, just a few days later, we were
able to. Quote, Numerical results for the critical
temperature of the U.S. model in three dimensions,
four, five, six and up to seven dimensions that we
compare to to the field approximation to observe
that the visual approach became more accurate as a
number of nationalities increased. So obviously
those numerical results were not attained by
something over all microstates states and the
corresponding system. And instead took an approach
of sampling a subset of those microstates selected
in some pseudo random way based on the pseudo
random numbers that are available to us. On
computers, as we saw on the computer project, and
then by reducing this overall sum over microstates
to just a sum over a small set of randomly sample
microstates. We would get predictions for the
usual, for an anemic observables, energy
magnetization and so on. That's. The law of large
numbers would relate to the true expectation value
so long as a sufficiently large.
Number of states we consider. So this general
approach, which uses the pseudo random numbers
available to computing hardware to sample a subset
of the possible microstates is known as. A Monte
Carlo method, which is a whimsical name, that is.
Referencing a casino gambling center in Monaco,
the south of France, and these multicolor methods
are very widely used and very crucial in
statistical physics and all sorts of related
disciplines, thanks to their applicability to
interacting systems where we are not able to
obtain exact solutions or benefit from the
factorization of non interactive systems.
It's been a bit of intuition for how to use
multiple methods are working by. Actually doing a
Monte Carlo calculation here in class to
numerically evaluate a simple integral. So the
idea is the so-called Monte Carlo with the
creation. That's. Rather than evaluating the
integral analytically or approximating its
function as a piece, a smooth quantity, they can
be fed through a.
Trapezoid, rule or elaborations thereof? We can
randomly sample points in the integration domain,
evaluate the integrity at each of those points,
and then normalize by the total number of points
that we sample. So if we consider the integral of
the two dimensional plane, which does not quite
fit on the screen with its illustration. So
integrating over X and Y both from minus one to
one of this heavy side function. Which is one,
whenever its argument is positive or zero and
negative for or sorry to zero for any negative
arguments, we can see that negative arguments
occur when X squared plus Y squared is greater
than one which defines the unit. This with radius
one in this. Integration domain. With area four,
two by two in both X and Y. So by sampling, as
shown, the green dots in this figure, random
points in that integration domain and counting the
number that fall within that, this will end up
with a prediction for the area of Baptist's, which
is known to its friends as high higher squared
with R equals one.
So simply counting the fraction of the samples
that end up inside or outside of the this
evaluates that integration of the heavy side step
function and gives us pi up to some statistical
uncertainty that we can show. Decrease is
proportional to the number of independent samples
that we consider in order to evaluate. This
integral three multicultural approach and setting
up this calculation was what I was struggling with
just at the start of. The class today, this is the
very short python code that.
Is linked from the lecture notes, just a few lines
with a bit of elaboration for estimating the
statistical uncertainties that we can go into if
there is time and interest.
Since I had this all queued up in Google CoLab,
but it was not letting me log in, it wasn't
recognizing me on this system, so I need to head
back to it and hopefully just be able to paste
this code into a new.
Notebook as. A user who is the site was what was
causing trouble, so let's try.
Riblet.
Warick.
I want a basic python shell.
And see if I need to sign in to run this guy. Nope,
it's already up and under way, and in a couple of
seconds, we were able to evaluate the pie is
roughly three point one four three plus or minus
006. So a couple of decimal places there. I'll
just leave that running in the background for the
next few minutes, see what we're able to get out
by the end of the hour today.
We should see that we'll get four or five
significant figures in our determination of pi
from integration by the end of the hour, which.
It's amusing, but not the best way to compute PI.
It's much more efficient to take advantage of
specialized relationships and serious expansions
that end up being related to circular experiences,
hyperbolic functions. That's. We're talking about
his multicolor integration in the final unit on
broader applications, and that is because we're
motivated by multicolor integration being very
broadly applicable. Not just to computing power,
evaluating three dimensional integrals, but also.
Evaluating the high dimensional integrals, which
is the domain in which multicolor integration is
most useful, where by high dimensional integral I
have in mind that we take our statistical system.
And it's partition function, for instance, and
interpret that system as an integration over all
of the degrees of freedom. That can vary as we
change from one microstates to the next. So the
idea is that if we have a billion degrees of
freedom, like that's the typical scale of.
Numerical research using multicolor methods that
goes on here at the university. Those billion
degrees of freedom at all interacting with each
other can be represented as an integral over a
billion variables like ability, dimensional,
integral, and then the value of that integral in
the corresponding expectation, values of
attributes that depend on those billion degrees of
freedom can just be evaluated by Montecarlo
sampling. And in particular, what logical
integration? That's sort of the state of the art
that is accessible with the supercomputers that
exist today. Well, beyond just that simple three
dimensional piece of pie that we're running in the
background now.
That is to wrap up today with a few. More comments
there is. An election you might make something you
might be worried about. If you think back to where
we started off, this unit of other applications by
noting that explicitly evaluating all of the
microstates of the system would take far longer
than the age of the universe, if we are sampling
some subset of those microstates in some
reasonable amount of time, say a day or a week or
a month, that amount of time is very small
compared to the universe, which implies that the
fraction of the microstates that we can possibly
consider in that time is correspondingly,
extremely small. And. You might be worried about
the risk of. Claiming that we can extract reliable
results for these expectation values from sampling
such a small number of microstates, so this is
essentially the same. Issue that we started off by
worrying about, we just sort of turned it on its
head by saying, rather than worrying about how
long it takes you down with everything, we're
worrying about how little we can evaluate. In a
reasonable amount of time, so just to make this
concrete. Suppose we go back to that tiny easing
system with roughly a thousand degrees of freedom.
And suppose that we have some computer that can
sample a of that system every nanosecond, so a
billion microstates, every second, which is a bit
generous but not completely absurd. In terms of
what is possible with
the laws of physics that govern how computers
operate. So if you look over the course of the day.
We have about a quarter of thousand seconds per
hour and over twenty four hours of the day, so
there is ten to the four. Seconds of the day,
during each of which we evaluate the microstates
in the system, ending up with roughly 10 trillion.
Spin configurations sampled out of the total. That
was about 10 to the power. Three hundred
microstates. So any numerical results we obtained
from that sampling?
Would take into account only one part in 10 to the
power to eighty seven of the total number of
microstates, so this is a vanishingly small
fraction and it's very easy to imagine that. The.
One out of every 10 to the power to 87,
microstates that we look at are not necessarily
representative of the vast majority of microstates
that we should really be accounting for in order
to predict what the quantities. And things
actually get much worse if we consider larger
systems where the number of micro states increases
exponentially in the number of degrees of freedom.
In addition to each individual microstates also
requiring more computation in order to to be
considered. So as a illustration of how this
operates, I've linked here. The reference for some
of the work on using models and five, six and
seven dimensions that produced the values of the
critical temperature will be compared to the
Medfield approximation. Last week. Or the larger
scale calculations that this work was able to
consider is a system of sixty four to the fifth
using spins in five dimensions, so sixty four
spins on each of the five dimensions of the system.
Which, if we convert that to base 10, is. Roughly
a billion Tagami degrees of freedom, so the number
of microstates is down to two billion, two to the
10 to the power line which converted the base, 10
is roughly ten to the three hundred million
possible microstates. And in that result for the
political temperature that we predicted. We saw
that outside only in this work, about ten thousand
or fifteen thousand of those ten to the three
hundred million microstates were considered. So
it's reasonable to ask how much trust do we or how
much do we trust those results?
There is a.
Not quite going to finish this discussion today.
We'll come back to it on Friday, along with the
other broader implications if we think about the
easing system in. More specifically, that is being
considered in this case, we could make an argument
that in the high-temperature disordered phase,
things are like, OK. Because we started off by
seeing that as the temperature gets higher and
higher, the various different microstates are
adopted with equal probabilities and the
expectation values then are determined by which of
the energy levels has the greatest degeneracy, the
greatest number of microstates responds to it. So
the more microstates there are, the more likely
they are to be among that. One out of the 300
million that is sampled by this pseudo random
numerical procedure. So it is at least plausible
that we could get reasonable results in this phase
by averaging even over such a tiny fraction of the
total number of microstates in the system. But of
course, the opposite is the case in the low
temperature ordered phase. Where we saw that. The
expectation values in this phase. Are dominated by
a very small number of microstates, approaching
just the two degenerate micro states that have the
minimum value for the energy. All of the is
aligned in one of the two directions that they can
point either all up with the value plus one or all
down with the value minus one and then. On top of
the contributions from that ground state, there
would be only exponentially suppressed corrections
from higher energy levels and. If we were to
proceed by randomly sampling one out of every 10
to the three hundred million microstates, there is
essentially zero chance that we would randomly
happen the sample, one of those special minimum
energy states where all the spins are ordered
completely up or down. There's. Essentially, one
hundred percent chance of missing the dominant
contributions to the expectation values. Making it
seem as though. The approach of randomly sampling
microstates to medically evaluate the expectation
values is doomed to fail. So the solution to this
conundrum that we will. Go through on Friday is to
sample microstates not completely randomly, with a
probability proportional to the bolson factor with
which they appear in the partition function and in
the expectation value that we want to go after. So
that is known as important sampling and is where
we will pick up on Friday. I will stop.
Going through that now as we are running out of
time, and you think if you have any questions
before we end, we can hop back to. The
calculations going on here to see that we have not
quite gotten through the. Final round of computing
pie through Montecarlo integration, but in the
space of about five minutes, we were able to find
a value of pie that was three point one four one
eight plus or minus seven in that last digits. So
correctly reproducing the node value. And with a
statistical accuracy that steadily increases as
advertised, like the square root of the number of
samples that are being considered. If I had been
able to plug into the Google CoLab, that provides
a bit more powerful computing than.
This calculation would have taken only about.
Several times would have completed several times
more quickly, taken several times less computing
and given us the answer,
they here that you can go and run. Yourselves, if
you are so inclined, see how many digits you can
get in
here down to uncertainty from the statistics of
two in the fourth decimal place.
Wrap up there for today and then back on Friday to
finish off the broader applications and any
dangling loose ends for the Marshall.
OK.
So.