Okay, we can get under way. Welcome back to the
final day, part one.  We can start off with
the the last of these codes for this term.
We'll see if the system sticks around.
Anyway, the code for today is seven five,
zero five, two six.
And we will see today how well I've planned out the
last bit of material to go.  First, are the very questions
about the module
up until now, before we keep going with the last
few topics on broader applications.
So just see.
Thirteenth of May and the first half of this week,
we went through.
Was one year.
Duality.
What were these two dimensional using model, the
square lattice?
Which predicted the exact critical temperature of
the system to cover the log of one plus route to
Jefri, plug in the numbers to that exact formula,
temperature is enough to want to settle. And this
was obtainable through the duality without
actually. Being able to solve the original to
match up with a model or its dual system, which in
this special case turned out to be a similar look
at using model, is defined with dual speed
variables on the dual lattice, another square
lattice that just shifted about half a unique
dimension and is dualities are. A major. Tool in
the twenty first century theoretical physics
applied to all sorts of situations, mostly less
precise and less solidly defined than simple
creators wanted to do reality.
Where certain systems exhibits in some
circumstances the same behavior as other dual
systems that may be easier to analyze, the special
case should have holographic duality. Is that
really quantum gravity to quantum field theories
that are so different from the system systems
we've working with and will probably pop up before
the end of this hour? And another? Equally
widespread. Tool in the.
Modern analysis of complex systems.
Numerical analysis of contract statistical systems.
Making use of the.
Has computers that have been developed over the
past 70 years or so. Where? We saw that.
If we were to try to do a brute force computation
of all of the microstates, then a statistical
system, even with the most powerful supercomputers
we can imagine building that obey the laws of
physics, a calculation of that sort of small,
simple systems would require far longer than the
age of the universe to complete. So. The only way
we can actually get results from these miracle
analysis is to do so-called sampling. Not a small
number. Of microstates in the system, which. Leads
to that same challenge and a different guys where
the number of microstates, the proportion that we
can reasonably sample in the amount of time we
want our calculations to run before we have
results is vanishingly small. One example here,
where only about one out of every 10 to the power,
three hundred twenty four million microstates
could possibly be sample in. This was for the
prediction of the critical temperature of the five
dimensions and the solution to this we mentioned
Tuesday. But any details about it is a approach
known as important sampling. Where?
What we do is instead of randomly sampling or
pseudo randomly sampling microstates just drawn
without any knowledge about the system or the full
range of possible microstates, we design
procedures that.
I guarantee to sample any particular microstates
with a probability that is proportional to its
factor factor, the amount to which it contributes
to any given expectation value or. Arbitrary
expectation value is given by some of microstates
of the observable itself, weighted by. This
probability in the multifactor neutralized by the
protection function.
And the procedures that are designed to do this.
I'm sure you've heard the term algorithm's, you
may not
know that it's named after actually a 9th century
Persian mathematician for his
name, got Latinist to allegorically. And the idea
is. And that's where as an illustration, going
back to the example with the last time we're
worried about a low temperature phase of the U.S.
model where we would have to. Find the minimum
energy microstates to all the expectation values,
if we do have such an algorithm that samples
microstates proportional to the exponential of the
speed of times, their energy that in that low
temperature regime is very large, this exponential
factor is going to be exponentially enhanced for
exactly those low energy states that we want to
find. So if we have such an algorithm, then it
will sample exactly the microstates that we need.
And it also continues to work with the high
temperature phase where the probability is for
each of the microstates become similar. There's
less of an issue. With sampling only a very small
number of them.
So. Let me know if that general idea is not clear.
What I'll do in the meantime is move on and start
thinking about how we actually get important,
simple algorithm. Rather than assuming that we
have one. Given the challenge that you don't
actually know the probabilities of the microstates,
that trying to sample after this depends on the
energies of all those microstates and also
mobilized by the petition function. So actually,
computing all of these to check whether our
algorithms sample them correctly would get us back
to require that brute force computation at the
forward function and then waiting far longer to do
so.
So there are various solutions to this that. Have
been.
Invented. And the essence of. Each of them is that
is the casting aspect of the algorithms, the use
of the pseudo random numbers are. Taking advantage
of to guide the system to these important high
probability microstates that actually knowing what
those probabilities are in absolute terms, but
only in in relative terms and. Importantly,
whatever procedures in place to encourage the
system to go to these of microstates, this has to
be done without introducing the other bias that
could lead to incorrect results being predicted
more generally. Again, we have only this tiny
fraction of microstates available to analyze. So
probably the most famous way of doing this. Is an
algorithm that was developed now almost seven
years ago in nineteen fifty three by these five
folks, Nick Metropolis, Arianna Rosenbluth, Marcia
Elizabeth Taylor and Edward Teller. And I'm going
to call this metropolis, even though there are two
residences and two towers, there is sort of a.
Infamous misfiring of the alphabetical order here
that leads to this frequently being referred to as
chocolate.
Even though Petropolis himself was not actually
involved in developing the algorithm, he was the
source of the computer equipment that in 1953 was
very highly specialized and was used to test the
algorithm with a simple calculation that says you
can do pretty much instantaneously some.
And the. The approach that this Emirati metropolis
wrestles with tower algorithm takes to find high
probability microstates is that none of those
probabilities is to work with the Markov chains
that we actually introduced way back in February,
be the first unit of this module. And since it's
been a while since we saw that, I'll remind you
that this Markov chain is a process,
the state of the system and based on its state
microstates in the context of the samples, we
generate a new state that becomes a new link in
this chain. And importantly, that depends only on.
The.
Initial microstates that we start off with without
having any memory of looking for it. So if we had
to visually represent this sequence of states,
we'd have one sample here. This is used with some
aspects of some pseudo random number. What is
reproducible in the American population to
generate a new state that we forget all about that
previous states. Just keep the process in this
current one that still.
Up until we have the statistics that we need to do
the prediction for expectation values. Without
power, with controlled statistical uncertainties,
so. To illustrate the idea of the Metropolis Tower
algorithm. More concretely, we can go back to
choosing a model that we are now quite familiar
with. So each of these links in the chain is going
to be a configuration of the spin's. And you can
start off with any pseudo randomly chosen spin
configuration. So we microstates people. Well, as
the initial states at the start of the Walk of
Shame. But then from this initial configuration,
which was just one of the spins in the system,
changed it. So the only thing you can do on the
easy model is have only. Two values is the fact
that stem from up to down to vice versa, and then
we have the key step, which is to decide what the
next step is going to be based on flipping the
split. So. There are two possibilities, either we
define the next state to be the original system
unchanged or we define it to be the modified
system with the single been flipped and we accept
that spin flip with this maybe funny looking
probability, the minimum of one hundred percent
would be exponential of the change in the energy
divided by the temperature multiplied by.
So we can.
See, before we dig into this acceptance, probably
in more detail, it is crucial that we have the
capability of having the next
stage of the next stage of the identical to the
one that just came, because if we think back to
that low temperature phase where we want the
ground state to dominate expectations, bellman's.
You would want to see that ground states being
first weeks, this procedure then repeated over and
over again so that it does indeed make the
greatest contribution to the nation's interest in
which. Accounts for its alleged culpability
without actually knowing anything about that
microsleep probability. So. Talking through this
equation, one twenty four in more detail, we have
two possibilities when we look this spin.
First, the spin flip could lower the total energy
of the system or keep it constant, in which case
with the Alpha Delta E that is either negative or
less equal to zero. In both those cases, the
exponential factor is. More than one hundred
percent. And we always accept that change, so many
students look, that lowers the energy is accepted
100 percent probability, which helps US policies,
an approach that renewable energy to a seat so
long as it can be reached by the individual states.
But on the other hand, if we have inexpensive that
increases the energy, we'll still have a non-zero
chance of accepting that higher energy microstates
moving away from the ground states. But that
transition probability to the higher energy state
is exponentially suppressed and goes to zero as
the temperature goes to zero, which encourages the
system to hang out in its ground states. So if we
look at. The ratio of these transition
probabilities for to spin configurations that
differ only by flipping a single spin and this way
he calls it a B. And from our definition of the
acceptance probability. For them, the trouble was
not them, the probability of transitioning from A
to B is going to be the minimum of one or the
exponential of that difference, A minus equally
divided by the temperature
for going in the other direction from D.. A, it
will be the same to interchanging the roles of A
and B.. So its energy B minus energy divided by
the temperature and regardless of which of these
two microstates has the higher temperature. We
will always come out with. This ratio of ability
is being exponential by the speed of times by the
CIA. So we can just see through the two
possibilities if the energy bill is lower today
than the numerator here is one. And the
denominator is the exponential time to speed up by
the speed at which we can negate the argument of
the exponential spread from the denominator up to
the numerator. If we go the other way with the
exponential factor comes directly to the numerator,
the dominator is one. And we can then break up
that difference in the energies to just be the
ratio of the and factors for the two final stages
the day so the states have the change into. Are
selected proportional to their bottom factors
without actually having to impute or know those
factors in advance before we randomly propose the.
So. Both in this case and more generally, again,
these sorts of important sampling Markov chain
Monte Carlo algorithms are very likely applied to
all areas of the mathematical sciences and beyond.
Their statistical physics plays a big role in all
of these cases, so long as every micro stage can
be generated from every other microstates from the
series of pseudo random changes to the individual
degrees of freedom. Then this results the
acceptance probability that those guarantees that
the microstates are going to be stable with the
probability, without knowing those probabilities
in advance in this condition, that all the
microstates are accessible based on these
individual changes is called ergotism. Be funny
looking technical term where.
If we had an algorithm, which is not the case that
was not regarded, then the argument we went
through with this equation, one twenty five would
fail because there would be microstates that could
not be reached in the first place, will not show
up in the process through which the algorithm is
guided or feels out. The high probability
microstates it will be overlooked, omitted from
the averaging over the samples. That gives us
excited values and those expectation values. You
can either be completely wrong or at least biased.
Through overlooking those particular microstates.
So that is. All that I'm going to say about. These
numerical methods for interactive statistical
systems, the. It's pretty easy to design a full
module on that topic, one place you can look if
you want to play with this a bit more is in the
intruders introduction to general physics. The
second item on the list of which should be at the
library that actually provides a. Annotated a
program for running the metropolis, a for two
dimensional model that fits on a single page and
was used to generate the black and white speed
configurations that we looked at spent exploring
the easy model. A couple of weeks ago.
And I'll just mention, since it's very close to my
research, that although this metropolis wasn't
with our group is both very famous and very simple,
it's. In many cases, far from the best of the best
that we could have. And I don't think time is
going to permit, but one of the big issues that
this sort of algorithm encounters and Markov chain
multicolor algorithm to calculate generally, is
that because each link in the chain, which
microstates is pseudo randomly sample, depends on
the one that came before. It obviously resembles
that one that came before. This is especially
clear in the case of applying the sort of the easy
model where all of this is except one are
identical, even if the proposed update is
acceptable. So that means that the links in this
chain microseismic example are correlated to each
other. Let's call autocorrelation. And this
requires the chain to be run long enough so that
the micro say we started off with is forgotten, we
get something that is called in front rather than
being the same thing with just a few spins flipped.
And depending on the details of the algorithm that
is used to move from one of these states to the
next, those other correlations can linger for
exponentially longer numbers of samples, whereas
more clever algorithms I'm talking about this
afternoon if if there is time. There's more. It's
exponentially speed up the calculations. Or
equivalently, exponentially improve the
uncertainties and the results that we get for a
fixed amount of.
So are there any questions about. An important
sampling for multicolor. The metropolis was ruined
before we talk about the last sort of.
Formal theoretical topic for module.
This last topic before we do some a quick tour of
some border applications going into this afternoon,
because as you can see here, known as universality,
which has to do with phase transitions and in
particular the critical experience that govern
these transitions when in the case of second phase
transitions. So the perimeter is continuous and
there is typically a divergence in one or more of
its derivatives with respect to the control
parameter. So last week, the easy model, we looked
at the critical exponent governing the behavior of
the magnetization as the critical temperature is
approached from below, which. We found two very
four different numbers of dimensions and the
different approximations this is to be was a half
mean case. It was. And indeed, for the exact
solution to the 2D model, and it's just under a
third in the 3D case. That's not analytically
solvable. That can be analyzed numerically if you
algorithms like those just discussed. And in
addition to characterizing the behavior of this
system around its. Phase transition, the regime
where it undergoes its most dramatic changes in
response to these extraordinary parameters in the
course of the 20th century, it was discovered that
precisely the same sets of critical exponents turn
out to appear in these transitions of various
different systems that. You would not have guessed
have anything to do with each other so we can
illustrate this by considering the liquid gas
based transition to the one that we get when we
boil the water in the kitchen and the liquid water
in that kettle goes at first of all, depending on
the pressure on the first or second phase
transition into the atmosphere of the scene. This
is a fascinating topic to look at and could have
been a another supplement if we had more time to
get through things, because it does help to
illustrate even better than the simple, easy model
with the track extends just how. The difficulty
becomes to analyze. Statistical systems, when they
are interacting, so moving away from an ideal gas
to an interacting gas that can have strong enough
interactions to change to a different phase of
being a liquid at lower temperatures.
That removes the factorization that we rely upon
and dealing with with classical or quantum gases.
Before the break. And requires very elaborate.
Mathematical analysis to make any progress,
obtaining predictions from the microscopic degrees
of freedom. So just to not go through any of those
calculations, but sort of flash the results from
them. At least in regimes of low intensity, it's
possible to introduce a systematic approximation
scheme, what's called a cluster expansion that
produces, in the end a modification of the
equation of the state that deviates from the ideal
gas pressure times the volume of the gas equal to
the number of molecules in the gas times its
temperature. And to that leading turn, we can
introduce a series of corrections that depend on
the intensity of the number of atoms per unit
volume in this case that defines, well, that
appears here in the expansion, assuming the role
is much smaller than one. And each term in this
expansion has a factor that depends on the
temperature. It's known as a variable coefficient
for obscure historical reasons. And if you go
through that cluster expansion, you can compute
what this leading variable coefficients is, which
in turn, not surprisingly, depends on the
interaction between. Two particles in this gas, so
moving away from idealogue particles have the
interactions between the particles described by an
interaction energy. And because these gas
particles are not confined to a lattice, we have
no concept of Iraq's neighbors. Rather, the
interaction energy becomes a function of how far
apart those particles are. When they come closer
together, we expect them to tell each other, push
each other away. And larger businesses that can
either continue pushing each other apart or even
become attractive. And. Counteract that short
range reposing.
And while that's that's about the best we can do,
starting from the microscopic degrees of freedom,
this is insufficient to look at the liquid gas
field condition itself just because that phase
transition occurs.
That's a.
Higher density, which is not surprising given the
distinction between the density of liquid versus
gas, is one of the ways they can be distinguished.
The other chief where the professor or how hard it
is to to squeeze. Particles in these two phases
together, how much pressure do for a change? So
the liquid phase can be distinguished from the
gases by the higher density of liquid compared to
a gas. And the political temperature of that
liquid gas based transition can then be identified
when. The gas and liquid phase have equal
densities. Which then implies that this is the
intensity, that the transition is the largest that
the gas can actually reach while still remaining a
gas before it transitions to become a Liquidnet.
So as an alternative approach to this sort of
analysis, rather than starting from the
microscopic interactions between individual pairs
of particles and the gas. We can start from the
end point, that equation states that we would like
to drive instead of driving it, take it as a model
and propose modifications to this model to account
for the features of the interactive gas based on
some qualitative physical arguments. This was.
This approach was pioneered by a fellow named
Denver was so particular equation of state I've
written here is now known as the pendulum swing
states. Miss Daniels was awarded the Nobel Prizes
and one hundred, twelve years ago for work on this
declaration of state and world. Everyone's. In
this case, there are two modifications that would
be. Argued for through handwaving policy arguments
where compared to at times the intensity of the
gas war, you modify both the pressure and the
volume of the gas to account for more realistic
description of the gas particles than the non
interacting, zero sized point particles that we
worked with earlier in this module. So looking
first at this factor of the volume we are
subtracting in times a unknown. Numerical
parameter B, we can assume that. India are
positive numbers. And the interpretation of this
fact that we're subtracting that would get
seclusion is that this B represents the. Nonzero
void is occupied by each of the particles and the
gas, which then has to be subtracted from the
total amount of space, the total volume that the
gas particles have available to themselves. To to
explore and bounce around the.
So that's a fairly simple modification, the change
in the pressure is a little bit trickier to.
To get a handle on it, particularly the fact that
it depends on the density squared, is that the
correction is a bit so small to say that this is
not Zeltzer model. That we can propose to to
analyze interacting gases and their phase
transition to the liquid phase where what's going
on this term is that as the density increases, the
particles, if it's volume, are going to be closer
to each other and their interactions, we can see
what going to be. More likely to produce those
large, repulsive forces that keep the particles
from occupying the same space. So as those
particles are packed more closely together,
they're exerting forces on each other, pushing
each other apart. And that pushing is the same
sort of force that we started off with to derive
the concept of pressure so that this independent
effect gets added to the pressure in this
vanderpoel's equation space as a second deviation
from the ideal gas. So. There's obviously no
detail, derivation or calculation going into all
that. It's just some physically motivated
argumentation.
This these two modifications are sufficient for
this equation of states to correctly describe the
existence of a phase transition between liquidy
gas phases, one with a. Zero permissibility,
another with a larger capacity and similarly with
different values, the density. Now, the details of.
That phase transition and the properties of. The
press's influence on either side of it are not
very accurately described by the variables
equation of states in that sense. Somewhat similar
to the bean field approximation, or at least of
dimensions be correctly predicted, it was a phase
transition of the critical experience that came
out of field analysis were incorrect by
significant factors in the case of two or three
dimensions.
From the analysis of liquid gas disquisition,
based on the Vanderwal equation of states, we can
do that same sort of analysis, find the critical
temperature and predict the set of critical
exponents governing the behavior of observables in
the system around that critical temperature.
This is a second order of transition that is
predicted by the federal secretary of state and if
we look at the inverse of the density. And the
difference between the imprecisely and the cash
space and the liquid phase, this is something that
needs to vanish at that transition, that that's
equal. And. At temperatures slightly below that,
his transition, if you were to. Consider the.
Destitution, the two phases, we would find that
they depended on the temperature. In terms of the
critical experience of the half, which is close
but not quite the value that it can be measured in
physical experiments looking at the densities. Of
these objects, not just for liquid water, boiling
steam before any liquid gas phase transition and
even more, well, various other quantities that
mercury alcohol. Do you think that has a dash
space actually has the same critical explosion be
just under a third independent of precisely what
molecules are showing up in this liquid, this gas?
So it is a. Remarkable fact that this critical
examiner describing the details of this transition
does not depend on. What molecules are the
quantities being condensed to oil? But the even
more surprising bit is that most people want to be
that provisos when looking at the densities of
liquid gas. His transition is exactly the same
value just under the theory that we found for the
magnetization, ferromagnetic transition in the
easy model, in three dimensions on the simple to
replace.
It's tempting to suppose that this may just be a
coincidence. I will just tell you to read the
section that it is not just a coincidence, there
are.
A full set of critical expenses, depending on
which. Observables, we consider it to be a
transition that can be computed to many more
significant figures than I've put down here, and
in all cases they match up precisely between both
that fairly easy transition and the liquid gas
phase transition. And this is. Exactly, the
universality that's. We started off this we
started off to motivate this discussion with
regards to this transition.
So we can appreciate what universality means that
these two completely different systems, a three
dimensional model of interacting spins.
And the liquid gas based position will water or
any other substance are governed by exactly the
same set of critical exponents? Even though the
systems have no connection to each other, there's
no way we can model a bunch of H2O molecules, as
is expensive L.A. and vice versa. But despite that.
The phase transitions that the systems have
behaved exactly the same way as governed by their
set of critical exponents around the phase
transition in this particular set of critical
exponents defines. What has become known as the
universality class, and you can learn a great deal
about any given patronization, any system just by
determining what universality class. This
transition belongs to that immediately tells you
all the most critical explanations of how various
observables behave vicinity of that phase position.
So that's what universality is, where it comes
from is beyond the scope of this model of what it
would be, a focus of a.
Second graduate level follow, of course, if we
were to offer.
This is. The derivation of universality, the
explanation of how and why it can occur in these
physical systems was developed largely in the
1960s and 70s and some important names in that
process. Of course, there more the prominent folks
include Michael Fisher, the catastrophic Nillson,
of whom only Ken Wilson was awarded the Nobel
Prize for this work in the early 80s. And in fact,
at the time, he objected to being the only one
recognized say that all three of them should have.
Should have become the lawyers for the.
Developments of what is called the reorganization
group, even though it's not a group that explains
universality and how it rises. The takeaway
message that was then justified by the work of
these folks this year, Kenneth Wilson and others,
was that. The large scale behavior of statistical
systems and the interactive particles in the
vicinity of critical points is insensitive to the
details of the underlying systems, the degrees of
freedom that define the different possible
microstates. So this is. This can be both a
blessing and a curse this week, we'll see mostly
this afternoon when we look at some broader
applications in the review of this module. The
fact that the microscopic degrees of freedom may
not matter, gravity transition may be covered by
this universal, predictable behavior is one of the
keys that allows simple statistical models like
the easy model to. Really be. Rigorously
applicable in widely different domains.
To. Accurately model and describe and predict the
behavior of physical systems, from theoretical
physics to sociology, epidemiology and more. On
the other hand, there is a downside to
universality if we care what those fundamental
degrees of freedom are, because if in our physics
experiments we are restricted to relatively large,
everyday scales, then all that we can see is
universal behavior that could conceivably have
arisen from widely different sets of fundamental
particles and directions at the. Underlying
microscopic level. So this is, for example, why it
is so hard to establish whether or not string
theory, maybe the physics that underlies phenomena,
perhaps the sales that we're able to access, even
with the Large Hadron Collider proving scales that
are roughly one billion, 10 to minus 15 meters,
that's still large scale compared to the
hypothesized size of fundamental strings that
might be responsible for that scale behavior. But
because that large scale behavior becomes
insensitive to the details of the underlying
microscopic degrees of freedom that interact to
produce it. We can't really say whether or not
string theory is responsible for any given
observation in these experiments. It's just one of
many possibilities that become very hard to to
disentangle.
So I think all more or less wrap up there for the
morning, it's a nice place to stop at the end of
this section to where we've dealt with the last
large scale physics concept of universality that
is important to take away from this molecule. And
just as a preview for the afternoon, I think a
decent use of that final tutorial will be a sort
of quick whistle stop tour of various sorts of
broader applications of the concepts and tools of
statistical physics in other areas of mathematical
sciences represented by other molecules here in
Liverpool, as well as some applications far beyond
what really considered the mathematical sciences.
So what we talk about a few of those this
afternoon won't say much about them. Just a.
Qualitative discussion of motivation and that
could upset some of the power of statistical
physics. It's not worth getting into that here.
I'll just stop. Wrap up by. Reminding us what
we've looked at to round out the. Real
mathematical content of the course, the important
sampling, what the of the various algorithms that
could be defined as to sample microstates
proportional to their unknown probabilities and
then the power of universality to make the
predictions coming from these empirical analysis
or other methods very broadly applicable to full
universality classes with completely different
underlying physical degrees of freedom. So are
there any questions before we take the break, the
meantime, before coming back in the afternoon?
You'll have the chance to ask anything about this
or the module itself the afternoon, so come up
with questions or requests for things to cover,
then take care. Until then.