All right, we can get under way this Friday
morning, after the final homework assignment was
due, so congratulations for completing all of
those in-term assignments.  And before I forget I have six
digits for you this morning:
Four nine, eight three, nine four.
And yes, the remaining milestones to look forward
to are one final week of
content then a couple of weeks until the final
exam on the first of June. So let's do a quick recap
of what we focused on earlier this week to pick things back
up,
so is. Of the today and. Last time we focused on
the Minnifield approximation to using model in
these dimensions. And in particular, the solutions
of self-consistent condition expressed allowable
values of the order parameter, the magnetization.
In terms of function of that, the perimeter itself
is.
To.
The and then
the the over where does not appear be.
So Peter H.
In particular, you're taking a graphical approach
to the intersection of those two functions. We saw
that the.
Solution to this were faced with vanishing or a
parameter becomes unstable. And.
Prefers instead a non-zero value of the
mobilization as the temperature.
Decreases, which is sort of related to that
expression. And we further were able to predict
things to the bean field approximation, giving us
a theory that this change from disorder to to
order the. Phases was actually a true second order.
Phase transition.
At the critical temperature, you see this place,
the number of dimensions of the system, and we
introduced the concept of. And critical questions
of the way in which.
The order parameter, the magnetization. Varies as
the temperature approaches from below is
proportional to the difference to the one half
hour.
For tea, less than political temperature.
And when we wrapped up with a bit of. A bit of a
rush at the end of yesterday was looking at how.
This Manfield approximation, how accurate that
actually is or systems of various dimensions. And
before we revisit that, are there any questions
about the approximation more generally, the way we
derive solutions to it or other aspects of
interacting systems or the biological?
So.
After this. Refer to it a bit more detail about
how well we feel fortunate because we want to turn
from that sort of graphical analysis to something
more mathematical, getting some exact results for
the U.S. model for one dimension, and then in two
dimensions, the two dimensional case will probably
spill over into next Monday. But one dimensions,
we will surely see that there is, in fact, phase
transition at all. This is a model which slightly
contradicts the prediction from the battlefield
approximation of that second of transition at TCT
sequels to one equals one. So we will prove an
absence of a phase transition that the complete
failure of your model and we will also see we
won't be able to solve the two dimensional case
and see why, but we will be able to determine.
It's critical temperature that. Can be found
through a trick of this duality and actually
agrees with the exact solution that all results
are derived. It's a famous work in the 1940s. And
comparing that exact solution to meaningful
approximation, things are a bit better than the
one dimensional case, we now have the exact
solution. And believe your approximation, the
prediction for a second phase transition at some
of the quantitative details are not quite right.
So the critical temperature and the exact case is
just over two. It's up to point to seven point
forty four. And that should be compared with the
ticker for predicting that we could feel more. So
it's all about a factor of two. And the critical
exponents that the legislation is proportional to
comes out to be one based in two dimensions rather
than the one half that we feel. That theory
predicts the approximation, as you call it. So.
There's a correct qualitative prediction of your
second phase transition, but the real details of
that transition are still not captured by the wind
field approach, but aside. Mentioned things do
keep getting better and higher and higher
dimensions. The reason for that being that in
higher dimensions, each site has more nearest
neighbors, so
replacing those by an average would mean over them,
does a better job of capturing the actual behavior
of the system. And the complication now is that
once we get to dimensions, there is no known
analytic solution to the using hole, and such a
solution may not even exist. But both the.
Parameter and. Critical experience can be computed
from numerical analysis to establish that there is
indeed a phase transition for all the time the
national theories. And you can use those numerical
calculations to compute the corresponding critical
temperature and critical exposures that we can
compare to the Millfield predictions. So in three
dimensions, which has been studied, a lot of this,
the focus of the magazine article I put up on the
site there is. Actually, precise values to several
significant figures for both the critical
temperature and the critical time only put down to
significant figures here just because that's all
we need to compare to the need for oxidation.
We're now about three quarters of the way to the
minefield prediction of three dimensions, critical
temperature of six compared to the true four point
five. And the critical exponent compared to lower
dimensions is steadily creeping up toward the main
field limit. So from. One eighth to a little under
a third president predicts about half. And sort of
similar calculations with less precision have been
carried out in four or five, six and seven
dimensions. Finding. For instance, the critical
temperature is steadily approaching, that too deep
coming from the main fuel approximation. So if we
compare. The numerical results, two, eight, 10, 12
and 14 for those for different nationalities that
the use, the model, we see that the discrepancy
drops from about 20 percent to about 10 percent
going up through those higher dimensions than the
formal limit where the dimensionality goes to
infinity. Every state has an infinite number of
nearest neighbors that capture the true
magnetization of the system there in the field.
Approximation actually becomes exact in that
abstract limit. So. That was just a few final
comments about the mutual approximation that ran
out of time to cover Tuesday. And now we will turn
to justify some of the claims in here for the
other dimension to exact results right now and
then going into some of the ideas behind those
numerical analysis on. In both cases, the showing
of techniques that can be applied to using
violence that are much more generally useful for
more complicated sorts of systems and reactions.
Some of the questions about that wrap up before
moving on to some more formal mathematical
manipulations.
So let's begin this consideration of the one
dimensional exact result just by recalling the
system in question, back up the. Figure from last
week that I used to adjust the focus of the
project this morning and here recalled that with
periodic boundary conditions, the inside is a
model in one dimension simply can be represented
as the circle, the wagons and the number of links
between nearest neighbor pairs of sites is
actually the same number as the overall number of
sites there are and links for and sites. Because
we can just see by observation or count by seeing
that each site connected to links connects the two
sites. So this allows uniquely in one dimension.
This special property is that we can take
advantage of the. A limited number of links per
site to rewrite some of our nearest neighbour
cares just as Asama over those links. We count
from one up to n take the product of the spin it
side in and the spin cycle plus one that accounts
for every single link that we have in this picture,
which I'll probably put up on the board in just a
few minutes.
So. We. Take this some oversights and some of the
links with some of the some of the sites, we can
combine that with the some of the sites that
already appeared in the internal energy for the
U.S. model coupled to that external magnetic field.
For later convenience, we do a trivial
manipulation of adding each side twice and
dividing by two in order to have the two terms and
the internal energy, both involving spin and plus
one. The product coming from your name appears in
the net coupling to the.
So inserting this into our petition from the
so-called spin configurations of exponential
growth. Might this be the times, the internal
energy that some so the exponential of the song
turns into the product of exponential and the sum
over speed configurations? It is just this long
series of different sounds over the two values,
plus or minus one that each of the hospitals can
adopt. So what we want to do is the same. Approach
is not an attractive case, but we were able to
distribute all of those and sums over the spins in
a hyperbolic cosine out of each one that just
recently have power. But now there's a
complication coming from the. Term with both sub
and an estimated one, namely that on any given
spin is going to appear twice in this product over
the site once when excellent response to anyone
else wants to. For example, spend five is going to
appear both equals five and you have to spend five
times to six, but also in equals four. It has been
four times five. And if we were to freely solve
both of those contributions over those values of
spin, we would include inconsistent on physical
contributions where the value of the spin was not
being treated so consistently. We're looking at
one of the two nearest neighbor interactions
compared to its other one.
So the. Elliott, way to impose these constraints
that the. Spain has the same value. Both times, it
appears, is to recast the.
Exponential factors multiply here as a matrix and
use matrix multiplication to ensure that.
Carry through the information about what speed has,
so first to define this two by two matrix. I'm
going to call it an oversight and where each of
the components corresponds to the four possible
combinations. Of values, the spins that site and
then one in these exponential factors. So as an
example, if both S7 plus one are one, we pick up E
to the positive Baida and one plus one of the two
is to be the H in the next one for the final term
as the sun cancels its drops out of the products
minus one.
And if we consider taking the product of two of
these matrices.
You will see that in that Matrix product. The. The
road here, for instance, is going to be contracted
with the first column, so the value is where?
Spirit then has minus one or both going to be
contracted.
I should have focused on the diagonal pieces,
really, so contracting both of these spin minus
ones with the second column of the next matrix in
the row incorrectly pick up the value of the spin
minus one in a consistent way. So hopefully, if
this is not intuitively obvious and something, you
can convince yourself that possibly by writing
down some further examples, but going over the
product of all these two by two matrices, we will
end up contracting all of the internal indices
that correspond to the repeated values of the
spin's will be left only with the spin one and
spin capital and plus one either side of that
product and periodic common conditions then
identify those. So we call that. Economic
conditions imposed plus one is exactly the same as
a one, so. Closing that loop and ensuring that.
The value of this single spin wrapping around the
periodic boundary is also self-consistent, just
gives us the overall cyclic trace. Of that product
of all matrices. My question
is, why was. And. The choice is what better
conditions to perform order? Of the Trece.
So what that trace is doing, if we write that out,
we can drop the index and because as we can see,
all of these matrices are actually independent of
them, just call the T.. So this trace is giving us
benefactors of this matrix so as to buy that I
enjoy are those two values of the spin system one
and two. That is correct. That's been true. It's
been three. We have some consistent values of
students. That's why the state index appears to be
sold over shake and so on. Similarly, T.J., L. all
the way to this tea and call it capital and then.
What would be enforced when that is identified
with speed by the very first Conex? So we have the
in the final index on this product of matrices is
the same as the first one and also has to be some
over. In that song, to produce or to impose this
constraint that the same value of the state
appears in.
Both terms in both the actions that was involved
and we can recognize that I already put the sign
there, but this Matrix product with all of the
indices cyclically contracted is indeed the
definition of the phrase. Which is also useful
because it gives us just the single number that
the petition function is rather than a two by two
matrix. So this is the simplest case we can also
consider.
More complicated situations where periodic
boundary conditions are not imposed and some of
the standards will have different numbers in your
state attraction to that case, you would still get
a trace of all of the spins in the middle of that
chain with different factors appearing to accept
the absence of periodic boundary conditions. But
it is the. I guess the trace, in essence, is that
reflection of how the periodic boundary conditions
simplify the set up, as we saw before, by ensuring
that all of the sites have the same number of
links.
So. I'll leave that there for now. I keep thinking
about all of this remains unclear. We can move
forward to, actually. Try to solve our partisan
function, which is now written in a more compact
way, and we originally had it's just the trees and
powers of this two by two matrix that are in the
business is known as the transfer matrix, the idea
being that it's transferring information about the
value of a given spin from one week to the next so
that the links are treating. That's been in a
self-consistent way.
And if we want to.
Figure out the trace of a large number of
identical products in The Matrix. The simple way
to do that is to diagnose the Matrix and then all
of these powers simply.
Carry through into powers of the eigenvalues that
appear on the diagonal, so multiplying diagonal
matrices, it's easy in that sense and then taking
the trace itself is also easy is just the sum of
those powers of in this case for two by three
matrices, these two. Different eigenvalues, I've
called them the plus and minus.
Yes, this may well be the. First time of matrices
and relations are appearing in this particular
module, so I can. Check in and remind you or ask,
what is the strategy to stabilize the matrix of
this or how do we find these eigenvalues lamda
plus or minus?
See?
Rather than.
Putting that on your list gives you the reminder
this is the. So the first appearance that the
eigenvalues are coming from the roots of the
characteristic polynomial. So we take the
determinants of this matrix to the transfer matrix,
subtract. Lamda minus the identity and the look at
the detriment of vets that are represented by the.
Square eliminators on either side of that matrix,
so. Subtracting that language just modifies the
diagonal components of this matrix, using the data
in the data minus lambda.
Either the White House made the afternoon holds
the key to the beat of the White House page, again
minus Linda, if we take the determination that
it's just the product of the was minus the product
at the time to two cities are simple in that way.
So we can pull out that positive factor of Lambda
Square. It will be two negative factors,
Portugal's lamda, both of which have either
positive baylon, one of which has either debated
each other as to why this day and age.
Plus, sign about the overall negative sign there.
And then finally, the product of those commercials.
Gives us the use of the two Beira plus or minus
chancel and subtracting the product off nine one
is each of the minus two data, which we can.
Recognize as corresponding to some of those nice
hyperbolic trigonometric functions, we have the.
Lambda Square. Minus Lamda times to Coche. That is
the way to cool. For the rival, so will either the
X plus, even minus X, the cosine and similarly the
two terms in the X minus equal minus six are twice
the hyperbolic sign now of two data rather than a
H. And we want to find the lambda, which is
characteristic polynomial is equal to zero which.
We can get just from the.
Quadratic equation varlet, why I was calling the
eigenvalue Linda plus and minus is there will be a
plus or minus appearing in the solutions here that
we. That factor over to a survey was commissioned
by the Square. That's one A minus B is the
negative of the coefficient of 11 to. Used to be
the hyperbolic cosine each. And then plus or minus
the square root of the discriminant B squared, or
he'd be to bad A. Cos squared in H and then minus
four, a C factor of eight.
Some of you better
and we can check easily enough that this
expression. First of all, we can cancel out the
fact that you to all the way through with it seems
to a slightly simpler.
Because we're interested in systems with. Now,
negative temperatures and zero positive, as well
as negative externalities like fields, how we
define the.
Those parameters that appear in here for those
regimes, both of these eigenvalues possibilities
are real. So that you factor in the square root is
positive. And it's easy enough to see that the
solution that the plus side is always going to be
larger than that with the negative side. Thanks to
the reality of that security factor, we can check
that has been close to zero, this expression, so
the temperature is going to be a very high
temperature limit there by cosigns. Go to one. Has
to be exponential factors. And we end up with the
factor of one from the first term and the
sensuousness hero square root of one from the
second term, which is one plus or minus one.
Independent of that external fuel and especially
case zero field easing automotive, we turn off the
external fuel set to zero. That also puts those
hydraulics lines to one. And. We ended up just
with.
Because in that. It's somewhere.
So I think the margin will be zero. And the plus
minus is just. That's E Tanabata. From seven to
one with zero plus or minus the square root. Two
data from the cost minus the essential to the data,
which is needed to be the. Minus the. Minus two
beta taking account of that factor of two in their.
Those two factors cancel out the positive, the
minus two beta squared. That gives us either the
beta plus or minus the minus beta as advertised.
Is twice the sign, the sign satisfying? The
overall. Expected behavior that the task is always
truly greater than divide us, and if if we we can
numerically plot all of this for the case of both
non-zero speed and age, the typically this.
There's a very large exponential hierarchy between
those two eigenvalues, but in any case, because
LAMDA plus is the larger eigenvalue, we can
rewrite our partition function
before we have to trust the power in this name
minus the power. And if we pull out of a factor of
LAMDA plus to the end times one plus that ratio of
the two eigenvalues as then becomes sufficiently
large.
Something less than one race to a large power.
It's going to be driven down to zero, leaving us
just with. And even simpler expressions for the
action function is the largest eigenvalue to the
power of the number of spins in our one
dimensional system. It can be right here pulling
out the overall factor of the hyperbolic cosine of.
Just to further emphasize how this is always. A
real positive result. So there it is, we've solved
the one dimensional using model. That's what the
solution looks like and it's not really.
Revelatory to sit and stare at all these
exponential factors, what we can do to extract
information from the solution is to use this to
predict some observables and in particular, we're
interested in the order parameter for the. Ordered
in disorder phases that we've been considering
this week as the metaphysician that we have
related to a derivative of the free energy. With
respect to the external magnetic field and maybe
worth mentioning, we're emphasizing in this
calculation that the order of limits.
Those that will take an interview tomorrow and
we're going to consider the zero field.
Is what the countries where we obtain solutions
from the population on Tuesday and.
Considering that Israel will limit, we have to set
the field to zero only after. Taking this
derivative of the free energy and getting the
result for people to parameter by doing that, we
don't have to worry about the absolute value that
we. Introduced, we were doing things more
heuristically last week.
And what we find so. We. Like in.
The.
Expression here that the petition functions said
is land of lost to power and then.
There is some simplification that.
Occurs to the derivative, so first of all, the
more that that power can bring down a factor in
the case that the one in the denominator and the
derivative of the logarithm is one over argue into
the law of the law. So.
Instead, at the end, pick up that one over there,
plus you still have to bailout the derivative of
us with respect to that magnetic field and then
evaluated that it will set off the magnetic field.
So what is that derivative of eigenvalue, the
transfer matrix with respect to the field? But at
it from. I work above
the times, I'd like to assign each the positive
side. And the square root. On to the costs would
have been a. Miles, to synch
to to better.
So each of these terms is going to. The main after
taking the H. On the eve of the bailout, we'll
just pass through the derivative of the cost is
going to give us hyperbolic some of bit H and when
we take the derivative of the square root of this
discriminators the quadratic equation, something
interesting happens, people.
So the argument for the square root will go to the
denominator. We have one over that square root of
the square and then the. Chain rule takes the
derivative of that argument.
Into the numerator, and if we call that, we can
pull out net overall growth sector. We can see
that in the second term, there will be an overall
factor of. Two times the coshed times the senge,
so overall up to some complicated, no matter what
the square root equations, both terms here and the
proportional to the hyperbolic senge, and when we
set that set H to zero, the argument of that
hyperbolic sentence goes to zero and we find
overall. That would setting it to zero in the
expression for the immigration.
We have zero magnetization with the zero
independent of the temperature, so. This is
something this application coming from the zero
field case. And what's more, it is the.
The proof of the claim that we discussed at the
end of our consideration that we feel
approximation. Zero field using one dimension has
no pasteurisation at all. The position is always
zero responding personality disorder phase, even
as the temperature goes to be vanishingly small
value. So. That is, of course, revealing the
administrations of the need for an approximation
before the election where there are a minimal
number of nearest neighbor interactions for the
system. We can also recall that last week we tried
to treat the independence of the dimensionality
and claim that there were always these two
different places at high temperatures and this one.
And that argument that we went through with
General mention is. Again, it is also being
contradicted by this exact result in the
individual case, so it's worth Rabinow. This.
Consideration of the individual case by thinking
about what went wrong in our discussions last week,
a bit more heuristic in terms of.
The two faces of these high temperatures will be
argued that high temperatures, all of the
microstates Appu with roughly equal probability.
And therefore, to the distribution of spin's with
the largest multiplicity wins. So that's the
factorial enhancements of the disorder stage with
roughly equal distance. And in contrast, we have
argued that more temperatures there is an
exponential preference for border states close to
the ground states where. We claim that the first
extended interview level was exponentially
suppressed and corresponded to the value of the
mobilization that was close to the maximum value
on. We treated that first extended energy level as
what we would have upon flipping a single skin.
Against the line, the others have taken this from
the ground, say the line to this first excited
state and there were no objections when we went
through that class is true for two dimensions at
higher. But there are uniquely in one dimension.
Difference.
States that also have the same energy as you can
get the biggest single step, and this is where it
might be worthwhile to draw that. So. Motivational
system on the board, if I suppose that you can
have. The same number of spins, more circular
pattern, feeling the links between them, one of
the ground states is where all the moral and the
negative about this line is to denote the minus
one down for the spin and consider flipping one of
those two plus spin plus one. This was one of the
microstates that. Has the maximum next of energy
for One Direction's. Instead of a minus and all
this in line to take out a positive contribution
to the energy of a plus two from each of you to
separate your actions of that spirit, that is an
energy, a minus and plus for. And there are days
where any one of these things can be said. So that
is what we went through before. And what happens
in one dimension or in one dimension, but not in
higher dimensions, is if we were to slip another
step and say this one up here, you would have a
higher energy positive contributions for those two
things, which is those two things. But if we were
to foot one of the two things, number one, we
already flipped. We now get back to a negative
contribution for the interaction between those two.
They are alive. And we still only have two
positive contributions now from these two. And
there's not clear for me to distinguish things in
here from these two links that surround the. Set
of neighboring spins that are aligned in the
opposite direction. So this is another microstates
that contributes to that first excitement and
again. Imagine rotating all these around the
circles near the other end possibilities,
and the same thing happens if we took the next
step again only
to positive contributions at the energy level as
more and more of the overall mobilization is
decreasing further and further away from. The
value of one, and in the case that I have out here,
we have flipped enough spins to have a vanishing
position with the same energy, that first energy
level. So it is not the case that all of the
microstates in this first extended interview will
have evangelisation close to one of the largest
Nimetz.
That is unique to one dimension where the rough
argument from last week was too, too quick to be
correct in that we have an exact solution. We can
see that accounting for all of these other
microstates with different elements of the
taxation that contributes to that first excitement,
excitement, energy level.
Ends up.
Removing the possibility of an order phase and a
transition in this one dimensional case. And.
It is useful in this exercise to. Draw and sort of
what I have here with these.
Double lines separating these domains of skills
that are on the line in one particular direction.
So this sort of analysis is often presented in
terms of walls, barriers between those two domains
where for the students boycott all the students
put down. And because if either of these domain
walls move around the system, they don't introduce
any energy costs. They. Shift the positive
contribution from one week to the next without
change the total number, we can analyze the system
as well as they can create a group so that we as a
country to grow without any energy costs. Covering
all values of the magnetization. With at least one
spin.
Not aligned with all the others, so covering that
nearly full range that approaches the full range
of atomisation as in increases so.
That's where our earlier discussion went wrong
with the one dimensional case and we will pick up
on Monday with the calculation of the two
dimensional critical temperature
there's. Not much point in starting that just in
the remaining minute shipping, this stopping point
at the end of the exact one dimensional solution I
just mentioned historically, this is this exact
solution and one dimensions is but using found is
the work that led him to conclude that the easy
model could not actually describe phase
transitions. Of course, at that point. So the
demonstration. That these conditions are indeed
possible, higher dimensions is a necessary step to
using models adoption and brought use to talk
about all sorts of things that the motivation.
When coming back from the spring break last week,
so we'll pick up with. What do you do about Monday?
Are there any questions about the one that is
involved before we shut down for this morning?
Not seeing any I will see you back in the
afternoon to over the. Variations of the model and
different set of structures and possibly other
fun things as time permits accuracy, then.