Okay, I think we can get going. Welcome to the final week of the teaching
term in Statistical Physics.  With the printer again
having trouble, we'll be a bit more impromptu
than usual today.  So starting with the six-digit code
for the system: six one, seven seven,
zero three.
The plan for today is now that we're in the last
week, we can do some more fun stuff looking at so-called
Kramers--Wannier duality that may be the most
mathematically complex bit of calculation that
we do.  But before we dive into dualities, let's
just regroup after the weekend and recall
the other part of the supplemental information
that we've been going through, on exact solutions to
these simple realizations of the Ising model.  So in
one dimension on Friday, we exactly solved that
using model, just this chain of spins pointing
either up or down with a vicious circle, the power
to split itself with the one, and that exact
solution gave us some nasty closed form expression
for the partition function, which. We don't
directly care about so much except as a means to
compute observable expectation values through
derivatives of free energy. So first of all, the
reason that we were able to solve this model in
one dimension and more was thanks to. The relation
between the links and sites, so there were the
same number of links as there were sites, and you
could rearrange the some of our nearest neighbor
interaction terms so as to recast it into a some
oversight's with constraints imposed on the values
of the site every point it appeared in that
petition function. That will be resolved through.
Formulating the calculation in terms of the
transfer matrix, matrix multiplication. Imposing
those constraints automatically for us, those
constraints will be something that comes up again
today in two dimensions. Now from the results for.
Magnetization coming from the. Derivative of the
free energy with respect, the feel feel our exact
solution. That was always vanishing for any
temperatures, for increased temperature data. So.
There is no easy transition at all in the one
dimensional realization, the easy ball that was
initially studied in the 1920s, which means, first
of all, that meaningful approximation that
predicts a second order phase transition. At a
critical temperature of two in this case would be
a critical experience of a half. You confirmed
that this fails badly in what direction, given
quantitatively the right results and our earlier
discussion in Section two that identified the
order disorder phases of using model without
explicitly considering the dimensionality also
failed.
Because it didn't take into account.
The.
Tussler microstates for that first excited energy
level that could have any value of the
magnetization.
Serrations.
We phrase this in terms of domains of upward and
downward, what extends with domain walls between
the necrophiliac to move around the system,
producing microstates with any value of
magnetization, but the same energy.
Is one of the arguments that we went through more
quickly, probably we than first considering using
moral high and low temperature limits.
So are there any questions about. The one the
exact solution more. Anything that came before it,
before we go and see what we can do in one
dimension higher up in the two dimensional system.
Although. The two dimensional using model with.
Zero zero feel and the square lasts without any
frustration. There is an exact solution for the
system by Morrisson Singer of the 1940s, which is
sort of a superhuman feat of mathematics. That is
one of those things you can read through it and
don't really learn anything except that the
Vatican installations all over Dallas. But
historically, in fact, before about three years
before Einziger came up with that solution, there
was a bit of a breakthrough made by two other
physicists named Tom Kramers and Gregory William.
We're actually able to determine the exact
critical temperature of the two dimensional using
model without being able to solve it. And then
Ozgur subsequently proposed a solution, is able to
confirm and check that it did indeed reproduce
this critical temperature that we will be dropping
today, possibly wrapping up tomorrow morning. This
is one of the more complicated calculations that I
don't want to to rush through the basic idea. Just
to have a goal in mind as we go through this
supplementary subsection is that we want to show
that two different easy models at different but
related in temperature is better until they are
related with these funny looking three factors
that we were hoping to derive to the petition
function for that to the easy model that
temperature data is that proportional to. The
partition partition for the difference is the
model in two dimensions at a different.
Temperature, Tilde, and the specific relation
between beard and beard is held, it is given by
the inverse relationship between a hyperbolic
cinches of too big and too big to kill. So this is
this relation is now known as Kramers
biodegradability and is one of the earliest
examples of. This more general concept of duality,
not the earliest, but one of the real
breakthroughs in its development where duality has
become one of the most powerful tools in twenty
first century theoretical physics, perhaps most
famously through so-called holographic duality,
stimulate certain theories of quantum gravity to
simpler systems that resemble, in many ways the
physical systems we've been working with,
especially in this unit on track and theories. So
one thing to note in this equation, 120 to related
to temperatures of the two parties and functions,
is that when one of these babies is large, as
large, the the other must be small. So there's an
inverse relation between the temperature and the
dual temperature. The same thing holds if it is
small, the atmosphere must be large. And so it's
also for the temperature itself. So this is
another general feature of Dallis that. One of the
pairs of dual systems is that some high
temperature or resemble settings, a strong
coupling, and it gets related to a different
system and a low temperature or recoupling. And
vice versa, which allows different approximation
techniques to be applied in those different
regimes. So one thing we could do to the build up
to this overall result of going after is then
carry out the high and low temperature expansions
of the two dimensional model, much as we did for
knowledge and systems. And also, as we saw for
some of the homework problems even last week,
really, we replaced discrete spins with variables
and looked at the high temperature limits simplify
in the interests of time. Even though this is a
supplement, we will skip over that exercise.
You can find the basic methods to do it in some of
the the references that
are in the very beginning of the lecture, notes
David Thomas lectures on statistical physics. The
only downside to skipping that motivational
exercise is looking at the high and low
temperature limits of existing models. Is that
some of the tricks we will apply are motivated by
that and that seem to come out of thin air just
going through things more directly. The first of
those is is an example where we start off with two
is multiplication function that we know of
exponential with minus beta types. The energy
energy itself is that some of our own neighbor
repairs of the product of spins on those nearest
the sites magnetic field is set to zero and we fix
two dimensions. So each site has four nearest
neighbors in this cell. Left, right and up and
down. Now, as usual, the exponential sum is
converted to the product of exponential factors
and then
uniquely because the speed variables and the easy
model are always just plus or minus one another,
they are multiplied or not. We can rewrite the
exponential factor in terms of hyper trigonometric
functions, which is easy to check just by brute
force. If we plug in the possibility SJS K
positive one, then on one side. This identity
we've declared would have. Plus, Lustbader, and on
the other side, you would have a clash. He's a
debater plus into the minus beta, plus the cinch,
if the beta minus even want to speed up. Where
those two terms cancel and we get even better
equals to the better. And similarly, the only
other possible.
Set up where the product is negative. On the left
hand side, that picks up the negative one to be to
the negative bitter and the negative sides appear
in a slightly different place from the other
presence of that factor of SJT Times case. So now
it's the Pluspetrol terms that cancel. And we've
confirmed this first. Rewriting of the protection
function in terms of. Cautious and cinches of the
temperature with this factor, the nearest neighbor,
skin products, time to ask.
And. What we are going to do with that expression
is rewrite the sum of two terms as an explicit sum
over two terms. Where we will raise this product
spent SJS Cages of Power PJAK, so a different
power for every year as they prepare for the every
link in the labs and we will multiply that by a
baby dependent's prefecture, the capital C, with
that same subscripts, that power of zero one
responding to the side of. Times something to the
power. Zero is just cosmetic by itself, when see
when P equals one, we identify C one with the of
data with a escaped space. The power one.
So. We now have a product overall to add links in
this two dimensional lattice and we some over a
variable power that takes two values for each of
those to add links.
And if we just simplify the organization of this.
Is to rearrange this product of Solms into the
so-called configuration systems of just the same
sort of setup that we've been dealing with in
terms of the spins on the log and the partition
function, the microstates are defined by all
possible configurations of spins, happy values,
plus one or minus one point down. And we can
recognize that this combination of the product and
some is also accounting for all possible
combinations of these powers being either zero or
one now on the two end wings of the two
dimensional. That is with us.
And I will probably start talking more loosely
that whenever one of these powers, PJAK equals one,
we can say that the corresponding link between
sites Chain K is on and similarly, that link is
off when that power equals zero sum of all
possible configurations of. Ways of turning the
two lakes all off in the system. So that is sort
of the first big step toward the Kramers wanted.
Well, it is so clear so far what we are doing is
not necessarily by.
If there are objections coming up for that, I was
shocked about, but by recasting this product of
cells in terms of their configuration, so we are
left with a convenient. Products as the innermost
level of operations we have to do to define this
function, which is convenience, we can split it up
into the two parts, one of which depends on the
temperature data, but not Austins, the other of
which depends on spins, not on that in temperature.
And.
Focusing on the. Only remaining evidence of the
spin that isolated this to be a product of all
pairs of skins, nearest neighbor gators over all
the links to the LAS. So within that product, over
all of those legs, any given spin is going to show
up four times. So if that is the standard
deviation of these four nearest neighbors in two
dimensions all over each of those four legs.
Next
on this one at.
Yes.
Up. The four powers of Essive Ed raised to the
four different key variables to respond to
individually each of these four legs. I think
what is shown on the next page,
so there was a. Type in here that I connected my
hands and that was printed and copied, so each
link appears in four times the sum over words for
nearest neighbors. So we can define the overall
part of those four factors of the spin as that
leads to a capital P power that depends only on
the site and sums over all of the. Lower case
powers, zero or one, the corresponding to these
four banks being either on or off.
And then.
Repeating that for all and of the links all end of
the spectrum, the system. Accounting for all of
the. Links that they are attached to. We can move
the configuration over to the spin's themselves
through the skin independence concept vectors, see
the OR side. And consider what happens in the
overall plot oversights as we sum over all
possible values for the individual things that are
now raised to this complicated power, some for.
There are variables to zero one that live on the
four legs that has to be slight.
And as there are.
Only two possible values that each state can take,
the sum of each of the state variables in the
configuration. Some is fairly easy to think about.
It will break up in the usual way like this on the
long track, Chase will have. Horsfield. Yes, and
because neither minus one, plus one in the song,
you have the stuff going to one to this karaoke
and plus minus one race to the. So if Pat is on,
then those positive and negative contributions
will cancel. It will be the contribution of 08,
the petition function from that particular site
for this particular stinking federation. And as it
is a product overall site, the product as a whole
will be set to zero and just vanish. So the only
contributions to the petition function will come
when this summer over the powers of the four
nearest neighbor lakes is even either zero, two or
four. Those are the only possibilities that we
have, in which case these two contributions will
add some up to two. So. Any non-zero contribution
to the protection function will bring in this
factory to. And a chronic or delta defined here,
that is Delta up two to develop the knowledge to
chronic or Delta where this is very similar to the
usual chronic delta. It is one whenever the
argument is that even number. So it equals zero
bodies to.
Vanishes if the arguments over the powers are
never as much as non-zero.
So we can pull out those benefactors of to. In
front of all of the rest of the mutilations going
on that were left with just a. Product. Well,
that's. Break down, what is going on in? This
equation, 123 of the milestones of the procedure.
We have. No more thumbs over the stills, so all of
the original spin degrees of freedom have been
sold over that configuration. So you've accounted
for all of them and are left with the Cortini
configuration. So we introduced over the Powers
011. So Oversight's.
And for all of those considerations, we take the
product of regulatory functions. Over all of those
sites and then multiply that by the product out
and by two product deltas that require that. For
peace on both sides or add up to an even number,
some even number of links connected to each site
is turned on and. The key that makes this tricky.
Is that in order for that product to be down zero,
every single site has to have an even number of
links connected to it as we go across this whole
two dimensional lattice and sites. So there are
there's a set of and interrelated constraints on
this petition function. As
as we checked, to make sure that all the powers
connected to giving sites and even number of those
powers also affect the similar things at all, the
nearest neighbor sites that have their three other
contributions that then have to add up to even
numbers in terms.
Although we've taken care of the original some of
the Oscar configurations you now have at the.
The new configuration cell that we introduced over
configurations of links being pulled off is now
subject to an interrelated constraints.
Ensuring that at every later sites there is a.
Even number of links to another zero two four four.
And what these constraints are. Effectively
telling us is that the on off variables we've
introduced are not really independent, which may
be intuitively obvious given that there are twice
as many links interventions as there are sites.
And if we started off with a statistical system
that had only been seven degrees of freedom with
two values we've tried to rewrite, we've
successfully rewritten that in terms of a
different set to enter those again, each with two
values, zero one rather than plus or minus one.
There is necessarily some redundancy in. The sum
of all configurations of that larger number of
degrees of freedom that is representing the
original system. So at this point, if you were
trying to solve the easy model in this way, we
might seem a bit stuck in possibly going down the
wrong alley.
And maybe I should pause before going out just to
check in that everything, the manipulation is
going on so far here, along with the qualitative
story that. We've done a bunch of manipulations to
our system and something that, if anything, looks
even trickier to solve than be at our starting
points in terms of the degrees of freedom.
The. triple-O. The key is that having gone through
this procedure to replace the original seven
degrees of freedom with these new link variables,
people subject for years, they say, OK, we can
partially undo, unwind that work by introducing a
new set of. Spins plus or minus one, and then try
working backwards to get more or less back to our
starting points, but we're not exactly undoing
everything we've done. And getting back to the
original case, we want to do something a bit
different. So that we don't just. Undo all the
work we did, but instead simplify the current
expressions to get back to something that we can
recognize as. No easy model. So.
While we are introducing a new set of plus or
minus one spins, these have to be a different set
than the original ones we started off with so that
we can then. Come up with some relation between
the original spinnerets. And these so-called dual
spins, so still that that are associated with each
side and like the original spin's, take the values
plus or minus one. That we now want to relate to
the values of the powers that without the link.
The mathematical expressions here at the bottom of
the page that do this relation are maybe.
Unintuitive to look at what we have, we can easily
check that these products of the Tilted Spin's
take values plus or minus one, so that when we
have one minus that product of the two that
corresponds to.
Link powers of either zero one player, but how
exactly we decided that the. Power of link one
four should be related to dual spans, three and
four is best revealed by. Identifying these dual
stems with the geometry of the latter system. And
specifically identifying them with the so-called
dual address, which is on a more basic concept
that we've not really gone into so much in this
module. The idea is that.
Dual legacies are those that connects the central
points of each of the cells of the specifically
two dimensional lattice, it's easier to see where.
We draw a small
square lattice in two dimensions and go through
the procedure, I mentioned connecting all the
symptoms of this.
I swear that is the size of that square lattice
identified with the centers of the placates of the
original letters and what we have done in the
equations on the previous page,
20 feet on the screen, or what is related to the
two dual spins to the link of the original lattice
that crosses between them. So if I draw in the
duel links that do a lattice. We can see that. We
want to hear between spin one, spin two is
separating dual spins, one to agree with that. But
if we go to the other side where that link one for
separating the other pair of dual spins. As to the
three and the four, and it's this graphical
procedure that uniquely specifies how each link in
the original lattice is connected to the pairs of
dual standards that separates so.
That duopolies construction is how all of these
relations are determined, specifying which link
variable is connected to which to spin variables,
and
what we can see based on that connection is, first
of all, that we are reaffirming that the link
variables are not all dependent. We can see that,
for example, two of them are depend on each of the
first things that we have considered here. So if
you want to amplify both depend on which will spin
as to the one.
And for instance, one four people, one three both
depend on the doorstep, three rapidly, that's just
because there are.
Links to the original Latisse appearing on both
sides of each of the dual Spillane's that we've
put into this universelle that is that generalized
for all and. Spins in the form two dimensional
lattice, as well as the dual two dimensional as.
In addition to confirming that the link variables
PJAK, the powers that be introduced, manipulations
of the petition function
in addition to confirming that there's not
independence, the patterns of dependence that we
have introduced by working in terms of these dual
variables are exactly what we need to take care of
the. Not to try to belittle factors in the sense
that if we look at the four powers that
contributes to. This particular spin at the center
of the cell here.
And add up all of the foreign contributions in
terms of the two things we get for factors, half
the world is.
For factors of happiness, for relations and then
subtracting from that, the sum over all four pairs.
Of products of dual spins, which we can factor
into a product of to some of the spins. With
digital spin as being either. Plus one or minus
one, there are only three values that the sum of
two of them can take.
Minus two, zero and plus two, if we have both of
them being a plus two, then we have four of the
two is to try to give us a zero. If all four of
them are, if you like, minus two. We have. This is
the same minus two squared is four two two zero,
if any of them are zero factors. So plus one minus
four plus one plus minus one that we just have the
two left over. And if one set is.
Plus two and the other is minus. And we have two
minus two or four, so the only possibilities that
are allowed by the usual spin formulation are for
the number of links to other sites to be even so
that the product over all those interdependent.
Trying to give Delta functions not to just
collapses to to be one.
And.
We already, to some extent, went through the other
exercise, the other piece of the puzzle that needs
to be in place in order for this dualistic
formulation to be a legitimate way of rewriting
the system.
We have to be able to show that all possible. Oh,
values or possible ways of obtaining. Even numbers
of links to sites are accounted for by the dual
standards that we have defined their relations to.
The links that appear between them.
So we've shown that zero, two and four are all
accounted for and right at. Explicitly.
If we set this sum over the next one to be four,
then that's rearranges to tell us that the product
of these two sons of the dual spin's.
Has to be negative for. So. Rearranging, pulling
that one half spin product backward to the left
hand side, we get it equal to two times to minus
for just two times negative two, which is four.
And the only way to achieve that with the spin is
plus or minus one is to have one of the factors,
the two multiplied by the other being negative two.
So. There are two ways.
Achieving that either.
One in three, both being one, two and four, both
being negative one or the opposite, flipping every.
Stephen.
In a coordinated way.
So in general, at least for single example, we've
been looking at here.
There are two configurations of the dual spin's
that leave the corresponding to each configuration
of the link powers that be reformulated our system
and to start off with so interchangeable.
Of those dual spins to negative values.
And all of the P j k factors. Would be unchanged.
So.
This isn't quite the full proof that this is
possible to generalise before and spin the system,
which you can find in a pretty nice way, the
interview from before any of us were born.
I was just. Say that it turns out to be the case,
that what we've done for one side here generalizes
to the full dual system despite the
interconnections between the different sites and
links. So if we rewrite that configuration so over
the powers of the link, the links are off in terms
of the usual using. Configuration some over these
dual spins, minus one. You just need to stick in
this extra power, but have to compensate for the
double counting from negating all values of those
things. So
we now have even further progress and got rid of
the.
Of all dependents or explicit dependents, I should
say, on the spin degrees of freedom and all that
is left apart from factors of two, it's just a
bunch of hyper trigonometric functions that now
depend on the values it spends at the side of the
door and sort of taking the product over all those
nearest neighbor pairs dual Latisse.
Which just requires a little bit more
trigonometric manipulation. Where we can proceed
just by doing another identification that is easy
enough to check. Remember that we want this
capital city to be hyperbolic, cosine, what is
index is zero and we assign the index as one. So
this idea of identity is easy to check in both of
those cases are confirmed, that will be a zero.
The exponential factor, that's one we get the
cosine. The key is one that we have been
exponential of the law, which just brings down its
arguments, the senge over Coche of the cost and
the.
So that is quick check and then we substitute in
the. Relation between each of these links and the
original letters, which we define as capital C
variable and the product of dual spins of the two
sides that are separated by the corresponding link,
and conveniently because we're doing this for
every site, Bilitis, we don't have to be careful
track of exactly which dual speeds are separated
by exactly which links. We just know that all
pairs will be accounted for in the overall sum. So
the two factors in this exponential. Are going to
be or can be just broken up, how this first term,
the one half can be moved inside the log and the
exponential of the cancers that were actually left
with the torchbearer, the times, the square root
of attention. So that cancels out the square root
of the cause. It brings in the square root of the.
Out front reduces to that factor and then there is
just the dual spin defense attorney now hiding out
as the coefficient on the one hand and exponential
so somewhat. Normally, when you're packing things
that we can simplify by converting the product
overall,
nearest neighbor, pairs of the dual. So we have
here. The product. Exponentially now can be recast
just as the exponential of some reversing the very
first thing that we did, everything else is
independent of the dual spins that can come out in
front of the configuration. And if we say. That's
the three factor on the song over the years,
repairs is just some.
Dual temperature, dual temperature in Childhelp,
then we can recognize everything apart from that
pretty factor as the partition function for the
two dimensional using model. Add this to Obeida
given by negative a half of the log of the
tensions of the original temperature. I guess
there's just enough time to.
Confirm that this is. The destination we started
targeting right at the beginning, so we have the
dual production function where if we rearrange
this equation to isolate. The typical tangent of
Peter. There has to be an exponential besides the
negative two times of the children. So if I take
so easily to belittle that and then subtract the
minus to the child, that is.
One over the of the inverse of this relation,
minus the tangent itself.
We can break up into a.
Of simply because.
Within.
And.
Then getting that all into. The common denominator
is what to do with half square miles of central
square, the usual. Relation, one that we're
probably familiar with, and then that cost the
times since Batur, which we can recognize or churn
through the.
The formula cost. They have essentially the best
quarter. In the Beda plus either minus beta, the
minus minus beta. Gives us quarter EBITDA minus.
Minus two, which was a half.
Synch to data, we are not putting in the values
factors, other half with this since Peter.
Research, censorship of. To ensure that equal to
one over. I don't like the formula since to date
itself, which was the point we started off
targeting the relation between the temperatures of
the two. I do all systems, so run out of time with
just final qualitative comments to get through, we
got through all of the mathematical manipulations,
so we'll pick up tomorrow morning in the other
room, quickly, see what it means. What benefit
does this do you give us that for there to be some
more broader applications to start ramping up the
pull the module? So the final question, questions
for today
have a chance to follow up about anything until
tomorrow morning. But I've got a few.