All right, I think we may as well get under way
and wrap up the final meeting and recording for
statistical physics. I'm not surprised that there's a
small crowd at this point because it's fairly
obvious that there won't be any new
content coming this afternoon that will be on
the exam. We will try to have some fun looking at
some of the broader applications of
statistical physics, including lattice field theory.
So this is picking up from the end of the formal
concept we went through this morning, and even
though it is a tutorial, I think it's fine just to
chat a bit about these broader applications, not
doing detailed calculations or anything very
rigorous, but just sort of spotting where the
concepts and tools from statistical physics can
find use. Of course, this is the last scheduled
opportunity for you to ask anything, any burning
questions before we enter the exam period. I
probably won't. Continue holding the schedule
office hours over the next few weeks, but you're
always free to schedule a meeting.
If you need one through the Web interface link
from the. Lecture notes in Canada site before
actually getting into things. You can have.
Actions to up. That through the last six
or nine, seven seven.
In the first of a broader application that.
I have in my interview to talk about is actually
something I mentioned without details earlier in
the week as the domain in which a lot of
theoretical physics research your little world
operates through important mathematical
calculations applied to quantum field. It is. And
this is what I anticipated and started talking
about in the. The introductory remarks, but
quantum field theories are several molecules ended
up with cells. The basic idea is that. We have
some fields that are defined at every point in
space and time, and they interact with each other
and even with themselves in order to. Produced
essentially all of the behavior that we observe in
the universe from the strong nuclear force to
investigations here. The report for applications
to the Higgs boson on dark matter and even that
holographic duality that relates these quantum
field theories to particular proposals for quantum
gravity. The.
Fundamental object that governs the behavior of
the particular set of fields and interactions that
arise in any given quantum field theory, is this
object here known as the find the path to go after
the Senate declining to introduce it around the
middle of the 20th century? And what this is, is a
big old integral over all of the configurations of
all of these fields at every point in space and
time of the exponential of what's called the
actions of the integral over three dimensional
space and the time dimension of the production of
the system that depends on those fields and
includes the information about how the fields are
interacting with each other.
And then this exponential comes with the argument
that she comes to the pretty factor, the imaginary
union divided by constant and.
Looking at the overall form of this equation. Even
the fact that we call this a Z is a sense that we
should try to interpret it as something like the
partition function of a statistical system that
we've been introduced to in this module dealing
with for several weeks.
The one of the main differences is that both the
passage of the bill and the graduate itself are
functions of the people, so they depend on those
fields, Capital Phi, which in turn are functions
of space and time. And there are also some.
The other key difference in here is the presence
of this factor of turning this exponential into a
pure phase. Rather than a real number like the
magician functions.
So the football analogy to that petition function.
This has not been a place of the energy cost of
securing a place of the temperature that we can
interpret as quantum fluctuations that depend on
global timescales to play that role similar to
thermal fluctuations in the canonical ensemble and
to get rid of that. Imaginary factor that gets in
the way of this analogy, you can do the trick of
formulating the theory in an imaginary time. We're
zoom in to see if that helps to focus on the
screen, we define this imaginary time tell that is
related to the usual time t by a factor of
plugging that in gives two factors. That squares
make it one. And we have a path integral that
looks essentially the same as a precision function
with observable expectation values. Given, as
always, by the control over all these operations,
but the value of this observable, it depends on
that field configuration weighted by. This also
factor.
So this is the. System that we analyze through
multicolor point sampling algorithms. One
limitation to this approach is that working in
imaginary time that is known as overprotection is
only valid in thermal equilibrium. So we are
restricted in this approach from being able to
access any non equilibrium quantities, but as
we've seen in this module, that was itself
entirely equal, that we understood a lot we could
do with that limitation.
The last complication in this formulation of
quantum field theory is that this package itself
is written for all these configurations, formally
becomes an infinite dimensional integral when we.
Imagine those fields to be filled every point in a
continuous space time and infinitesimal shifts
with a new degree of freedom from each of the
fields of play, which. Is something that, well, as
you might expect, for a interactive system that
can only be evaluated in very special, very
simplified situations and in general, we need to
regularize this integral, somewhat similarly to
how we regularized the momentum of the ideal gas
particles when we first looked at those in Florida.
And we do that by getting rid of continuous space
of time and actually replacing space and time by
less of the same so that we look for the easy
model. The conceptual difference here is that.
Because the easy model, we can imagine that
Latisse representing the locations of magnetic
dipoles and molecules that are.
Arranged into a regular grandmother, interactions
with each other. So they are objects that live in
a continuous space of time in this perspective, it
is space and time themselves that are no longer
continuous but only exist at these three points in
the regular lattice. So this approach of. With
rotating and then this ties in space and time
defines lattice field theory and the image here
that I'm using to give a feel for what a lattice
looks like is actually taken from a lattice field
through calculation of properties, of protons,
based on the quarks and blue, all that they are
composed of. So. And each of the individual points
in this three dimensional grid that corresponds to
a snapshot of the lattice calculation at
particular points in that imaginary time, we have
a value for the court field, which carries what is
called a color charge that's somewhat analogous to
electric charge. The difference of a few and one
is one of which being that instead of being just a
single number, electric charge could be one unit
two units, one to one ratio on the colored charge
is a linear combination of red and blue and green,
which is the characteristic feature that led to
this becoming known as color in the first place.
And these linear combinations are shown by the
colors of the individual points of the quark field
in this discrete space. We're the size of the
point indicates the magnitude of the charge that
comes along with its orientation in this
particular space. So that's the sort of games you
play with a quantum field theory, democratized in
a lot of space time
and. The key final step for going from numerical
calculations that can employ this finite number of
degrees of freedom on a finite computer to get
back to the quantum field theory that we started
off with and to analyze in getting you a space and
time is to repeat these calculations a few
different times, each time with a larger number of
states, time points that are located closer and
closer to each other, eventually allowing
extrapolation to what's called the continual
limits, where you would have infinitely many
lattice sites close together, reproducing some of
the very continuous space of time. And at that
point that week, rotation to imaginary time can be
undone. We are. Restricted to equilibrium
quantities, and we get back the predictions for
the real world in which we live and in particular
very successful predictions with quantities like
the masses and interactions of subatomic particles
being predicted to better than one thousand. And
Premal.
And also broadly applicable not just to. Theories
like the strong nuclear force that govern
subatomic particles, but also to. Systems of dark
matter experience holographic Beechcraft as well.
And in all of these cases. Thanks using a sample
of Monte Carlo, the uncertainty as they come along
are under control and can be systematically
improved if we just. I tackle the problem with
additional resources, or if we come up with more
clever and more efficient algorithms. That the.
Get more bang for your computer, Buck. So. That,
of course, lettuce field theory is an example
within the mathematical sciences, so it's.
Perhaps intuitively obvious that statistical
physics can be relevant and applicable to this.
Sociology is an example of the discipline well
beyond mathematical sciences, where it may be more
surprising that statistical physics has anything
to say. But there is a. Diverse and active field
calling itself social physics, that is.
Credible and able to use the tools of statistical
physics to accurately describe various aspects of
the social and political behavior of humans, and
one particular example that is so easy to get a
grip on and see how statistical physics can
connect to these sorts of political behavioral
dynamics is what we call voter models, which have
been around for half a century or more, used to
model not only elections, but also the process of.
Debates and opinion, information concerning
various different questions about political
propositions, individual candidates or political
parties.
Where? The question itself is boiled down to baked
into the definition of this model. Individuals are
represented as spin degrees of freedom, similar to
the easy model for the value of the spin
represents the opinion that they hold on whatever
question or candidate is under consideration. So
we can say that the spin indicates support for
this candidate or question downstairs indicates
opposition and the interactions between different
voters have some drive to align the voters with
each other through that process of debate and
discussion on this topic. And then there are
various ways this can be generalized beyond the
easy model itself, because adding a third option,
the value zero indicator, people who don't
actually have an opinion on whatever is under
consideration, or we can extend the range of
opinions to quantify how strongly different people
might hold. Some might be very committed to their
opinion and wanted to change it and eager to
change other people's minds. Some people might
might not be neutral, might not care enough to
make a big deal out of that. Can be. Incorporated
into this model, these sorts of generalizations,
but perhaps the key generalization, distinguishing
all models from the easy model is the.
The draft structure that's there to find out why
use the word drafts rather than Baathists, because
they should be. Not as regular as the lattice
structure that we've been dealing with, different
people can have many different interactions, both
with different numbers of individuals and also
interactions that carry greater or lesser weights
similar to the different coupling and the links
that we've introduced for the easier model. So
maybe the picture is worth many words about this.
So what's shown here is an example of this sort of
graph coming from the publication of about 10
years ago illustrating how things can work in one
of the simple cases where there are only two
possibilities. So let's open up his clues and down
this color red. And in this particular analysis,
the. Well, you can start off by seeing that
depending on which person we should note in this
graph we're considering, it could have different
numbers of connections to the other nodes or even
some that are isolated all by themselves, some
that have a very dense collection of links to many
other individuals. And the key feature of the
model that was being analyzed in this work was
that. The graph was dynamic and evolving, these
links between different individuals would be
repeated and destroyed with greater probability
for creation between people with similar opinions
on this topic and a greater probability for
severing links between people with opposing views.
The.
Result of this particular analysis that included
that that type of evolution of the graph structure
itself was a phase transition to two different
phases here. Once the system is reached, one of
these spaces was characterized by a consensus that
developed the vast majority of the individuals
with only a few outliers, whereas the other things
that is pictured here saw the whole population
become increasingly polarized, splitting into
distinct groups that increasingly only had
connections with those who shared their opinion
on this topic. And over time, there was a clear
boundary forming between those groups with fairly
few relatively small number of connections
crossing that boundary and that sort of behavior.
That polarization, which drew stable, long lasting
camps with opposing views, also appears in simpler
analysis or simple models that keep the
connections fixed. Is there are connections of
individuals lives that are very difficult to to
suffer long term friends or family, even with the
connections fixed and not being created or severed?
A similar transition to consensus can result once
an opinion reaches a critical concentration that
can be quantified through numerical multicar
calculations, and there is a possibility for these
so-called stable consensus spaces where even
though the population is roughly evenly split. The.
The different opinions are. Concentrated in two
clusters of voters that agree with each other and
interact with each other with only limited
interaction with those who have the opposite
opinion, and the only difference compared to this
work with the evolving graph is the interpretation
where.
Now, instead of forming or breaking connections
between people with civil war or opposing views,
the main dynamics of people's lives changing
depending on who they interact with, a fixed
pattern. And, of course, in general, you can have
both sorts of contributions in the mix at the same
time. So.
A caveat, caveat that you can see in this is that
there are lots of modeling choices you can make
and know the fundamental theory of human
interaction to guide them. What has to be done is
to compare the predictions of these sorts of
calculations with actual observations of opinion
polls and election results, which can then
validate various different aspects of the model or
invalidate them as the case may be.
So that, I think, is something about voter models,
which are a nice place to start due to their
similarity with the U.S. model. And maybe
something else that might be more familiar these
days is using.
Interactive statistical systems to battle the
spread of disease in populations.
The degrees of freedom are, again, individuals
interested in. The interactions of these degrees
of freedom with each other are now influencing
whether or not susceptible individuals pick up
whatever infection is present in the broader.
Population and.
We
go through this link in the. Lecture notes, we can
see.
Some quick examples of the sorts of problems with
that, this is a quick example of. A simple
modeling of spread of some disease from the ground
with the disease and their interactions with the
folks who have not yet had the disease spread the
infection until eventually almost everyone is ill
and gradually recover. In this case. And. Just by
a an amusing coincidence, the two hundred little
circles that are bouncing around in this. A little
simulation. Which is different every time with a
different set of pseudo random numbers being
sampled. This is very nearly the same scale as the
very first important sampling multicolor that was
ever done by Petropolis, Rosenbluth and Teller in
nineteen fifty three, where they looked at two
hundred twenty four discs in a two dimensional
volume and computed the pressure of the equation
of state from Montecarlo. Important sample. So
back in nineteen fifty three, this calculation
took several days and the most powerful
supercomputers in existence. And now it's quick
and easy to run on your phone without incurring
any significant stress on the processor or the
battery. And by.
Tossing in further similar generalizations to this
type of modeling, somewhat similar to voter models,
you can back up the effects of, say, closed
borders or more general quarantines. You can see
what happens if a border that was closed happens
to bump involved. The disease is still spreading
on one side and quickly passes into the other. Or
if you suppose that some of the individuals, the
degrees of freedom in the simulation are locked
down and not moving around. So in this case, I
think three quarters of the population is fixed in
place. And the number of. Sick individuals grows
much more slowly as a consequence of that is there
are fewer. InterAction's.
Occurring to spread that disease, which can even
be made even more extreme by supposing that seven
eighths of the population is. Stuck in place. And
we can compare what we're used at once to judge
what sorts of interventions and. Can help to
reduce the numbers of sick individuals over time
and in some cases even protect some people from
falling ill at all. And.
This is obviously a very simplistic and
unrealistic example put out by The Washington Post,
but larger scale and more realistic versions of
these sorts of epidemiological simulations.
Some of which are connected to research in the
School of Engineering here in Liverpool, Simon
Maskell's group of distributed, distributed
algorithms to do the sort of thing quickly and
efficiently that feeds into government operations
and depending on the government, can help guide
the decisions about what restrictions to impose in
the interests of public health and how long it
would be best to retain those restrictions. And
just to connect this with the actual content of
our module, the.
As we discussed in Section one point, to enforce
laying the foundations for.
Probability spaces and statistical ensembles. Each
of these numerical simulations needs to be
repeated many times, just slightly more sets of
random numbers in order to gain some control over
the central values of the predictions and also the
scale fluctuations that come out to quantify what
the proper advice is and what weight it should
carry, how reliable it is in terms of its
uncertainty, its various.
So feel free to ask any questions you have about
any of these topics or generalizations, if there's
just one last
voter application to another biological example
there. Various animals can. Where am I going here?
Exhibit. Collective behavior examples can be both
flocks of birds or swarms of insects or even
traffic on busy streets or crowds of pedestrians
and as an example to. Actually show you what I'm
talking about, rather than just trying to explain
the words, I'm not talking about family, but we'll
get through. Or go down five.
And look at this flock of several hundred or
possibly thousand starlings in Europe that are
carrying out some coordinated motion. Forming
shapeshifting clowns that.
Break merged together and.
In general, wander across the sky with some
influence from possible predators searching for
food or other external driving processes.
Turn down the volume
over
water and see the individual degrees of freedom at
its most elevated, relatively small number of
physics terms.
All of which are. Coordinating with each other
much more tightly than you. Well, we expect just
from all of these animals. Behaving independently,
so the. Interpretation of this, the body of this
in terms of statistical physics is to.
Model them as model, use this sort of behavior or
swarming with just the emotion of crowds as an
interacting gas. Of particles that have a tendency
to align the direction of their motions with the.
Fractured emotion of there, of the particles that
are near them, as this is a guess, what particles
are near them is varying over time. And about
twenty five years ago, one of the foundational
models in this sort of analysis was published is,
again, one of those where it's named only after
the first author would have five or six authors
that work during nouns
that provide formulated the statistical physics
model for particles in a gas interacting with each
other to avoid the direction of their motion and
show two different phases, one in which the
average angle of the motion of all the particles
of that gas is disordered. So it averages to zero.
And another phase in which there was a. Long
distance or large scale order among the directions
in which many departments are moving, which then
produces these sorts of patterns, they're called
reverberations, is for Fox because shapeshifting
flaps.
And ever since the mid 90s, there's been lots of
time to apply, refine and test these sorts of
models with a good deal of success, empirical
verification that the statistical physics analysis.
Is. A good basis on which to analyze this sort of
behavior so that on Tuesday there was a paper
published that.
Inc. another. Variable into. Models of this sort
allowing the. The birds, the particles to change
their change, their speed and its magnitude, as
well as its direction, which allowed them to
obtain good agreement with observations of flocks
ranging from as few as it was a couple of dozen
birds, up to several thousand. Qualify by filling
those those blocks of the high speed camera and
quantifying the overall shape of the properties of
that order phase that they were forming. And one
thing that we can do actually with this
statistical physics model is Helen. Is become a
bit more quantitative about what these phrases
really are and particularly the existence of a
bona fide phase transition between them. So rather
than be qualitative and saying. In some cases,
they're just ordered some places that look like so
you can express things in terms of that or rather
the average fight and map out the prediction of
the model, depending on the density of the
particles and the systems and what the density is
low where there are few interactions with those
interactions are we could strength we end up with
particles that are more free to move in any
direction that do not been for many of those
migrations or storms and high density. This is
where that changes and this large scale collective
motion can appear arising just from those
interactions between. The individual particles in
the system, rather than without having to put in
any modelling of the
whole large scale collection of all those degrees
of freedom, just the interactions between the
individual microscopic particles predicts the
large scale behavior through the process of
statistical physics. And depending on exactly what
variation of this model you apply, you can predict
either a first or second or the transition between
those two faces. Again, those are both defined in
that thermodynamic limit of an infinite number of
particles. And
the with these finite flocks of observe, the best
thing we can do is try to map out the. Dependence
on the size of the flock that is covered by the
critical exposures in the case of a second order
phase transition, there are a few models that
predict difference universality classes for those
critical experience and can in principle be either
confirmed or ruled out by the observations. Of
these migrations in nature, and I'll also mention
that in some cases there is severe diffusion, so
anomalous diffusion just like that, and the
computer project where certain of these birds end
up randomly walking very far distances, much more
quickly than you would expect from the ordinary
law of diffusion coming from the central.
So those are sort of for fun illustrations of how
the concepts and tools of statistical physics can
be recognized or applied in. Domains very far from
sophistical physics, both within and even beyond
mathematical sciences.
Looking at the time we made it, may as well just.
Back up with. A quick look back at what we've done
through this term, which is the section in the
lecture notes, is mostly therefore for you and for
others who may be watching the recording to have a
quick reference guide to what was discussed,
whether from one unit to the next, and also to see
how those topics flowed from one to the other,
starting with the definition of probability
foundations in that unit, one looking at
expectation, values and stochastic systems that
involve large numbers of degrees of freedom, where
the central limit theorem relates stable, large
and properties of that full system to the.
Underlying elementary degrees of freedom that
allows for stable behavior to emerge even from
random or at least Karslake processes from
resolving one of the historic debates around the
origins of statistical physics and the existence
of atoms and molecules as the components of large
scale substances like gas fields.
And the particular
sort of probability spaces that we are focusing on
in the specific context of statistical physics are
not surprising. Statistical samples where the.
The.
As community spaces, statistical ensembles are
viewed as a collection of microstates that's
subsystem of a large number of particles can adopt
as it evolves in time and if it adopts each of
these microstates with some corresponding
probability. And by imposing laws of nature like
the conservation of energy and the conservation of
particle, no, we define various sorts of
statistical ensembles through the resulting
constraints. The micro canonical ensemble is the
most direct example where conservation of energy
is imposed on the system itself, which implies
that it must be completely isolated from all the
rest of the universe, unable to exchange any
energy or particles.
And gets to the temperature being derived. From
the fundamental conservative quantity, the energy.
No. And through the second law of thermodynamics,
the first being that conservation of energy, Iran
will show that the entropy is always not decrease
in function as time passes so that we can identify
something that's real by searching for. The
condition of maximum entropy that we then applied
to a more practical set up to be that three was
called the canonical ensemble. We're canonical
does carry the meaning that this is the usual one
we would work with, where the system is allowed to
exchange energy with some large reservoir that
fixes the temperature and the particle number
itself is still fixed, so. The ability of the
system to interact with the rest of the universe
is what allows us to set it up, manipulate it and
observe it and measure quantities such as the
capacity entropy and now the internal energy as
observables rather than the defining qualities.
And by maximizing entropy to impose them going to
have to keep. We define partition function where
equivalently the.
Helmholtz, free energy is the water in the world,
that petition function, which are the starting
points for driving all of this? Essentially, it is
like. Energy capacity, so we looked at. Some of
those convictions for the case of simple,
distinguishable, indisputable systems have not
attracted expense. Where is that pure information
content, whether or not the degrees of freedom
could be distinguished, led to observable changes
in energy and entropy. And we also do torrealba
able to. Consider or analyze models like the phone
and the better, the devices of cell phones that
reproduce experimental measurements for the heat
capacities of various materials. Maybe one useful.
Aspect of this work to highlight was the trick of
simplifying the system by looking at this behavior
in the high temperature limits and avoiding work,
using that to guide our analysis of the more
complicated situation of intermediate temperatures.
So with the economic slowdown and we went through
two main applications. So we're looking at
classical novelistic ideal gas's. Well. We went
through that same process of regulating the theory
by democratizing the movement and then taking the
limits of continuous variation that replace those
discrete cells with continuous.
And. Also. Derive the pressure and I guess as an
equation of state, also looking at the mixing of
two gases, if they're distinguishable in the same
particles, which can be distinguishable in case
produced a non-zero mixing entropy corresponding
to an irreversible process. In contrast to that is
that in this case, we're combining and we separate
the gases is reversible and can be done with no
obstruction. And then. Further building on. Those
concerns about the Agassiz took systems of ideal
gases, put them in some container in contact with
two external thermal reservoirs, one them coal,
and use the flow of heat from the reservoir to the
core reservoir through the idea of gas as a way to
extract work.
On the violence definably, the tension. Which
involves not just the flow of heat, but also
various manipulations, expanding and pressing or
just holding the volume fixed for the system and
by. Introducing preferably diagrams of the entropy
temperature diagrams. We had a nice visual mediums
to monitor sequences of some of those processes
that. Produce a close group that can be repeated
arbitrarily many times to finance the cycles of.
That can produce a steady flow of work from that
heat transfer or going the other way. Can take we
can use work that we've done on the system to
transfer these.
And operate as a refrigerator, so the.
Balance of the work that a heat engine is able to
produce based on the amount of heat it is to
operate, it finds its efficiency. And we spent
some time showing that the cycle achieves the
maximum possible efficiency. That is allowed by
the second law that whereas other psychos on the
other side of this cycle model, the operation of
internal combustion engines are less efficient,
but have access to greater sources of heat through
burning fuel rather than waiting for heat transfer.
And the third and final statistical example we
looked at further generalizes to the situation by
putting the system in contact with the progress
that allows both the energy and the number of
particles to fluctuate while the temperature and
chemical potential are kept fixed. And. We did the
same sort of interview maximization to find some
dynamic equilibrium. That's gave us the tools to
apply this to systems of quantum gases. The other
main ingredient for me to be part of the system is
that rather than looking at all of the possible
microstates of a single particle and then. I'm
just taking the power of that single political
prediction function to define the important
opposition function. We saw how that approach can
break down when there's a measurable probability
for the idea for multiple identical articles to
occupy the same energy level, whereas instead the
quantum approach. But considering the energy
levels themselves, the organization microstates in
terms of possible occupation numbers for each of
those energy bills, gets around that problem and
allows two different types of quantum particles to
be distinguished. The boatswain's. That can have
any number of identical bosun's occupying the same
energy level, while fermions can only have at most
one identical formula in any given energy. I also
notice the exclusion principle and in the limit of
high temperatures with sufficiently negative
chemical potentials that you can no virgin recover
the classical limit. And the. Earlier approach
that we talked about, so just to wrap up the
applications more quickly, is that getting more
recent? We looked at the full time gas with the.
Those Einstein statistics and an. And the grand
finale coopetition function from the ensemble,
seeing how it provides a good model both for solar
radiation as well as the cosmic microwave
background, even though it's making the assumption
that all of these photons are not attractive. That
turns out to be not an issue in throughout that
whole range, from the coldest to the hottest
regions of the of the universe.
And similarly, looking at not attractive females,
we focused on the low temperature regime. So where
the family function that defines the occupation
number of fermions as a function of energy purpose
is a step function at low temperatures where all
of the low lying energy levels are filled by the
single phenomenon that can occupy them. And the
higher energy levels are all empty, which defines
the fairly energy is the boundary between the
filled and empty sets of energy levels and also
leaves a non-zero energy and a non-zero degeneracy
pressure even in the limits of absolute zero
temperature. That plays a key role in Type 1A
supernova as being possible. And since the spring
break, we've spent all our time looking at this
reaction, interacting statistical systems where
there are a broader based model to consider, but
also a lot more difficulty in analyzing the
systems precisely because of the interactions that
keep the factories into a bunch of contributions
from independent single particles. So the. Testbed
for all of this was the easy model of interacting
spins on a lattice of the dimensions where you
were able to obtain some exact results in one in
two dimensions. Compare those to the mean
approximation and in higher dimensions. Look a bit
this week at the numerical methods that are
broadly applicable. Not only to the U.S. model,
but to a vast swath of interactive statistical
systems, both within and sciences, so. The. Basic
three pillars of that margin were the foundations
like these, the physical examples of the walls of
the premix applications to things like ideal gases,
thermodynamic cycles and conditions, along with
some more advanced topics like numerical methods,
universality. And that is the model that
you enjoy the trip and is the master.
Yeah, so
that is correct. Everything that we've gone
through the lectures, it's fair game for the exam
and I guess you'll see in a couple of weeks what
what turns out to be out there. I have the get
about the play. There are two sample exams on the.
I can kill this. This is one of them where there
is indeed a question on fazing bottle. This is an
illustration of the sort of thing you can expect,
but we are well over time already. So to leave the
sample exams on the module's page for you to
explore on your own, yet feel free to contact me
with any questions about the program that's at.
Sancta.